<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Window of opportunity]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F702D098ED2EBAA6CD38182DDC3AFF8A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5B0BF172B2542072C372BBA7BEE174BE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D8E4F2081A7223C4FA6798C9831639B6"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=039E16341231F472BF70EE1F83CE9815"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A16600E9E9728FC83615D6B5DF3BCB5A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="View out of aeroplane window, flying over city" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9187F0CDCBE48A7C06ED9575DC1BAFE6" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9187F0CDCBE48A7C06ED9575DC1BAFE6"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Treasurers are taking advantage of favourable market conditions for debt financing – but which funding routes are most attractive in the current market? And with the ECB beginning to wind down its quantitative easing programme, how long will the current window of opportunity remain open?</em></p>
<p> Raising finance is a key part of the treasurer’s job – and the good news is that despite potential headwinds such as the ongoing Brexit negotiations, funding conditions continue to be favourable. Published in October, the Q317 Deloitte CFO Survey found that large corporates have easy access to credit, with 80% stating that new credit is somewhat available or easily available and 90% saying that new credit is cheap.</p>
<p>“Markets are extremely strong,” comments Richard King, head of UK&amp;I, Nordic, and Benelux Corporate Banking at Bank of America Merrill Lynch, who focuses primarily on investment grade and implied investment grade businesses. “So our clients currently have an enormous amount of choice when it comes to raising finance.”</p>
<h3 id="why-are-markets-favourable">Why are markets favourable?</h3>
<p>There are a number of reasons for these robust conditions – not least of all the continuing low interest rate environment, despite recent rate increases in the US and the UK. “The expectation is that interest rates will go up over the next 12 to 18 months,” comments King. “But obviously that is against a backdrop of very low levels – so the absolute rates that clients can raise money at are still incredibly competitive.”</p>
<p>Likewise, news that quantitative easing is drawing to a close in Europe has not had a negative impact on the credit environment, says Fenton Burgin, Head of Deloitte’s UK Debt Advisory team. “The ECB is saying that it will gradually unwind quantitative easing this year,” he explains. “But the pace of that unwind is going to be relatively slow, and the ECB will be very focused on making sure it doesn’t stave off the current recovery in GDP in continental Europe.”</p>
<h3 id="taking-advantage-of-positive-conditions">Taking advantage of positive conditions</h3>
<p>Corporates are making the most of these favourable conditions. King notes that bond issuance in the UK has been “very strong” in the last year, with many large UK corporates taking advantage of benign markets and strong conditions to raise funds from the debt capital markets at competitive levels.</p>
<p>As of mid-December, UK/Ireland debt capital markets volumes across all currencies were US$93.6bn, compared to US$81.4bn in the same period in 2016, according to Dealogic figures. “This speaks to the desire for UK corporates to take advantage of current market conditions and issue early and ahead of potential Brexit uncertainty in 2018/19,” notes King. European corporate bond issuance, meanwhile, was on track for a record year, boosted by the ECB’s decision to begin purchasing corporate bonds directly in March 2016 as part of its quantitative easing programme.</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Cost and availability of credit</h5>
<p>Net % of CFOs reporting credit is costly and credit is easily available</p>
<p><img alt="Cost and Availability of Credit Chart" height="411" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2018-01and02-tt-07-fu__chart-01__cost-and-availability-of-credit__967.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=AEA9B1B8A176DC79D6A3A58227E53E65" width="967"/></p>
</figcaption></figure><figure class="center">Source: Deloitte Q317 CFO Survey
</figure>
<h4 id="impact-of-m-and-a">Impact of M&amp;A</h4>
<p>In some cases, issuance has been driven by M&amp;A activity: high profile deals in 2017 included Reckitt Benckiser’s US$18bn acquisition of Mead Johnson and BAT’s US$49bn purchase of Reynolds American.</p>
<p>Burgin says that conditions are set for corporates to look seriously at M&amp;A this year. “With very high cash balances sitting on corporate balance sheets, there is going to be a lot of pressure from shareholders to grow – and growing organically, when compared to M&amp;A, looks quite a slow proposition,” he notes.</p>
<p>At the same time, Burgin predicts that larger corporates will expand the range of M&amp;A that they are looking at in order to drive shareholder return. This is leading to a growing focus on corporate venturing, whereby corporates invest directly into startup companies. “Essentially, when large corporates are sitting on cash in a low interest rate environment, the return on that cash is low,” says Burgin. “We think there will be an increase in corporates participating in M&amp;A processes where they are essentially looking at investments in the same way that a private equity firm would.”</p>
<h4 id="pre-emptive-action">Pre-emptive action</h4>
<p>In other cases, corporates have been pre-emptively raising finance while conditions remain favourable. For example, King says that many of the bank’s clients have been raising funding from the debt capital markets in order to increase their liquidity levels, or to pre-fund debt maturities that are coming up over the next two years.</p>
<p>This may be at least partly driven by a sense that there is a window of opportunity which will not remain open indefinitely. “With interest rate expectations starting to tick up, and likely to do so through 2018 certainly in the US, corporates who need additional liquidity are looking to raise it now, before the rates go up further and while markets are strong,” says King. As a result, he explains, some corporates have been raising more liquidity than they actually need: “Since the financial crisis, corporates have learnt that you can never have too much liquidity. They’ve spent the last few years tidying up their balance sheets, so their leverage levels are very low and they have plenty of debt capacity, but they are also ensuring that they continue to increase their liquidity levels.”</p>
<p>Indeed, George Dessing, Senior Vice President Treasury &amp; Risk at Wolters Kluwer, says that in early 2017 the company refinanced a €750m bond, due to mature in 2018 at approximately 6.4%, with a new €500m ten-year Eurobond at 1.5%. He adds, “this allowed us to use the attractive rate environment to lock in long-term funding.”</p>
<p>John Feeney, Head of Global Corporates at Lloyds, agrees that corporates currently have plenty of access to liquidity, with funding models which provide a certain amount of flexibility in case of future uncertainty. “We don’t see corporates locking themselves into one specific approach,” he says. “It’s much more a case of keeping the appropriate level of flexibility in their funding models and ensuring there’s ample access to liquidity, to be well prepared for the uncertainty that people are expecting.”</p>

<h3 id="choosing-the-right-funding-source">Choosing the right funding source</h3>
<p>Bank loans and bonds naturally have different characteristics, so corporates have to factor in a number of considerations when deciding which route to choose. King points out that the bank term loan market provides a certain amount of flexibility. A bond is raised for a specific period, with a breakage cost typically payable if a company wishes to change the maturity. A bank loan, meanwhile, has more flexibility when it comes to early repayment.</p>
<p>In practice, King points out that companies are likely to make use of a number of different funding routes. “They may have a revolving credit facility for general liquidity. They may have a term loan to help their short-to-medium term financing, which they can repay depending on cash flow over the next few years. And they may have longer dated bonds for more permanent capital requirements. It’s possible to build a nicely mixed funding profile between those markets.”</p>
<p>Another point that treasurers need to consider is what the right currency mix is for their businesses, particularly in light of the impact of Brexit on sterling rates. “Considering what is the right currency mix of your debt to provide a natural currency hedge for your international business is definitely more important in this different FX world,” comments Karlien Porre, who leads Deloitte’s UK Corporate Treasury Advisory team.</p>
<p>King adds that while treasurers can enter into swaps in order to match the currency they are looking for – for example, by raising financing in the dollar market and then swapping it to euros – they are increasingly trying to match their underlying currency to their financing needs. “They will still do swaps, because some markets will be cheaper than others at any particular time, but they are trying to provide a more natural hedge when they can,” he explains.</p>

<h3 id="funding-options">Funding options</h3>
<p>For corporates looking to raise finance this year, a number of different funding routes are available, from bank loans and bond issuance to direct lending.</p>
<h4 id="bank-borrowing">Bank borrowing</h4>
<p>Deloitte’s Q317 CFO Survey found that 85% of respondents rated bank borrowing as very or somewhat attractive as a source of external funding for UK corporates, whereas corporate debt was rated attractive by 80%. Indeed, the survey shows that bank borrowing has largely been seen as more attractive than bond issuance for the last three years – whereas corporate debt had the edge earlier in the decade.</p>
<p>King says that bank term funding has seen something of a comeback in the bank market over the last 12 months. “After the financial crisis, we went through a phase where clients were mostly doing bridge-to-bonds,” he says. “Meanwhile banks have been more stretched in terms of their own balance sheets over the last few years. That’s now starting to stabilise, and we’re seeing a re-emergence of bank term funding.” King adds that there is no shortage of supply: “Aside from some particularly large M&amp;A financings last year, M&amp;A activity was fairly subdued overall, so there is something of a pent-up demand on the bank side to provide loan financing to clients.”</p>
<p>Again, some corporates are taking advantage of the current window of opportunity by refinancing their existing revolving credit facilities in order to extend their maturity profile. “A lot of refinancing activity was done two or three years ago, and generally the revolving credit facilities have maturities of five years,” King explains. “So a lot of clients are now looking to extend those maturities with two or three years to go – partly because they are being conservative in terms of their debt maturity profile, and partly because they are taking advantage of strong market conditions.”</p>
<h4 id="bond-markets-a-global-perspective">Bond markets – a global perspective</h4>
<p>According to the Deloitte survey, 86% of respondents said that now is a good time to issue corporate bonds. Looking ahead to the coming year, Burgin says key questions for the bond markets will focus on the pace of inflation and how quickly interest rates rise. “Generally, as interest rates rise, bond prices fall to increase yields,” he explains. “In a rising interest rate environment, you will typically see bond yields rise to match that rise in underlying interest rates.”</p>
<p>Consequently, he says, the last six months have seen a pick up in terms of companies using index-linked bonds to shield themselves from the impact of inflation. “We think that trend will continue as people perceive that inflationary pressure might build back into both the UK and European economic landscape,” he adds.</p>
<p>Another factor is the ECB’s plan to wind back its quantitative easing programme. Burgin points out that while bond markets are strongly driven by the QE programme at present, the unwinding process is expected to be gradual – so “that mass of liquidity is going to continue to prop up the European bond markets, making them highly attractive for issuers and keeping rates at close to record lows”.</p>
<p>Conversely, in the US Burgin predicts that yields will continue to move slowly upwards off the back of the US economic recovery and anticipated interest rate rises, which will “inevitably widen out the gap between US and European rates”. He notes that this is a somewhat unusual situation: “Traditionally US markets are lower cost than Europe, so the fact that the ECB is continuing with its quantitative easing programme is actually going to keep the window of cheap finance open in Europe for the next nine to 12 months.”</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-2">Chart 2: Cheaper borrowing costs</h5>
<p>Yields on euro-denominated bonds dropped to record lows in 2017</p>
</figcaption>
<img alt="Cheaper Borrowing Costs Chart" height="428" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2018-01and02-tt-07-fu__chart-02__cheaper-borrowing-costs__967.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=624FD9805AF8E115ED96E9FA3FF777A9" width="967"/><br/>
<p class="source">Source: Bloomberg Barclays index data</p>
</figure>
<h4 id="drivers-in-of-funding-in-asia">Drivers in of funding in Asia</h4>
<p>In Asia, meanwhile, different trends and catalysts are coming into play. “Historically, Asian companies are bank funded,” says Gourang Shah, Head of Treasury Services Solutions for Asia Pacific at J.P. Morgan. “So if you want to get a better distribution, it may be important to add bonds to the capital structure. As Asian companies grow, they are getting more exposure to best practice in capital structure and are raising more money.”</p>
<p>At the same time, Shah says that Hong Kong is trying to position itself as a viable option for Asian companies to look at in addition to the UK or New York. “Historically, IT companies in India have tended to raise money in Europe or New York – these locations may come with more liquidity and a better regulatory environment.” More recently, Shah says that the arrival of dim sum bonds has proved to be a good step towards creating a market in Asia for RMB. He adds that progress is also being made in the regulatory environment and in making sure investors feel comfortable with the jurisdiction.</p>
<h4 id="us-private-placements-and-beyond">US private placements and beyond</h4>
<p>Beyond bank lending and bond issuance, King says that many UK companies have been accessing the US private placement markets. “Clients can raise as much as a billion dollars or more from that market, without having to go to the public markets, at very favourable rates and a range of maturities,” he comments.</p>
<p>Burgin says that he anticipates more direct UK private placements, whereby companies go directly to insurance companies to do a bilateral deal, in contrast to the traditional bank-led private placement route. “We are seeing more and more insurance companies saying they are happy to look at direct deals,” he notes.</p>
<p>Another notable trend is the rise of direct lending, particularly in the mid-market space. Burgin says Europe is moving towards a US model, in which funds and non-bank lenders are the primary source of capital for the mid-market, rather than banks.</p>
<p>“Essentially, there has been a flood of insurance company money, private wealth money and specialist debt investors looking for yield in a low interest rate environment, where gilts and treasuries are yielding low returns,” Burgin explains. “In the US, these lenders provide the bulk of capital into the mid-market – and we think Europe is transitioning rapidly to that sort of model.”</p>
<p>In conclusion, while rising interest rates and the winding down of QE in Europe may affect funding conditions over the course of this year, it’s clear that there are plenty of opportunities currently open to treasurers looking to raise finance. As Porre observes, “Treasurers who are currently looking at their annual or five-year funding plans really have a wide range of options to consider.”</p>
<h4 id="corporate-indias-debt-binge">Corporate India’s debt binge</h4>
<p>One country that proved especially popular with bond issuers and investors alike in recent times is India. From March 2016 to March 2017 corporate bond sales in India were valued at US$51.5bn – a 40% increase from the previous year – according to data from Prime Database.</p>
<p>Driving this trend has been Prime Minister Modi’s progressive economic reform, which has opened the domestic market and attracted more investors, especially from overseas, to buy Indian corporate debt. The increasing demand for this debt has seen spreads tighten, making bonds a cheaper source of financing for corporates able to tap the market.</p>
<p>The attractive 7% average yields on India corporate bonds saw international investors flood the market. By the end of July, foreign ownership of corporate debt surpassed 92% of the US$38.1bn quota permitted by the government. This led regulators to suspend issuances of offshore rupee-denominated bonds to stem the inflow for a short-time.</p>
<p>It seems, however, that if the demand is their corporates will continue to issue. This is especially true given that the Indian banking sector is currently facing a multitude of issues limiting its ability to lend to corporates.</p>
<h4 id="panda-bonds-on-the-rise">Panda bonds on the rise?</h4>
<p>Another exciting bond market in Asia is the panda Bond market – RMB denominated bonds issued by international companies or sovereigns in China. After the first Panda bonds were issued in October 2005 by the IFC and the Asian Development Bank, the nascent market failed to live up to the initial hype with very few foreign corporates issuing bonds.</p>
<p>In more recent years interest has grown, especially because of some high-profile issuances from companies like Daimler. Yet, despite this the panda bond market still only accounts for a tiny fraction of China’s US$3bn onshore debt market, meaning that there is still plenty of room for it to grow.</p>
<p>By the end of August 2017, 42 panda bond issuers had entered the Chinese interbank market, including international development institutions, sovereign governments, financial institutions, and non-financial enterprises, from North America, Europe and Hong Kong, according to the International Capital Market Association (ICMA). This accounted for total of RMB11bn panda bonds through 57 transactions.</p>
<p>The ICMA believe that panda bonds may become increasingly attractive to corporate borrowers in the coming years because:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Funding onshore operations:</h5>
<p>Raising RMB directly onshore can simplify cash flow operations and reduce potential currency risk to match their RMB funding needs for foreign corporates with operations in China.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Investor diversification:</h5>
<p>The large Chinese bond market investor base presents a significant opportunity to expand the base of creditors.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Liquidity:</h5>
<p>The onshore bond market is perceived to be generally more liquid than the offshore dim sum market.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Marketing considerations:</h5>
<p>Issuance of panda bonds by foreign institutions helps domestic market participants to develop a better understanding of how these institutions operate, builds trust between the two sides, and ultimately fosters the sustainable and efficient operation of foreign institutions in China.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Global funding:</h5>
<p>The Chinese onshore bond market, like other international markets, may present an opportunity for foreign issuers to obtain funding in their primary currency (usually USD, EUR or GBP) at attractive rates by issuing in RMB and entering into a cross-currency swap for their primary currency.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Market innovation:</h5>
<p>The issue of some panda bonds to date has been motivated at least in part by a desire to be one of the first to market with an innovative transaction.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="continued-opportunity"> </h3>
<h3 id="continued-opportunity">Continued opportunity</h3>
<p>As we move into 2018, the outlook for corporate funding remains positive. Indeed, no matter what part of the world the company is looking at, there are lots of opportunity out there to raise reasonably priced debt.</p>
<p>For corporate treasurers, the advice is to begin reviewing their options now and perhaps take advantage of the favourable conditions whilst they exist. Indeed, Patrick Tai, Finance Director, CNOOC and Shell Petrochemicals Company Limited, who features in this editions Corporate View and whom has built a career on raising finance to fund some of the world’s largest petrochemical projects says: “One issue that I see many companies have is that they only focus on debt when they need it. We work on this even when times are good so that we can call on it when we need to.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Treasurers are taking advantage of favourable market conditions for debt financing – but which funding routes are most attractive in the current market? And with the ECB beginning to wind down its quantitative easing programme, how long will the current window of opportunity remain open?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/city-aiplane-window-ss629465288.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2018-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Funding where it is needed]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B4F40109B2ADCF961F07E36AC3FD5600"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DF6DE936CC97DE6D8B95CB3F6B886617"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C1074688CF7FCF3C7C18460AC29A3F93"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FB57B65F09A09C561F45CAFF8D08369D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=922CECA083D5CCB71915C615A0C68AC3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Oliver Schimek, CEO &amp; Founder, CrossLend" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4621E1101A703105BBDF373B70E7FD32" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4621E1101A703105BBDF373B70E7FD32"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>CrossLend believes that the financing space needs a shake-up and has developed a solution that aims to do exactly that.</em></p>





<h3 class="fn">Oliver Schimek</h3>
<h5 class="title">CEO &amp; Founder</h5>
<p><img alt="Crosslend" height="21" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/crosslend-logo-2017-120x21.png?la=en&amp;hash=6DBB2641BCCEA0E03DD33A65DBA3C590" style="margin-top:1.5em;" width="120"/></p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<h4>Tell us a bit about yourself and your background. How did you get into fintech and why did you want to build a cross-border marketplace lending platform?</h4>
<p>After studying Physics and Economics at the Freie Universität Berlin, I went on to found my first company, Quantea, in 2010. This company specialised in the development of trading algorithms and currency trading IT infrastructure.</p>
<p>Three years later, I joined Kreditech Holding – a company which leverages technology to enable people with little or no credit history to access finance – as Chief Financial &amp; Investment Officer. It was in this role that I became exposed to the European lending economy and it was when I developed the idea behind CrossLend.</p>
<p>CrossLend was founded in June 2014 and began operating officially in in September 2015. Initially, we were focused on the business to consumer (B2C) lending market, but we have since moved into the business to business (B2B) space. As a result of this work and expansion the business has grown markedly in a few years and today we have roughly 50 employees.</p>
<h4>What were the biggest challenges getting the company off the ground?</h4>
<p>The complexity of a highly regulated product in the B2B segment is significant. There are a lot of things that need to be developed at the same time. We’re not selling clothes via an online shop. We are engaging with highly regulated entities and regulators, developing new solutions for an economy that is not particularly fast or reactive when it comes to change driven by cutting-edge technology. However, at the same time this of course is also the basis for a great opportunity. With our innovative platform we can really change something in the financial ecosystem.</p>


<blockquote><p>I like to think that CrossLend is quite unique because we are not a competitor for banks; we consider ourselves very much as a partner to the banks thus generating a true value for the existing ecosystem.</p></blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h4>What makes fintech such an exciting space and what do you find most interesting about it?</h4>
<p>The pace of change and the solutions that are being created are what makes fintech an exciting space to work in. But I like to think that we are different to most fintechs who have decided to focus on a niche area of financial services. In some respects, these companies are competing with the banks for a finite amount of business. I like to think that CrossLend is quite unique because we are not a competitor for banks; we consider ourselves very much as a partner to the banks, thus generating a true value for the existing ecosystem.</p>
<h4>How do you expect fintech to develop, especially in the corporate space, in the years to come?</h4>
<p>I expect a clear consolidation in the fintech market in the next few years. Fintechs need to have a clear value proposition towards corporates in the B2B space. If you just improve single parts of the value chain of a corporate it will copy or acquire you. On the other hand, if you act as missing link or enabler for new products, you create a true value to the overall economy and create something scalable.</p>
<h4>In corporate treasury, few are feeling the impacts of fintech as yet. Where do you think that fintech can have a real impact on the day-to-day operations of corporate treasurers?</h4>
<p>Most fintechs so far are targeting the B2C space since many of the founders are coming from the eCommerce space. This has changed recently, however, and we are seeing more and more native fintech founders tackling B2B problems. Corporate treasurers will benefit from that development, but the ecosystem is young and needs to grow.</p>



<h3 id="how-it-works">How it works</h3>
<p>The solution works by CrossLend purchasing loans that have been granted by banks and issuing a series of notes – debt securities that can be purchased by investors.</p>
<p><img alt="Crosslend infographic 1" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2017-07and08-tta-11-ff__infographic-01-borrower-loan-series-of-crosslend-notes-investors-1000x144.png?la=en&amp;hash=5279FD8DAD2309211C3F478A71364670" width="1000"/></p>
<p>When a borrower makes their loan repayments, CrossLend makes the corresponding payments of interest and principal pro rata to the holders of the notes. Insofar as a borrower neglects to make their loan instalment payments, CrossLend owes the holders of the notes no payments. Costs for the collection of overdue loan amounts may arise, which may be deducted from any payments to the noteholders.</p>
<p><img alt="Crosslend infographic 2" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/201707and08tta11ffinfographic02borrowerloanpaymentsseriesofcrosslendnotesinvestors1000x178.png?la=en&amp;hash=64B38AEB73976483920A4B77DDAA33CA" width="1000"/></p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h3 id="transforming-the-credit-market">Transforming the credit market</h3>
<p>CrossLend connects originators such as banks with investors such as insurance companies and pension funds. Originators can offload loans on a single loan basis from their balance sheets. CrossLend makes these available as a flexible asset to investors via 1:1 securitisation (one loan – one security, no pooling). “We have created a new European bridge between banks and investors to help bring the European Capital Markets Union to life,” says Oliver Schimek, Founder and CEO at CrossLend.</p>
<h3 id="changing-direction">Changing direction</h3>
<p>Established in 2014, CrossLend’s founders originally set about developing a European cross-border, peer-to-peer lending platform for private investors to access consumer loans. However, Europe’s changing economic fortunes and the regulatory pressure on banks that is forcing them to shrink their balance sheets, seeing them able to lend less, gave Schimek and his team an opportunity to push the company in a new direction.</p>
<p>This new direction would see CrossLend introduce its peer-to-peer model directly to the back offices of banks, giving them a flexible instrument for refinancing their lending operations. “Our concept lets them keep the customer relationship, monetise it and service the loan without the full balance sheet implications. In that sense we make banks peer to peer capable,” explains Schimek. “At the core of our approach is a new way of securitising loans where instead of issuing a bond against pools of loans, CrossLend securitises single loans with single bonds, translating the loan receivable into tradable securities with the advantage of full transparency.”</p>
<p>“Our original idea alleviated a symptom of the sub-optional lending environment that existed in Europe,” says Schimek. “Our new idea reflects the times and we think that our new solution can solve the root of the problem.”</p>
<h3 id="a-sign-of-the-times">A sign of the times</h3>
<p>“Europe is in trouble and we want to stabilise its backbone, which is the financial system,” says Schimek. “Politicians and regulators have been working on the concept of a Capital Markets Union (CMU), linking savings and growth to improve conditions for savers and investors. Their action plan says we need to connect institutional and retail capital to the lending side of the economy, preferably via securitisation. Compare that to our business plan and it’s basically a one-to-one match. Banks would need many years to start such a platform and it would not be independent. We are the speedboat in this market.”</p>


<h3 id="company-timeline">Company timeline</h3>
<ol id="timeline">
<li>
<p><strong>July 2014</strong></p>
<br/>
<p>Founding CrossLend</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>September 2015</strong></p>
<br/>
<p>CrossLend platform goes live</p>
<p>Series A Financing Round with Lakestar</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>August 2016</strong></p>
<br/>
<p>Reorganisation: service for banks, insurance companies and other credit marketplaces</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>February 2017</strong></p>
<br/>
<p>Investment of Luxembourg Future Fund</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>April 2017</strong></p>
<br/>
<p>New investors: CME Ventures, Fund Promus Ventures</p>
</li>
</ol>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[CrossLend believes that the financing space needs a shake-up and has developed a solution that aims to do exactly that.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/oliver-schimek-fintech-focus.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2017-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[China’s credit challenge]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F89DB2F8AF9862BFC15A7C871BDBE838"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D7828A7B3E2731D84115887AB54F27F0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3C813D90F395CF8BEA3EF8EEBAE7A654"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=181B0C21F31AB7092825C2299F4B3F76"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F22B9985737A986061E6C40F08218152"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Hiker walking in the moutains on a trail with flowers" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AC4263FD21C6AC0E290C4D54C658E88" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AC4263FD21C6AC0E290C4D54C658E88"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>The syndicated loan has proved a useful product in supporting China’s recent growth. But will the strong demand for loans seen in recent years continue? And if it does, will the banks be in a strong enough position to meet it? We take a look at some of the key challenges now facing the markets fuelling China’s growth engine.</em></p>
<p>In much of Asia, the global financial crisis brought about a sharp decline in syndicated lending. But that didn’t happen in China. On the contrary, China was one of the few countries where syndicated lending continued to grow through the crisis. Syndicated lending volumes have continued to grow steadily over recent years as well, to the point where the product is now one of the most popular sources of finance for businesses in China.</p>
<p>The credit financed through the syndicated lending channel has therefore played a critical role in fuelling the nation’s recent growth story. But will it continue to in the years ahead?</p>
<p>The outlook is mixed. Despite the talk of a ‘hard landing’, China’s official growth rate in 2015 was 6.9%. Slowing – but still robust – growth figures, should mean that demand is still there (especially while M&amp;A continues to surge and more corporates look to refinance the foreign currency loans weighing on the balance sheet). The real question, then, is around supply and, in particular, if the ability of banks to lend might be restricted by the non-performing loans (NPLs) now accumulating on their balance sheets.</p>
<p>But there is also another, perhaps bigger, story to tell here. The history of China’s loan market very much mirrors the country’s economic development, more specifically the transition from a centrally planned economy to a market-based one. Consequently, syndicated lending in particular has been subject to tremendous changes in recent years and with the economy continuing to open itself up to market forces, there is very likely more still to come.</p>
<h3 id="the-journey-so-far">The journey so far</h3>
<p>In the not too distant past, syndicated lending in China was the near exclusive domain of Chinese banks, the so-called ‘Big Five’ in particular. In 2006, this began to change following reforms that allowed more foreign participants to commence lending in renminbi onshore and in foreign currency offshore, often collaborating with domestic banks to take advantage of their superior origination and distribution networks. Much of the liquidity supplied through the expanding loan market went into infrastructure financing, where syndicated loans became the preferred vehicle for extending the credit since it reduced the risk of default caused by a single bad project. Since large amounts could be arranged relatively quickly compared with the other available channels, they also became popular with borrowers. Before too long syndicated lending began to dwarf other financing channels in China.</p>
<p>Today China dominates the syndicated lending market in Asia, with volumes of $100bn recorded in H215, accounting for around 31% of all lending in Asia, excluding Japan. Chinese banks remain the dominant players in the domestic market and, furthermore, have been very active players across the Asia Pacific (APAC) region with Chinese institutions representing four of the top mandate arrangers in the region. Even in highly developed markets like Australia, Chinese banks have been competing with domestic institutions and participating in syndicated deals. Foreign banks, meanwhile, tend to focus their financing activities offshore in Hong Kong in credit denominated in euro, dollar or yen. Occasionally foreign banks will arrange a syndicated loan for a European subsidiary that have not been able to build relationships strong enough yet with the Chinese banks. By and large, however, most of the large RMB denominated transactions we see being executed onshore in China come from Chinese lenders.</p>
<h3 id="a-turning-point">A turning point?</h3>
<p>Taken together though, the credit extended through syndicates onshore and offshore account for much of the credit growth that we have seen across the region in recent years. “China has really been at the forefront of syndicated lending in APAC in the past few years, largely due to the overall growth in investment in infrastructure,” says Amit Chopra, Syndicated and Commercial Lending Specialist, at Misys. “If we look at year-on-year growth, 2015 has not been as great in terms of percentage growth, but China has still been the biggest contributor in the region, excluding Japan.”</p>
<p>More moderate syndicated lending activity is being reported offshore especially. Does this mark the beginning of a turning point in which demand for syndicated financing begins to fall off, both in Hong Kong and mainland China? Not necessarily. To understand why syndicated lending has not been so robust during the past year, it is important to consider where a large chunk of the demand the banks were seeing originated from. While a lot of demand for financing has come from clients with an underlying requirement for foreign currency, such as an acquisition, a sizeable portion of it has also been arbitrage driven. For some companies it made sense to borrow in foreign currencies like US dollar or euro, before converting back to renminbi to arbitrage between the low offshore borrowing costs and the high onshore CNY deposit rates. But since the two downward ‘adjustments’ to the currency made by the Peoples Bank of China (PBoC) last year, activity around that carry trade has all but vanished.</p>
<p>“I think demand is still there,” a loan syndications head at a foreign bank in China told Treasury Today Asia. “It is a little bit more subdued than it was, but the nature of the demand has changed a little bit,” he explains. “A lot of [arbitrage driven financing] has fallen away over the past six months. But there is still a drive to go offshore and buy and acquire Western companies, whether it be to obtain technology, manufacturing capabilities or natural resources offshore. That strategically driven demand for credit remains in place, the bit that has fallen away is the companies borrowing cheaply in USD.”</p>


<blockquote>China has really been at the forefront of syndicated lending in APAC in the past few years, largely due to the overall growth in investment on infrastructure.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Amit Chopra, Syndicated and Commercial Lending Specialist, Misys</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Phil Lipton, Chairman, Asia Pacific Loan Market Association, agrees that diminished opportunities for arbitrage is likely to mean less offshore syndicated lending in foreign currencies. “I think we have seen a shift back to onshore borrowing,” he says. “That is not just the depreciation – China has cut interest rates too, so raising money in China is now a lot more attractive than it used to be. For these two reasons there is more liquidity in the country now. As a result, you will see companies, in relative terms, raising more onshore – and I think that is going to increase going forward.”</p>
<h3 id="bad-loans">Bad loans</h3>
<p>Meanwhile, the outlook for the onshore loan market remains relatively favourable into the medium term, underpinned by prospects for strong – although decelerating – economic growth (which the IMF expects to remain above 6% until 2020). However, slowing growth and the commodities slump will have some impact on the market, with lenders expected to become a little more selective in what they finance. Already we are seeing a decline in syndicated loans and one sector, in particular, is facing some steep credit challenges.</p>
<p>In a 2015 report, analysts at Australian investment bank Macquarie looked at the figures on China’s debt profile and found that companies in sectors such as mining, smelting, and material now have debt levels that are so high the firms are under “extreme strains to survive”. Essentially, corporate debt in this sector increased substantially in the past three years, and the earnings of the companies who have borrowed have not increased at anywhere near the same pace. Naturally, banks are becoming a little reticent when it comes to meeting demands emanating from this space.</p>
<p>But while that has been the focus of much of the concern, the change in sentiment has not been entirely restricted to the commodities sector. On the contrary, privately owned enterprises and even some of the less eminent state owned enterprises (SOEs) are also feeling the squeeze. Several years ago, banks were lending to nearly everyone who required it. But today, financing – especially for companies linked to commodities – is becoming much more difficult. There is also less enthusiasm to finance third or fourth tier SOEs than before, while some banks refuse to touch privately owned enterprises altogether, due to the perceived risk.</p>
<p>Also weighing on the minds of lenders, perhaps, is asset quality deterioration from problematic legacy loans. New non-performing loans (NPLs) held by Chinese banks more than doubled in 2015 according to recent news reports. Even by the Chinese authorities own, more optimistic statistics, bad loans rose to RMB 1.27trn by the end of 2015, sending the NPL ratio up to 1.67%. “The NPL ratio is alarming,” says Chopra. “And it gets even worse when you look at the second and third tier of the banking sector.”</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: China NPL ratio</h4>
<p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-chart-01-china-npl-ratio-967x563.png?la=en&amp;hash=9C41DAE0A078F6A5B06E9D217B528A90" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: China NPL ratio" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-chart-01-china-npl-ratio-967x563.png?la=en&amp;hash=9C41DAE0A078F6A5B06E9D217B528A90" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: Bloomberg</em></p>
<p>This worrying development has not escaped the attention of the institution responsible for regulating the Chinese banking system, the China Banking Regulatory Commission (CBRC), who recently introduced a minimum loan loss provision ratio (although the central bank, now in full easing mode, recently cut the requirements in order to stimulate borrowing and prevent a further currency devaluation). Consequently, banks now have to set aside more cash than they did previously for future losses by the total of NPLs.</p>
<p>Chopra says this change will inevitably have a big impact on the flow of credit and syndicated lending in particular: “The CBRC is taking an active step in this and, obviously, this will impact the banks’ ability to lend as openly as they did in the past,” he notes. “One of the steps is around Loan Loss Provision (LLP) ratio and Chinese banks are required to keep a minimum ratio of 150% and some of the large banks are currently very close to this LLP ratio. This obviously means that banks will have to infuse more capital if they want to remain above this ratio while continuing to lend in market. The NPL’s and interest rate liberalisation can have an impact on bank’s profitability going forward.”</p>
<p>But credit should continue to flow, so the experts say, to the less distressed areas of the Chinese economy, irrespective of the NPLs accumulating on the balance sheets of banks and the debt troubles of commodities firms. Perhaps this is why, despite all the market turmoil at the beginning of the year, credit expanded by 12.7% in January, the fastest pace since April 2015. “The banks will be lending to companies where they are seeing growth,” says Lipton. “There may be an aversion to where there is stress in a sector. Corporates that are having more problems are going to be a lot more cautious about borrowing new funds and leveraging up, whereas on the domestic front there’s still growth, so we will probably see banks moving their focus in that direction.”</p>
<h3 id="advice-for-borrowers">Advice for borrowers</h3>
<p>What should treasurers take from this? Well, those who require financing in the near future – as many companies will all the while the M&amp;A upsurge continues – should not have too much difficulty raising it through the loan market, with the notable exception, that is, of all those heavily leveraged companies in sectors most exposed to the slump in commodity prices.</p>
<p>For everyone else, the advice is twofold: do not hang around, and do not get too distracted by the pricing. Companies with a financing requirement should go to the market as early as possible, and understand that it may make sense to pay for certainty in the current market. That might mean paying banks to underwrite or dealing with banks that are slightly more expensive, but the cost of debt is not going to be as important as making sure the company achieves what it want to achieve from a financing perspective.</p>
<p>But with lower borrowing costs and wider availability of funds on the debt capital markets, will syndicated loans continue to be the fuel in the Chinese growth engine? Chopra believes we will see more companies in China financing themselves through bond issuance going forward, but this should not, he says, have too great an impact on the demand for syndicated loans. “The bond market is certainly an attractive option, especially for organisations that have already exhausted syndicated lending or wish to diversify their overall portfolio”, he adds. “But I would say that any company that wants to raise considerable capital from the market, syndicated lending will continue to be one of the favoured vehicles.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[The syndicated loan has proved a useful product in supporting China’s recent growth. But will the strong demand for loans seen in recent years continue? And if it does, will the banks be in a strong enough position to meet it? We take a look at some of the key challenges now facing the markets fuelling China’s growth engine.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-03-fi-hiking-trail-with-flowers-ss222968578__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-02-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Funding strategies in Asia]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<p>“Since the financial crisis, corporates in emerging markets (EMs) have been able to borrow increasingly cheaply in foreign currencies, leading to record dollar denominated bond issuance in Asia. Where should EM corporates focus their funding strategies following the rate lift-off recently embarked upon by the Federal Reserve?”</p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Thiam Hee Ng, Principal Economist, Asian Development Bank" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-01-qa-thiam-hee-ng-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F395C46098EC3A2983A0D07383AE0AB6" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Thiam Hee Ng</h3>
<h5 class="title">Principal Economist</h5>
<h5 class="org">Asian Development Bank</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>With the Federal Reserve raising its interest rate, US dollar funding will become more expensive for the region’s corporates looking to issue US dollar bonds. At the same time, the more volatile economic environment and increased risk perception of emerging markets will likely further push up the cost of borrowing in US dollars.</p>
<p>Corporates that have borrowed in US dollars are facing higher debt servicing cost now with most of the region’s currencies having depreciated against the US dollar. In some cases, the increased debt servicing cost from depreciation has far exceeded the savings from lower interest rates from issuing dollar denominated bonds. This highlights the risk of borrowing in US dollars for corporates especially if the borrowing is unhedged or if the corporates do not have substantial US dollar revenue which can help serve as a natural hedge.</p>
<p>One alternative would be to explore funding in other currencies. The cost of borrowing in euro and Japanese yen remains low. However, going down that route would mean corporates would be exposing themselves to exchange rate risk. Also the offshore bond markets in these two currencies are smaller and less liquid.</p>
<p>Going forward, Asian corporates should look more towards using the domestic bond markets to satisfy their funding needs. For domestic oriented firms borrowing in local currency, this will help mitigate the exchange rate risk. This is especially true if they expect the US dollar to appreciate further.</p>
<p>There has been considerable growth in Asia’s local currency bond markets since the 1997/98 Asian financial crisis. Following the crisis, the region’s governments started the Asian Bond Market Initiative to promote the development of local currency bond markets to avoid the problems of currency and maturity mismatches. Since then, the local currency bond market has grown by leaps and bounds. The total outstanding amount of local currency bonds in emerging East Asia reached almost US $9trn as of the end of September 2015. Early on in their development, the corporate bond markets tended to be much less developed than the government bond markets. But the gap has narrowed considerably. This means that the local currency bond market is now a viable option for meeting corporate funding needs. Efforts are also underway to make it easier for corporates to tap the regional local currency markets by streamlining the processes and procedures. This should further facilitate corporate funding through local currency bond markets.</p>



<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Jan Bellens, Asia Pacific Banking &amp; Capital Markets Leader and Global Emerging Markets Leader, Ernst &amp; Young" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-01-qa-jan-bellens-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=4FCE30F2D611D42DFE40CFC8F84B9195" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Jan Bellens</h3>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Banking &amp; Capital Markets Leader and Global Emerging Markets Leader</h5>
<h5 class="org">Ernst &amp; Young</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Given current regional economic uncertainty and exchange rate volatility, yet interest rates rising following a prolonged low cost period, corporate treasurers in emerging Asia Pacific (APAC) are increasingly challenged in servicing and refinancing their USD-denominated debt. Effectively, higher real rates and lower capital availability are spurring them to revisit funding options to optimise on capital efficiencies.</p>
<p>For now, we expect bank financing to remain the dominant source of funding for regional corporates, with these loans proving to be most cost effective especially for seasoned organisations with good track records. Bank financing continues to account for approximately 50% of corporate borrowing in EMs as compared to below 25% for peers in developed markets. As such, despite the region’s slowdown raising risk premiums for EM borrowers (particularly for industries such as energy and power, materials and real estate that are at higher default risk due to weaker demand from core markets like China), banks are still competing to capture big ticket lending opportunities and jostling to offer more attractive loan pricing to the blue-chip clientele.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, with steadily increasing USD-denominated rates as the Federal Reserve tightens policy, corporates in EMs that depended heavily on foreign currency loans for inexpensive financing while generating cash flow domestically could consider less-volatile local currency alternatives. Those that rely largely on shorter tenured loans are also exposing their organisation to rising rates and should lock in borrowing costs over longer repayment periods in advance of further expected rate increments.</p>
<p>Besides financing corporate activities via loans, bonds offer further funding diversification for EM corporates. While issuance has tapered drastically since H215 (with investment banking fees from bond issuance for the full year declining 18% globally), bonds remain a popular funding choice for EM corporates. However, credit quality has been deteriorating over the last three years with defaults for speculative grade corporates likely to increase. While EY is taking a sanguine view on the corporate debt market, banks are raising yields in response to growing corporate risk (perceived or otherwise) and bonds will become an increasingly expensive form of funding in the mid term. But despite a less robust debt market, bonds will remain a viable fund-raising option primarily for well-established corporates, though fund raising will be tougher for sectors struggling with the current downturn.</p>
<p>For EM corporates with USD and other foreign currency denominated bonds, those that lack natural hedges and sufficiently sophisticated currency risk hedging mechanisms are likely to face currency mismatch challenges and increased credit and refinancing risk. This would encourage the development of more robust in-house treasury departments, as well as spur the respective local currency bond markets to enhance services to corporates seeking more efficient onshore replacement funding and protection from forex volatility. This obviously does not happen by chance and would need support from EM governments to raise market efficiencies, transparencies, and foster higher issuer and investor participations.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, fund raising via follow up equity offerings and new public listings will remain lacklustre until turbulence in global markets eases and investor confidence returns. Investment bankers already felt the pinch in 2015, with a 13% year-on-year fall in global fees from equity products. Waning risk appetites will continue to dampen corporate’s enthusiasm to list their shares until the markets turn calmer.</p>
<p>All in, despite the current market volatility, investment grade corporates continue to benefit from a reasonable selection of funding options. It is the smaller, newer organisations that lack established track-records we see struggling to realign their funding strategies following the recent rate increases. With bank financing getting increasingly scarce for this demographic, there is a massive white space for alternative lenders such as peer-to-peer and debt and equity crowdsourcing platforms to expand rapidly into the EM regions with alternative, more accessible funding options.</p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Ranu Dayal, Senior Partner &amp; Managing Director, The Boston Consulting Group" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/2016-03-04-tta-01-qa-ranu-dayal-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=5F1A2D66F46D8E53044F9596D214A65F" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Ranu Dayal</h3>
<h5 class="title">Senior Partner &amp; Managing Director</h5>
<h5 class="org">The Boston Consulting Group</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Before addressing current funding strategies, it is important to understand the situation in years prior. If you go back a few years, the APAC markets had high growth rates. It was a time when the prospects looked desirable: the appreciation of exchange rates and low interest rates in OECD markets, for instance. There was the view that it was a great opportunity to raise capital and the ability to pay down debt was seen as good. Now, with the US interest rates starting to rise and EM currencies declining, the attractiveness of foreign debt and the ability to service that foreign debt from domestic earnings is a difficult issue.</p>
<p>In terms of the right cost of capital, even sophisticated treasuries are not very consistent in their approaches. There are a variety of ways in which corporates have thought about, and are thinking about, their cross border funding and capital raising. In  addition to the moving parts of exchange rate changes and interest rate changes, the fundamental growth drivers in EMs have been changing – all of which results in differences in terms of funding approaches corporates in Asia are adopting today versus five years ago.</p>
<p>With the Federal Reserve announcing higher rates, the strength of the US dollar resulted in a reduction in how much funding corporates wanted to do in USD. Now the Fed is being encouraged to slow down the rate of interest, or the timing of the rate increases. The inflationary pressures that were beginning to appear in the US are abating – for instance, if the price of oil stays put, then it reduces the likelihood that US rates will increase. In some ways, this is a counterbalance to the fact that US funding will appear less attractive than it was some time ago.</p>
<p>This uncertainty points to the need for corporates to undertake scenario-based assessments of the alternatives available. They need to model what the company’s cash flows will be given different situations. If, for example, they are orientating debt in renminbi, corporates should question whether the currency is likely to appreciate or depreciate, what the ability is to pay down current debt, how much of it would be serviced by revenues from where the company is operating in renminbi and where it will need to be serviced from revenues in other parts of the world. It is about knowing what kind of cash flow stress each scenario would create on the different parts of the business that have different underlying currency and interest rate dimensions. Corporates should be using a structured set of analytic techniques, not relying on their conviction or a single point estimate, in order to lead a more comfortable position from which to service the debt.</p>
<p>Where home market weakness may diminish the capacity to service foreign currency denominated debt, detailed cash-flow modelling and liability matching is even more critical when assessing options. However, for some of the leading EM corporates, foreign currency financing for acquisitions abroad may make sense if focused on foreign revenue-generating options. All in all, assessing the impact of the large number of moving macro parts – some of which are outlined above – requires: sound analytical framework, development of different business scenarios and active dialogue with lenders to fully appreciate the range of options available.</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<p><em>“Unethical business is increasingly in the spotlight. How can treasury help improve their company’s ethics?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[“Unethical business is increasingly in the spotlight. How can treasury help improve their company’s ethics?”]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-02-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Stuck in the middle with you]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>The mid-market corporate community has relied heavily on bank-sourced funding in the past but with a new-found regulation-driven prudency, borrowing is more difficult for such firms. There are newer models of credit in the market and the banks say they are keen to lend, so does the ‘squeezed middle’ still exist?</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EAD470ED19127C610AD4054172872E89"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7DE979980F1456807501ADFD7A4F7719"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6AF972586FD2A02E8056030AD62CC04A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EE76A25ABF4DB2F0113839B927AC8013"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=60E2B716B4B54553D18BE257E6033904"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Baseball stuck in a rain gutter full of leaves" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DF3C84F90081669201D5D951B5F387CE" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DF3C84F90081669201D5D951B5F387CE"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>One unintended consequence of the raft of ‘post-financial crisis’ regulations, Basel III in particular, is that the supply of bank funding is becoming less of a reliable option for some corporates. The largest corporates are still a safe bet for them and although small firms have long since been subject to punitive risk-based pricing, they are increasingly able to look to alternative funding sources such as angel investors and crowd-funding. Stuck firmly in the middle of all this are the mid-market corporates – those sitting approximately in the €500m to €1.5 billion revenue bracket – which are seemingly at a funding crossroads.</p>
<p>Whilst many feel the need to keep the favour of their banks to help finance day-to-day operations, the mid-market treasurer will need to work out which of their partners they wish to continue working with. But just as treasurers need to decide where their business will go, the banks are taking the view from the other side of the fence. They want to know that they will be getting a decent slice of the corporate wallet to warrant offering the full range of products. With regulation and negative interest rates placing a high cost on taking in short-term money, banks will not be afraid to say goodbye if the wallet is not forthcoming. Gone are the days when banks lined up to offer cheap money; now it’s all about mutual trust and depth of relationship.</p>
<h3 id="we-have-the-money">We have the money</h3>
<p>Some mid-market firms might feel they are being squeezed but a number of banks are now saying they have the funds to support good quality businesses however the appetite for debt of those firms has diminished. Bank lending volumes in the Eurozone have been falling for around two years, the FT reported in May last year. At that point they were nearly 3% under the May 2012 level. Anecdotal evidence suggests little has changed. One explanation for this is the continued lack of confidence in the markets – no one wants to commit to debt when revenues are so unpredictable. According to S&amp;P Capital IQ stats, net loan issuance to non-financial corporates turned negative in 2012 and remained so throughout 2013. Has this changed in the last 12 months?</p>
<p>“It’s not necessarily a question of a squeezed middle as there’s plenty of liquidity in the lending markets,” says Farouk Ramzan, Head of Commercial Banking – Europe, Lloyds Bank. Where banks have been accused by mainstream media of turning down too many business loan applications, Ramzan points out that whilst an individual bank may have a strong balance sheet it will never be unlimited. “I would much prefer to do business that has continuity to it because it is that type of value-added client business that gets the bulk of our client relationships through any economic down-turn,” he comments. Ramzan further argues that restrictions on balance sheet may in part be an unintended consequence of Basel III. Despite that, he acknowledges that regulation is imposed for a reason. “The challenge for banks is how to own that regulation and work with regulators,” he says. “We need to ask how we can align ourselves with it in a way that allows the best outcome for our clients.”</p>
<p>There is, he continues, “more flexibility out there than people think.” Clients with sufficient funding needs can maintain their banking relationships as well as explore other options open to them with large institutional investors. Increasingly, credit funds are looking to play in the mid-market space via the Private Placement market. However, he notes, a mid-market client may feel “rather vulnerable” if it decides not to have a trusted advisor at its side with a deep understanding of the clients’ needs when approaching large institutional investors. “It is our duty as a bank to look after our client and manage the covenant structure, the pricing and the options on tenor to make sure we can optimise those deals for the client,” he states. “It’s all part of the process of being more accountable to our clients.”</p>
<p>The availability of bank funding is a theme taken up by Benoit Desserre, Global Head of Payments and Cash Management, Societe Generale. The concept of the ‘squeezed middle’ may have existed a couple of years ago, he agrees, but he is adamant that now there are few constraints on lending: bank funding is available but firms are just not increasing their level of borrowing. “This is really a matter of confidence,” he notes, adding that no matter how cheap borrowing is, even if rates are zero, if companies are not confident that their investment will generate extra revenue they will not borrow. “That is a simple economic fact.”</p>
<p>In an attempt to make banks safer with larger capital buffers, their increased regulation pushed them into a position where they had to bring in more deposits and keep fewer assets on their balance sheets. This in turn forced the wider financial community to bring other sources of corporate finance to market. This, notes Desserre, was the genesis of France’s EuroPP market, the growth of the USPP and Schuldschein, and the general expansion of interest in corporate bond issuance.</p>
<p>However, the banks have now moved to a third stage where some central banks – notably the ECB, but also Swiss and Danish to date – have imposed negative deposit rates. This gives the banking system two choices, says Desserre: lend more or change the inflow of cash. Lending has been naturally curtailed by low business confidence so taking cash deposits suddenly becomes undesirable. “We’re still very keen to have corporates manage their cash flows with us; that is for the long term. But the ECB deposit rate is currently in effect a 20 basis point charge on all excess cash. For a short period of time it may not be an issue, but if negative rates recur then it could be detrimental to end-customers if it constrains bank’s ability to lend. I have never seen this before, it is so unusual.”</p>
<p>Indeed it must be unusual because the industry was certainly not ready with the tools to compute negative interest on deposits. With low growth levels almost everywhere you look in Europe, working out how to increase business confidence is a task for the politicians, says Desserre. But in the meantime, he acknowledges that the corporate community will be tightening its collective belt. It will also be looking to other forms of funding.</p>
<h3 id="an-alternative-offering">An alternative offering</h3>
<p>As more businesses seek alternative sources of funding, it could be that the mid-cap community no longer needs to rely fully on the banks anyway. Indeed, the range of finance solutions open to ‘quality’ mid-market firms has expanded in recent years. Traditional bank lending has been joined by an increasingly well-trodden path to the debt capital markets, in particular private placements. This model is well established in the US (with roots back to the 1930s) but there is a nascent equivalent market in the UK, Germany (the Schuldschein serves the country’s ‘Mittelstand’ sector of mid-market businesses) and France (Euro PP). Although EuroPP is just two years old, it has already raised more than €7 billion, albeit mostly for French companies funded by French insurers.</p>
<p>Although the USPP is by far the biggest market, even for European companies, one benefit of having a ‘local’ market is that investors will more likely know the companies they are dealing with. If there was any doubt that, globally, these offerings are of interest, S&amp;P Capital IQ figures state that European companies raised around €60 billion on the US and European private placement markets between 2012 and 2013. There is little sign that this is slowing down.</p>
<p>Investors are clearly coming round to the idea that the mid-market asset class is a serious means of diversifying their own holdings. As yields in some traditionally secure asset classes hover barely above ground, pension funds and insurance firms – the institutional mainstays of the PP space – need to find an acceptable return on their ‘buy to hold’ investments. The quality mid-market sector has shown itself to be a useful addition to their lagging portfolios. In May 2014, Deloitte’s Alternative Lender Deal Tracker reported 33 leading alternative lenders as having taken part in 105 European mid-market deals over the previous six economic quarters. Private debt funding, it seems, has an equal appeal for both the institutional investor and the mid-market corporate. With the flexibility now to offer delayed draw-down, firms do not even have to time their approach to the market quite so perfectly.</p>
<h3 id="getting-noticed-mid-market-ratings">Getting noticed: mid-market ratings</h3>
<p>The word ‘quality’ has purposefully been used above in reference to mid-market companies seeking funding. Objectively assessing a company for ‘quality’ – the strength of its business and financial models and market appeal, for example – involves more than a simple credit check. This is why many large corporates seek a credit rating from an independent agent such as S&amp;P, Fitch or Moody’s, to ease the funding process (and potentially even lower its costs).</p>
<p>Mid-market corporates can do the same but obtaining a rating is quite a lengthy process, involving considerable effort and cost. One of the credit agencies – S&amp;P – believes it has come up with a solution that, whilst not intended to be a credit rating per se, is based on a simplified version of its own corporate rating methodology. Pitched at businesses with group-level revenues below €1.5 billion and total drawn and undrawn reported debt facilities below €500m, the mid-market evaluation rating (MME) “increases the transparency in this sector and provides a common benchmark for issuers, investors and lenders to assess specific credit risks,” says Roberto Rivero, Head of Market Development, EMEA for S&amp;P.</p>


<blockquote>We’re still very keen to have corporates manage their cash flows with us; that is for the long term. But the ECB deposit rate is currently in effect a 20 basis point charge on all excess cash. For a short period of time it may not be an issue, but if negative rates recur then it could be detrimental to end-customers if it constrains bank’s ability to lend. I have never seen this before, it is so unusual.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Benoit Desserre, Global Head of Payments and Cash Management, Societe Generale</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Driven by the apparent lack of financial information about mid-market companies, MME is intended to provide investors with a “standardised and objective means” of assessing prospective mid-market borrowers without those companies jumping through the many, varied and expensive hoops of the full rating process.</p>
<p>A firm will be ranked on a range from MM1 (highest) to MM8 (lowest) and MMD (default). The same scale is applied to issuers and to debt instruments, although instrument ratings also incorporate S&amp;P’s view of the expectation of recovery if ever a default occurs.</p>
<p>The rating gives S&amp;P’s views on the creditworthiness of a mid-market company relative to firms of a similar size. It assesses the firm’s capacity and willingness to meet its financial obligations based on a number of data and information sources including annual audited financial statements, interim reports and liquidity status, and also includes a review of governance, strategy and financial policy.</p>
<p>In theory, investors get an independent view of the mid-market companies in which they are considering investing, and the mid-market companies improve their access to investors which may otherwise be off-limits.</p>
<h3 id="seeking-diversity-a-corporate-view-on-private-placements">Seeking diversity: a corporate view on private placements</h3>
<p>How easy is it for a mid-market firm to wean itself off traditional funding sources? As Group Treasurer at Neopost, France-based global leader in mail, communication and shipping solutions, Christophe Liaudon has first-hand experience of just such a re-balancing act. Speaking at last years’ EuroFinance event in Budapest, he explained that in 2012, two thirds of all Neopost’s borrowing was from banks; a year later, bank credit accounted for just one tenth, Neopost having turned to the private placements market in a big way with investors spread across Europe, the US and Asia.</p>
<p>The company, listed on Euronext Paris, can be placed at the upper end of the mid-market sector with annual sales of around €1.1 billion from its direct presence in 31 countries (39% coming from North America). Although it has been dipping into the US private placement (USPP) market since 2003, it saw 2012 as “a year of challenges and diversification” for its finance structure.</p>
<p>It sought a refinancing package of €808m but diligent balancing of bank and private funding saw Liaudon and his team eventually raise €867m, and $270m between June 2012 and January 2013. The team managed to extend average maturities from under two years to more than four, and reduce its average interest rate to below 4%.</p>
<p>Neopost returned to the USPP market in early 2014, securing a further $50m. By June it was issuing its first unrated bond, Liaudon describing this as “a natural next step”, benefitting from an “attractive market” enabling it to issue €350m with a seven-year maturity at just 2.5%. Three months later, back in the USPP market, Neopost established a $140m shelf facility agreement (with a total of $90m drawn from first day and $50m for future drawings). The company’s new debt profile, post-refinancing, extends out to 2022.</p>
<h3 id="be-prepared">Be prepared</h3>
<p>The secret to success in the ‘alternative’ markets is to be fully prepared, says Liaudon. This starts with the buy-in from top management from day one. The process, which in most cases takes between four to eight weeks to execute, kicks off by selecting the most appropriate market. A bank that has partnered a business for some time will not only be able to explain and precisely position its client’s credit status to potential investors, it should also know the markets well and be able to help its client “talk to the right investor at the right time.” The usefulness of the banks in this process is undeniable but they are only the intermediaries: as Liaudon says, “we like to keep control of the process and of the relations with investors.”</p>
<p>At an early stage – “the sooner the better” – it will be necessary to select essential third-party advisors, states Liaudon. The list will most likely include key players such as the book-runner (the lead arranger bank or banks), a legal team and an agent (the bank intermediary between the corporate and the various investors). “Proper” selection should consider that “some advisors have deeper knowledge of certain markets.”</p>
<p>Documentation will need to be prepared detailing the business and finance model of the company, its aims, the funding required and its purpose, existing facilities and so on. The loan contract mandate letter (appointing the third parties) and the term sheet (the main contract) will also be drawn up at this stage. As far as contract terms are concerned, equality is the watchword: “most investors are looking for pari-passu,” he states.</p>
<p>Preparation of PP documentation can be laborious but the process received something of a boost in January this year when the LMA launched its template documents, based on English law and incorporating both a loan and a note option, for use in European private placement transactions. Commenting at the time, Calum Macphail, Head of Corporate Private Placements, M&amp;G Investments, said the creation of standardised private placement documents in Europe “will simplify the borrowing process for corporates and has the potential to encourage new liquidity into this market.”</p>
<p>The French authorities, with European agreement, had issued a charter (‘Financing for mid-sized Companies’) in March 2014 for developing Euro Private Placements (Euro PPs) and creating a benchmark market for them, both in France and internationally. Commissioned by Banque de France and the Paris IDF Chamber of Commerce and Industry, it sought to explain how “capital markets can provide a significant share of the financing for mid-sized companies that might be unable to access international bond markets designed for large corporations with agency ratings.”</p>


<blockquote>Preparation of PP documentation can be laborious but the process received something of a boost in January this year when the LMA launched its template documents, based on English law and incorporating both a loan and a note option, for use in European private placement transactions.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Aside from establishing the French Euro PP as a fully-fledged market segment and “a standard of quality for French and international issuers, intermediaries and investors,” one of its chief objectives is to determine a specific execution framework, based on international credit market best practices. It has already produced a model for term loans and in January this year produced a model for bonds. Liaudon believes that this work shows the willingness to cooperate of all the different actors of this market including investors, associations, governments and issuers.</p>
<p>For the corporate borrower in the PP space, whether a first time player or an old hand, Liaudon stresses the importance of establishing a solid relationship with investors from the start. The first contact will likely be the roadshows and Q&amp;A sessions with individual potential investors and making a good impression is important. Thereafter, it is common practice to submit, at least annually, an update on company progress. In the interim it may be prudent to arrange meetings or calls with the main investors “to maintain contact and explain strategy.” Neopost recently secured an extra tranche from one investor on the strength of its communicative nature. After all, he notes, “investors are looking for a long-term relationship.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[The mid-market corporate community has relied heavily on bank-sourced funding in the past but with a new-found regulation-driven prudency, borrowing is more difficult for such firms. There are newer models of credit in the market and the banks say they are keen to lend, so does the ‘squeezed middle’ still exist?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/loans/rain-gutter-full-of-autumn-leaves-with-a-baseball-114347593.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Spotlight on centralisation]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>For many treasurers, embarking on a centralisation project is a white-knuckle ride, with many points to potentially derail it along the way. But the prospective efficiency and cost benefits make the end result worth the ride. Treasury Today Asia provides some tips for ensuring a smooth journey.</p>
<p>Centralising treasury operations is sometimes like riding a rollercoaster, according to Michael Spiegel, Global Head of Trade Finance and Cash Management Corporates, Deutsche Bank, speaking on a Corporate Forum panel entitled ‘Best practices in the centralisation of treasury functions: are corporates and banks aligned?’ at Sibos 2013 in Dubai. “And that is fine if, by the end of the ride, there is a smile on your face and the only thing you remember is that it was very exciting.”</p>
<p>Industry research shows that treasuries across both the developed and emerging markets are increasingly looking to centralise their operations. Based on the results from its Treasury Diagnostics Benchmarking Survey, Citi identified three key trends that reflect the growth in scope and influence of the corporate treasury, the second being an increased adoption of centralisation structures. The report, entitled ‘Navigating headwinds in 2013: top priorities for corporate treasurers’, stated: “The rise of emerging market multinational companies (MNCs) and expansion of their Western counterparts into these markets has accelerated treasury centralisation: 66% of respondents operate a centralised treasury, 60% use netting structures and 48% use an in-house bank (IHB). Of the companies with a centralised treasury, 72% use a TMS.”</p>
<p>Yet many treasurers are sympathetic to Spiegel’s analogy because the fear factor is very high in such projects. The act of pulling together the many different strands of treasury activity across a multitude of subsidiaries worldwide is daunting to say the least – “Where to start?” is the first question that comes to mind. It takes a lot of time and effort to design a plan and map out the path to centralisation.</p>
<p>A number of barriers are thrown up from the outset. Often local operations put up resistance out of fear of losing control over their cash flows. Then there is the material issue of losing local knowledge and expertise. In addition, as Spiegel pointed out in the Sibos discussion, the decentralisation of the regulatory environment is not supporting the centralisation effort, as jurisdictions implement their own interpretation of global regulations. The ‘spaghetti junction’ of technology systems that most corporates have inherited through mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;As) can also be a barrier to effective centralisation.</p>
<p>The biggest and most overwhelming issue, however, is the right strategy and cost consideration. Anita Prasad, General Manager – Treasury, Microsoft, speaking on the same panel as Spiegel, said: “We have gone through a few of these projects and the cost can be sizeable given the size and complexity of what we are trying to achieve.”</p>
<p>For Microsoft, the expense was well worth it. “As a treasury professional, I look at the return on investment (ROI) which has been tremendous – after the first wave of implementation, a third party was brought in to do an assessment and they estimated that we were reaping benefits that were approximately 45 times the initial outlay,” said Prasad.</p>
<p>Satisfying its main objective, treasury is able to tell the Corporate Vice President and Treasurer, George Zinn, exactly how much cash the company has, which allows senior management to make the right strategic decision in the moment. “That ability to drive strategic decisions pays for itself and is where the value is,” she said, adding that it is not just about driving the data but also about business intelligence.</p>
<p>Also speaking on the Corporate Forum panel, Alawi Alshurafa, Treasurer, Saudi Chevron Phillips, a Certified Treasury Professional, said that he thinks of centralisation as an operational necessity. “Cost may be an issue for some companies, but this is the nature of your business. It is a critical project because at that point in time you just can’t run in the same old way anymore – you need to get out from under your legacy systems,” he said. “It is also a project where you can’t completely quantify how much benefit you will receive; but in terms of a qualitative difference, it was an easy sell for me.”</p>
<p>In an interview with Treasury Today Asia, Tatiana Nikitina, Senior Cash and Banking Analyst, British American Tobacco (BAT), says that some of the biggest benefits of centralisation from a treasury perspective is greater process consistency and efficiency, which in turn gives treasury greater control. “In addition, through centralisation you also achieve benefits and savings due to economies of scale. This is probably one of the driving factors in any treasury transformation project because you need to have a business case behind any change or project proposal.”</p>
<p>Centralisation is not for every treasury, thinks Nikitina, and depends on each company’s structure, systems, business model, geographical mix and internal culture. There is also the option to centralise selected parts of treasury. For example, although she would centralise most processes, such as bank account maintenance, payments and receivables processing, Nikitina would not think of centralising strategic decisions such as bank relationships, projects and risk management.</p>
<p>Prasad similarly believes that centralisation is not necessarily the end game for every company. During the panel session, she made the point: “It may or may not make sense for you. There is centralisation of policies, compliance and processes, but then there is centralisation of cash management, such as how we pool or bring the cash together, and those are two distinct areas. Having a dialogue with your peers or banks, those which are willing to share with you what other companies have done and what they can offer, is a great place to start.”</p>
<h3 id="microsofts-story">Microsoft’s story</h3>
<p>Microsoft has long operated a centralised treasury – the entire infrastructure, which includes more than 80 banking relationships, 190 countries, 45 currencies and 98 employees, is managed through Redmond, Washington. The only team that is not part of its centralised infrastructure is the credit services team because they support the sales team; as a result they are based in the same locations as the sales teams. In a separate interview with Treasury Today Asia, Prasad said that the credit services staff also serve as treasury’s eyes and ears and can provide insights with local regulators and banks, retaining that local knowledge needed to understand changes in domestic regulations.</p>
<p>The trigger for an increased level of automation within this centralisation framework was when the treasurer asked his direct reports a simple, but which in reality turned out to be, difficult question – how much cash does the company have? With a global footprint, treasury needed to have information as to where the cash is, what currency it is in and what Microsoft entity owns it. “Each one of us went back to him with a very different answer; the answers reflected the functional area of his directs. For example, the portfolio team looked at total investments, while the cash management team came back with a number that reflected total cash in bank accounts,” Prasad explained during the Corporate Forum. “Because we couldn’t come back with a single answer, we started searching into how to attain consistency in defining cash, and how to automate and ensure we can put a finger on the exact number.” This was the beginning of treasury’s journey towards business intelligence capability within the centralised treasury, so that today it can answer the question in real-time.</p>
<p>As part of this process that involved ensuring all its banking partners are on SWIFT’s ISO 20022 XML format, Microsoft treasury wanted to rationalise its banking relationships. It has now consolidated with approximately 80 that have strong commitment to SWIFT roadmap and have migrated to bank-agnostic connectivity through SWIFT, using a common implementation methodology with all its banking partners. Prasad believes that having a common implementation has created a win-win for both sides. “It has helped the corporate side in terms of ease of use, cost and efficiencies. It has also helped the banks employ the same methodology with all their corporate clients, which allows them to bring value-add activity to the fore.”</p>
<p>Electronic bank account management (eBAM) is the next big step for Microsoft because it will enable the centralisation of all bank account management processes. “I know we have all been talking about eBAM at Sibos for the past three years, so it is now about making it a reality and working on the digital identity and authentication,” she said.</p>
<h3 id="saudi-chevron-phillips-journey">Saudi Chevron Phillips’ journey</h3>
<p>SCP’s Alshurafa told a similar story about centralising bank connectivity. SCP’s treasury and shared service centre (SSC) supports five Chevron-Phillips ventures in Saudi Arabia and UAE and effectively looks after of all aspects of cash management for the group.</p>
<p>Its centralisation programme was driven by the need for greater efficiency. Throughout the history of different ventures, treasury had various offshore and onshore banking relationships, with bank accounts in London, Saudi Arabia and UAE. “In the past, we were managing each relationship separately through a dedicated platform with each bank, which wasn’t efficient. Therefore, we needed to develop a solution, which is a payments factory concept,” Alshurafa explained to the audience in Dubai.</p>
<p>Two years ago SCP treasury began searching for a solution to increase its efficiency and help it to streamline the cash management processes across the whole group, as well as the day-to-day payments plus the liquidity needs of separate ventures. SCP decided to go with SWIFT in order to have greater visibility over its cash and went live in January this year.</p>
<p>Despite many banks leaning towards host-to-host connectivity, Alshurafa, like Microsoft’s Prasad, wanted to be bank-agnostic. “With the devolvement in the credit market, you need to look holistically at your bank relationship. You want to have the flexibility of delinking if and when you need to.”</p>
<p>He agrees that centralisation is “a wild ride”. “Banks have different technical capabilities. With some banks we went smoothly through the SWIFT implementation in a couple of weeks, but with others we really struggled.</p>
<p>“One of the problems we encountered, and it could have been our fault as well, is that we didn’t include enough technical people from the bank side in our initial planning meetings – and this is very important. If you only talk to a relationship manager, you wouldn’t necessarily get enough details about what the bank is or isn’t capable of – for example, specific interfaces with SWIFT. You need to put together a checklist and go through implementation and planning with the technical people on both sides,” said Alshurafa.</p>
<h3 id="bats-transformation">BAT’s transformation</h3>
<p>BAT’s centralisation project touched many more areas than solely banking relationships and like SCP went down the SSC route. In her presentation entitled ‘Treasury transformation: a way towards centralised treasury’ at the EuroFinance International Cash and Treasury Management conference in Barcelona, Nikitina detailed BAT’s decision in 2005 to move from a partly decentralised treasury structure to a centralised treasury operation with streamlined and integrated processes, which is “fit for servicing our global business”. BAT decided to consolidate treasury transaction processes into financial shared service centres (FSSCs).</p>
<p>According to Nikitina, treasury wanted greater effectiveness through:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Full overview of group funding and foreign exchange (FX) exposures.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>One view of global treasury risk profile.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Optimisation of cash management across the group.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Automation to reduce manual treasury controls.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The aim was to reduce financing costs through leveraging bank relationships and infrastructure, cash mobilisation, improved multi-currency cash flow forecasting and reduced funding lines.</p>
<p>The project was rolled out in four phases:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Phase 1:</h5>
<p>Included standardising treasury processes, banking standards and master data; facilitating FSSC migrations; and building new key systems enablers, such as multi-currency cash flow forecasting (MCFF).</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Phase 2:</h5>
<p>Involved implementing key system enablers, such as MCFF and SAP Treasury; rationalise bank relationships and infrastructure; and transform skills and capabilities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Phase 3:</h5>
<p>Implementing treasury line organisation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Phase 4:</h5>
<p>Embedding transformation and drive continuous improvement.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The company completed seven request for proposals (RFPs) over the past five years resulting in:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Facilitation of the move to FSSCs in Romania, Kuala Lumpur, South Africa and Costa Rica.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Standardised and simplified banking processes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Improved control and security around banking.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Reduction in the number of banks globally by approximately 80 (33%).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Significant reduction of group banking fees.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In the future, the company plans to roll out SAP ECC6, move to one format (XML) and SWIFT, take advantage of the new opportunities for centralisation that the Single Euro Payments Area (SEPA) opens up, migrate more markets and processes to FSSC and continue bank rationalisation.</p>
<h3 id="tips-for-success">Tips for success</h3>
<p>Before embarking on a treasury centralisation project, both Spiegel and Prasad encourage treasurers to identify what they want to accomplish and what the end business goal is, and then bring in the technology and resources to help reach that goal. In answer to Alshurafa’s problem, Prasad explained how they brought their banking partners together for a three-day workshop. “Ten banks came with their relationship managers and cash management and IT experts. We also had a SWIFT team as our neutral ‘Switzerland’ in the room. Because of this, we could agree a single implementation of the connectivity via SWIFTNet, as well as message formats.”</p>
<p>Nikitina’s advice includes getting stakeholder buy-in, which is true for any change management programme, and beginning with some system consistency, because a SSC can’t efficiently process payments coming from hundreds of different small systems. “In addition, I think that it is important to challenge everything that has been done from the very beginning. Ask why it has been done this way and if there is a better way of doing it, because this will enable a much bigger step forward. Centralisation is a huge project and it is more worthwhile doing that when the end game provides more benefits than incremental ones.”</p>
<p>She believes that SEPA has shown many treasurers just how many ways of doing the same thing exists, even within a centralised treasury – for example different file formats and ways of processing payments. “Once they have overcome the initial technical problems, there is a huge opportunity to centralise much more and make all payments from one euro account for example, or move to one format for payroll. During the SEPA migration, many treasurers discovered a lot of inefficiencies that could be eliminated or streamlined in future.”</p>
<p>Before the centralisation project begins, Alshurafa suggested starting with original research, including market study and visits with vendors, to see what is available; once the research is complete, conceptualise a plan and then shortlist preferred vendors or service providers. Scorecards and a RFP process based on company requirements and compliance are both useful. “It can be a tedious process but I encourage anyone who is embarking on a centralisation project to spend time researching and planning, because it is critical to get this right and any mistake in this process will be very expensive in the future,” he warns.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2013-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Funding solutions]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>In the ever changing world of business, it is important to have support and insight from a trusted financial partner. Raising funding is now more challenging than ever before. Many treasurers are looking beyond straightforward bank debt and overdrafts, to consider a broader range of complementary solutions, which may include asset backed financing such as supply chain finance, trade finance, factoring, leasing and asset finance, as well as exploring debt capital markets and equity components.</p>
<h3 id="funding-beyond-bank-loans">Funding beyond bank loans</h3>
<p>It would be difficult to talk about funding in 2010 without referring back to recent events that sent shockwaves around the world. Before 2008, many companies were accustomed to accessing the leveraged finance markets. For many corporates, there was little reason to look any further when considering funding options. In today’s uncertain economic climate, however, there is much to be gained by exploring a wider range of solutions.</p>
<p>Far from being unwilling to lend, many banks are working proactively to assist corporations by facilitating a more diverse approach to funding. Mark Stokes is the Managing Director of Lloyds Banking Group’s “Lloyds” Large Corporate division. Speaking to Treasury Today, he was keen to counter broad media criticism:</p>
<p>“My team is alive to the dynamics of UK businesses. We are working closely with our customers, understanding their needs and supporting them right through the cycle. In fact, we now have more relationship and business support managers across 24 offices in the UK, than we have had before. We are lending to create growth for our customers, and growth for the economy.</p>
<p>“You will not be surprised that we are working closely with the government too, and with the rest of the banking industry through the Business Task Force. We are as mindful as anyone of the important role we play in assisting the UK’s economic recovery. What we are not doing is lending for lending’s sake. That would be short-sighted and wrong, and no one would want that.”</p>
<h4 id="the-refinancing-countdown">The refinancing countdown</h4>
<p>In early 2009, economic uncertainty in the funding markets prompted many corporates to refinance early. However, at that point final maturities were typically three years. As a result, a lot of companies will need to refinance again by early 2012 and many are looking to do so now.</p>
<p>Many of these companies are now willing to consider a wider spectrum of funding sources than before. These may include rights issues, US Private Placements and Eurobonds as well as bank debt. “Larger issuers have relied increasingly on the debt markets, and debt markets have gained importance relative to bank lending,” comments Robert Pierce, Managing Director, Head of ECM at Lloyds Banking Group. “Companies are also increasingly looking at equity.”</p>
<p>Although many providers have exited the lending market altogether, or have changed policies by sector, Lloyds has remained committed to supporting strong management teams. It aims to provide a full financing product suite. In this Product Profile we consider the alternative types of funding offered by Lloyds and explore how the funding markets are currently positioned.</p>
<h3 id="capital-structure-advisory">Capital Structure Advisory</h3>
<p>Lloyds provides financing solutions that often encompass a range of different products. In each case, the bank seeks to ensure solutions are appropriate for a client’s given circumstances and this desire to work proactively with clients at the earliest stage is manifested in the recently-established Large Corporate Capital Structure Advisory team which, as the name implies, provides corporate customers with a strategic analysis framework to help shape their funding strategy.</p>
<p>Lloyds’ Capital Structure Advisory is part of the bank’s Large Corporate relationship business, which looks after UK-based corporates with annual turnover above £15m, and typically up to £500m. In contrast to the Debt Capital Markets and Equity Capital Markets teams, which focus on particular product areas, the aim is to review, forecast and explore potential financing requirements at the earliest stage, before specific product needs are explicitly identified.</p>
<p>The purpose of the Capital Structure Advisory team is to provide a deeper and richer analytical capability to meet corporate clients’ increasing demand for forecasting, planning and front-end tactical discussions with their lead bank. From this a wide range of experts can be called in with practical advice based on financial projections and identified product requirements.</p>
<p>“Many clients were picking through the issues that surfaced as a result of the liquidity crisis, principally the economy swinging very rapidly into a recessionary mode and the impact of that on traditional corporate funding sources,” comments Michael McCartney, Director, Capital Structure Advisory.</p>
<p>“Equally, it should not be seen solely in the context of planning for the downside. Due to our close working relationships with good management teams, many of our clients are actually in very good shape. They have been managed well through the downturn and are in a good position to take advantage of opportunities in the market. This is another way our Capital Structure Advisory function can help clients by exploring tactical options which might be open to them due to the wider market conditions – in some instances, opportunities that haven’t appeared in decades.”</p>
<p>Forming the front end of planning, raising funding or refinancing, Capital Structure Advisory allows the Relationship team to act as a trusted partner, opening up strategic discussions with customers that typically focus on the following areas:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Evaluation of the client’s business, identifying key constraints as well as areas for growth.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Reviewing different funding solutions that could be employed to fulfil the client’s objectives, keeping credit lines open for when they are needed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In conjunction with the credit team, early identification of the extent to which Lloyds is able to support the company in its chosen strategy going forward.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>“A great testament to how we are adding value is the fact that many financial teams have turned around at the end of our meetings and asked for electronic copies of our analysis, so they can share the findings and strategic options with their board,” comments McCartney. “We are seen very much as part of our client’s advisory ‘team’ rather than simply a bank they can borrow from – they see professionals that can add material value to those strategic conversations they have internally every day of the week.”</p>
<p>Following on from the initial assessment and discussions, the Relationship team will then typically introduce finance teams to experts from particular product areas in the bank once a course of action is under consideration. When a product team has picked up the lead, Capital Structure Advisory steps back but continues to shadow the project, making sure that the eventual outcome meets the objectives that were set out in the opening discussions.</p>
<p>In terms of the funding strategies ultimately chosen by corporates, Lloyds offers a spectrum of options from straightforward loans to equity issuance. We explore these in more detail below.</p>
<h3 id="general-corporate-lending">General corporate lending</h3>
<p>Summarising Lloyds’ strategy in the general corporate lending arena, Wendy Whewell, Relationship Director, comments: “We are here to support businesses through the cycle, ensuring that we understand the issues that they are facing and to work with our customers to find the most appropriate funding solutions.”</p>
<p>Under the heading of general lending, Lloyds offers a number of different products:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Asset based lending, including confidential invoice discounting, factoring and leasing.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Asset purchases via asset finance, for example vehicle funding and technology financing, which can be used to purchase certain types of computer equipment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Traditional overdraft and term loan products.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Revolving credit facilities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Trade and supply chain finance.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Mark Stokes, trade finance is up 40% year on year as dynamic businesses explore new markets for their products and services. “We are seeing more opportunities to bring a wide range of international risk management and trade finance solutions to corporates.”</p>
<p>In addition, Lloyds works with its corporate clients to look more widely at their businesses in areas such as carbon emissions where clients are looking for funding in order to replace vehicles.</p>
<p>Beyond these offerings, the relationship team is a conduit to dedicated product expertise, such as Debt Capital Markets, Equity Capital Markets, Financial Markets Risk Management, Lloyds Development Capital and other specialist product teams. Relationship management provides Lloyds Banking Group’s customers with an easy and practical route to a significant array of financing solutions.</p>
<h3 id="debt-capital-markets">Debt capital markets</h3>
<p>The Debt Capital Markets (DCM) team enables its customers both corporate and financial institutions to access debt financing from the syndicated loan, private placement and bond markets. Rather than focusing on a specific debt product, members of the DCM team specialise by industry sector and provide expertise and lead transactions across a full range of products.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Syndicated loans.</h5>
<p>Lloyds is currently ranked the number one bookrunner for UK Investment Grade loans. (Source: Dealogic)</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>US Private Placement.</h5>
<p>Lloyds continues to deliver transactions on behalf of both debut and repeat issuers via its alliance with Bank of America Merrill Lynch, the long standing number one agent in the market.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Bonds.</h5>
<p>Lloyds has invested heavily in its bond capabilities and has become a lead player in both investment grade and high yield sterling issuance. The build out of its European coverage continues apace.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1-loan-market-overview-investment-grade">Chart 1: Loan Market Overview – Investment Grade</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-15-pp-chart-01-loan-market-overview-investment-grade.png"><img alt="Chart 1: Loan Market Overview – Investment Grade, pricing conditions improve" height="162" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-15-pp-chart-01-loan-market-overview-investment-grade-t.png" width="300"/></a>
<p class="source">Source: Lloyds, Dealogic</p>
</figure>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-2-loan-market-overview-investment-grade">Chart 2: Loan Market Overview – Investment Grade</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-15-pp-chart-02-loan-market-overview-investment-grade.png"><img alt="Chart 2: Loan Market Overview – Investment Grade, with longer tenors available" height="156" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-15-pp-chart-02-loan-market-overview-investment-grade-t.png" width="300"/></a>
<p class="source">Bubble size relates to Deal size</p>
</figure>
<p>The significant improvement in loan market conditions during 2010 has surprised most market commentators. “Competition for loan mandates is fierce again, which means that corporates are able to obtain facilities at tighter pricing and for longer tenors than was possible during 2009” comments David Cleary, Director, Corporate Debt Capital Markets. “If you are a strong multi-national corporate, then a five year maturity is now achievable on terms broadly in line with those seen in the market before the collapse of Lehman Brothers. This marked improvement will benefit corporates and enables bankers to underwrite M&amp;A facilities with confidence.”</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the US Private Placement market is on course for a near record-breaking year in 2010 with around $40 billion to issuance. Cleary reports strong interest from UK corporates in this market. “This year we’ve seen companies dip their toes in to the market to explore investors’ reception to their name/sector as they seek to reduce reliance on the loan market for their debt financing. They’ve typically issued around $150-300m, with a view to going back at a later date as when other debt facilities mature.”</p>
<p>Despite a promising start to 2010 and favourable conditions for UK issuers, volumes in the sterling bond market are lower than 2009. This is in part due to low M&amp;A activity and sizeable financings undertaken in 2009 by non UK corporates. “The markets are open and they’re crying out for supply from corporates, many of whom are currently watching from the sidelines. There is unmet investor demand and we expect a strong pipeline, particularly from high yield issuers in 2011,” comments Cleary.</p>
<p>In addition, Lloyds recently issued its own £75m retail bond that is quoted on the LSE’s retail bond platform. The expertise acquired during this process is being deployed to help corporate customers, particularly those with strong consumer recognition, to diversify their sources of funding and tap into pent up demand from retail investors.</p>
<h3 id="equity-capital-markets">Equity capital markets</h3>
<p>“Today the FD is going to have to look at a funding solution rather than a product,” says Robert Pierce. “The solution is going to encompass multiple products. And one of those products is likely to be equity, because the only way to keep your leverage under control is to have enough equity on your balance sheet.”</p>
<p>Lloyds provides advice and executes primary and secondary equity issuance as well as equity private placements. The services provided by the equity team can be summarised as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Market intelligence</h5>
<p>Analysing the risk appetite available in the marketplace and understanding what the markets are willing to do in terms of providing equity funding to any given issuer.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Expert advice</h5>
<p>On the equity component of the client’s financing solution and how it should be structured.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Underwriting rights issues.</h5>
<p>“Our clients appreciate the value of associating our name to their transactions; it is a reassuring signal to the investor community in terms of the balance sheet commitment that the bank is providing to an issuer,” says Pierce.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The equity team typically works with clients which are either looking to strengthen their balance sheets in order to support the business through a difficult period, or which are looking to finance growth, both organic and by acquisition. “We are seeing a shift from the recapitalisation repair of the balance sheet type transactions, which we saw a lot of last year, to companies that are looking to take the business to the next step, contemplating making an acquisition outside of the UK or into a different sector – in other words, taking advantage of the opportunity,” says Pierce.</p>
<h4 id="overview-of-the-equity-markets">Overview of the equity markets</h4>
<p>The IPO market so far in 2010 has been variable. Some public offerings have been successful, with others less so. A number of scheduled IPOs have been postponed or delayed because it was felt that the market was not ready for them.</p>
<p>“Investors have shifted their interest from the FTSE 100 to FTSE 250,” comments Robert Pierce. “Investor appetite has also shifted from helping corporates rebuild their balance sheets to helping companies to fund growth. But there is no certainty.”</p>
<p>“In the current market, we recommend to our customers to think about their strategy very carefully. They need to make sure that what they are planning to do is completely consistent with the strategy they have announced and with the key drivers of their business.”</p>
<p>“Another point is that these windows of opportunity open and close. Corporates need to be very well prepared and ready to pull the trigger on a transaction when the time is appropriate. It’s a combination of doing enough homework and communicating with investors.”</p>
<h3 id="outlook-for-2011">Outlook for 2011</h3>
<p>Across the industry there is continuing uncertainty regarding the likely direction of the funding market in 2011.</p>
<p>“There continues to be a lot of uncertainty with respect to the future,” says Robert Pierce. “If you go back to 2005 or 2006, I would say that on average, earnings forecasts for the FTSE 100 one year out were within a 5-10% range from the median. Today, earnings forecasts for the FTSE 100 are within a 20% range, or maybe more, on either side of the median. That tells you that we just don’t know where the economy is going.”</p>
<p>The range of analyst expectations for FTSE100 earnings remains wide:</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-3-ftse100-analyst-earning-estimate-spread">Chart 3: FTSE100 Analyst earning estimate spread</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-15-pp-chart-03-ftse100-analyst-earning-estimate-spread.png"><img alt="Chart 3: FTSE100 Analyst earning estimate spread" height="84" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-15-pp-chart-03-ftse100-analyst-earning-estimate-spread-t.png" width="300"/></a>
</figure>
<p>At the time of writing, Cleary comments “the loan market outlook for 2011 is one of ongoing strength and stability with fierce competition for lead mandates likely to prevail. However, there could be a shock within the Eurozone that would have far reaching consequences across the bank market. The US PP market has been a relative safe haven for investors during the financial crisis and we expect the current favourable issuance conditions to continue in 2011. Bond issuers will continue to look for relative value across the main dollar, euro and sterling markets and, assuming that Sovereign risk does not increase, the technical mismatch between low corporate supply and strong investor demand will result in the bond markets remaining open for issuers.”</p>
<p>“It will still be a tough year,” adds Wendy Whewell. It is worth noting that more businesses fail coming out of recession than going into recession. This is because there is a greater demand on business’s cash as they seek to make the most of the opportunities that are coming their way from either new contracts or competitors that have failed. It is important that businesses manage their cash and balance sheets to ensure that they can fund this growth.</p>
<p>In the context of continuing uncertainty, and with treasurers now willing to look beyond bank debt in order to meet their funding needs, there is likely to be continuing strong demand for a wider range of funding strategies and for advice which will help them to navigate the changing landscape. As such, the suite of funding solutions offered by Lloyds is well positioned to meet corporate treasurers’ needs.</p>

<h3 id="lloyds-banking-group">Lloyds Banking Group</h3>
<p>Lloyds Banking Group’s corporate business provides comprehensive expert financial services to businesses ranging from privately-owned firms to multinational corporations and financial institutions. As well as offering the expertise and capabilities our clients need to compete successfully in the marketplace, we are proud of the relationships we build with our customers. We work closely with them to understand their business and offer the best financial solutions to meet their distinctive needs.</p>
<p>The wide range of services and innovative solutions we can deliver includes;</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>dedicated relationship banking;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>capital market funding;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>debt and equity finance;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>treasury and risk management services;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>structured finance solutions;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>asset finance;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>leasing;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>company registration and employee share schemes;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>competitive e-trading facilities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>import and export trade finance;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>tailored cash management solutions; and</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>structured credit investments and securitisation facilities.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="contact-details">Contact details:</h5>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">David Cleary</dt>
<dd class="title">Director, Corporate Debt Capital Markets</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+44 (0) 20 7158 8251</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:david.cleary@lloydsbanking.com">david.cleary@lloydsbanking.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Michael McCartney</dt>
<dd class="title">Director, Capital Structure Advisory</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+44 (0) 20 7356 1761</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:michael.mccartney@lloydsbanking.com">michael.mccartney@lloydsbanking.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Robert Pierce</dt>
<dd class="title">Managing Director, Head of Equity Capital Markets</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+44 (0) 20 7158 1549</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:robert.pierce@lloydsbanking.com">robert.pierce@lloydsbanking.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Wendy Whewell</dt>
<dd class="title">Relationship Director</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+44 (0) 20 7661 4871</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:wendy.whewell@lloydsbanking.com">wendy.whewell@lloydsbanking.com</a></dd>
</dl>

<img alt="Lloyds TSB Corporate Markets" class="logo org" height="15" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/lloyds-tsb-corporate-markets-logo-2010-187x15.png" width="187"/>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2010-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Loans]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
