<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[How to think like a money market fund portfolio manager]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2022 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=97B46577D03907BF67E9393CFD5C24A0]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>In today’s rising interest rate environment, it can be tempting to lock-in yield – but making the wrong call can leave companies trapped in an unbreakable bank deposit, or in a difficult-to-unwind treasury position.  BlackRock’s Beccy Milchem and Matt Clay explain why it’s time for treasury teams to adopt the mindset of a money market fund (MMF) portfolio manager.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AE23879F9FAAC5319D4B90168B983039"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1E18B71E0DE64ACCA390DF7CFCD481BA"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B3AF85C685794C6DC53A9F1527A45D42"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=091A31437E4C0438FE3BD965D1D94F03"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8FAD9728E02346EC2B3FC8DB6EAF7C6E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Row of coins superimposed on a city background" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=97B46577D03907BF67E9393CFD5C24A0" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__double-exposure-city-rows-coins-finance-525525397__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=97B46577D03907BF67E9393CFD5C24A0"/></picture> </div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body">
<div class="vcard">
<img alt="Portrait of Beccy Milchem, Head of EMEA Cash Management" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__blackrock-beccy-milchem__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=3777F7F74B3913932197796A91E0F741" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Beccy Milchem, Head of EMEA Cash Management" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Beccy Milchem</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of EMEA Cash Management</h5>
<h5 class="org">BlackRock</h5>
<p><img alt="BlackRock logo" class="org" height="" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/blackrock-logo-2020__1252x178.png?la=en&amp;hash=D9047D0839D53238DD56617A07CF10AA" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="BlackRock logo" width="120"/></p>
</div>
<div class="vcard" style="clear:both;min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Matt Clay, Head of International Portfolio Management for Cash Management" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2022-07-08-tt-00-sf__blackrock-matt-clay__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=290DC6AFC667F8C3A3CA3B73B61BCDE4" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Matt Clay, Head of International Portfolio Management for Cash Management" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Matt Clay</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of International Portfolio Management for Cash Management</h5>
<h5 class="org">BlackRock</h5>
<p><img alt="BlackRock logo" class="org" height="" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/blackrock-logo-2020__1252x178.png?la=en&amp;hash=D9047D0839D53238DD56617A07CF10AA" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="BlackRock logo" width="120"/></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Central bank interest rates are finally on the rise following years of a low/zero interest rate environment.  For corporate investors, this is welcome news – but in practice, many treasury professionals have never experienced the current interest rate environment, which can make it challenging to know how best to proceed.</p>
<p>“There’s a lot of excitement from clients and investors as we move off the zero-yield environment for cash investing,” comments Beccy Milchem, Head of EMEA Cash Management at BlackRock.  “But the excitement can sometimes cause people to react very quickly – we’ve certainly heard from clients that are locking-in seemingly palatable yields on bank deposits.”  In today’s investment environment, she warns, it is “very easy to make the wrong call.”</p>
<p>As such, she argues, treasurers have much to gain by understanding how money market fund portfolio managers are looking at the current markets – and that means making the right choices on duration and liquidity, while making every effort to stay close to the markets.</p>
<h4 id="stay-short-on-duration">1. Stay short on duration</h4>
<p>Matt Clay, Head of International Portfolio Management for Cash Management at BlackRock, says there are two main components to consider when managing portfolios.  The first is the way in which the firm manages overnight liquidity that clients can access on a daily basis.  The second, more strategic part of the portfolio involves investing cash down the yield curve in investments such as commercial paper and certificates of deposit.</p>
<p>“Whenever we move through periods of uncertainty, we increase the liquidity and decrease the duration,” he explains.  “When we entered 2022, we were already in a period of relative uncertainty because of the central bank pivots, and the fact that we were now looking at rate hikes after a number of years of policy accommodation through central banks.”</p>
<p>In these circumstances, says Clay, “we take an opportunity to invest in shorter-term trades and increase that overnight liquidity” – an approach that builds in flexibility as interest rate hikes are delivered.  As well as allowing money market funds to be as nimble as possible when opportunities arise, this approach also ensures that fund yields increase quickly after an interest rate hike.</p>
<h4 id="dry-powder">Dry powder</h4>
<p>For treasury teams, the prospect of adding yield by buying a fixed term instrument or adding a fixed term deposit might look appealing in today’s market.  “But after a rate hike, the yield that they achieved a week or a month ago suddenly doesn’t look so good anymore,” warns Clay.</p>
<p>MMFs, in contrast, are positioned in short, overnight trades which provide the dry powder needed to capture any central bank or market pricing moves.  As Clay notes, “That’s the benefit of investing in portfolios like these: the yield evolves over time and rises into the new interest rate environment after a central bank has delivered a rate hike.”</p>
<p>Another feature of the current landscape is that in the past, interest rate hikes have been immediately reflected in bank deposits, whereas MMFs – which have some elements with longer duration – can take a few days to catch up.  Today, says Milchem, this lag effect has diminished, not least because the bank appetite for deposits has reduced: “One thing we’re seeing is that banks are passing on less proportionally as central bank rates rise.”</p>
<p>In addition, today’s treasury teams are better able to segment cash into different buckets and use the buckets of cash that aren’t needed for day-to-day use in a more strategic way, adds Milchem.  “Perhaps you’ve got some capital markets activity coming up in a period of time, and you can afford to lock-in a little bit more from a duration perspective,” she observes.</p>
<p>With further rate hikes expected, treasury teams need to assess the implications of adding duration carefully and make sure they understand their breakeven points, particularly if their investments take them beyond a key central bank date.  “It’s very important to work out which points on the curve you need to invest in to be compensated correctly for the risk that those rate hikes are delivered,” says Clay.  “These things are bread-and-butter considerations for my team.”</p>
<h4 id="dont-forget-liquidity">2. Don’t forget liquidity</h4>
<p>Liquidity is, of course, a critical consideration for treasury teams.  Term bank deposits are typically unbreakable, particularly with today’s current banking regulations – meaning that penalties must be paid if cash is accessed early.  As such, it’s important that companies consider their liquidity needs, and ask whether they are being fairly compensated for having a concentrated exposure to a single counterparty.</p>
<p>“With the market backdrop regarding the ongoing conflict in Ukraine, we are seeing credit spreads widen more than we have done over the last few years,” says Milchem.  “That’s something that investors need to be mindful of.”</p>
<p>In addition, she notes that some clients have been going into highly rated short-term government exposures.  These do offer significant liquidity – “we use them as a tool within pretty much all of our portfolios,” says Milchem – but spreads on these exposures have also been more volatile due to the recent dynamic market pricing.</p>
<p>Clay cites the example of a US Treasury bill, which is one of the most liquid instruments available in the money markets space.  With further rate hikes expected from the Fed and the Bank of England, he says, “There is a possibility that a trade available today won’t give you the return you want if you need to sell it to raise liquidity some weeks from now.  If yields move higher, the price of this asset will move lower.  Whilst a US Treasury bill is almost certain to return you par at maturity, if you need to sell that asset before it matures you will likely lose money.  Having a blended fund approach protects you from this single asset exposure and related mark to market risks.”</p>
<p>Money market funds, in contrast, are designed to catch up with the new interest rate environment.  “We’ll be investing into higher yields than were available a few weeks ago,” says Clay.  “You need a team of experts looking at this day in, day out to be ready to trade when opportunities arise – or not to trade if the timings aren’t right.”  He adds that the scale provided by a large fund manager means that companies can maintain access to liquidity in the event of geopolitical concerns translating into more meaningful risks.</p>
<p>On another note, Clay says that conviction is “incredibly important” for portfolio managers.  “While a safety first, liquidity first approach is more important, something that we’re always looking at is the level of conviction we have when we place trades.  If our conviction rate is low, that’s another way of saying we are less certain about future outcomes – so at certain points we’d almost rather see yields fall back a little bit but have a lot more conviction before using more of our risk budget.”</p>
<h4 id="stay-close-to-markets">3. Stay close to markets</h4>
<p>With markets moving quickly, it is all too possible that investors who are tempted to lock-in seemingly attractive yields could rapidly find themselves trapped in an unbreakable bank deposit, or in a treasury position that would be costly to shift.</p>
<p>In this environment, it is more important than ever to stay close to the markets.  “The market environment is tricky, and is evolving very rapidly,” says Clay.  As such, companies need to work with money market specialists who can maximise liquidity and access to cash, while providing the lowest possible level of volatility – “and also enjoy the new yield environment that we are in now.”</p>
<p>It’s clear that treasurers are paying attention.  Milchem says BlackRock is seeing greater demand for market-related content, with higher levels of attendance at the calls the firm provides focusing on cash markets.  She adds: “Where viable, treasurers should be focusing on their cash investment strategies on a daily basis – and if that’s not possible, consider working with a money market fund manager who has the necessary ability and resources.”</p>
<h4 id="walking-a-tightrope">Walking a tightrope</h4>
<p>In closing, Clay points out that central banks are currently walking something of a tightrope.  “You have the growth implications on one side, and inflation on the other, and central bank mandates are pretty clear in managing inflation risks,” he notes.  “Although at the moment the direction of yields has been one-way, there will come a point where things will change – and that’s when having a dedicated resource at your disposal will be critical.”</p>
<p>As such, he argues, investors should consider outsourcing to dedicated cash portfolio management teams who have experience of volatile interest rate cycles.  Finally, he advises that investors should sign up for market update calls such as those offered by BlackRock Cash Management, “and speak with a relationship manager about our latest portfolio positioning.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[SMA demystification: liquidity, flexibility and yield]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2022 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=89D450A354DFDF164142F28807FB54E5]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><img alt="Clearwater and Goldman Sachs Asset Management logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/clearwater-and-gsam-logo.png?la=en&amp;hash=F0477188EAE20D07488F41669FEBBB67" title="Clearwater and Goldman Sachs Asset Management logo" width="400"/></p>
<p><em>In a recent webinar, a panel of experts discussed how Separately Managed Accounts have evolved to offer corporate treasury teams bespoke cash management strategies that combine yield, liquidity, tilted ESG exposure and hands-on asset management expertise.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E7A78585E55A13055860CDF3D9A4EC15"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=00E03FA63C261E5A345C06742083BC8C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B0E6D368866104037362A7EE9510B57B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=697D04D3E35C10E4458DE4997B539E4C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=262139707701BB77F5867A253BF480E4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Server stand abstract background" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=89D450A354DFDF164142F28807FB54E5" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__stand-server-hardware-lighting-room-motion-729123634__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=89D450A354DFDF164142F28807FB54E5"/></picture> </div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Portrait of Will Nossier, Director of Group Treasury, Booking.com" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__gsam-cw__will-noissier__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=159E8127A85B4D8AE79A143E7C82C525" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Will Nossier, Director of Group Treasury, Booking.com" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Will Nossier</h3>
<h5 class="title">Director of Group Treasury</h5>
<h5 class="org">Booking.com</h5>
</div>
<div class="vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Portrait of Lauren Oakes, Global Co-Head of Liquidity Solutions Client Business, Goldman Sachs Asset Management" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__gsam-cw__lauren-oakes__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=31F9DDBF850BD6128F8A7FEA4E6EDE34" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Lauren Oakes, Global Co-Head of Liquidity Solutions Client Business, Goldman Sachs Asset Management" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Lauren Oakes</h3>
<h5 class="title">Global Co-Head of Liquidity Solutions Client Business</h5>
<h5 class="org">Goldman Sachs Asset Management</h5>
</div>
<div class="vcard" style="clear:both;min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Damien Cahill, Sales Director, EMEA Corporate division, Clearwater Analytics" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2021-12-14-tt-00-web__gsam-cw__damien-cahill__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=77BEADA747C7AF984A08700BE5868BD3" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Damien Cahill, Sales Director, EMEA Corporate division, Clearwater Analytics" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Damien Cahill</h3>
<h5 class="title">Sales Director, EMEA Corporate division</h5>
<h5 class="org">Clearwater Analytics&lt;</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p style="margin-bottom:2em;"><a class="button--red-stroke" href="https://view6.workcast.net/register?cpak=5043383718494560&amp;referrer=TTarticle" target="_blank">Watch on demand</a></p>
<p>Separately Managed Accounts (SMAs) have a reputation for complexity, but an increasing number of treasury teams are opting to invest in these bespoke vehicles. Speaking in a recent webinar, Lauren Oakes, Global Co-Head of Liquidity Solutions Client Business at Goldman Sachs Asset Management, Damien Cahill, Sales Director, EMEA Corporate Division at Clearwater Analytics and Will Nossier, Director of Group Treasury at Booking.com, leading global travel platform, explained how SMAs have evolved to offer treasury teams customisable liquidity solutions.</p>
<h4 id="evolution">Evolution</h4>
<p>One of the key reasons behind growing SMA take-up is market evolution. Corporate allocations to traditional MMFs have ballooned during the last decade, creating a launch pad from which treasury can confidently allocate to next-step SMAs. SMA use is also growing as more corporates, led by US treasury teams, hunt for yield on their cash in a low rate environment and consider bespoke exposure, especially on relating to ESG.</p>
<p>Today SMAs comprise of key pillars in a simplified product offering, explains Oakes. Custodians offer standardised paperwork for set up simplifying the onboarding process; asset managers like Goldman Sachs focus on providing the investment expertise and market access while partnerships with service providers like Clearwater Analytics have changed backend reporting, introducing the ability to monitor SMAs daily with on-demand performance analysis.</p>
<p>“The management of relationships, multiple agreements and the operational undertaking has historically put investors off the product,” says Cahill, explaining that Clearwater as a SaaS solution can remove the administrative and IT burden for treasury teams by working with its library of connections and custodians, asset managers, treasury management systems and enterprise resource planning applications. Typical onboarding time is four to six weeks. The Clearwater team take care of the data migration, including the coding of the chart of accounts, and can support multiple currencies and bases, as well as regulatory reporting such as IFRS9 and Solvency II.</p>
<p>SMAs differ from MMFs in some key areas, says Oakes. Assets in the SMA are owned outright by the investor; the investor chooses a manager to execute on specific objectives, benchmarks and timeframes and can opt for expertise around, for example, ESG alignment or currencies.</p>
<h4 id="education">Education</h4>
<p>Demand for SMAs has also grown with treasurers’ knowledge of the product. Treasury teams are better informed of the flexibility SMAs offer around the size of vehicle, and no longer view them simply as a high-yield product for longer-term cash allocations. Treasury teams are more aware that different maturity ladders of SMAs can ensure a constant flow of cash for withdrawal or reinvestment in an SMA: money can be available in just a few days and compliment any programme run in-house. An investor’s objectives are written into the Investment Management Agreement (IMA) by the investor and manager, customised to a specific mandate.</p>
<h4 id="ima">IMA</h4>
<p>Putting in place an IMA had its challenges when Booking.com began using SMAs, explains Nossier. However, the process was smoothed by the firm’s asset manager being on-hand to help set the risk profile, eligible assets and any specialist portfolio requirements for the company. Asset managers shape a bespoke balance sheet strategy around clients’ cash usage which informs allocations to issuers, sectors and decisions around credit quality, duration, and yield within the SMA, he says.</p>
<p>Treasury teams also need to think about restriction lists or parts of the policy that are a little more actively managed depending on a corporate’s evolving strategy. “It all ties back to the flexibility you can build into your SMA,” says Nossier.</p>
<p>Having the proper governance was also essential. It is why using tools offered by providers like Clearwater is helpful. Once a rules engine has been configured, alerts can be triggered upon detection of portfolio breaches which is useful for audit purposes.</p>
<p>Nossier concluded that the SMA structure allowed his treasury team to call on its asset manager during market turmoil in March 2020. “Back then it would have been challenging competing with institutional trading desks when attempting to sell positions,” he says. Fast forward to today’s potential rising rate environment and that relationship is just as important as the company seeks to align its SMA exposure with its conservative risk profile, drawing on hypothetical portfolio models and macro analysis proved by its asset manager.</p>
<p style="margin-top:2em;"><a class="button--red-stroke" href="https://view6.workcast.net/register?cpak=5043383718494560&amp;referrer=TTarticle" target="_blank">Watch on demand</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Cash flow forecasting]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2021 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=6AEEA3FDD54AA3F79962E0B669E725EB]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>The pandemic has made cash flow forecasting both more difficult and more important. For most businesses, the last year up ended plans and forecasts. For many bankruptcy looked perilously close. Banks initially struggled to assess risk amid such uncertainty. Only massive fiscal stimulus kept credit flowing. Good practices are more important than ever in cash flow forecasting. This article will look at the what, how and when of cash flow forecasting.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=43E737D97E65A1D2380CE428B45E8A8D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=635A040D5A238C873A867A236806C445"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7990596F4ADD5B8845CFEC0EFA0A90D4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A35E1441864027B4EC3B6171C4072A22"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DF62674CA2607BCACC89CEE9A8FABDD4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6AEEA3FDD54AA3F79962E0B669E725EB" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2021-03-04-tta-09-pv__telescope-view-overlooking-city-paris-78627187__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6AEEA3FDD54AA3F79962E0B669E725EB"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<h4 id="foundational">Foundational</h4>
<p>Cash flow forecasting is the bedrock of treasury. Treasury is fundamentally forward looking, and basically concerned with future cash flows which generate liquidity, foreign exchange, interest rate, credit and operational risks.</p>
<p>Without cash flow forecasts, treasury cannot operate. Without cash flow forecasts, the risks are unknown and risk management becomes impossible. Worse, practicing risk management without forecasts risks at best inflated costs and at worst added losses. For example, entering into foreign exchange forward contracts without properly understanding the underlying foreign exchange exposures risks increasing rather than reducing foreign exchange risk.</p>
<h4 id="what-how-when">What, how, when</h4>
<p>As with many business processes – only more so – cash flow forecasting processes must address what, how and when. What are we trying to achieve? How will we succeed? When should we do it (with what frequency)?</p>
<p>The what element requires clarity about the purpose for the cash flow forecast. The how element relates to the process design and the tools used. The when element is concerned primarily with frequency.</p>
<h4 id="what-means-objectives">What means objectives</h4>
<p>Simplifying, most businesses use three distinct cash flow forecasts:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>FX exposure forecast serves to capture FX exposures (however defined) across the group, so that they can be effectively hedged (however defined). This is often for a rolling 12 month period by legal entity by currency.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Rolling 12 month cash flow forecast serves to determine subsidiary and group level funding needs, so that these can be met cost and tax effectively. This is typically a rolling 12 month period by legal entity in functional currency.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cash positioning serves to ensure that individual bank accounts have just enough balance to cover upcoming payments and to minimise idle balances. This is typically daily for five to 30 days by bank account and currency.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>(For simplicity, I am ignoring the long-term or strategic forecast often for three to five years at group level.)</p>
<p>The FX exposure forecast (1 above) could logically be a subset of the rolling 12 month cash flow forecast (2 above). Many businesses plan and manage in functional currency, which means that the FX exposure forecast has to be a separate exercise.</p>
<p>Cash flow forecasts can also serve for reporting and control purposes, but the above are the key intrinsic treasury functional purposes which relate to capital structure and funding, risk management, and short-term cash management respectively.</p>
<p>In the latter instance, cash positioning can allow businesses to progress from ‘just-in-case’ cash balances to ‘just-in-time’ balances. This can produce material reductions in idle cash.</p>
<h4 id="granularity">Granularity</h4>
<p>A key issue with granularity is avoiding excessive demands on reporting entities. Too many treasuries seem to espouse the notion that more detail is better. They seem to ignore how much work this means for colleagues across the organisation.</p>
<p>In general, the guiding principle for granularity must be accountability. Granularity should be sufficient to enable treasury to identify whom to contact in case of anomalous variations – but not more. A simple example is to split internal vs external flows, since these are often handled by different teams. Another is to split direct and indirect procurement because often they are managed by different teams.</p>
<p>Another critical factor is what actuals are available. Cash flow forecasts more granular that what is available from actual (historical) reporting are basically unverifiable.</p>
<h4 id="when-means-frequency">When means frequency</h4>
<p>Frequency of cash flow forecasting also has to be modulated according to the utility of the information. Again it is a question of applying minimum work to generate maximum actionable information.</p>
<p>For example, in cash positioning, the 20% of bank accounts that generate 80% of flows should maybe report daily or twice a week. For most accounts, weekly forecasting should be sufficient. For less active accounts, monthly may be sufficient.</p>
<p>Most of the other two forecasts are most commonly monthly. In some businesses more regular updates might make sense.</p>
<p>Many businesses specify a materiality threshold for ad hoc updates ie when material new information arrives within the organisation. Ad hoc inputs are disruptive to the planning cycle but enable closer management of balances and risks. What constitutes material will vary between different businesses.</p>
<h4 id="how-means-tools-and-processes">How means tools and processes</h4>
<p>Although many geeks will want to use the latest gee whizz technology, in most cases technology choices should probably be predicated on more prosaic criteria.</p>
<p>Since cash flow forecasting in its various guises often requires input from teams across the business, not just treasury, the starting point should be what is already widely used at least within the finance community of the business.</p>
<p>To many this will mean Excel. However Excel, for all its flexibility and widespread use, is not a platform for operationally critical processes. Excel is wonderful for experimentation and exploration, but it lacks the sustainability and resilience of ‘proper’ systems based on distributed databases with robust access control and availability. More importantly, Excel solutions often rely on extensive copy pasting which is a minefield for unnoticed errors. Excel’s very flexibility is its Achilles heel because there is no data validation and no error correction.</p>
<p>For treasury, TMS will seem the logical choice but not all teams outside of treasury will be familiar with TMS, and using a system once a month is a recipe for frustration. ERPs – where usable for forecasting – are generally well supported at least in the finance function. BI platforms are similarly broadly used, and may thus be a good choice.</p>
<p>In general, the technology platform for cash flow forecasting should probably be based more on user accessibility than technical merit.</p>
<h4 id="ai">AI</h4>
<p>AI – or more prosaically machine learning (ML) – is being used for forecasting with some success and much fanfare by some businesses. Digging deeper almost always reveals that ML is only trusted with extensive human sanity checking.</p>
<p>In current times when COVID-19 has disrupted whatever was normal before the pandemic even for businesses who have weathered the crisis well, the limits of ML have been exposed. ML is based on extrapolating from historical data patterns. To the extent that historical data patterns have been invalidated by the pandemic, ML has limited utility – ML is basically a pattern matching game, when the patterns are no longer valid, ML’s magic evaporates. In true disruptions, wetware (aka humans) are the best predictors.</p>
<h4 id="scenarios">Scenarios</h4>
<p>In times of great uncertainty, best practice is to produce forecasts for different scenarios – normally optimistic, expected and pessimistic aka minimax scenarios.</p>
<p>Scenarios help businesses prepare for different possible outcomes, which is critical in times of disruption. Scenarios can help elucidate the true value of real options.</p>
<p>McKinsey recently wrote a pertinent piece on scenario based cash planning.</p>
<h4 id="sustainability-and-resilience">Sustainability and resilience</h4>
<p>Although more and more treasuries aim to contribute to growth and profitability, ultimately treasury is a risk management function whose role is to enhance the sustainability and resilience of the business.</p>
<p>Management sets strategy and tactics, and treasury ensures the business survives to deliver, by providing adequate but not excessive risk capital at optimal cost to support the business.</p>
<p>Cash flow forecasting in its various forms is critical to this role of treasury. Without good forecasts, treasury has to provide ‘just-in-case’ capital rather than ‘just-in-time’ capital, which is inefficient and costly.</p>
<p>Another aspect of resilience is to ensure that treasury can continue to support the business adequately even when processes such as cash flow forecasting are disrupted. BCDR (business continuity and disaster recovery) is a critical aspect of cash flow forecasting, since it is critical to the functioning of the business.</p>
<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>
<p>Cash flow forecasting has always been foundational to treasury, because treasury cannot manage risk without forward looking information, however imperfect it may be. The disruption brought by COVID-19 has made this priority even more clear. Pragmatic and functional approaches are essential to ensure treasury enables the business to thrive in troubled times without draining internal resources.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">David Blair, Managing Director</h2>
<div class="copy__body">
<img alt="David Blair, Managing Director, Acarate" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/perspectives/opinions/2018-01and02-tta-12-pv__david-blair__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=83E408EEC9F2F36A596A39CEE86EA5D6" style="float:right;margin:0 0 2em 2em;">
<img alt="Acarate logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/acarate-logo-2013-130x44.png?la=en&amp;hash=61B2AD6D73E50559482F937EE4100F9E"/>
<p>Twenty-five years of management and treasury experience in global companies. David Blair has extensive experience managing global and diverse treasury teams, as well as playing a leading role in eCommerce standard development and in professional associations. He has counselled corporations and banks as well as governments. He trains treasury teams around the world and serves as a preferred tutor to the EuroFinance treasury and risk management training curriculum.</p>
<p>Clients located all over the world rely on the advice and expertise of Acarate to help improve corporate treasury performance. Acarate offers consultancy on all aspects of treasury from policy and practice to cash, risk and liquidity, and technology management. The company also provides leadership and team coaching as well as treasury training to make your organisation stronger and better performance oriented.</p>
<p><a href="mailto:david.blair@acarate.com">david.blair@acarate.com</a> | <a href="http://www.acarate.com" target="_blank">www.acarate.com</a></p>
<p><em>The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors</em></p>
</img></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[How investors are ensuring they have sufficient liquidity in a time of crisis]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=0FFA07F8E88871252B38925E1B5C94EE]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>These are testing times for investors. What are treasurers with short-term portfolios doing to maintain the right levels of liquidity? Pia McCusker, Senior Managing Director and Global Head of Cash Management, State Street Global Advisors, explains how the market has evolved in recent weeks.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=87E23C3ACAA1DD736F564B6EE2C06650"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D4AC83AE309980A2DA6A2D65D20E253B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DAAFD2B3F70FD1496054D0E40076B5C6"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=862092D7776624F2B4D6A0D7A6025B44"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E3F329A9C2895A36798FE1B9EE4BC82C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Stacked coins with city and graph overlays" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0FFA07F8E88871252B38925E1B5C94EE" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__ssga__financial-investment-concept-double-exposure-city-1294175071__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0FFA07F8E88871252B38925E1B5C94EE"/></picture> </div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Pia McCusker, Senior Managing Director and Global Head of Cash Management, State Street Global Advisors" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2020-05-06-tt-02__pia_mccusker_150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F9A3894D9E65455EE60A2599920FE0EC" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Pia McCusker, Senior Managing Director and Global Head of Cash Management, State Street Global Advisors" width="150">
<h3 class="fn">Pia McCusker</h3>
<h5 class="title">Senior Managing Director and Global Head of Cash Management</h5>
<h5 class="org">State Street Global Advisors</h5>
<p><img alt="State Street Global Advisors logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/state-street-global-advisors-logo-2019-150x18.svg?la=en&amp;hash=F7D042EF438761B46F4A1EB05D66BB48" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="State Street Global Advisors logo" width="150"/></p>
</img></div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>March 2020 will be in the history books as one of the most turbulent on record for most of the planet. As the full realisation has hit home of what the COVID-19 pandemic means from a social and economic perspective, individuals and organisations alike have been justly concerned.</p>
<p>Whilst the healthcare emergency continues, and the economic impact is contemplated, corporate investors have taken stock and are now necessarily building cash cushions and raising liquidity in the capital markets, with many also drawing down credit lines to strengthen their cash buffers.</p>
<p>It’s perhaps not surprising then that in the US, our government money market fund rose from US$60bn to US$105bn in around four weeks. In an exodus from equities and other assets that exhibited something of a herd mentality, this tectonic shift was mostly new money too, with many investors exiting Prime funds in their flight to safety.</p>
<p>The trade-off to ensure essential liquidity at this time has inevitably been yield. However, at the beginning of March, even liquidity for US treasuries looked strained. It’s now clear that corporate treasurers have to start thinking about how best to manage liquidity with their eyes wide open.</p>
<p>Asset managers, certainly following recent regulatory reform in the US and Europe, are well-versed in stress-testing and scenario planning. But corporate treasurers now also need to be thinking along similar lines if their aim is to build a portfolio that meets their needs.</p>
<p>Where gaining incremental yield has been a driver, Prime portfolios were the corporate cash-bucket of choice for many. In highly stressed times, such as now, government funds have become the favoured lower-risk destination, hence the flight in recent weeks.</p>
<p>Indeed, with the apparent shift from Prime was not good for the fund, fund manager, nor for investors – treasurers have had to reconsider whether this is the cash-equivalent that really works for them right now, especially considering Prime (which invests in non-treasury floating-rate debt and commercial paper) has a credit component.</p>
<h4 id="full-facts">Full facts</h4>
<p>As ever, it’s a case of investing only when in possession of the facts and an understanding of the potential risks. Some do not. With State Street Global Advisors handling a significant number of client calls since March, it nonetheless came as a surprise that some investors still struggled to feel comfortable with a floating NAV fund, and that the concept of ‘breaking the buck’ is no longer applicable.</p>
<p>But this is perhaps understandable given the scale of MMF reforms implemented in 2016 in the US and 2018/2019 in Europe.</p>
<p>Fortunately, whilst some investors still exhibit signs of nervousness over core liquidity in the market, as evidenced by the growth in government funds, many now appear to be at a reflection point in terms of where their portfolios should be in the current phase.</p>
<p>Understandably, the hunt for yield still seems to be in abeyance, with treasurers not taking the risk of getting into credit or taking on longer tenors. Fund managers too have to be cognisant of the potential for a ‘second leg down’ scenario, in which the initial perception of liquidity risk could, if it continues, morph into credit risk. Deep trouble in the oil and energy sectors in recent weeks, for example, indicates that the threat is real for banks and corporates, and thus some funds, with deep exposures here.</p>
<h4 id="options">Options</h4>
<p>The choice of assets for investors with longer-term cash that do not share the herd-mentality may feel justified in allocating it to a Prime fund or an enhanced cash fund, knowing they can ride out the storm. There are a number of investments beyond a six-month tenor in high quality banks, where the pricing is still deemed advantageous, and these could still be in the mix.</p>
<p>Investors looking to protect their principal, and maintain liquidity, can still seek out government funds, but short duration and enhanced cash Prime funds are available; investors just need to be conscious of their credit component.</p>
<p>For investors in low volatility net asset value (LVNAV), where asset value cannot deviate by more than 0.2% from par, raised risk awareness is also required. For treasurers who understand and stress-test their cash flows, these can be worth considering if they want to participate in Prime or short-duration funds and they see a gap opening up between the two strategies.</p>
<p>Certainly, the current environment is difficult. But fund managers are keeping significant liquidity and remain prudent in terms of potential ‘second leg down’ risk. For State Street Global Advisors, the unprecedented market-wide stress seen in early March required no support from our fund parent. As such, our money market funds’ ideas and principles remain intact.</p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Data management and exploitation]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2019 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=9030662CE67BB71BB7296AA956C46223]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=ED9C88C7FE3B5FFC1127589DBFBCD2DA"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B93ACDBC65EEF9416E1B15652DBBDE30"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=ACDDAFF97D6C8A3C0DC7EB2753E813F8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F11C024AFC6EDF48E7749B7F2AA47781"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CDA4BA7B53B0EF0D8BF835F6521734ED"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="HSBC Thriving Treasury podcast series" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9030662CE67BB71BB7296AA956C46223" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/podcasts/hero__hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9030662CE67BB71BB7296AA956C46223"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>In this third episode of the <a href="https://treasurytoday.com/hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series">Thriving Treasury Podcast series</a>, brought to you by Treasury Today and HSBC, we explore the increasing importance of new technology – data analytics in particular – for treasuries as they look for ever greater insight into customers, competitors, operations and processes.</p>
<p>We speak to Suraj Kalati, HSBC’s Global Head of Liquidity &amp; Investments Product Management, who specialises in finding the right solutions for treasurers looking to turn data into actionable information to better manage working capital, liquidity and risk.</p>
<p>He explains how the mountains of data treasurers have normally kept in siloes – whether it be self-generated or from third parties, customers and supply chains – can now, with the help of new technology, be exploited to support good corporate decision making. </p>
<p>Corporate treasuries are highly unlikely to have the budget or inclination to build their own platform for warehousing and analysing data. Banks, however, can help by playing a vital role in helping them exploit data, says Kalati, pointing to areas such as benchmarking and forecasting. He also makes some interesting predictions on the impact data analytics will have on the treasurer’s role over the longer term. </p>
<p><a class="button-block button--red-stroke" href="https://treasurytoday.com/hsbc-thriving-treasury-podcast-series">Listen to the podcast now</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Live on-screen cash positions and ultimate real-time control for treasurers]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2017 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=D23AB90CA6C79C59C570CD02EF560E39]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=65BFB1F511CD7A6098378E886BAEA09A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=070366DD0D8D13D331F0D25D47B26DBE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5677151866D639A872A8DC07A617CE8F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3BF961CF4B1D235C228D8F9DB6BBE6AF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2DB3404BF8D7B5D4AEACF164AED6FA97"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Person on laptop typing" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D23AB90CA6C79C59C570CD02EF560E39" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/doubleexposureofbusinessmanhandworkingonblankscreenlaptopcomputeronwoodendeskasss306873251.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D23AB90CA6C79C59C570CD02EF560E39"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>Today, treasury teams want real time information about their cash positions at their fingertips. BNP Paribas’ new liquidity management module does exactly this, providing live on-screen consolidated cash positions from international subsidiaries and other entities in the kind of detail never before possible.</em></p>
<br/>
<div class="biography right vcard">
<img alt="Portrait of Laura Milani" class="photo" height="150" src="/i/2017/05/2017-05-06-tt-05-sf-laura-milani-100x150.jpg" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100">
<h3 class="fn">Laura Milani</h3>
<h5 class="title">Liquidity Management Marketing Manager</h5>
<br/>
<p><img alt="BNP Paribas logo" class="logo org" height="26" src="/i/logo/bnp-paribas-logo-2012-120x26.png" title="BNP Paribas" width="120"/></p>
</img></div>
<div class="biography right vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Portrait of Linn Birnbo" class="photo" height="150" src="/i/2017/05/2017-05-06-tt-05-sf-linn-birnbo-100x150.jpg" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Linn Birnbo</h3>
<h5 class="title">Strategic Cash Manager</h5>
<br/>
<p><img alt="GetInge logo" class="logo org" height="18" src="/i/logo/getinge-logo-2017-120x18.png" title="GetInge" width="120"/></p>
</div>
<br/>
<h4>New modules in Connexis<sup>®</sup> Cash centralise information and ease liquidity.</h4>
<p>Hard-pressed treasuries know a good thing when they see it. The increasing sophistication of dashboard control for company treasury is reaching breath-taking proportions and it is this kind of real-world innovation, born out of real customer need, that is truly raising the fintech bar. It’s become fashionable to assume that financial innovation is the domain of lean-and-mean start-ups, but sometimes it’s the larger players who have their ear closer to the ground.</p>
<p>BNP Paribas, one of the largest global banks, ranking among the top ten in the world by total assets, doesn’t trade its responsiveness to customers for sheer size. With the rollout of the new Liquidity Management Modules within its successful Connexis<sup>®</sup> Cash Management e-banking system, the buzz among treasury insiders is growing.</p>
<h3 id="familiar-interface">Familiar interface</h3>
<p>The new modules are seamlessly embedded in the familiar Connexis<sup>®</sup> interface, with no steep learning curve, fully tuned to treasury needs. And no software installation is necessary.</p>
<p>Already Connexis<sup>®</sup> gives treasurers multi-bank visibility and control over all accounts worldwide. Cash and treasury transactions are optimised: easy access to crucial information reduces idle cash and allows effective management of funding levels, while daily and intra-day visibility of cash positions and projected flows leads to better short term investment decisions and yield maximisation.</p>
<h3 id="full-overview">Full overview</h3>
<p>“Our customers tell us every day how easy the system is to implement and use, and this new functionality has just become part of the familiar day-to-day system,” says Laura Milani, Liquidity Management Marketing Manager, BNP Paribas.</p>
<p>This is certainly the case for one of the world’s leading global providers of products and systems within healthcare and life sciences. Getinge, based in Sweden, employs more than 15,500 people in over 40 countries, and recently made the decision to centralise the organisation and bring its diverse brands together under the Getinge name.</p>
<p>“It’s a challenging transitional phase we’re going through, and we’re appreciative of the help we get from our bank,” says Linn Birnbo, Strategic Cash Manager, Getinge.</p>
<p>“As a Nordic company, we’ve been used to different cash-pooling methods, but BNP Paribas has created a structure which works for us right across the world, and all in the same set-up. We have a full overview of all our operations in one place. It makes a big difference, and it’s helping us a lot.”</p>
<h3 id="live-on-screen-cash-positions">Live on-screen cash positions</h3>
<p>The new Liquidity Management Modules bring much needed transparency to cash concentration and intercompany lending operations.</p>
<p>Through the Cash Concentration Module, treasuries can now access live on-screen consolidated cash positions from international subsidiaries and other entities, and in the kind of detail never before possible.</p>
<p>This centralised reporting provides consolidated as well as detailed views on cash positions across regions. Booked, intra-day and projected transaction flows, as well as cash pooling sweeps are represented in real-time, and here’s the big advantage: the expected daily closing balance is updated and available at any time so that cash investment decisions can be fine-tuned, and any need for short-term financing can be identified.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Benefits checklist</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><ul class="checklist">
<li>Global visibility on cash.</li>
<li>Reduced idle cash.</li>
<li>Real-time visibility of cash positions and projected flows.</li>
<li>Optimised short-term investment.</li>
<li>Maximised yield.</li>
<li>Centralised cash and risk management.</li>
<li>Reporting of aggregate cash and liquidity positions across cash pools.</li>
<li>Integration of cash with short-term investment.</li>
<li>Monitoring and management of intercompany term loans.</li>
<li>Harmonised reporting and full transparency.</li>
<li>Direct access to reporting for managers and local treasury.</li>
<li>Customisable user profiles.</li>
<li>Audit trail of liquidity management across the Group.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<h3 id="keeping-track-of-intercompany-lending">Keeping track of intercompany lending</h3>
<p>The Cash Intercompany Module offers enhanced reporting to support intercompany lending and borrowing position monitoring, and administration, making it much easier to manage and track intercompany loans.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>
<p>The online treasury dashboard delivers full global cash position visibility and control. Centralised reporting provides consolidated as well as detailed views on cash positions across regions. Booked, intra-day and projected transaction flows as well as cash pooling sweeps are displayed in real-time, automatically updating the forecast daily closing balance available for cash investment or needing short-term financing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The module reports the consolidated lending and borrowing positions of accounts in a liquidity structure, as well as providing a drilled-down view on single account details. Standardised information is displayed real-time in one single location, eliminating fragmentation across banks and geographies.</p>
<p>Intercompany positions and intercompany account statements are updated intra-day in real-time. Indicative interest statements are updated daily, while display time can be adapted to suit the time zones of the accounts included in a treasury’s cash pool structures.</p>
<h3 id="settling-intercompany-interest-automatically">Settling intercompany interest automatically</h3>
<p>The Cash Intercompany Module does much more than this, however. A newly deployed feature caters for intercompany interest settlement between parties within the pool, where tax regulations allow it. All of this works automatically or, alternatively, payment flow information can simply be prepared, awaiting client go-ahead.</p>
<p>For the internal interest calculation, the client can instruct BNP Paribas to use fixed rates or market reference rates, with a stated margin. Different rates or margins can be set for different entities or accounts.</p>
<p>For Getinge’s Cash Manager, Linn, this automation is crucial when busy treasuries are up against the clock: “Month end is a critical time for us, when we only have a short time to close the book. There are only so many hours in a day, and the more things we can automate, life is made so much easier.”</p>
<p>“Settlements are fully automated. With no intervention needed from our side, the days of frantic last-minute calculations are finally over.”</p>
<h3 id="comprehensive-reporting">Comprehensive reporting</h3>
<p>Online reporting is comprehensive, and harmonised with systems across the bank, and there’s also a downloadable historical record.</p>
<p>With this up-to-the-minute information and detailed reporting, BNP Paribas is confident that decisions on moving cash around have never been easier. It’s a big step forward that could offer everything a busy treasury needs to help put company cash in the right place at the right time.</p>
<h3 id="uncompromising-security">Uncompromising security</h3>
<p>Security is not forgotten amid the innovation. Any information accessed through Connexis<sup>®</sup> is considered sensitive and uses an encrypted link to prevent eavesdropping, tampering and message forgery. The system also uses the secure principle of Single Sign On (SSO) where a user doesn’t have to re-authenticate to access every application within Connexis<sup>®</sup>.</p>
<p>The BNP Paribas security infrastructure also comes with a password generator for both authentication and validation of payments, as well as data encryption, allowing segregation of user access rights by service or by account.</p>
<h3 id="efficient-and-smart">Efficient and smart</h3>
<p>BNP Paribas and its Cash Management division work closely with company treasurers to improve services and products and reinforce the bank’s claim to be at the cutting edge of innovation.</p>
<p>“Our work is far from finished. We’ll be listening to customers so that we can continue to be at the forefront of liquidity management,” says Laura.</p>
<p>Linn goes along with that: “BNP Paribas is showing us that they’re committed to developing systems with flexibility and functionality, customised to our needs.”</p>
<p>“We look for efficient and smart solutions from a bank. BNP Paribas gives us just that.”</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Cash management: a firm commitment to cash</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Through its local presence on all continents, BNP Paribas provides cash management services to more than 40,000 corporate clients worldwide. A community of 2,500 experienced and committed cash management professionals operate across BNP Paribas’ international network, in 208 business centres in 55 countries, covering more than 130 currencies.</p>
<p>Along with a streamlined international payments and foreign currency offering, BNP Paribas offers its clients customised liquidity management solutions, enhanced collections efficiency and a wide range of global and local connectivity and reporting services.</p>
<p>BNP Paribas was designated No. 1 Cash Management Bank in the European large corporate sector, in the latest Greenwich Associates survey.</p>
<p>For more information, please visit our website: <a href="https://cashmanagement.bnpparibas.com" target="_blank">cashmanagement.bnpparibas.com</a></p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[A smooth flow]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jul 2016 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=A1A124BED1BB3E675B31B42483269EC7]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9430847E521AD3E7B481D3668B42B68A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5E31899FBED368DF9B1EFD3BF5C4F25C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2252CEBE673ACE24B31C17298D015E2E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B45D800944B0C29C873033ABACB1B1E4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=467913E77021FEC3928983DEF6F47FF8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Abstract waterfall flowing down" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A1A124BED1BB3E675B31B42483269EC7" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2016-07-08-tta-11-cm-abstract-water-flow-waterfall-and-light-427661947__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A1A124BED1BB3E675B31B42483269EC7"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>An accurate cash flow forecast is a must for every treasury organisation. In fact, it is the fundamental piece of information on which all treasury decision making is based, and an inaccurate forecast can (and probably will) have a detrimental impact on treasury and business performance. Nevertheless, corporates around the world frequently cite cash flow forecasting, and achieving sufficient visibility over their cash more broadly, as being a key challenge.</em></p>
<p>For many organisations, the inadequacies around cash flow forecasting were brought to the fore in the wake of the global financial crisis (GFC). At this time, corporate boards turned, in the midst of the market chaos, to their finance function to find out how much cash they had and their exposures. Unfortunately, many treasury and finance functions simply could not deliver this information quickly and accurately.</p>
<p>Since then, the focus on liquidity management has grown as corporates in the region have looked to effectively manage the significant cash piles that were built up in the aftermath of the crisis. In more recent years, the economic uncertainly, evolving regulatory landscape and the growing scale and complexity of businesses across the region has made achieving an accurate and timely cash flow forecast a mainstay at the top of the treasurer’s priority list.</p>
<h3 id="where-is-my-cash">Where is my cash?</h3>
<p>“Achieving an accurate cash flow forecast is the Holy Grail,” says Jeffrey Ngui, Head of Regional Sales, Cash Management, BNP Paribas. “But attaining this remains elusive for many of the region’s corporates.” At a fundamental level, this is because simply gaining visibility over cash on hand can be challenging – let alone predicting future cash flow.</p>
<p>There is a good reason for this. “Banking in Asia Pacific (APAC) is more fragmented – due to disparate infrastructures and regulatory environment – when compared to the US and Europe,” adds Ngui. “Banks like ourselves have invested to ensure that we are able to utilise all the data we have for the benefit of our clients’. For instance, we can provide information around our clients account balances across the world, in real-time and through a single channel which is flexible to match their technological capabilities.”</p>
<p>But this isn’t the case with all financial institutions. And whilst corporates may be able to obtain real-time visibility from the global and regional banks, this is not often possible when dealing with the smaller, less technologically advanced local banks – some of which do not offer basic tools such as an online banking platform or SWIFT connectivity.</p>
<p>In fact, the Cashfac Operational Cash Index, which recently surveyed corporate treasurers in APAC, supports this comment, as almost two-thirds of the corporates interviewed were unable to view their cash positions in real-time. “Of those who said they have a real time consolidated view of their cash, only an average of 54.8% said that all of their cash was visible in real-time,” says Alastair McGill, Managing Director, Global Business at Cashfac. “This leaves the rest of the cash to be consolidated manually in order to achieve a complete view of cash positions.”</p>
<p>Echoing Ngui’s comments, McGill highlights that the main reason for this is that the “number of transactional service relationships represents a complex management challenge for treasury functions.” That being said even those corporates with less complex banking arrangements – like those in Malaysia, who on average only use three banks, also struggle – and in the case of Malaysia have less visibility than their peers in Singapore and Hong Kong.</p>
<h3 id="seeing-clear">Seeing clear</h3>
<p>To overcome this challenge, some corporates have looked to centralise their treasury activities, pooling cash into core operational accounts where possible and in some cases establishing in-house bank and on-behalf-of structures.</p>
<p>Cashfac’s McGill also outlines virtual accounts, or to be more accurate, virtual bank technology platforms, as being a potential solution to this challenge. “Virtual accounts have historically been one mechanism that corporates have used to inject accuracy and timeliness into their cash management processes,” he explains. “Today, virtual accounts have been surpassed by broader and more complete virtual bank technology platforms which harness advances in workflow, integration, matching, analytics and real-time reporting via functionally rich virtual accounts to provide greater flexibility, customer self-service.”</p>
<p>In this set-up, expectations of payments and receipts can be pre-populated against individual accounts so when money movements occur they are automatically reconciled against the expectations and an accurate real-time view maintained. This can also be connected to multiple banks through various channels to again enhance visibility and accuracy around cash flow forecasting – albeit around a limited scope of data fields.</p>
<h3 id="communicating-the-importance-of-cash-flow">Communicating the importance of cash flow</h3>
<p>Yet, with these solutions still not widely used, corporates continue to have a lack of visibility over their current cash positions. As a result, treasurers are already at a disadvantage when it comes to creating an accurate future prediction of future cash flow. Unfortunately, the task doesn’t get any easier and as many treasurers can attest to, obtaining the required information for predicting future cash flow can be even more challenging than getting visibility over current cash. The key to this being that the necessary information resides in other business units and, all too often, these functions sit in siloes where communication with treasury is minimal.</p>
<p>This is a challenge that Russell Phillips, Head of Treasury, Asia Pacific at British American Tobacco (who outlines how his treasury has created a robust cash flow forecasting process see page 34) knows only too well. “There are many moving parts and stakeholders involved in the process – and it becomes more complex the larger and more diverse the business,” he says. “Also, many of these stakeholders in the individual business units do not see delivering a direct cash flow forecast as a key competency and deliverable in their role.” And if inaccurate or incomplete information is provided then this will lead to inaccurate forecasts and a subsequent incorrect assessment of cash needs by treasury. This can be a major risk for the entire company.</p>
<p>There is a requirement from the treasurer therefore, to make sure that the business units understand what the treasury is asking for and why it is so important that it is done correctly. “Education and clear communication is vital in achieving this,” explains Phillips. “Treasury needs to go out into the end market and ensure that they are very clear about what treasury is asking them to do. A benefit case will also have to be presented because without it you won’t change behaviour.” Phillips also highlights that senior management buy-in can also be key in changing behaviour across the organisation.</p>
<h3 id="the-role-of-technology">The role of technology</h3>
<p>Whilst it is important that treasury communicate the significance of cash flow forecasting to the business, this is only one step on the way to improving the accuracy of the forecast. Once the information is received from the business units it needs to be consolidated. This, historically, has been a highly manual and cumbersome task which ultimately leads to errors.</p>
<p>“Cash flow forecasting, for the time being at least, still requires some manual work given that data collection involves multiple stakeholders – even with best-in-class systems,” explains BNP Paribas’ Ngui. “But, technology can add efficiency to the process.” He outlines that corporates can use their TMS or ERP system to improve the cash flow forecasting process. “Work for the treasurer will be greatly reduced if data input can be automated,” he adds. “The analysis, modelling and continuous management of the process becomes more effective as a result.”</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>Cash flow forecasting, for the time being at least, still requires some manual work given that data collection involves multiple stakeholders – even with best in class systems.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Jeffrey Ngui, Head of Regional Sales, Cash Management, BNP Paribas</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Even if a company has constraints in technology investments, Ngui believes a well-constructed, well-defined and well-managed spreadsheet can still be an effective tool for treasurers to manage the information. “This data can then be uploaded into a TMS or ERP system which can automate the consolidation process and check this against the data that already sits in the system to eliminate errors and flag up anomalies,” he adds. “The analysis, modelling and continuous management of the process becomes much easier as a result.”</p>
<p>However, most corporates in the region still rely on spreadsheets as the sole tool to compile their cash flow forecasting and have very little automation. A recent study on FX by Deloitte highlighted this fact. “Thirty-five percent of corporates in the region didn’t use a TMS to manage their FX,” says Koh. For those that did, the vast majority focused on the operational elements and very few invested in technology to capture exposures. “Corporates need to reconsider this focus and spend another dollar to more effectively forecast and capture exposure,” adds Benny Koh, Managing Director – Treasury Advisor at Deloitte.</p>
<h3 id="guessing-games">Guessing games</h3>
<p>When the complexity around gaining visibility over cash is combined with the difficulty in receiving accurate and timely information and added to the burden of consolidating this, cash flow forecasting turns into somewhat of an (educated) guessing game.</p>
<p>“As it stands, many treasurers are faced with a poor set of numbers that they can’t operate effectively on,” says Koh. “Treasury, by its very nature, is a risk aware business and as a result, it is typical for it to use conservative estimates around cash in hand and utilise buffers around predicted cash flow.” And this can come at a cost. “A treasurer may not invest all its cash on hand, leaving idle pools sitting in low-interest bearing accounts around the world,” he explains. “Alternatively, they may invest too much and then have to draw on credit lines and incur interest charges. Consequently, treasury is left with a forecast that lacks clarity and contains numbers that cannot be trusted.”</p>
<p>Whilst, on an individual basis, these may be minor costs, sizeable and unexpected losses may also occur as a result of inaccurate cash flow forecasting. Take large FX hedging contacts, for instance. If the forecast is significantly wrong, treasury may be hedging a position that does not exist. This will expose the business to trading and open positions that are not backed up by real business flows.</p>
<p>Of course, achieving 100% accuracy in a forecast, especially for the longer-term view, is probably unrealistic. But that being said, it is clear that treasurers need to do more to increase accuracy and they need support from their banking partners, technology providers and the business units to do this.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, as British American Tobacco’s Phillips outlines on the previous page, with a mixture of internal endeavour when communicating with business units and the smart, yet not always complex use of technology, corporates are able to achieve high degrees of accuracy over their cash flow forecast.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Case study</h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">Best practice cash flow forecasting: The British American Tobacco way</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><img alt="British American Tobacco" height="51" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/british-american-tobacco-logo-2004-90x51.png?la=en&amp;hash=5DDCF38A7189D9BA3A73D118F18CD210" width="90"/></p>
<p class="management-summary">Here, Russell Phillips, Head of Treasury, Asia Pacific at British American Tobacco (BAT), outlines how his treasury have been able to tackle the discussed challenges and achieve greater accuracy over its cash flow forecast.</p>
<p>When the global financial crisis hit in 2008, BAT was one of many companies that found their cash flow forecast, and the process that supported it, was not good enough to deliver the information required in a timely fashion. Back then, data had to be pulled from numerous sources, all of which used different Excel templates. This was then manually consolidated before being presented to senior management.</p>
<h3 id="a-solid-process">A solid process</h3>
<p>After 2008, BAT were given the mandate to deliver a more accurate and timely forecast. The treasury set about developing a robust process that would deliver a medium-term (18 month) monthly multi-currency forecast and a short-term (one month) daily forecast. “The short-term forecast is for daily cash management purposes, and all companies will need this,” he says. “The medium-term is for forecasting our funding needs and supporting our FX risk management.”</p>
<p>With the objectives clear, and standardised forecast templates created, treasury then had to tackle the challenge of conveying the importance of an accurate cash flow forecast to the business units. “Education, communication and achieving management buy-in is critical at this stage,” say Phillips. “Those providing the reports need to be very clear about what you are asking them to do and they also have to see the benefit for putting in the extra work.”</p>
<p>When doing such a project it can be easy to get quick wins. But, as Phillips points out, it can be just as easy for business units to slip back into bad habits. To limit the risk of this happening the treasury implemented a feedback loop to ensure that standards are maintained and to continuously drive for improvement. “It is vital to transform the perception of cash flow forecasting (CFF) and make it a key deliverable for the business units,” adds Phillips. “The aim is to create a cash conscious culture in the business.”</p>
<p>Treasury must not to be dogmatic in its approach. This was a key learning for BAT who initially set out to achieve 95% accuracy over its one month forecast. “Very few business units were able to achieve this despite the work they were putting in,” he explains. Not only was this discouraging, it also caused some unintended consequences, such as payments being delayed in order to hit the forecast target. As a result of these factors, BAT reduced the accuracy target to 85%. “We concluded that for what we wanted to achieve, the difference between 95% and 85% accuracy was an acceptable trade off versus the extra effort and resources required to get there.”</p>
<h3 id="the-technology-factor">The technology factor</h3>
<p>Once the information has been received it has to be consolidated and transformed into actionable intelligence. And Phillips is keen to highlight that complex technology is not always needed to do this.</p>
<p>“Initially we used a basic consolidation tool to complete our CFF,” he explains. “And we were able to achieve numerous value add benefits.” Phillips explains that on the FX side the treasury was able to copy and paste the information into an Excel model which calculated the data and suggested what hedges should be used in accordance with target hedge ratios within BAT’s FX policy. In more recent years BAT have migrated its CFF to SAP. “We have been able to take the standardisation and automation of our CFF to the next level as a result,” explains Phillips. “Our short-term forecast has been fully automated, whilst the medium-term forecast is now consolidated in SAP. We are then able to execute hedges using an online dealing platform which is integrated with SAP.”</p>
<h3 id="central-benefits">Central benefits</h3>
<p>The benefits of this project for BAT were multiple. Primarily the treasury was able to use the forecast for more effective decision making. “More confidence in the forecast allows the treasury to make bolder decisions in terms of group financing, for instance issuing less debt can lead to substantial interest savings,” says Phillips. “We can also be confident that we are reducing volatility by hedging currency exposures.”</p>
<p>In addition to this, the ability to create an accurate cash flow forecast allows the treasury to make a more fundamental change. “Treasury has been leading the way centralising and standardising over the past decade, and now the rest of the finance function is also aggressively standardising,” he says. “This has included leveraging financial shared services to do the transactional activity, allowing the business units to focus on their core function. We now have a centralised treasury shared service centre based in Bucharest. Without the accurate and automated cash flow forecast giving visibility to the centre, we would not have been able to achieve this organisational structure.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Show me the money]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Oct 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=2CE2E930B87D5752F478011543ABA449]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>In recent years, survey after survey has shown ‘improvements to cash visibility’ to be near the top of the corporate treasurer’s wish list. Achieving that desired level of visibility, however, seems always just out of reach. Why are companies still finding it tricky to get proper visibility over their cash? Is technology always the answer or should treasurers be thinking about more fundamental changes? In this article, industry experts give us their take on this perennially thorny issue.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AEE70E7E7A477C6888DF3FC5EC4AA350"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=54C6D5F6B1C293BF2F375280C9205115"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8335AA46B8F942B3A8F2A0091094CA63"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5B248AC0D78443405928D7AA6FA026C3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=10EC8857666EA9AD4BAD3CD0B72BF9FC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Person holding multiple coins in both hands" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2CE2E930B87D5752F478011543ABA449" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm-hands-holding-money-ss283016375__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2CE2E930B87D5752F478011543ABA449"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>Treasurers have one overriding strategic priority at the moment. Put simply, it is to get a better view of their day-to-day cash balances across the business.</p>
<p>In the second edition of Bank of America Merrill Lynch’s Asia Pacific Treasury Barometer Survey, published in late May, improving visibility of balances and cash forecasting was the most cited (21%) priority of treasurers for the year ahead. Moreover, according to a March 2015 online poll by cloud-TMS providers Kyriba and the ACT, improving cash forecasting was cited as a priority for 39% of the 303 treasurers from global companies surveyed. This may not be so surprising to many in the industry. Cash visibility, if not number one, usually comes near the top whenever treasurers are asked about what they are focusing most on improving. And rightly so. Failure to achieve sufficient visibility over the company’s cash carries significant risk. In fact, without clear visibility, companies cannot adequately control group cash. In turn, this means they cannot use that cash at optimum efficiency, or maximise investment opportunities for it. Reducing borrowing costs and improving foreign exchange (FX) risk management will also be extremely challenging without full visibility and control.</p>
<p>Why the increased focus of late though? Perhaps, ponders Glen Giffen, Director of Sales at Visual Risk, it has something to do with recent corporate balance sheet trends. As we are reminded by industry study after study, corporate balance sheets have ballooned across the globe since the 2008 global financial crisis. Recent figures from Moody’s reveal that the cash holdings of companies in Europe, the Middle East and Africa have risen 69 per cent in euro terms since 2008. In US dollar terms, the total cash held by EMEA companies was $1.06trn at the end of 2014, slightly lower than $1.13trn at the end of 2013.</p>
<p>“There is a lot of cash on corporate balance sheets,” says Giffen. “Treasurers are naturally focusing more of their efforts on managing that excess cash than they have had to in the past. And if managing surplus liquidity is a much bigger feature of your day-to-day job, then cash visibility is obviously going to come into much greater focus than perhaps it has in the past. Moreover, credit and counterparty concentration risk becomes a huge concern so understanding and managing this effectively becomes a big part of the cash visibility story. For example, what is the impact on cash and investment holdings if the credit quality of a counterparty deteriorates?”</p>
<h3 id="cutting-through-the-fog">Cutting through the fog</h3>
<p>What corporate treasurers want, at the base level, is to be able to get a snapshot of all the cash across the organisation, together with the details of any transactions that are forecast to be made throughout the day; and they want to be able to obtain all of this information in an efficient manner. That way, when they arrive at their desks in the morning they are able to anticipate whether the company will have, come the end of the day, a surplus of cash that will require investing or a shortfall that will necessitate some form of borrowing.</p>
<p>Yet the fact that improving cash visibility is still listed by so many treasurers as a top priority would suggest that, despite the apparent simplicity of what they want, initiatives designed to provide them with it have so far only seen mixed success. Why does the optimal level of visibility seem, for so many, still out of reach?</p>
<p>Industry commentators each have their own take on why this might be. “The treasurers that we talk to are typically under-resourced and frequently wrestle with the challenge of accessing data in a timeframe that allows them to make informed decisions,” says Alastair McGill, Managing Director, Global Business at Cashfac. The issue stems from the fact that despite the increasing sophistication one sees in the sorts of technologies implemented by multinationals at the top end, for the vast majority of companies these activities remain heavily reliant on manual input. In emerging markets, such as those found in Asia, this can be especially troublesome given the geographic regional spread, the multiple currencies, multiple time zones and the multiple banking relationships companies typically maintain.</p>
<p>“For the treasury function, identifying real-time balances of cash across these dispersed operations and across different bank relationships remains a considerable challenge,” says McGill. Indeed, the Cashfac Operational Cash Index, which recently surveyed corporate treasurers in Asia Pacific reveals that almost two-thirds of corporates in the region do not have access to a real time view of their transactions and cash. “This is a worrying statistic,” he adds.</p>
<p>Thomas Knudsen, Senior Manager in the Treasury team at PwC believes that, fundamentally, the issue comes down to the structure of corporate banking relationships. “Often it depends on which banks a company uses,” he says. “In some developing markets you find that your core relationship bank(s) might not be able to support you for the local services that you need. So while you can get reasonably good visibility with an international bank, you might still need to use other, smaller and less capable banks, some of which might not be connected to a banking network like SWIFT.”</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Treasury priorities 2015</h4>
<a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm__chart-01__treasury-priorities-2015__1797x852.png?la=en&amp;hash=8009A835C5CE5D88F31CD36E23E45E3C" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: Treasury priorities 2015" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2015-10-tt-09-cm__chart-01__treasury-priorities-2015__1797x852.png?la=en&amp;hash=8009A835C5CE5D88F31CD36E23E45E3C" width="967"/></a>
<p class="source"><em>Source: Bank of America Merrill Lynch Treasury Management Barometer Survey 2015</em></p>
<p>In fact, some banks in some countries won’t even provide you with an electronic banking platform of any sort, adds David Stebbings, Head of Treasury Advisory at PwC. “That means, in some instances, you have to be more manual,” he explains. “You have tiers of standards around how you do these things depending on what country you are in. That is why there is no one-size-fits-all solution. There are different ways of addressing the issue and what you do will depend on your cost benefit analysis and the banking infrastructure in that part of the world.”</p>
<p>What is clear though is that centralised treasuries with fewer bank accounts have a distinct advantage over those with more decentralised structures when it comes to the issue of cash visibility. Getting that visibility over banking infrastructures – and in an efficient manner – is never easy for those that must wrestle with a multitude of security tokens, logging into multiple banking interfaces and extracting the required data manually. In fact, as McGill explains, even having done this many times, treasurers will still not have the full picture “as the bank account data showing balances and historic transactions makes no allowance for the imminent expected receipts and payments, or those that should have been credited or debited but for whatever reason failed to materialise.”</p>
<p>The results of the Cashfac Operational Cash Index supported this notion showing that among those corporates with a real-time view, on average less than 60% of their total cash and ongoing transactions was visible in real time. That leaves the remaining balance being consolidated manually in order to achieve a complete view of their positions. As such, it’s rare for most firms to have complete real-time cash visibility at an operational level that allows treasurers to effectively maximise the treasury tools at their disposal; sweeping and pooling strategies, for example, could all be enhanced if the real-time view of cash was better understood.</p>
<p>One way in which firms can gain better visibility of operational cash is to exploit Client Managed Accounts where the bank account infrastructure remains bank-connected but resides under the corporate’s control; either deployed as an in-house system or as a bank-provided service. Client Managed Accounts are simply an evolution of the virtual account model, where corporates have the scope to determine their account structures; mapping them to their business requirements and establishing the rules that determine their behaviour. The way in which money is routed when it hits the main account can be predetermined and automated.</p>
<p>Expectations of payments and receipts can be pre-populated against individual accounts so when money movements occur they are automatically reconciled against the expectations and an accurate real-time view maintained.</p>
<p>Where companies are multi-banked the same principles can apply, connecting multiple banks to a single set of Client Managed Accounts is less of a challenge than most assume. Either via direct connectivity channels or through industry initiatives led by organisations like SWIFT, there are plenty of options that can be deployed to make life simpler and accelerate the aggregation of balance and transaction data.</p>
<h3 id="forecasting-inaccuracies">Forecasting inaccuracies</h3>
<p>Visual Risk’s Giffen believes there may be another factor preventing treasurers from attaining that desired level of visibility: the accuracy of cash flow forecasting. Corporate cash balances, it probably goes without saying, are never static. Throughout the day, money will flow in and out of a business altering each time the company’s cash positon. For treasurers then, it is simply not enough to have visibility over cash at certain intervals. They need to be able to see what is coming down the line.</p>
<p>This is where analytical software comes into play. Solutions like these can help the treasurer to identify the key risks that might lead an organisation to deviate from a forecast. This allows a stress test to be performed where the treasurer can analyse how a particular market risk – currency or energy price volatility, for example – might impact cash flow projections.</p>
<p>The degree of sensitivity to such market risks will vary between companies, for reasons that are not difficult to understand. A manufacturing company that is exporting 100% of the goods it makes will, naturally, have a much higher sensitivity to movements in the currency markets than another manufacturer that only exports, say, 5% of its goods. Similarly, a soft drinks company is going to find its cash flows to be highly sensitive to the price of sugar, especially if it is unable to alter the price of its products.</p>
<p>“What if there is a product issue that means not all of the investments the treasurer holds can be liquidated at current market rates?” says Giffen. “What if a particular currency or central bank interest rate moves in an adverse way? Visual Risk has always been very strong in sensitivity analysis.”</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>I think a move to systems-based solutions is really the first step. Because at this point in time a lot of the cash processes we see out there are incredibly inefficient. It can take an inordinate amount of time just to arrive at a simple end of day cash position.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Glen Giffen, Director of Sales, Visual Risk</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Technology quite evidently has a significant role to play for treasuries determined to optimise the visibility they have over their cash. The greatest advantage systems-based solutions offer is the time saved, adds Giffen: “I think a move to systems-based solutions is really the first step. Because at this point in time a lot of the cash processes we see out there are incredibly inefficient. It can take an inordinate amount of time just to arrive at a simple end of day cash position.”</p>
<h3 id="still-top-priority">Still top priority</h3>
<p>As we have seen, the issue of cash visibility is inextricably linked to two perennial pursuits for the treasurer, centralisation and the quest for process efficiencies through the harnessing of technology. Experts seem to agree, however, that while structural or organisational solutions are certainly helpful, there is nothing quite like the power of technology when it comes to improving cash visibility.</p>
<p>And now, with an ever-growing range of sophisticated and – thanks to the cloud, increasingly affordable – technologies on the market, those treasurers who say improving cash visibility is their top priority for the year ahead should have the means at their disposal to help realise that objective.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Re-engineering cash flows]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Sep 2014 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=0C5C890D5C5578CDFBC21D2C1278A7BD]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=469ADD41F1B3AE8047832D8AD2F88BF2"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B61F8F23D30D6944D9FC7F5E2FC91386"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3624B6D559E943E8FFD21455B8EF0389"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=04E543D3C6E72D21212CCD5986695899"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AF70E86DCCA416A702DCB352427AC87C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Super streamlined train in Milan central station" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0C5C890D5C5578CDFBC21D2C1278A7BD" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/super-streamlined-train-in-milan-central-station-210145885.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0C5C890D5C5578CDFBC21D2C1278A7BD"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The next time one of your treasury peers tells you that managing cash flows are not a significant challenge for his or her company, there is a good chance they are either bending the truth or simply disconnected from reality.</p>
<p>According to research published by American Express Global Corporate Payments, 95% of businesses say cash flow continues to be a major priority in 2014. The same study found that 93% of businesses were experiencing delays in getting paid by their customers. Now, that’s no minor issue.</p>
<p>That most corporates face an uphill battle in managing their cash flows is not news in itself. The interesting question is why do companies experience these difficulties – especially in the age of technology and automation? What is more, how can companies ‘re-engineer’ their cash flows and transform their working capital position without starting completely from scratch, or interrupting day-to-day business?</p>
<h3 id="lifeblood-of-the-company">Lifeblood of the company</h3>
<p>The importance of cash flows to the long-term success of a company is clear. “Working capital management is a strategic topic for treasurers and is key to the success of a business because astute investors always analyse the cash flow generating capability of a company,” says Joerg Wiemer, CEO at Treasury Intelligence Solutions (TIS). “Cash flow is a value driver. Generally the better the cash flow, the higher the company value and the share price will be. The credit ratings agencies place a clear emphasis on companies’ ability to create cash flow, so there are huge benefits to speeding up the process,” he says.</p>
<p>An analogy Wiemer uses is to look at cash flows as the lifeblood of a company. “Just as doctors measure the pulse and blood pressure of their patients as signs of life, so too should a company’s cash flows give key signs as to the financial wellbeing of a company,” he says. “Excess cash sitting in local subsidiary accounts is destroying shareholder value because this cash is not earning interest, or being used at headquarters to grow the business. Improving visibility over cash flows and balances is crucial to addressing this,” he adds.</p>
<p>There are essentially three areas which combine to influence a company’s working capital situation: How quickly it collects from customers, how quickly it is paying its suppliers, and what size its inventory is at any given time.</p>
<p>So far, so simple. But if it all comes down primarily to these three factors, why can it be such a headache for corporates? One reason is that payments from customers can be difficult to keep tabs on, especially in large companies with a widely spread customer base.</p>
<h3 id="cash-flow-problems">Cash flow problems</h3>
<p>“The incoming side of cash flow is the crux as corporates often don’t know exactly where, when, and how much cash actually comes in,” says Tobias Schaad, Treasury Consultant at treasury advisory specialists Zanders. “And once the cash reaches the organisation, depending on the structure, it can be very decentralised.”</p>
<p>James Waud, Head of Subsidiary Clients and Sales Performance, Global Transaction Services at RBS, concurs that large corporates with internationally dispersed operations are particularly prone to cash flow issues. “As companies expand into new markets, this can create currency risk, as well as a host of potential issues with trapped cash, cross-border transfers, tax and regulation, among others, all of which make cash more difficult to manage,” he explains.</p>
<p>He goes on to say that acquisitions can also impact a company’s cash flow. “This adds to the number of banks and bank accounts, which need to be integrated into the relevant ERP, TMS and banking platforms. Acquisition can also dig deeply into balance sheet cash which, in turn increases the need to determine where cash flow efficiencies exist internally, as opposed to resorting to external funding sources, particularly when you consider the yield advantage of ‘self-funding’.”</p>
<p>Beyond these factors, corporate culture can exacerbate cash flow problems. This is particularly the case when company policy prioritises achieving revenues over how and when cash flows come in. “Salespeople often have the wrong incentives (from a cash flow perspective),” says TIS’s Wiemer. “Their compensation is linked to recurring revenues, but not to cash flows.” While revenues are obviously a key indicator of financial health, cash flowing into the company should not be overlooked. For this reason Wiemer recommends that at least part of salesforce compensation should be linked to when the proceeds from a sale actually hit the company’s account. However, it is also important to bear in mind that cash flow alone does not present a complete picture of profitability.</p>
<h3 id="re-engineering">Re-engineering</h3>
<p>So what else are corporates who are experiencing cash flow issues to do? A good place to start is by looking at the three components that have the largest impact on cash flow. Indicators such as days’ sales outstanding (a measure of the average number of days that a company takes to collect revenues after a sale has been made), days’ payable outstanding (a company’s average payable period), and days’ sales of inventory (a measure of how long it takes to turn inventory into revenues) should be analysed over time and compared with peers. Often the ‘collect fast, pay slow’ maxim can make a big difference if made a part of a company’s culture.</p>
<p>Many corporates find the payables side easier to influence. “In our business the focus on working capital is more likely to be on the payables side rather than receivables side, namely in delaying cash flows,” one head of cash management at a MNC in the technology sector tells Treasury Today. “We expect it to be easier to be able to negotiate better payment terms with our suppliers.”</p>
<p>Buyer-initiated payment solutions and expense management tools can both help corporates actively dictate the speed at which suppliers are paid, the latter with the added advantage of cutting overhead. This initial analysis can also sometimes show that cash flow issues are arising because working capital is simply blocked in inventory.</p>
<h3 id="seeking-outside-help">Seeking outside help</h3>
<p>However, where do you go when there are no more cash flow gains to be squeezed out internally? A logical second step might be to seek assistance for your bank or banks. And indeed in many cases this can do the trick. A bank (or banks) lengthening its credit lines to a corporate to act as a buffer against the vagaries of late-paying customers can be of great help, for example. However, banks have become much less willing (some would say able) to extend the support they already have in place for corporate customers.</p>
<p>“A number of corporates we have spoken to, especially in manufacturing industries, that have traditionally relied on a line of unsecured credit from their banks over time, are now struggling to obtain additional bank credit,” says Alan Gillies, Vice President of Sales at American Express Global Corporate Payments.</p>
<p>This is forcing them to seek alternative sources of cash flow. Beyond extending bank credit, there are a number of ‘traditional’ methods available to corporates to ease the strain of restricted cash flow on their business. These include supply chain finance, invoice discounting, and credit insurance.</p>
<p>These can indeed take on some of a company’s cash flow risk, although each solution has its drawbacks.</p>
<p>Take invoice discounting, by which money is drawn against revenues before cash is received, for example. While it can be an effective solution for some companies, it can also lock those who use it into an awkward situation. “Invoice discounting can be like a drug for a company,” warns TIS’s Wiemer. “It may well bring significant benefits in terms of working capital optimisation in the first year, but to maintain this higher level a company has to keep using the technique. Once you stop using it, your working capital will suffer. Plus it comes at a cost.” He says a better way is to analyse cash flows in a more sustainable way and devote more time and effort to negotiating better payment terms with customers and suppliers.</p>
<p>He is equally wary of resorting to using credit insurance before considering alternatives. “If you manage a business you should know your customers and their credit profiles. If you are a strategic supplier to them, why should you buy credit insurance? Even in a difficult economic environment, the case for credit insurance is weak, although that depends on how it is priced.”</p>
<h3 id="innovation">Innovation</h3>
<p>Other than the ‘traditional’ methods, there are also more innovative solutions to help re-engineer a company’s cash flows. Card providers, for example, offer corporate cards that allow companies to insert a fixed number of days’ cash flow benefit between them and their suppliers. “This kind of solution is becoming popular as working capital performance is on almost every finance director’s scorecard,” says American Express’s Gillies.</p>
<p>In-house banks can also revolutionise a company’s cash flows, by allowing corporates to make payments in-house, which is cheaper and faster than using external banking infrastructure. They can also help reduce operating costs and banking fees. Wiemer says in-house banks can play a crucial role in addressing cash flow issues. “The time that cash spends stuck in the banking system is painful for corporates as it isn’t earning interest.”</p>
<p>However, he adds that this solution should not be the first port of call for a company looking to improve its cash flows. “In-house banks are more of a fine-tuning measure – a second step to be taken only after a corporate has streamlined its payment processes and increased the visibility and control over its cash flows,” he says.</p>
<p>Payments factories, whereby payments processes are centralised, are also becoming increasingly popular with corporates. Enhanced by virtual accounts, these structures can help with a company’s cash turnover from the outset. Furthermore, the growth of payments factories is being driven partly by connectivity to the SWIFT financial messaging system and the implementation of the Single Euro Payments Area (SEPA). One drawback of the setup is that it can be complex and time-consuming to implement, however.</p>
<p>So it seems there are solutions – albeit somewhat cumbersome in some instances – to help corporates deal with their cash flow problems. But what is the role of the treasurer in all this?</p>
<h3 id="the-treasurer-and-cash-flows">The treasurer and cash flows</h3>
<p>Whatever the solution, the treasurer should be at the heart of the discussion when a company looks to improve its cash flows.</p>
<p>“The role of the treasurer in optimising cash flows is absolutely critical,” says RBS’s Waud. “They have the ability to leverage a company’s internal cash flows in an optimal way that leads to a reduced reliance on external sources, in particular the capital markets and bank debt.”</p>
<p>Waud adds that the treasury department can use its contacts in the banking world to gain expertise. “In managing bank relationships, treasurers have a very powerful ability to call on the considerable cash management advisory services of their relationship banking providers to demonstrate where they see best practice solutions. It is vital to demonstrate that they are running a world-class treasury function and are benchmarking that, constantly reviewing efficiencies against the marketplace,” he says.</p>
<p>Gillies agrees that the treasurer has an important role, but adds that collaboration with other departments is also crucial. “We are increasingly seeing that treasury, finance and procurement are coming together to decide how to influence goals from a working capital perspective,” he says.</p>
<p>Moreover, technology can help in the battle to improve cash flows. “In the future there could be a huge trend to leverage cloud-based technology in re-engineering cash flows. Some of the tools available are easy to use and can generate transparency and solve cash flow problems. It has the potential to be a real disruptive innovation in the working capital space,” says TIS’s Wiemer.</p>
<p>“Nowadays there are big data analysis tools that can improve your ability to forecast when you are going to receive cash,” says Zanders’ Schaad. “Having access to better forecasting is an important step in streamlining cash flows.”</p>
<div class="boxed">
<h3 id="cash-forecasting-a-checklist">Cash forecasting: a checklist</h3>
<p>The best way to improve cash forecasting, according to Treasury Alliance Group, is to evaluate the current process against five best practices of cash forecasting.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<strong>Simplicity</strong>
<p>A cash forecast requires two pieces of accurate information: the amount of cash on hand and the amount to be received net of expenses. Add the dimensions of time and currency; when will the cash be received, and in what currency and you have a reasonable and very effective cash forecast. When asking business units to forecast cash, keep it simple. Don’t ask for a detailed weekly flow of funds report requiring forecasts of inter-company receipts/payments, loans/investments and third-party receipts/payments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Cooperation</strong>
<p>Good quality forecasting input is the primary determinant of a good quality forecast. And the quality of the input is in the hands of your business partners. Building trust is an important step in this process. If forecasting accuracy is used as a punitive tool by treasury, units will hedge forecasts and refrain from sharing key strategic insights, diluting their value.</p>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Communication</strong>
<p>Forecasting in a global company adds the challenge of multiple currencies, language and culture. It is critical that all business units adopt common definitions in the cash forecasting process. Cash in bank ledgers and available cash are two different concepts, familiar to treasury associates but less familiar to accountants or others involved, so make sure everyone completing the forecasts understands and uses the same definitions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Structure</strong>
<p>Cash forecasting problems arise when business units lose faith in central treasury’s ability to respond to their urgent funding needs in a timely manner. They respond with excessive caution in forecasting receipts and even hold onto their own cash reserves, diluting the accuracy and value of the forecast. The solution is to have an efficient account structure serviced by a reliable network of banks. This can take time to develop but results in reduced administration, transaction and other costs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Technology</strong>
<p>You can increase simplicity, cooperation and communication with the effective use of technology such as gathering forecast information through an intranet or file-sharing site. Using an intranet adds security and administrative efficiency as well. Work with your technology team to develop a form for collecting the forecast input. These are relatively simple to develop and the data gathered this way is typically stored in a database on one of your servers. This is a winning approach from a number of perspectives; it is consistent, enterprise-wide, secure and administratively efficient.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The best practices outlined above won’t get you perfection but will give you a good start.</p>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Adam Smith Webinar launching with Microsoft Treasury]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Oct 2013 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><img alt="Microsoft" height="24" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/microsoft-logo-2013-110x24.svg?la=en&amp;hash=16AC7DDE4ADEC144E3D7E457F8EB6B4E" width="110"/></p>
<p>Treasury Today has launched its series of Adam Smith Webinars highlighting best practice in corporate treasury. Kicking off the series was Anita Prasad of Microsoft, winners of the Top Treasury Team Adam Smith Award in 2013.</p>
<p>Anita provides a vision of the future demonstrating Microsoft’s solution for turning big data into business intelligence allowing for:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>More efficient management of a large number of banks across over the world.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The ability to compile multiple sources of data into a virtual warehouse then convert this data into manageable business intelligence.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The creation of a visual platform to simply present the data but also be able to drill down into the details through the click of a button.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Access to nearly 100% visibility of Microsoft’s cash.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This webinar was held on Wednesday 23rd October 2013.</p>
<div style="text-align:center;">
<a class="button-block button--red-stroke" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/pdf/webinar-slides/tt-2013-10-adam-smith-webinar-microsoft.pdf?la=en&amp;hash=CB91918AF8BA0804AD286B7083A27C76" onclick="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','Download','PDF',this.href]);" target="_blank">Download slide pack</a>
</div>
<h4 id="watch-the-webinar-presentation">Watch the webinar presentation below and then view the video demonstration of the software Microsoft uses</h4></div>
</div>
<div class="video-panel v-spacing--bottom" data-component="video-panel" data-height="" data-videourl="https://vimeo.com/521441822" data-width="">
<div class="video-panel__item">
<a class="video-panel__link" href="#video-player">
<img src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/tt-2013-10-adam-smith-webinar-microsoft-splashscreen.jpg"/>
<span class="video-panel--overlay">
<span class="icon-play">Watch video</span>
</span>
</a>
</div>
</div>
<div class="video-panel v-spacing--bottom" data-component="video-panel" data-height="" data-videourl="https://vimeo.com/521443025" data-width="">
<div class="video-panel__item">
<a class="video-panel__link" href="#video-player">
<img src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/tt-2013-10-adam-smith-webinar-microsoft-powerview.jpg"/>
<span class="video-panel--overlay">
<span class="icon-play">Watch video</span>
</span>
</a>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Cash flow forecasting]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Apr 2013 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFDF4ECC241CD011CE458A3E170E54A1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=69E5AF54A6052F2670FDCE0C1340ABEC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D453431E89174943914A1E9B77EEF04F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=13EF3DB5DEBC45694ABFCCA0015286D4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EE56E6C2D747C2EB4C0A26F5902BBE29"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Stack of coins" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><figure class="portrait right"><img alt="Portrait of Daniel Blumen, Partner, Treasury Alliance Group" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/04/2013-04-tt-02-qa-daniel-blumen-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="daniel-blumen-partner-treasury-alliance-group">Daniel Blumen, Partner, Treasury Alliance Group:</h5>
<p>The best way to improve cash forecasting is to evaluate the current process against five best practices of cash forecasting.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h5>Simplicity.</h5>
<p>A cash forecast requires two pieces of accurate information; the amount of cash on hand and the amount to be received net of expenses. Add the dimensions of time and currency; when will the cash be received, and in what currency and you have a reasonable and very effective cash forecast. When asking business units to forecast cash, keep it simple. Don’t ask for a detailed weekly flow of funds report requiring forecasts of inter-company receipts/payments, loans/investments and third-party receipts/payments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Cooperation.</h5>
<p>Good quality forecasting input is the primary determinant of a good quality forecast. And the quality of the input is in the hands of your business partners. Building trust is an important step in this process. If forecasting accuracy is used as a punitive tool by treasury, units will hedge forecasts and refrain from sharing key strategic insights, diluting their value.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Communication.</h5>
<p>Forecasting in a global company adds the challenge of multiple currencies, language and culture. It is critical that all business units adopt common definitions in the cash forecasting process. Cash in bank ledgers and available cash are two different concepts, familiar to treasury associates but less familiar to accountants or others involved, so make sure everyone completing the forecasts understands and uses the same definitions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Structure.</h5>
<p>Cash forecasting problems arise when business units lose faith in central treasury’s ability to respond to their urgent funding needs in a timely manner. They respond with excessive caution in forecasting receipts and even hold onto their own cash reserves, diluting the accuracy and value of the forecast. The solution is to have an efficient account structure serviced by a reliable network of banks. This can take time to develop but results in reduced administration, transaction and other costs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Technology.</h5>
<p>You can increase simplicity, cooperation and communication with the effective use of technology such as gathering forecast information through an intranet or file-sharing site. Using an intranet adds security and administrative efficiency as well. Work with your technology team to develop a form for collecting the forecast input. These are relatively simple to develop and the data gathered this way is typically stored in a database on one of your servers. This is a winning approach from a number of perspectives; it’s consistent, enterprise-wide, secure and administratively efficient.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The best practices outlined above won’t get you perfection but will give you a good start.</p>
<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Portrait of Paul Stheeman, Independent Treasury Executive and Consultant" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/04/2013-04-tt-02-qa-paul-stheeman-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="paul-stheeman-independent-treasury-executive-and-consultant">Paul Stheeman, Independent Treasury Executive and Consultant:</h5>
<p>Quite often treasurers will seek to improve the quality of their forecasts by adding details to their calculations or by looking for enhanced tools such as new or better software. But do these ideas really help solve the problem?</p>
<p>Adding detail may lead to more complexity and have the opposite effect – ie is less transparent, more prone to errors and more difficult to understand or disentangle when questions are raised. The treasurer should always stick to the motto “keep it simple”. He should regularly review the detail and critically ask whether it is required.</p>
<p>A new enhanced software tool may give a false sense of security. It is the information going in which will decide on the quality coming out.</p>
<p>When preparing a cash forecast the treasurer will seldom amass all the numbers himself. Typically he will have to aggregate information received from subsidiaries or operations. He is dependent on the high quality of this information. Therefore the most meaningful instrument he has are his communication skills. He will need to build a framework which the people from his operations will understand and he will need to communicate with them. It is not sufficient to send an email or a spreadsheet around once a month. The treasurer has to talk regularly with the experts from operations, firstly to ensure they understand what his requirements are and why he regularly needs them. He should give these experts an opportunity to communicate back to him, for example telling him why certain numbers cannot be provided with the degree of accuracy expected or why some may be fixed and others uncertain.</p>
<p>The detail and complexity around cash forecasts today mean that it is essential that communication lines work well. Good relationships make it easier to pick up the phone and share information. The treasurer must have confidence in his own numbers and he can only achieve this if he fully understands them himself. He must therefore proactively build relationships with the correct people and ensure a collaborative communication style with them. He should provide feedback on each report he receives, so that the operations people can see their input is valued.</p>
<figure class="portrait right"><img alt="Portrait of Ryan Smith, Treasury Manager, Mitsubishi Corporation International (Europe)" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/04/2013-04-tt-02-qa-ryan-smith-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="ryan-smith-treasury-manager-mitsubishi-corporation-international-europe">Ryan Smith, Treasury Manager, Mitsubishi Corporation International (Europe):</h5>
<p>Accurate cash forecasts are necessary to improve the liquidity management of the treasury function. In recent times it has become more important than ever to avoid unpleasant financial surprises and thus avert the spectre of expensive emergency funding or cash surpluses earning next to zero credit interest.</p>
<p>For best practice, a treasury should utilise the cash forecasting capabilities of their TMS as it will already hold the majority of the information required – for example: maturing loans, deposits, fx contracts and some future payments and receipts.</p>
<p>Using the TMS for forecasts will enable the treasury team, not just the individual who prepares and checks the forecasts, the opportunity to view the most up-to-date position.</p>
<p>The most difficult part of the process is to capture any further relevant data that should be part of the cash flow forecast. This can include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Accounting system data not automatically fed to the TMS</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Future business opportunities that may require additional finance.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Unpredictable flows to/from suppliers/customers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>To ensure an accurate forecast, the treasury team needs to educate persons within their company (or any relevant subsidiary) on the importance of providing accurate and timely information. This would include traders, accounting personnel and any other staff members whose daily business can provide the treasury team with future information of material monetary flows. Any information provided should be added to the TMS forecast (via manual entries) to provide the most accurate view of the company’s future position.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Precautionary note: no forecast will ever be perfect, so the management of a company’s assets and liabilities should always provide enough flexibility to allow for life’s little surprises!</p>
<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Portrait of Conor Deegan, Director, Cash Analytics" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/04/2013-04-tt-02-qa-conor-deegan-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="conor-deegan-director-cash-analytics">Conor Deegan, Director, Cash Analytics:</h5>
<p>The human element of a cash forecasting process should never be ignored. Challenges such as forecasting unexpected expenditure, capturing unpredictable flows and modelling external influences are common to most companies but large multi-location organisations, who are reliant on the inputs of personnel in business units, must contend with a range of other factors that can compromise the quality of their cash forecasts.</p>
<p>For these larger organisations the quality of the reporting output from a forecasting process is therefore dependent on the quality of information provided by each and every person involved. There is no doubt that forecasting cash movements can be problematic, even for companies with reasonably predictable cash flows, but ensuring the process is engaged with in a meaningful way by all contributors will give a treasurer comfort that the information on which decisions are based is of the highest quality.</p>
<p>A focus on the following areas should allow treasurers to achieve their long and short-term forecasting goals:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h5>Gain visible executive sponsorship.</h5>
<p>Generally the requirement for a cash forecasting process will be driven at executive/board level but gaining visible executive sponsorship is an important first step on the path to successful process implementation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>In-depth initial review.</h5>
<p>Before committing to a group wide forecasting structure, time should be spent understanding the operations and constraints of each business unit. Find out if cash forecasting already takes place and whether existing resources can be leveraged for the overall process.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Education.</h5>
<p>Cash forecasting is a knowledge intensive exercise and as an investment made in ‘educating’ both personnel at business unit level and head office with regard to the nature of cash movements, will contribute to the quality of forecast information reported.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Make it part of the day job.</h5>
<p>Forecasting can sometimes fall outside of the day-to-day remit of contributors to the process. Ensure sufficient time is committed to the compilation and review of cash flow information for efficient and accurate benefits.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Provide value to participants.</h5>
<p>A process that relies on contributions from multiple sources but only provides value at head office level can deteriorate over time due to a lack of engagement from business units. Finding ways to provide value to business units – such as through actual versus forecast reviews – will boost the quality of the overall cash forecast.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<div class="question">
<h3 id="the-next-question">The next question</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“What is the most effective way to measure and control counterparty risk?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Creating and issuing an RFP]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2013 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFDF4ECC241CD011CE458A3E170E54A1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=69E5AF54A6052F2670FDCE0C1340ABEC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D453431E89174943914A1E9B77EEF04F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=13EF3DB5DEBC45694ABFCCA0015286D4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EE56E6C2D747C2EB4C0A26F5902BBE29"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Stack of coins" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>When the time is right to introduce or replace a key part of your treasury technology, or to establish a major new banking relationship, the selection process can be daunting. Unless you know exactly what is required, issuing a request for proposal (RFP) may provide some valuable direction. What does it involve?</p>
<p>The technology and banking needs of a treasury vary from business to business and a one-size-fits-all solution for either does not exist. This means a choice will need to be made somewhere down the line when it comes to selecting for the first time or replacing a particular element. Regardless of the driver for change, sometimes these choices will be difficult, particularly when considering a complex proposition such as a Treasury Management System or a multi-country banking partner. The difficulty often lies in the fact that the differences between offerings may be subtle but nonetheless important to the success or otherwise of the project.</p>
<p>Some projects are built around a long-term strategic vision, in which case time to explore each facet may be afforded. Other decisions may need to be made under pressure in which case there is a risk of making a huge mistake or simply failing to take advantage of the opportunity to improve the workings of the treasury department.</p>
<p>In both cases, although the approach may be different, a well-managed RFP (Request for Proposal) can be a valuable tool in helping to ease the difficulties of the selection process whilst alerting treasury to any existing imperfections that should now be addressed. After all, a good choice now may well obviate the need for yet another project.</p>
<p>In the first of this two-part series, Treasury Today considers the requirements around building a technology RFP.</p>
<h4 id="requirements-definition">Requirements definition</h4>
<p>Most treasury technology projects can be broken down into three parts: review; selection; and implementation. In this article we look at the first two constituents.</p>
<p>The review process is intended to establish a requirements definition: by analysing treasury processes and technology currently being used, and establishing what treasury wishes to achieve with the project, it is possible to make a broad outline of what is required and how treasury feels it may be achieved.</p>
<p>The requirements definition is the foundation stone of the project and its solidity will inform the success or otherwise of subsequent project phases. However, it should be understood that a degree of flexibility on the part of both client and vendor is desirable as to the means of arrival at the final destination because as the project progresses new ideas are often revealed. In a complex treasury setup, a fully-scoped project may not even be possible until the core functions have been implemented and the ancillary requirements become apparent. There may also be the need for a discretionary trade-off where the lack of a certain aspect may be outweighed by the presence of another more important one. A suitably-worded RFP may go some way to revealing the preparedness of the vendor to accommodate the client.</p>
<p>A caveat on the corporate side to this call for flexibility is that it is not best practice to change core processes just because the chosen system cannot accommodate your needs. By the same token, customising the solution from the outset to meet your process requirements can also store up future trouble (customising is not to be confused with configuring; the latter will almost certainly be required to enable a solution to meet the specific needs of the business).</p>
<h4 id="teamwork">Teamwork</h4>
<p>The value of undertaking a requirements definition cannot be overstated, but it may not be possible, or even desirable, to execute it in isolation. Depending on the nature of the project, it may call upon input from other functions within the business (including various finance and business units, procurement, internal audit and IT) to highlight some of their specific technical requirements. This will be necessary when the systems of these functions (such as accounts or credit control) already (or will) interface directly with the proposed treasury solution and will in any case give an indication as to how the new system will affect other technologies up and downstream. If there are other functions that have any input, get it written down at this point as it will stop problems later on. It is essential at this stage to cover all bases, thinking carefully who should be involved in the consultation process, who will be impacted by the project and who could or should benefit from the outcome.</p>
<h4 id="project-manage">Project manage</h4>
<p>The consultation process, though hugely beneficial in the long run, will run the risk of developing so-called ‘scope creep’ (continuously adding to it) unless from the outset there is a coherent and simple project definition, a means of deflecting unnecessary diversions, and of taking firm and intelligent decisions. Scope creep can add substantially to the final cost. For this reason, the backing of a project sponsor (in the form of an executive with higher status than anyone else involved with the project) and a strong project manager (PM) are essential.</p>
<p>However, scope creep should not be confused with the controlled and planned modification of the project in the light of acquiring more detailed understanding of the capabilities of the technology. This can add new benefits that had not been previously thought of – but even here the change process must be managed.</p>
<p>Indeed, the PM should bring order to the process by planning the phases, defining roles, putting in place the right resources at the right time, and getting everything done in the right order. In doing so, the odds of missing something and having to go back to it later are greatly reduced. However, any changes to the structure put in place by the PM must themselves be managed and documented to maintain project integrity.</p>
<p>To be effective in the PM role, experience is highly desirable, particularly when it comes to change management (which must never be underestimated, particularly when it comes to dealing with office politics). Some firms choose to employ a consultant to take them through the entire process, from initial analysis to implementation. Whilst it may be desirable to employ an impartial third party who will not be subject to day-to-day operational distractions, it is entirely possible to select an individual internally, as long as they can remain objective – especially during the full-on implementation phase. If an internal project manager is chosen, it may be beneficial to have them dedicated to that role for the duration. Factoring in the resources needed therefore becomes part of the process.</p>
<h4 id="consider-your-initial-options">Consider your initial options</h4>
<p>By this stage, beyond confirming that there is a need to bring in new technology, you will have defined your exact goal, what is required of the solution to meet that goal, how the project may impact other parts of the business and what their requirements are, and then formed it all into a coherent requirements definition document. It is now time to consider possible solutions. The more effort put into this phase, the less time will be spent on unsuitable candidates.</p>
<p>Deciding which vendors to approach will involve some background research. Using publications such as Treasury Today, talking to other treasurers and having preliminary discussions with vendors at conferences and exhibitions will all provide valuable initial insight. It may even be prudent to send out your basic requirements definition to a wider panel of vendors, in the form of an RFI (Request for Information). An RFI is a high-level call for product information that can at least put you in the right ball-park regarding which vendors have suitable offerings.</p>
<p>Having created a long-list of potential systems (and this may include half a dozen or more), building an RFP can provide structure to the selection process, enabling you to focus only on the most appropriate offerings. In doing so, although positive past experience is a valuable indicator, it is important to clear your mind of all bias against any supplier. However, whilst some companies have strict procurement rules to ensure fair competition at all times, if you know what you want (and if procurement will allow it), just buy it. After all, putting a vendor through a rigorous RFP process when the decision is a fait accompli is a waste of everyone’s time (a process referred to scathingly by vendors as ‘the beauty pageant’). To this must be added the notion that by going through the process, it may uncover ideas and product and vendor capacities that were not previously on the radar.</p>
<h4 id="building-an-rfp">Building an RFP</h4>
<p>The aim of an RFP is to garner in-depth and specific responses from a small group of vendors and tease out the differences between their systems which, on the surface, may all seem much the same. It may even form the basis of a contract between client and vendor although many vendors would naturally baulk at this suggestion, especially if their responses have not been written with the requisite legal precision (it may be useful to ask how the vendor’s RFP responses are reviewed and authorised internally).</p>
<p>It is vital from the treasurer’s point of view to ensure that the RFP conveys precisely and clearly what is required, according to the circumstances underlying the project. A complex treasury will probably generate a larger RFP document and this should be broken down into manageable sections for the benefit of the vendor and for your own team when it comes to assessing the results.</p>
<p>The actual layout of the RFP can vary but it is mostly bound by common sense; just be aware of the importance of laying it out clearly, with a logical progression between each section, and giving sufficient space for suppliers to respond.</p>
<p>In terms of content, despite attempts at creating a standard RFP form (the AFP in the US has made one available to its members) the disparate nature of the businesses and the varied treasury requirements of those issuing them means a fully-formed, off-the-shelf, one-size-fits-all document has yet to emerge.</p>
<p>There is a big difference in requirements between buying a TMS and an FX trading platform, for example, just as there is a big difference in the eventual deployments of these systems by each user. Whilst a standard form will deliver some efficiency advantages for vendors and corporates alike, copy and paste questions will not cover the specific issues that are important to each business and could induce standard responses which will serve only to take the project team a limited distance down the path towards individual project fulfilment.</p>
<p>So, whilst some aspects of treasury may resonate across the industry, an in-house banking structure, for example, is very specific to one company and simply asking if a platform supports it is rather meaningless; you need to be able to express in the document what that structure looks like (even using attached flowcharts and models) to be able to elicit a usable answer.</p>
<p>For now, as long as the same document is issued to each prospective supplier, then the need for standardisation is arguably limited anyway, the vital part stemming from the need to reflect the individual needs of the company in what is asked and how it is asked.</p>
<p>Indeed, just as it is possible to fail to explain your needs clearly, or to provide too little information for the vendors to be able to respond in depth, it is also possible to over-burden suppliers with information; providing an in-depth view of the group’s entire business operations may not be required if it is only relevant to the project to offer a view of the structure of treasury and where it sits within that operation. There is, however, no known research on the correlation between size of RFP and success of implementation!</p>
<p>A major part of building the RFP concerns functionality. This is where the work that went into creating the requirements definition comes into play. The requirements definition states what you want; all you have to do with the RFP is to ask the supplier if they can do it. But whilst some responses may call for a simple ‘yes’ or ‘no’ answer, some may need more in-depth explanations of how certain functions are supported and processed and how the software relates to the way in which your treasury operates (including its connectivity with third parties, such as banks).</p>
<p>In addition to pure functionality, a key objective for a technology project is to configure sets of functionalities into workflows that fulfil the project’s business process objectives. This is where ‘how’ questions can help, as the buyer needs to understand how effectively the system solution can automate a specific treasury.</p>
<p>The client may take this opportunity to make clear its position on certain contractual conditions such as payment being explicitly linked to tangible deliverables. Whilst being business-like is essential, it is important not to appear unreasonable – an adversarial RFP will yield little in the way of success.</p>
<p>Be aware that open questions may be necessary to unearth how a supplier intends to meet some complex, potentially deal-breaking issues, but too many open questions will push the analysis phase into overdrive, making it difficult to draw accurate and fair comparisons between respondents.</p>
<p>This means the questions set out in the RFP have to be considered – and tested – carefully, to see if they are understandable, unambiguous, and likely to yield the type of answers that you seek. You are, after all, asking for more than just a cut-and-paste response from the supplier.</p>
<p>When asking about the implementation process it is necessary not just to pose questions but also to state a host of facts. The list may include points relating to the intended timescale, how many users, locations, functionality required in each location and how satellite units are structured within the company, the existing system configuration (listing current systems and what needs to be integrated), and any manual interventions.</p>
<p>It may be appropriate to provide a proposed technical integration plan for the new platform. Certainly any integration and reporting requirements should be defined in sufficient detail to avoid ambiguity, to enable vendors to have a sufficient understanding of the implementation scope to propose the implementation effort accurately.</p>
<p>In seeking a vendor’s thoughts on these matters it is necessary to secure from it a raft of reciprocal information such as how it intends to piece together an implementation team (size and structure and who will be involved, for example), what it proposes in terms of ongoing support (technical and staff training) and maintenance (with details and sample copies of SLAs and so on). In essence, you need to embrace the whole service of the product in one document.</p>
<p>It may be that treasury knows what it wants but does not know how to achieve it; the level of detail in the RFP can be used to provide vendors with the opportunity to deliver a creative response, mindful that it is not good form for companies to use it as a free consultancy service. It is also worth noting that unless the RFP conveys precisely what is required, the pricing is likely to be skewed; certainly beware of adding elements merely out of curiosity or as a demonstration of your depth of knowledge (it does happen) as these will push the cost up.</p>
<p>Whilst some aspects of treasury may be commercially sensitive, it should be borne in mind that conveying sufficient detail for a vendor to be able to provide the most appropriate response is beneficial to all parties, both in terms of getting the best solution and in getting the job done in the most efficient manner.</p>
<p>It is important to realise that RFPs that are the product of multiple departments are prone to duplicate or even triplicate questions. Care should be taken to remove any such instances from the final document as they can reflect poorly on the buyer’s professionalism. Of course, this caveat does not apply to carefully constructed functional verifications, designed to check the vendors’ responses for consistency.</p>
<p>When it comes to distributing the RFP, by all means send it to all those vendors that closely meet your requirements, but always bear in mind that the more vendors the RPF is sent to, the more analysis you will have to do when the responses come back. Typically a short-list of three or four will be called upon to respond. It is not unheard of for vendors to not respond.</p>
<h4 id="making-a-judgement">Making a judgement</h4>
<p>The RFP responses should give a clear demonstration of each vendor’s capacity to add value and differentiate itself from the others. Over and above what is sought by the treasury team, a good RFP response will also provide answers to the questions and issues that haven’t even been raised. Read them all.</p>
<p>The information you receive back will have to be compared on an equal footing. Depending upon factors such as the complexity of the project and how many suppliers are approached, a well-crafted set of questions should enable the project team to consolidate answers on a single spreadsheet set up to allow a quick view of scores for each aspect.</p>
<p>However, before scoring responses, it is common practice to ‘weight’ each section and component according to the relative value the team places on it. This ensures that the overall score reflects those values, and that the outcome is not unduly influenced by an aspect that is of lesser importance.</p>
<p>The weighting process must be discussed thoroughly by the project team. The process is arbitrary and therefore must have direction from the project manager to avoid endless re-working. Once scores are calculated it is advisable to resist the temptation to keep adjusting the weightings until you get the answer you want (in which case, the exercise will have been a waste of time).</p>
<p>The degree to which scoring is broken down within each component will depend upon time available and the relative importance of that component. Deep questioning and subsequent scoring of the minutiae of a certain function will in theory better reflect the view of that function. Whilst this may be appropriate for some aspects, doing this for every component will generate a lot of extra work.</p>
<p>When applying scores, it may be useful for each reviewer on the team to give their own to each weighted component, creating a weighted average total. There are various methods of reaching a final score, but in any case the chosen model should be agreed upon before starting to assess responses, to avoid any confusion or disagreement. In the end, the decision may come down to which vendor team you feel most in tune with or even price, but the RFP will have provided most of the technical and service information to be able to take such a decision comfortably.</p>
<p>Once completed and the decision made, the choice then is whether to use the vendor’s contract or to draft your own, which opens up a whole new discussion; suffice to say at this point that the corporate treasury needs to find a balance between encouraging and compensating the vendor whilst still giving itself scope to manage the risks of the project and getting satisfactory delivery.</p>
<p>The RFP document may be used as a reminder of what is expected of the vendor once the implementation is underway. Where a TMS implementation is undertaken, the project should be seen as an opportunity to re-engineer inefficient and outdated processes. This possibility often only becomes clear after initial selection has been completed, and once a particular TMS’s capabilities are better understood. Although it will involve changing, and perhaps expanding the project to some degree, it should not be seen in the same negative light as scope creep. Such changes will, however, need proper control and management. This possibility should ideally be covered in a contingency allowance in the initial project plan.</p>
<p>Ultimately, if the RFP is treated as a functional document with a serious purpose, and the information contained within is sufficiently detailed, it should be beneficial to both the client and the vendor.</p>
<div class="boxed">
<h4 id="checklist-of-rfp-processes">Checklist of RFP processes</h4>
<p>Before starting on a major project, secure the support of a senior executive sponsor.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Appoint a strong project manager. Consider a third party for the role.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If an internal appointment, ensure they can remain objective. Consider having them dedicated to the role for the duration.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Factor in all resources likely to be required.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Think carefully about which functions and individual within the group should be involved in the consultation process. Document any agreements with them in advance.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Establish ‘rules of engagement’, allowing vendor-contact only with this liaison person (probably the project manager). Log all interaction. A single point of contact avoids confusion and conflicting information. This rule should be extended to cover the implementation process.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ensure you clearly understand and have documented what your main issues are, why you are doing this and what you expect to achieve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Refer to this document often.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Be flexible regarding your plans and add a contingency allowance (for cost, time etc) for project expansion as awareness of the chosen system increases.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Do not confuse beneficial project additions with unwanted scope creep.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Don’t change anything in the project plan without managing and documenting it first.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Always establish a requirements definition.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Undertake preliminary research (using Treasury Today resources, conferences, vendor websites, discussion with peer-group etc).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Consider issuing a Request for Information (RFI).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When building an RFP always ask if it conveys precisely and clearly what it is you require.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ensure questions are clear, understandable and have been tested and proven as such.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Do not ask unnecessary or unreasonable questions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Some questions may be approached from different angles to test consistency of response.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Beware of simply repeating questions (most likely if the RFP is the product of multiple departments). Proper coordination is required to maintain professionalism at all times.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ask open questions where detail is necessary and closed questions where a simple yes or no is sufficient. Remember that open questions are more difficult to compare.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lay out the RFP clearly, in logical order and with sufficient room for a full response.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Complex requirements should be broken down into logical, manageable sections.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It is in your interest to provide sufficient information to enable the vendor to give the fullest answer possible.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Do not over-burden the supplier with unnecessary background information.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Weight each question according to your own values.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Agree upon weightings before sending the RFP to suppliers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Clear your mind of any bias for or against suppliers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Don’t send it to too many vendors: it makes analysis difficult.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Read all responses carefully.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Look for added value in vendor responses eg raising new but useful points.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Learn to distinguish between fact and sales talk.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Resist the temptation to adjust weightings to get the answer you want.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p><em>In the next part we consider how to build an RFP for banking relationships.</em></p>
<p>Thanks to the following treasury consultants for offering their insight and experience:</p>
<ul class="plain">
<li>
<p><strong>Kelvin Walton</strong>, Director, TreasuryWise</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Ken Lillie</strong>, Director, Lillie Associates</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Adrian Rodgers</strong>, Director, ARC Solutions</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Colin Jones</strong>, independent cash and treasury management consultant</p>
</li>
</ul></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Striking a balance]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Feb 2013 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=F98ABE2C4D506A94BE3AC4CC52AAAF55]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=484E2550B2ADB3AFD5BC36C7B7739A14"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=21C99218F1069C8887B239485CF2CDF0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=513D28971CE68CD844B1048A700D0451"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=010A8EF1250267E0082E3B255B44D842"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8752E20B255FF98D8666215DD118E124"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Photo of stones stacked on top of each other to represent team work balance" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F98ABE2C4D506A94BE3AC4CC52AAAF55" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-11-b2b-team-work-balance-concept-112212224__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F98ABE2C4D506A94BE3AC4CC52AAAF55"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The financial crisis means businesses should take a more holistic view of their balance sheets – and must do so in a timely manner. What does this mean and how is it best achieved?</p>
<p>It would seem prudent in any economic environment to understand exactly how much money you have coming in and how much you have going out. This is nothing new: Charles Dickens’ fictional character, Wilkins Micawber (from ‘David Copperfield’), dispensed the following words of wisdom:</p>
<p><em>“Annual income twenty pounds; annual expenditure nineteen pounds nineteen and six: result happiness. Annual income twenty pounds; annual expenditure twenty pounds ought and six: result misery.”</em></p>
<h3 id="back-to-basics">Back to basics</h3>
<p>So what is balance sheet management all about? Starting from the top, a balance sheet is an accounting report designed to give a snapshot of a business’ financial health at any point in time. It includes its assets, such as cash and debtor liabilities; liabilities, in the form of creditors such as banks and bond holders; and total or net worth, which is assets minus liabilities. Whilst asset and liability management are typically viewed as separate elements within the financial function, they necessarily come together under the balance sheet management regime.</p>
<h3 id="finding-focus">Finding focus</h3>
<p>The process of balance sheet management is equally applicable to private individuals and global corporations and yet, for many corporates, before the current financial crisis, few corporations were giving much thought to the issues that were impacting their balance sheets. “But as the downturn hit and businesses got caught up in bank insolvencies, there was a much greater focus on balance sheet management generally,” says Martin Hutchings, Finance Partner in the London-based banking team of international law firm, Freshfields Bruckhaus Deringer. Now many more companies are grasping the nettle “and taking it much more seriously”.</p>
<p>In the corporate sector, balance sheet management is closely aligned with working capital management. This focuses on controlling current assets and current liabilities to ensure a business remains a going concern and can meet its short-term debt obligations and operating expenses.</p>
<p>Daniel Windaus, Head of REL Consultancy in the UK, points out that before 2008, when funding was cheap and readily available, most businesses would question the need for sourcing more cash. But as the crash came and liquidity started to freeze up, the focus of corporates in many regions shifted towards working capital, at least in the short term. This rather changed the face of many operations: “During the slump, many companies realised their revenue line had disappeared and that all the materials to feed their supply chains were now going to have to sit idle as they didn’t have the revenue to soak it up. Suboptimal supply chains always get exposed in a downturn.”</p>
<h3 id="spotting-problems">Spotting problems</h3>
<p>One obvious need for a thorough understanding of the balance sheet is that it can help reveal financial issues before they become major problems. In the current climate this is a must, but even when times are good, solid balance sheet management can help companies put their capital to better use. In any case, managing asset and liability mismatch and maximising returns on assets is necessary to be able to keep the business running smoothly.</p>
<p>In addition to monitoring and anticipating actual and potential value differences between a company’s assets and liabilities, the process of balance sheet management calls upon company policy and procedure to control, or at least limit, the various financial risks a business’s liquidity may be exposed to. As such, it is also closely bound up with risk management. According to PwC, there are four main areas of balance sheet management:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Interest rate risk management.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Liquidity risk management.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Capital management.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Discretionary investment portfolios management.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="cash-first-ask-later">Cash first, ask later?</h3>
<p>Of course, from a working capital perspective, Windaus notes that it depends on organisational type as to whether liabilities or assets take precedence, although he argues that both should be managed with equal vigilance. A manufacturing business, for example, will have a heavier demand for assets and thus cash consumption will be higher. A pure service organisation, with very little inventory (if any), will most likely see a higher concentration on liabilities. In terms of building up working capital, he believes that less is better, to the point where negative working capital – when current liabilities exceed current assets – can actually be a good thing. To achieve this, trade-offs need to be well considered and managed so that the overall business is not negatively impacted.</p>
<p>Turning a net asset into a net liability in this way sounds counter-intuitive and in most cases it is a warning that trouble lies ahead. But when a supplier delivers products to a buyer, and it then sells those products to its own customers, cash up-front, before it has to pay the supplier (as with fast food restaurants or supermarkets), its low inventory married to low accounts receivable equates to efficiency. If it can maintain this model it will have no problem raising cash. So, rather than having cash stuck in everyday business processes, it is in-hand and can be used with purpose for activities such as debt reduction, M&amp;A and capex investments.</p>
<p>In Europe, working capital levels did improve post-credit crunch, but in the past couple of years it has deteriorated once more, notes Windaus. “Companies focused on it when they needed to because cash was not readily available, but now there are other priorities, management attention has probably wavered away from maintaining any improvements on a structural basis.”</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the discussion around the importance of cash, Hutchings believes that many companies have become much more focused on liability management over the past few years. These businesses may have a profile of debts maturing – such as bank loans or bond facilities – but have found themselves struggling to finance their repayments because the liquidity in the market has tightened. In response, when previously treasurers were rarely invited to board meetings, he says now they have become “quite central to that function” because senior executives are concerned how their business is being financed and what risks exist within that process.</p>
<h3 id="look-to-the-future">Look to the future</h3>
<p>Clearly there is a need to look beyond the immediate financial needs of a business. At a bare minimum, says Hutchings, there should be a view some 15 to 18 months out, simply because a business will need its auditors to give it ‘going concern’ status when signing off the annual accounts with a buffer that indicates it can continue to pay its debts, at least in the near term. “But any good company will look out longer than that, possibly to the next two to four years, identifying what needs to be refinanced and how best to do it.”</p>
<p>There is good reason for this. A notable problem with the market at the moment is that it can take much longer to raise money. Companies cannot automatically assume they can go to the same sources each time, as banks are more reluctant to make funds available.</p>
<h3 id="asset-or-liability">Asset or liability?</h3>
<p>The degree of importance attached to either asset or liability management does depend on the nature of the business. A company favouring debt should naturally err in favour of liabilities management, but whilst a cash-rich operation still needs to keep a watching brief over its liabilities, asset management becomes more pressing.</p>
<p>Despite the downturn, cash-rich corporates are on the increase. In early 2012, FT.com reported that in the US non-financial corporate sector “profit margins are at record levels thanks to savage labour shedding and companies are awash with cash”. It added that a similar “accumulation of cash has occurred in Europe”, and cited McKinsey’s estimate that European and US companies “hold about $2 trillion of surplus cash” (the amount outstanding over and above operating cash, defined as 2% of revenue). With such large surpluses, these companies need to consider the best place to deposit their cash, not just to generate the best return, but also to minimise counterparty risk.</p>
<p>The aim of a company is to assure its own success. Cash-rich is generally a good thing, but if there are liquidity issues because asset management is poor, a business may soon find itself in a position of actual or technical insolvency.</p>
<h3 id="getting-better">Getting better</h3>
<p>Improvements in balance sheet management are founded in improving operational processes, states Windaus. Where most would see it as a pure finance issue, he sees it firmly embedded in operational matters. Working capital management, for example, is all about how a company procures from its suppliers, how it contracts with its customers, how these processes are run and how the supply chain and demand forecasting are managed. “Very quickly you get out of the realms of finance, where a CFO or treasurer can influence, and into the daily operational processes,” he notes. It then becomes a matter of how efficiently the business is running, turning to decisions around inventory and production line downtime.</p>
<p>“The challenge for the treasurer or CFO,” says Windaus, “is to try and bring that cash awareness into the overall business, to make people aware of what they can do to influence the balance sheet and what that means for the business.” However, he warns, stepping outside of the finance realm to speak with supply chain managers, for example, often requires time and patience to explain the impact that the balance sheet has on the overall business.</p>
<p>But in building that bigger picture, Hutchings advises the need to consider a number of external risks as well. Counterparty risk information, for example, can be sourced from various business units regarding contracts with suppliers and customers. There is also a need, he says, to understand what sort of business is being carried out and with whom. “If there is a breakdown in your supply chain because a supplier has become insolvent, it could have a major impact on your business.” It therefore becomes another ongoing task to assess the health of these relationships and the financial wherewithal of the parties involved and the market risks they may be facing.</p>
<h3 id="how-its-done">How it’s done</h3>
<p>Effective balance sheet management starts with an understanding of what it is that is required of the process; not knowing some of the issues and consequences, and therefore not being sufficiently prepared to take advantage of opportunities at the right time, is a quick route to being caught out, says Hutchings.</p>
<p>Accessing and gathering financial data is a key function too. Whilst a treasury team should know its own debt maturity profile, if those debts are executed on a group-wide basis, it won’t necessarily know about some of the supply chain or credit collection issues, for example, making it more difficult to pull in the right data, in the right format, at the right time. In response to this potential issue, Hutchings says a centralised function “can give a full and proper understanding of the business needs”.</p>
<p>Clearly then operational processes must be optimised. Windaus suggests one of the duties of the finance professional (treasurer included) is to increase awareness of the power of the balance sheet by establishing clear key performance indicators (KPIs). These must be communicated across the business. And rather than just having a KPI at a corporate or business unit level, it should be cascaded down to the people who can influence processes, where the processes are carried out. All the measurements can then be brought together “to enable the levers to be pulled at an operational level, and at the same time deliver visibility and transparency across the organisation”.</p>
<p>Additionally, Windaus believes that CFOs have a key role to play in the introduction of incentives around the management of liquidity at board level. But one other important aspect – one that he feels is often underestimated – is how to communicate and manage the cash flow forecast of the organisation.</p>
<p>Predicting liquidity requirements can be an insular, desktop-based activity for a treasurer, but involving other business and process stakeholders in creating a cash flow forecast can be a means of changing organisational behaviour. If, for example, the cash requirement for a specific unit looks like it may unexpectedly and significantly increase over a short period – based on figures supplied to treasury by that unit – questions can be raised immediately. A solution may then be found to head off this demand by perhaps changing the way the unit’s business processes are conducted, for example by revising the collections process or credit terms.</p>
<p>With different operational stakeholders involved, Windaus argues that treasurers have the opportunity to turn a habitual set piece regarding liquidity, into “proactively doing something about the processes that generate cash in the first place”.</p>
<h3 id="preparation-preparation-preparation">Preparation, preparation, preparation</h3>
<p>Preparing the ground for that coherent view follows Hutchings’ belief that reporting systems should be created centrally and pushed out to the local business units, requiring them to report in a standardised format as required. Reporting may be carried out electronically into a central system but this is a rare occurrence. Standardised reporting of the different elements using spreadsheets will suffice as it at least enables treasury to form an overview and open dialogue as necessary with the various stakeholders.</p>
<p>Technology is often cited as the panacea for all process issues, but not in this case Windaus believes. “It can help and might make your job easier, but it will not solve a problem by itself,” he states, adding that it is “an illusion” to believe that if a business simply applies technology to a certain set of functions, all will be fine.</p>
<p>Indeed, at the centre of the process, in the treasury department, the need is for experience, professionalism and judgement. “Treasurers will know their business and their own markets better than anyone. Many will have been through similar cycles and will know some of the mitigants to use,” comments Hutchings.</p>
<p>At the highest level, balance sheet management requires a firm purchase on what the wider risks to the business are including, for example, the economic, political, geographic and social. Hutchings says: “It’s about trying to understand the potential issues. From there you can work back to the risks these present to the business, the exposure you have to these, and then deciding how to mitigate against them, making it less painful if and when those issues arise.”</p>
<p>For Windaus, effective balance sheet management centres on transparency, communication and process optimisation. Implementing these concepts in a cohesive way that will work on a day-to-day basis can often overwhelm the finance division “when they realise what it really means to change behaviour in their own company”. For financial minds, it may be quite straightforward, but opening up the mysteries of the balance sheet to the rest of the organisation on both a structural and process basis is not a “plug-and-play” exercise. Indeed, he notes, “managing mind-sets and behavioural changes will take some time and hand-holding. Do not underestimate the effort required here.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Planning]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[The visibility conundrum]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Feb 2013 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=C8CF39B494A1B8A82DB78EB4AFFADB36]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=37DB108D99DA0EBA644EEE52503EE657"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9F4FF62956B7C1AA54FC73408B64331C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A44F57E31BE5D19D173B76B3D1F3683F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=34438277BA819C6D2A1AC86C1A1EA72E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DDE615CAF7AC8B80223215FB130C0DFE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Photo of a science mircoscope" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C8CF39B494A1B8A82DB78EB4AFFADB36" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/financial-planning/2013-02-tt-10-cm-microscope-shallow-dof-is-4529539__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C8CF39B494A1B8A82DB78EB4AFFADB36"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>It may seem like a rather simple task, especially in the day and age of internet banking, but in practice, achieving full visibility across a group’s cash position is often harder than it looks. And although some of you will be reading this, happy in the knowledge that you know how much cash you have and where it is, many treasurers will not.</p>
<p>For proof of this, just look at the results of Ernst &amp; Young’s April 2012 study entitled ‘Reflecting on the future: a study of global corporate treasuries’. Approximately a third of treasury departments have daily visibility of more than 95% of the cash in the company, whereas just under half of respondents claim to have sight of 75% to 95% of the company’s cash on a daily basis. Somewhat shockingly, nearly 10% of respondents have less than 50% visibility.</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1percentage-of-company-wide-cash-visible-to-treasury-on-a-daily-basis">Chart 1: Percentage of company wide cash visible to treasury on a daily basis</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/02/2013-02-tt-10-cm-chart-01-percentage-of-company-wide-cash-visible-to-treasury-on-a-daily-basis.png"><img alt="Chart 1: Percentage of company wide cash visible to treasury on a daily basis" height="118" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/02/2013-02-tt-10-cm-chart-01-percentage-of-company-wide-cash-visible-to-treasury-on-a-daily-basis-t.png" width="300"/></a>
<p class="source">Source: Ernst &amp; Young’s, ‘Reflecting on the future: a study of global corporate treasuries, April 2012</p>
</figure>
<p>Failure to achieve sufficient visibility over the company’s cash carries significant risk. In fact, without clear visibility, companies cannot adequately control group cash. In turn, this means they cannot use that cash at optimum efficiency, or maximise investment opportunities for it. Reducing borrowing costs and improving foreign exchange risk management will also be extremely challenging without full visibility and control.</p>
<p>“It is hardly surprising, therefore, that the majority of companies (69%) plan to further improve visibility of and control over cash,” says the survey. The question, then, is how best to go about this?</p>
<h3 id="overcoming-visibility-hurdles">Overcoming visibility hurdles</h3>
<p>The level of cash visibility that a company can achieve will be heavily influenced by the level of centralisation, with centralised treasuries naturally having an advantage over their decentralised counterparts. In fact, centralisation is one of the key organisational tools that companies use to improve visibility.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, the company’s size and sector can affect visibility levels, as can the rate of growth of the business and its geographical footprint. Nevertheless, there are some fundamental considerations that all companies can take into account when identifying major challenges to visibility – and investigating how these can be overcome.</p>
<h4 id="technology">Technology</h4>
<p>This is the obvious answer to most visibility challenges. In fact, visibility is largely an exercise in deriving cash positions by accessing up-to-date bank account balances – the art is how to make that as simple (and automated) as possible. “We just download the information we need from the relevant online banking systems. The majority of the work is done automatically, with some small amount of manual input,” says Stephen Webster, Group Treasurer, QinetiQ. “As a FTSE 250 company, we don’t have a particularly complex set-up or extensive international presence, so with the ability to access our entire bank balances online, we really don’t find visibility to be a problem.”</p>
<p>Many very large corporates, or those with decentralised operations, often do not find this quite so easy – with extended bank networks and myriad reporting solutions in use. This is where SWIFT comes into its own. “It’s a great way to standardise reporting and get daily visibility over your global cash positions,” says Julia Persson, Former Deputy Head of Treasury at A.P. Moeller Maersk. Similarly, Edward Mundt, Senior Treasury Manager at Asurion, believes that “with SWIFT reporting, any treasury management system (TMS) can give you visibility into the vast majority of your global cash.” The diagram on the next page illustrates how this could work.</p>
<p>Many of the world’s biggest corporates report vastly improved visibility through the use of SWIFT. In fact, Microsoft, which has in the region of 200 subsidiary businesses, 110 global bank partners and over 1,000 bank accounts, has reportedly achieved 99% visibility over global cash through the use of SWIFT’s MT (FIN syntax) and MX (XML syntax) messaging standards.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, this solution isn’t foolproof. “Not all banks use SWIFT to the full extent,” warns Maciej Müldner, CFO, Skanska Romania. “This is one of the reasons that companies can find Eastern Europe a challenge from a visibility point of view. Take Romania, for example, with such low demand for SWIFT from corporates in the country, the value proposition simply isn’t there for many of the local banks to support it.” Certain Asian countries, such as Korea, pose similar challenges. “Even if you can get hold of an MT940 from the bank, expect it to be significantly more expensive than you are accustomed to in the US or Europe,” says Asurion’s Mundt. “Also, don’t anticipate that it will necessarily be in English.”</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="diagram-1-end-of-day-and-intraday-balance-reporting">Diagram 1: End of day and intraday balance reporting</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/02/2013-02-tt-10-cm-diagram-01-end-of-day-and-intraday-balance-reporting.png"><img alt="Diagram 1: End of day and intraday balance reporting" height="172" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2013/02/2013-02-tt-10-cm-diagram-01-end-of-day-and-intraday-balance-reporting-t.png" width="300"/></a>
<p class="source">*Treasury management system<br/>Source: SWIFT</p>
</figure>
<h4 id="bank-relationships">Bank relationships</h4>
<p>Let’s be clear, this is not an invitation to go and have it out with your bank about your visibility issues; however, your choice of banking partner(s) will inevitably have an impact on the level of visibility that you are able to achieve.</p>
<p>Lenovo, for example, has implemented a single bank model that allows the company to achieve superior levels of visibility. “We have domiciled all our operational accounts with a single bank,” says Damian Glendinning, Treasurer of the computer manufacturing giant. “This solution may not be to everyone’s taste, but it means that all the data is immediately available in the internet banking system of the bank in question, and can be downloaded easily into spreadsheets, or any TMS.”</p>
<p>Putting this kind of structure in place and scaling back existing bank relationships is by no means easy, though. “There are all sorts of issues caused by the relationships, by local issues and by the inevitable teething problems with the new, more concentrated service. We have been in the fortunate position of being able to start with a very concentrated banking structure – even then, it is a challenge resisting all the ‘helpful’ suggestions emanating from various parts of the business about how we would gain by opening relationships with more local banks,” Glendinning observes.</p>
<p>But he also reiterates that “the more banks you have, the harder and more expensive it is to collect the data, and to effectively control the cash, once you know where it is. A tough stance may not win any popularity contests – but it certainly improves efficiency.”</p>
<p>Nevertheless, in today’s world, the counterparty risk exposure of working with a single bank provider is simply not an option for the majority of multinational companies – or for those with significant borrowing requirements. Running a multi-bank relationship spreads that risk, but also spreads your cash – making visibility more challenging.</p>
<p>“At this point, you really have to think long and hard about the relationships that you choose,” says Persson. “If you work with global or regional banks and use the partner banks in their network to cover your needs, this will give you better visibility than choosing individual in-country banks. Not only because there is more integration, but quite often you will find that the local banks who are not in some kind of alliance simply do not have the technology to provide the information that you need – whether that be SWIFT capability or a proprietary system.”</p>
<h4 id="cash-management-structures">Cash management structures</h4>
<p>Where some companies are prepared to invest in technology to improve their visibility, others cannot justify the expenditure, or simply see another way. Lenovo, for instance, has taken a largely structural approach to improving cash visibility and control. “We have done everything to keep the cash structure as simple as possible: by having a single account in each country, we have been able to avoid the dispersion of cash which is a major cause of lack of visibility,” says Glendinning. “Also, we operate a physical daily sweep of cash to our centre – this avoids having cash balances build up around the world except, of course, in countries with exchange controls.”</p>
<p>Moving cash to a single location, often the company’s home market, or to a given location that is favourable from a tax or regulatory point of view, is a technique that is commonly employed by companies looking to achieve visibility over their cash position on a per currency basis. This can be achieved by using an electronic banking system to initiate credit transfers, which is highly manual, or through an automated cash pooling solution.</p>
<div class="boxed">
<h3 id="pooling-visibility-and-control">Pooling: visibility and control</h3>
<p>Here we stray more into the realm of cash mobility, than visibility, however the two are inevitable bedfellows when it comes to best practice liquidity management. In fact, the term ‘visibility’ is becoming almost synonymous with the double whammy of ‘visibility and control’. After all, as Persson puts it, “if you can’t control and mobilise the money, then the value of having visibility over it is vastly reduced.”</p>
<p>So how can pooling assist? While both physical and notional pooling can help to support improved real-time visibility and control over global cash positions, there are some important nuances to grasp. According to a recent whitepaper published by the Treasury Alliance Group consultancy: “Many companies are initially attracted to notional pooling because of its conceptual simplicity and the fact that much of the work is done by the bank. As corporate thinking evolves to include regulatory issues and price, physical pooling generally becomes the more preferred choice.”</p>
<p>While the whitepaper outlines several drivers for this preference, including the advent of the Single Euro Payments Area (SEPA) and the growth in enterprise-wide ERP adoption, another factor quoted in favour of physical pooling is that “virtually all cash is visible through web-based balance reporting solutions which allow treasurers nearly instant access to all accounts in the pooling arrangement.”</p>
<p>But for Mustafa Kiliç, former Head of Regional Treasury and Group Risk and Insurance Manager at a white goods manufacturer, the key to that statement is the word ‘virtually’. “We were operating in locations where it was extremely difficult to gain visibility, such as Russia.” Adopting one cash and liquidity management approach for all countries the company was operating in was simply not feasible. “Due to different rules and regulations some entities may not be permitted to participate in cash concentration or notional cash pooling agreements. This makes visibility very challenging, especially as the complex markets do not tend to have an advanced technical infrastructure in place,” explains Kiliç.</p>
<p>In conjunction with ING/Bank Mendes Gans, the company developed a hybrid cash pooling solution that would allow it a level of visibility and control that was not possible through physical or notional pooling alone. “Before we had the hybrid solution, we would be buying one currency, selling another and making inter-company loans. And if it was a significant amount of money, we would wait for the right time in the market to do the FX deal, perhaps as long as a week, meaning that even if the cash was visible, it was not reachable. The hybrid cash pool gave us instant access to our cash – as well as visibility, even in challenging countries such as Russia and Turkey.”</p>
<p><em>The technical details of this hybrid cash pool can be found on the Treasury Today website, as the solution was Highly Commended in the 2010 Adam Smith Awards in the Global Liquidity Management category. And for more information on physical and notional cash pooling techniques, refer to Treasury Today’s European Cash Management Handbook.</em></p>
<p><a href="/adamsmith/2010/winners/glm-highly-commended-indesit">treasurytoday.com/adamsmith/2010/winners/glm-highly-commended-indesit</a></p>
</div>
<h3 id="reaching-the-next-level">Reaching the next level</h3>
<p>Beyond the three macro factors outlined above, there are numerous tips and tricks that companies can employ to improve their cash visibility. The relevance of these largely depends on each company’s visibility goals – and even definitions, however.</p>
<p>Persson, for example, believes that a useful tool for taking visibility one step further is electronic bank account management (eBAM). “It may not offer account visibility as such, but having control around account management processes, data and signatories makes visibility sustainable.” Indeed, some companies implementing eBAM have reportedly discovered bank accounts that they did not even know existed before – so this adds a completely new dimension to the visibility concept.</p>
<p>For others, valuable visibility tools include commercial cards – these are often linked with expense management systems, which help improve visibility as they offer treasurers the functionality to consolidate their indirect costs in one place, allowing for a more accurate review of transactions and overall expenditure. “This greater visibility of outgoings also enables treasurers to track trends, such as potential over-expenditure and spend with suppliers,” says Karen Penney, Vice President and General Manager of Global Corporate Payments at American Express. “Companies with a relaxed policy may find that in allowing their employees to select suppliers, they are missing out on the opportunity to negotiate preferential rates for their company. Armed with the data, they can then ensure they establish a sharper policy, and shape conversations with their teams about the use of expenses in their company more effectively.”</p>
<p>What is more, says Penney, consolidating expenditure into a centralised system also saves treasurers valuable time cross-checking data. “Hundreds of hours can be spent checking costs, and making and recording payments, whereas a card programme can alleviate this time burden through creating automated and therefore more accurate processes.”</p>
<h3 id="technology-holds-the-answers">Technology holds the answers</h3>
<p>These two examples alone highlight that while there are structural and organisational solutions that undeniably help, there is nothing quite like technology and data to improve visibility; but that technology has to be centralised and fit-for-purpose. “Just make sure you’ve got the right technology and the right data, especially from your operations,” warns Skanska’s Müldner. Otherwise, it’s a case of ‘garbage in, garbage out’, which defeats the point of the exercise entirely.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
</data>
