<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Cash pooling structures]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=442D8EEB3855C7EE2EEE15E0118A66AB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=508C05D907380EA1536CC23DC53DDFE6"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C4584DD6EB3AC5D829BF43CDE48117CB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=45B2496E608F28A35B6B5FF7E30727AE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5A3C5609349D9B71C686D82EE6B4A318"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Two business people discussing charts on their laptops" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=047135B449D363E733CF77E4E45712B5" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=047135B449D363E733CF77E4E45712B5"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading">A fresh approach to the working capital challenges driven by market and regulatory factors</h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Rupa Mankad, Citi’s Asia Regional Liquidity Products Head explains how hybrid cash pooling structures support today’s working capital challenges. The impact of recent tax developments also needs to be closely followed and considered, says Rohit Narula, EY’s Asia-Pacific Financial Services International Tax and Transaction Services Leader in Hong Kong.</em></p>




<img alt="Portrait of Rupa Mankad, Asia Regional Liquidity Products Head, Citi" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/cash-management/2022-01-11-tt-00-sf__citi__rupa-mankad__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=CF088BFB8EA57CD140CD8E46DC2D6C4C" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Rupa Mankad, Asia Regional Liquidity Products Head, Citi" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Rupa Mankad</h3>
<h5 class="title">Asia Regional Liquidity Products Head</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Citi logo" width="50"/></p>


<img alt="Portrait of Rohit Narula, Asia-Pacific Financial Services ITTS Leader in Hong Kong, EY" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi__ey__rohit-narula__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=0BCCAE0940B6431A336F98EC1AA3A0BC" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Rohit Narula, Asia-Pacific Financial Services ITTS Leader in Hong Kong, EY" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Rohit Narula</h3>
<h5 class="title">Asia-Pacific Financial Services ITTS Leader in Hong Kong</h5>
<p><img alt="EY logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/ernst-and-young-logo-2017-90x43.svg?la=en&amp;hash=B3E50312A9A13205248D68136C0D25F8" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="EY logo" width="120"/></p>




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Cash pooling structures are in demand as companies continue to manage supply chain disruptions and consequent pressures on their working capital amidst the pandemic. Major reforms to the international tax system were suggested by the OECD in December 2021. These OECD published detailed rules will assist in the implementation of a new global minimum 15% effective tax rate. These changes are also likely to impact the design and management of cash pooling structures.</p>
<p>The rise in volatility and broken supply chains has created challenges of forecasting working capital requirements and FX handling. These factors are showing a clear need for companies to have adequate liquidity and working capital buffers to manage the volatility and seamlessly fund payment obligations. This is driving an increased focus on cash pooling solutions to achieve liquidity and funding efficiency.</p>
<h4 id="business-and-treasury-models">Business and treasury models</h4>
<p>Cash pools, are often hybrid in nature and consist of a combination of multi-currency notional pooling, physical cash pooling and virtual account structures with value-added services like interest re-allocation services. Such hybrid cash pooling structures allow corporates to have a firmer grip on their liquidity. Today, corporate treasurers need to demonstrate resilience by extracting liquidity and ensuring it is available in the right place at the right time, and in the right currency. This strategy minimises the corporate’s bank borrowing costs across group entities, and helps corporates centralise investments and bridge the cash flow cycle mismatch across entities and currencies.</p>
<p>In another trend, growing direct-to-consumer sales are also driving the demand for physical cash pooling structures. As they go global, Asia’s fast-growing unicorns have increased their focus on online and real time collections and this puts increased pressure on their working capital, accelerating working capital velocity and in turn adding to their forecasting challenges. Flows are no longer predictable, and online sales have also ushered in FX challenges as companies sell more in local currencies which is an important contributor to sales growth. Demand for physical cash pooling structures with embedded automated FX solutions and improved near-real time visibility of entities is becoming pivotal.</p>
<p>Mature corporate clients generally have a formally established treasury centre, or in-house bank entity, and operate with well-defined, centralised liquidity structures with embedded “on-behalf” collection and payment structures. Such large corporates also have well-defined, investment borrowing and FX policies, and prefer single entity multi-currency notional pooling structures to enable group funding from the in-house bank entity.  In fact, in-house banks which have FX netting arrangements in place generally prefer physical cash pooling structures given their “ownership treasury model” and automated inter-company FX netting.  Banks are also strategically pivoting to single-entity multi-currency notional pooling and physical cash pooling structures given regulatory costs and risks associated with multi-entity notional pooling structures.</p>
<p>Large companies have in recent years grown wary of single country risks and many of them are increasingly favouring multiple pooling structures across regions instead of one single global pool. This started with Brexit and the demand to diversify away from a single, London-based, cash pool structure. During the pandemic many corporates opted for a second pool in Asia to simplify the currency and time zone management.</p>
<p>In contrast to large corporates, many of the Micro-Small-and-Medium Enterprises (MSME) and going-global digital unicorns prefer physical sweeping structures across entities in the form of multi entity physical cash pooling structures. Their primary focus tends to be centralised funding, operational efficiency, and seamless funding of group entity payment obligations. The implementation of these physical cash pooling structures is simpler from an accounting, tax and legal agreement execution perspective compared to complex notional pooling structures.</p>
<h4 id="tax">Tax</h4>
<p>We at EY have analysed cash pooling structures from a tax perspective and have observed that tax developments are also impacting these structures. Over the years the impact has been driven by developments on tax treaty eligibility, concepts of beneficial ownership, substance over form and anti avoidance measures. The recent Base Erosion and Profit Shifting (BEPS) actions initiated at an international level, and anti avoidance measures historically implemented by specific countries in their domestic tax laws and judicial precedents, continue to change the tax landscape, preventing companies shifting profits to low tax jurisdictions and requiring a review of pooling structures.</p>
<p>It is important to note that at the end of 2021, 137 countries agreed to a two-pillar solution to reform international taxation rules and ensure multinationals pay a fair share of tax wherever they operate (popularly now referred to as BEPS 2.0)<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Pillar Two of the two-pillar solution, which will apply a global minimum 15% effective tax rate, is likely to come into effect from 2023. Treasury teams need to be cognizant of such changes to tax laws and the associated enhanced costs of compliance. On the back of these developments, we expect treasury teams to revisit their cash pooling structures and in particular, the cross-border intra group funding arrangements within such structures with a focus on the location of the treasury or in-house bank entity, mix in capital structures and the types of financial instruments used.</p>
<p>Given the developments, existing treasury constructs such as treasury centres or in-house banks, which involve intra-group lending through intermediate entities in favourable tax treaty jurisdictions, will need to be re-examined. In any case, given the introduction of the principal purpose test (PPT) in many of the existing tax treaties, any such intermediate entity that does not have substance but manages the risk and an appropriate amount of capital, could be questioned on its claim of tax treaty benefits.</p>
<p>When it comes to cash pooling structures, companies also need to review the eligibility of inter-company offsets considering restrictions such as thin-capitalisation rules on interest deductibility. Thin capitalisation rules augment the transfer pricing legislation which has been implemented across the Asia Pacific region and aids tax authorities in challenging interest free loans between related parties. Moreover, as more formal transfer pricing legislation has come into play, zero interest loans for related party financing are now no longer sustainable in the post-BEPS environment.</p>
<p>Major Asian economies, Hong Kong and Singapore, are gearing-up for BEPS Pillar Two implementation, evident in their respective budgets earlier this year. Hong Kong is looking to introduce a legislative proposal to implement global minimum tax rate and a domestic minimum top up tax. Similarly, Singapore is exploring a top up tax called the minimum effective tax rate or METR. Both countries are also likely to introduce several non-tax related measures to retain their competitiveness in terms of remaining the location of preference for regional treasury centres.</p>
<p>From an impact assessment and implementation perspective, the BEPS regulation is also seeing corporates focus on documentation around intra-company flow of data across locations. Consequently, there is an increased adoption of technology and value-added pooling features to drive compliance with the developing tax landscape.</p>
<p>We at Citi, have curated solutions such as Citi’s ‘Inter-Account Limit Alerts’, Inter-Account Limit Controls’ and ‘Principal Reset Features’ which support clients in complying with their thin-capitalisation requirements.  We notice increased activity when it comes to changes requested on interest re-allocation rates for intergroup borrowing and lending amongst mature corporates and equally so with MSME clients.</p>
<p>The new regulation may influence invoicing models, and as a consequence thereof, holding company details and treasury entity and funding structures will change. However, it is also important to note that corporates facing a tax bill that is likely to exceed the benefits of centralised investment may shift to liquidity sweeping only on a ‘need-to’ basis.</p>
<h4 id="digitisation-and-efficiency">Digitisation and efficiency</h4>
<p>During this pandemic clients have increased the frequency of review of their entire banking footprint across group entities, countries, and currencies, seeking to maximise the entities and accounts under liquidity structures, in the interest of better visibility and efficiency. Banks have been supporting corporates up-tier their cash pooling structures by delivering a digital end-to-end user experience, as well as offering value-added products and features:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Digital and frictionless account and structure on-boarding.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Self-service tools to make dynamic changes to structures.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Balance inquiry APIs for increased visibility of group liquidity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Improved global liquidity structure and balance visibility dashboards.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Insights and alerts on inter-company limits.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Virtual accounts to help them segregate cash by business unit and product.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>FX and hedging solutions to manage operational excess in non-functional currencies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Multibank visibility and concentration of liquidity from local collection banks.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In conclusion, corporates across the board are undertaking more regular reviews of their cash pooling structures. While the objectives of these reviews begin with internal factors such as the need to have improved visibility, control, operating and working capital efficiency, there are also external tax and regulatory lenses influencing these changes. Just as new accounts and entities continue to be added to widen the base of these cash pooling structures, new and enhanced pooling features and controls are being availed to up-tier cash pooling structures and to make them more efficient.  We are seeing active interaction between corporates and banks in this space and believe this may be just the beginning of a new journey.</p>
<p><em>IRS Circular 230 Disclosure: Citigroup Inc. and its affiliates do not provide tax or legal advice. This information provided in this article is for informational purposes only and may not represent the views or opinions of Citigroup Inc. or its affiliates (collectively, “Citi”), employees or officers. The information contained herein does not constitute and shall not be construed to constitute legal, investment, tax and/or accounting advice by Citi.</em></p>
<p><em>All tax related information and views are those of EY and Citi makes no representation as to the accuracy, completeness, or timeliness of such information. The readers of this article should obtain guidance and/or advice, based on their own particular circumstances, from their own legal, investment, tax or accounting advisor.</em></p>

<h5>Footnote</h5>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.oecd.org/tax/beps/statement-on-a-two-pillar-solution-to-address-the-tax-challenges-arising-from-the-digitalisation-of-the-economy-october-2021.htm" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Statement on a Two-Pillar Solution to Address the Tax Challenges Arising from the Digitalisation of the Economy – 8 October 2021 – OECD</a> <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Rupa Mankad, Citi’s Asia Regional Liquidity Products Head explains how hybrid cash pooling structures support today’s working capital challenges. The impact of recent tax developments also needs to be closely followed and considered, says Rohit Narula, EY’s Asia-Pacific Financial Services International Tax and Transaction Services Leader in Hong Kong.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2022-04-26-tt-00-sf__citi-ey__two-colleagues-formal-wear-working-together-2003398163__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2022-04-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury in a time of turmoil]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>In the latest episode of Treasury Dialogues, we discuss with Pramod Iyengar, CFO at global payments and money transfer business Veem, and Citi’s Will Artingstall how companies can ensure they survive and thrive in the Covid world.</em></p>
<p><a class="button--red-stroke" href="#video-interview">Watch video interview</a> </p> <picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=94F2216871392875B869957285431F6B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5266968438CFB67620BB95C65FB843A1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=74699F317AE68B702D9F20FCEF10C585"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FD1B38BEE069DABD92C9358B7525BCB2"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C37D825FF681D139B6A0094D35AEEC16"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Clock during rush hour at train station" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DB7BC9770CEBDAD6B32F51C64D45DBD3" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DB7BC9770CEBDAD6B32F51C64D45DBD3"/></picture> 


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Portrait of Pramod Iyengar, CFO, Veem" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__citi__pramod-iyengar__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=E5B27574B048B7114CDE67C1E8137448" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Pramod Iyengar, CFO, Veem" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Pramod Iyengar</h3>
<h5 class="title">CFO</h5>
<p><img alt="Veem logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/veem-logo-2020-110x24.png?la=en&amp;hash=1F14AED3A061ECD7419F63BEC8EA4267" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Veem logo" width="110"/></p>


<img alt="Portrait of Will Artingstall, Emerging Payments &amp; Business Development Director, Citi" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__citi__will-artingstall__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=53FB17F65BB34E7FB693551052D677C3" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Will Artingstall, Emerging Payments &amp; Business Development Director, Citi" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Will Artingstall</h3>
<h5 class="title">Emerging Payments &amp; Business Development Director</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Citi logo" width="50"/></p>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>When the pandemic struck, a main concern for global payments and money transfer business Veem was the welfare of its core SME client base. Many of Veem’s clients faced revenue streams grinding to a halt and difficult questions around staff retention, says Pramod Iyengar, CFO at Veem. Although government stimulus and support in the first months of the pandemic helped, it hasn’t stopped the uncertainty for many businesses.</p>
<p>A key question for the treasury teams within Veem’s customer base – as well as Veem’s own treasury department – was access to working capital. “It was and continues to be very hard for a lot of SMEs,” he recalls. Indeed, access to working capital is one of the most important learnings from the pandemic so far, he believes, urging treasury teams to look at how they invest and deploy credit, and to optimise their spend and access to funding to weather the blips – the assumption that access to capital and liquidity will always be straightforward has changed. “Get a pulse on your business,” he says.</p>
<p>Access to working capital is certainly one factor separating COVID’s corporate winners and losers. That said, analysis of companies that have done well through the pandemic and those that have struggled, reveals a surprising picture, explains Will Artingstall, Emerging Payments &amp; Business Development Director at Citi. Just like Veem’s client base, Citi found most companies faced disruption to their core business and had to pivot to some degree. Many were faced with resource constraints, particularly around their workforce, but technology companies have not been the straightforward winners.</p>
<p>The assumption that the tech sector has automatically fared better than, for example, an industrial giant, is simplistic. Artingstall explains that in many cases, organisations have responded with either “weather the storm” strategies or by focusing on growth. At the same time, tech companies have been challenged because they too still depend on physical supply chains that have been hit by the pandemic. Of course, reaching for growth in the middle of a pandemic is tricky. It involves addressing difficult questions like where to invest and what products to launch during an acute economic event, he says.</p>
<h3 id="dialogue-demand">Dialogue demand</h3>
<p>Both Iyengar and Artingstall note a sharp spike in demand for strategic dialogue between treasury teams and their banking partners. Companies want support in understanding how their products are working, and help planning (as much as possible) for the year ahead, says Artingstall. “We’ve seen a lot of engagement in strategic dialogue driven by COVID,” he says, noting that uncertainty is compounding the problem. “Nobody knows how long COVID will last or the right speed at which to execute strategies.”</p>
<p>It is these kinds of challenges that are also making strategic treasury important. Companies that have placed treasury at the heart of their business in a central, advisory role have weathered the pandemic best, says Iyengar. “We have learnt that rigidity doesn’t help,” he says. “It’s a team effort; especially at SME level.” Examples of how treasury can become a strategic partner to the business and integrate operations could include evolving online commerce capabilities or integrating global hedging strategies, he suggests. It is this kind of role that builds a healthy treasury; the back-end is important, but treasury needs to evolve and become a strategic player, he says.</p>
<p id="video-interview">The pandemic hasn’t altered Citi’s core advice to corporate clients, although the bank has strengthened its key messages around areas like cyber risk and digitisation backed by the next generation of financial infrastructure. Indeed, Iyengar notes that fraud risk and the need for tight internal controls has become a key treasury focus since March. “The importance of building up internal processes has been a learning curve for a lot of companies,” he says.</p>
<p>Perhaps one of the most important learnings from the pandemic so far has been the affirmation that Veem and Citi are people businesses. At Citi, the crisis has highlighted the need to support clients holistically, including ensuring they have the right governance in place or the technology to allow corporate treasury teams to work from home and get away from paper. Now the “dust has settled,” the emphasis has shifted to continuity and partnering for the long term, as well as keeping clients focused on the future.</p>


<a class="video-panel__link" href="#video-player">
<img src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/tt-2021-02-18__citi-veem-video__1920x1080.jpg">
<span class="video-panel--overlay">
<span class="icon-play">Watch video</span>
</span>
</img></a>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[In the latest episode of Treasury Dialogues, we discuss with Pramod Iyengar, CFO at global payments and money transfer business Veem, and Citi’s Will Artingstall how companies can ensure they survive and thrive in the Covid world.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2021-01-02-tt-02-sf__rush-hour-fast-moving-evening-traffic-1562693662__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2021-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Are you receiving me? Exploring the ‘dark side’ of the balance sheet]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F9F75C0DB92ABB5B5E9B881A0B7C2A3A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1CE415E2DDD24F282C5CB609C76760AA"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3D21E0FDAD182ED300F76B9C69EE98E8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7A8F34DA804BFA10EE37C9EBF86DB065"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7B47A0D3F947EA07EAC06AEF4DF940F4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Dark night sky with only a little light part of the moon" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FEDE92CAE5E5A7C2AFEB85CB326E04BF" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FEDE92CAE5E5A7C2AFEB85CB326E04BF"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Companies are increasingly finding alternative ways to improve their working capital.</em></p>



<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="John Murray, EMEA Industrials Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__john-murray__citi__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=C1D803A55085216F0E4748BC74740A25" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">John Murray</h3>
<h5 class="title">EMEA Industrials Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" width="50"/></p>

<!-- BOXED -->



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Today, challenges such as geopolitics, cybercrime and regulation vie for attention with opportunities offered by innovation, collaboration and optimisation. These are interesting times and every business has to find a careful balance because, regardless of sector or specialism, they share one common goal: to survive and thrive.</p>
<p>A big part of the challenge is keeping working capital metrics healthy, says John Murray, EMEA Industrials Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi. “Analysts often report on the success of balance sheet management, assessing whether a business can deliver the returns that it promises to the market.”</p>
<p>Murray notes that companies in the industrials sector are increasingly looking to alternative sources of financing as they manage their balance sheets and generate free cash flow.</p>
<p>At Citi the industrials sector covers six sub-sectors ranging from automotive and airlines through to shipping and logistics. It therefore presents a diverse set of needs and challenges. Automotive, for example, has to respond to the drive for electrification, digital connectivity and in-car payments as well as changing business models of ownership and use. Meanwhile, shipping and logistics companies are having to manage greener fleets and greater digitisation. In each case, delivering on expected returns is vital.</p>
<h4 id="meeting-the-challenge">Meeting the challenge</h4>
<p>Sustainability and efficiency issues are being tackled by all sectors with “every company focused on improving shareholder return,” Murray reports.</p>
<p>Traditionally, companies have used supply chain finance and B2B card solutions to improve their working capital and free cash flow. This gives access to different streams of liquidity and improves quarter and year-end working capital for the buyer and seller, says Murray.</p>
<p>With digitisation and disruption driving change, Citi is enhancing its value proposition to give immediate benefits to buyers and suppliers. Today Citi’s corporate card programme is used by buyers to pay suppliers earlier. This protects their working capital flow whilst extending buyer days purchasing outstanding (DPO) and reducing supplier days sales outstanding (DSO). Today, Citi is working with a fintech to extend the solution and allow companies to pay their suppliers who do not accept card payments within the card programme.</p>
<h4 id="rise-of-receivables">Rise of receivables</h4>
<p>To be truly effective, both sides of the balance sheet need to be considered, as treasurers look for diversified sources of financing and sales teams seek new ways to unlock revenue growth.</p>
<p>Treasurers are now looking for ways to further improve their metrics and are using their receivables to do so. Increasingly, they are considering sales financing and distribution finance programmes that harness the power of receivables not only to improve working capital but to provide strong sales incentives to customers.</p>
<p>So-called ‘sales finance’ uses traditional receivables financing structures in a more sophisticated way, allowing companies to offer selected customers and distributors extended payment terms in exchange for increased business. The financing programme mitigates the impact of the extended term and results in better working capital for both buyer and seller – a ‘win-win’ scenario.</p>
<p>“In the last 12 months there has been a surge of interest from our industrials sector clients to explore alternative financing solutions that tap into the receivables side of the balance sheet and drive sales growth,” says Murray.</p>
<p>For example, companies in the paper and packaging and chemicals sectors are aiming to improve their buyers’ purchasing power to increase sales volumes and are implementing these solutions to improve and maximise their returns.</p>
<p>Emirates Global Aluminium’s recent Highly Commended Working Capital Management award in the Treasury Today Adam Smith Awards, was in recognition of its off-balance sheet funding solution.</p>
<p>This was based on a bespoke Citi receivables purchasing programme which is helping to accelerate free cash flow and ultimately improve return on invested capital (ROIC). The company achieved this through maximising liquidity from a portfolio of its clients, both large and small.</p>
<p>Murray notes that many industrial companies have sought to meet quarter and year end working capital targets through the sale of their receivables whilst achieving off-balance sheet treatment under International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS). “One client with a diversified customer base recently completed a Distribution Finance Programme to optimise their working capital each quarter and release excess cash.”</p>
<p>Regardless of whether global sales, procurement, credit, treasury or another function instigates a receivables financing programme, Murray believes that it is essential for all parts of the business to be aligned with the ultimate goal of delivering expected returns.</p>
<p>“Clients are working with us and exploring these alternative solutions to optimise their balance sheets,” he continues. “With solutions on the receivables side of the balance sheet refined and modernised for today’s needs we provide detailed support and analysis of each client’s unique frame of reference before providing the solution, whether that is for one customer or for a portfolio of hundreds.”</p>
<p>When it comes to healthy working capital metrics, treasury is well-placed to discover alternative sources of finance. With payables solutions typically well met, depending on the mix of receivables in any given market, the treasurer can also now play a decisive role in exploring the other side of the balance sheet.</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Companies are increasingly finding alternative ways to improve their working capital.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2019-09-10-tt-03-sf__dark-side-moon-background-material-elements-358025306__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2019-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Working capital]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8B370F3E03D2E6FDB264A503D122ED18"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4F2C3D5356B8A5AB2F484C400475AB3D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7D002B57FDB906BD8742EFF5E5CC5ECC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7F3E67ED9FACC91EAF65D9577C947DD5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F62B6B2D16C58D579E5CA906F05C8AC7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Silhouette of team building question mark" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AE67A8A55633FE6E7F6271F26929D66" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AE67A8A55633FE6E7F6271F26929D66"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question:</h3>
<p><em>“My business is struggling with working capital and payments are often too slow for our suppliers. What can I do?”</em></p>




<img alt="Portrait of Venkat ES" height="150" src="/i/2018/09/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__venkat-es__100x150.jpg" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 0 1em;" width="100"/>
<h4 style="margin-bottom:5px;">Venkat ES</h4>
<h5>Head of Asia Pacific Treasury Product, Global Transaction Services</h5>
<h5>Bank of America Merrill Lynch</h5>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Efficient and effective management of working capital is crucial for any enterprise. The traditional definition of ‘working capital’ as current assets minus current liabilities is a very simple concept but it is core to the day-to-day running of a business.</p>
<p>To have sound financial and operational efficiency, optimising the cash conversion cycle (days sales outstanding (DSO) + days inventory outstanding (DIO) – days payments outstanding (DPO)) is an integral part of financial supply chain management. This helps in reducing bank debt but also ensures sustainable and stable links in the supply chain.</p>
<p>The rapid developments in the payment landscape also mean businesses are increasingly looking to payment solutions, both traditional and modern, to unlock hidden cash to achieve effective working capital management. Businesses can explore the following:</p>
<h5>Holistic view:</h5>
<p>Businesses can adopt a holistic view of suppliers and dealers by categorising them as either strategic or non-strategic partners to gain better payment terms. Deep dive analysis of payment terms has shown that there are opportunities to leverage large dollar value supplier payments to extend payment terms, particularly with strategic vendors. Dynamic discounting is also another tool that can be effectively deployed for working capital management. Providing discounts and rebates to dealer side of the receivables may improve payment terms and cash flows.</p>
<h5>Supply chain financing (SCF):</h5>
<p>SCF is another option that helps to stabilise financial liquidity by using third-party financing in place of the organisation’s own balance sheet to fund early payment discounts. With an increasing demand for procure-to-pay automation, more companies are showing their interest in SCF to attract and enjoy early payment discounts. Buyers can benefit by reducing spend on goods while suppliers can obtain liquidity and maintain flexibility over receivables.</p>
<h5>Corporate cards:</h5>
<p>Another great way to accelerate cash flow is through the use of purchase and settlement cards (P-Cards). P-Cards are a traditional fit for financial supply chain management as they combine payments and financing. The benefit of using cards comes from the extended payment dates. Suppliers can receive payments within a few days so they receive money quickly. On the other hand, buyers would have a longer period to pay the bank, enabling them to maximise their working capital for a longer duration.</p>
<h5>Going digital:</h5>
<p>Effective use of business analytics and intelligence, moving from paper to electronic modes of invoicing, adopting electronic modes of payments, digitalising the reconciliation processes would help the management of working capital and its efficiency.</p>
<h5>Effective usage of real-time payment (RTP) mechanism:</h5>
<p>The mass adoption of real-time payment globally has contributed to an environment where consumers and businesses are expecting to make payments, settle bills and transfer money securely and quickly. It is all the more crucial for businesses to leverage available real-time payment infrastructure to manage cash flows and working capital.</p>



<img alt="Portrait of Nicholas Soo" height="150" src="/i/2018/09/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__nicholas-soo__100x150.jpg" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 0 1em;" width="100"/>
<h4 style="margin-bottom:5px;">Nicholas Soo</h4>
<h5>Director, Regional Head of Payments, Global Liquidity and Cash Management</h5>
<h5>HSBC</h5>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Like most solutions in life, there is no quick fix and patience, due-diligence and analysis are required – but you can take short-, medium- and long-term actions to rectify the issue for good.</p>
<p>In the short term, you should assess your relationship with suppliers, especially your more strategic partners, to determine if slow payments will pose a significant business disruption risk. If business critical, consider immediate solutions (even if they are likely to be pricier), such as bank facilities (working capital funding, or providing early payment discounts) to ensure your business can continue to operate smoothly.</p>
<p>In the medium term, which could be anywhere from three to six months, you should seek to undertake an end-to-end assessment of your working capital cycle – with a particular focus on the order to cash cycle. Ask yourself: where are the inefficiencies coming from? Many companies face issues in matching and reconciling incoming payments which, if resolved, can free up anything from two days to two weeks cash flow. You should also take the opportunity to consider whether terms with both customers and suppliers can be renegotiated.</p>
<p>From client conversations, we have also learnt that undergoing a stocktake of credit terms across both suppliers and buyers, as well as seeking opportunities for standardisation, is an important step in tackling such issues.</p>
<p>As your payment is someone else’s collection, you may also want to consider speaking to your supplier on their reconciliation challenges and whether you can structure your payment (ie providing the right payment in the right place) accordingly to ease their administrative burden.</p>
<p>Such engagements could benefit you by providing improved chances of discussing favourable terms, or at the very least assist to eliminate some processing float.</p>
<p>Then there’s the long term. At HSBC, we’ve observed that market trends, changing buyer behaviour and enablement via technology are dramatically changing the distribution channels for our clients. These include selling directly online and participating in marketplaces, among other digital platforms. Embracing technology to improve efficiencies is a game changer in the market, and we’d recommend exploring how these opportunities can supplement your business strategy and have a positive direct impact on your working capital model.</p>



<img alt="Portrait of François-Dominique Doll" height="150" src="/i/2018/09/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__francois-dominique-doll__100x150.jpg" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 0 1em;" width="100"/>
<h4 style="margin-bottom:5px;">François-Dominique Doll</h4>
<h5>Director, Treasury Advisory Services</h5>
<h5>Deloitte Southeast Asia</h5>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>When talking about working capital, it is worth highlighting that it is made up of three main components: receivables from customers, payments to suppliers, and inventory levels of primary or finished goods.</p>
<p>The dynamics of these three components can vary depending on the type of business and/or industry. For instance, retail companies and others in the service-driven industry will not have the same working capital issues as an industrial manufacturing group.</p>
<p>For treasurers, while they may have little direct control over inventory management, they are able to directly influence receivables and payables.</p>
<p>Where collections are concerned, it is about establishing the right level of agreement with the customer, either through open account or letters of credit, to ensure that payment is made on time for the goods and services delivered.</p>
<p>A key index for collections is DSO, whereby the CFO is able to see the status of the payment terms – are they on track or behind? Minimising the DSO involves having the right controls and procedures to reduce any delays in payments and therefore, translating receivables directly into cash.</p>
<p>Utilising electronic collections can help reduce the float on receivables as well. Banks offer a number of solutions to improve working capital, including corporate credit cards, virtual accounts and lockboxes, all of which enhance the collection reconciliation process and identify early any late payments from customers.</p>
<p>On the payments side, recent surveys in Europe show that there is a significant increase in late payments from corporations, which is often not sanctioned. Some companies voluntarily delay their supplier payments to make a gain on working capital. It can be a matter of size where large players take advantage of their smaller suppliers, knowing that some SMEs cannot do without their business.</p>
<p>While it is good practice to minimise payment cycles to once or twice a month to optimise resources, the reduction of bank fees through automated payment method such as ACH makes it possible for companies to support their suppliers by putting in place a number of SCF programmes. These can be done through the banking partner, and suppliers can be onboarded in order to be paid earlier on their receivables and they can also get an extension on the DPO.</p>
<p>SCF is a key topic for treasurers in 2018. Yields on cash invested are still at low levels and treasurers realise that they can better leverage their working capital by offering financing solutions to their suppliers. Over the last few years, a number of fintech companies have emerged to connect directly suppliers with customers. These collaborative tools work by proposing dynamic discounting or by agreeing to a rate for payables based on supply and demand. This tends to be a win-win for both parties where working capital can be optimised in exchange for better returns.</p>
<p>With all these metrics, it then becomes essential for treasurers to use data analytics to regularly measure the value they contribute to the business and justify their importance to their senior management.</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<p>“To what extent is treasury being changed by consumer behaviour?”</p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[“My business is struggling with working capital and payments are often too slow for our suppliers. What can I do?”]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2018-09and10-tta-11-qa__silhouette-team-business-engineer-work-knock-604389833__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2018-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Working capital optimisation]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9B9B9CCBEA4A017D5145324F31683C9E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C2AAAB78562297B4F041060BC4CA6088"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CFA491F794DDDA3D2971DA8DCF1682B0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=901F84FB07EC0553DADA5C5AD0D3CE27"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=783B78B6D3DD652300EF7B0761C736AE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Gears over money notes" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=619B3CFE026093745C4E5443D301BA6C" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=619B3CFE026093745C4E5443D301BA6C"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Treasurers are increasingly playing a more central role within the organisation when it comes to optimising working capital. Where are the opportunities for treasurers to drive improvements in this area – and which challenges are likely to arise along the way?</em></p>
<p>Working capital management is a perennial concern for companies around the world – and in today’s environment, corporate treasurers are paying closer attention to this topic than ever before. So where are the most attractive opportunities for optimisation?</p>
<p>It’s clear that working capital optimisation is nothing new. “Capital has always been an expensive and scarce commodity for businesses to set up, run and grow,” says Varoon Mandhana, Senior Advisor, APAC Solutions, Treasury Services, J.P. Morgan. “A good part of this capital is tied up in day-to-day running of the business in the form of cash, payables, receivables and inventory (collectively referred to as working capital) besides other capital investments.”</p>
<p>As such, working capital is a significant concern for companies around the world – and one in which treasurers can play a key role. “This is a subject that is on every corporate client’s agenda,” says Michael Vrontamitis, Head of Trade, Europe &amp; Americas at Standard Chartered. “Treasury is becoming much more focused on working capital management as technology evolves and we move into the real-time world. This is being driven by the emergence of real-time payment systems and real-time information, particularly in Asia where developments like Alipay, WeChat and others are blazing the way.”</p>
<p>Of course, not all companies are equally focused on this topic. Vrontamitis observes that the competitiveness of particular industries may affect the extent to which working capital optimisation is seen as a priority. “For example, working capital management techniques are heavily used in the retail industry,” he says. “Margins in this sector are thin, so treasurers are particularly focused on any techniques that can help transfer risk, improve DPO and reduce costs for suppliers.”</p>
<p>In contrast, Vrontamitis notes that high-margin, cash-rich industries like oil and gas have traditionally placed less focus on working capital. However, he says that some of these sectors have seen increased pressure on their margins more recently – leading to a greater focus on conserving cash via working capital management.</p>
<h3 id="unlocking-working-capital">Unlocking working capital</h3>
<p>There are considerable opportunities to tackle this area more effectively. PwC’s 2017 Working Capital Study found that for companies in Asia, cash is increasingly locked up within lengthening working capital days. The report adds that with one of the worst net working capital days (NWCD) positions, “the average Asian company is well-placed to focus on releasing this cash to reverse current capex levels and stimulate return on capital employed (ROCE) improvements”.</p>
<p>Mandhana explains that companies that are able to optimise the use of capital through effective working capital management are able to generate higher ROCE by reducing their overall capital base and improving shareholder value. “Cash released through working capital optimisation presents an opportunity for companies to potentially retire expensive debt, internally fund projects and acquisitions as well as pay back shareholders,” he adds.</p>
<p>Venkat ES, Head of Asia Treasury Product Global Transaction Services at Bank of America Merrill Lynch (BofAML), adds that the efficient use of working capital is particularly critical today. “For one thing, working capital is especially important in the current market, where growth rates are moderate compared to the days of double-digit growth,” he says. “Secondly, with the pressure on margins and ROCE coming under severe strain, large enterprises have to rely on working capital optimisation to deliver better results.”</p>
<p>Venkat also cites the significance of evolving sales models in this area. “The model is changing from traditional sales to online sales,” he notes. “And this will have a significant impact on companies’ cash flows.” Indeed, a report published by the GSM Association last year in collaboration with Boston Consulting Group, Embracing the Digital Revolution, notes that digital technologies will influence up to 45% of all retail sales in India by 2025.</p>
<h3 id="taking-action">Taking action</h3>
<p>There are many reasons for focusing on working capital management – but how can companies tackle this area effectively?</p>
<p>For one thing, it’s important to look broadly at the different components of working capital: days payable outstanding (DPO), days sales outstanding (DSO) and days inventory outstanding (DIO). Companies can improve working capital in a number of different ways, such as by taking longer to pay supplier invoices – and, conversely, by collecting payment faster from customers. While benefits can certainly be gained by focusing on one of these areas on its own, these can be limited. A more effective approach is to tackle the full range of working capital metrics, while also taking into account the impact on the company’s buyers and suppliers.</p>
<p>“In the past, a lot of companies have focused only on getting benefits on the payables side by delaying payments to their suppliers,” says Venkat. “But increasingly companies are focusing on receivables and inventory as well.” Where receivables are concerned, the goal is to collect and reconcile payments as quickly as possible – and this is an area that Venkat says any company should be focusing on. “There are clear opportunities, irrespective of industry, for them to adopt the tools and solutions that are being developed both by banks and third parties,” he explains.</p>
<h3 id="adding-value">Adding value</h3>
<p>Working capital optimisation is an activity that extends across many different parts of the organisation. So where can treasurers add value to this process?</p>
<p>“While traditionally working capital optimisation has been a CFO-led and shared responsibility, treasurers are now playing a more strategic and pivotal role in company-wide efficiency initiatives,” says Mandhana. “Treasuries have a lot to bring to the table, considering their visibility over cash, cash management expertise and increasing role in managing financial risk and bank relationships.”</p>
<h4 id="promoting-cash-culture">Promoting cash culture</h4>
<p>Mandhana explains that treasuries are taking a lead role in working capital optimisation initiatives in a number of ways. For one thing, he points out that treasury is “uniquely positioned to promote cash culture throughout the organisation, not only by improving cash visibility and forecasting but also by building awareness within each business function about how their activities affect company cash performance.” He notes that both finance and the broader organisation – ie sales, operations and procurement – need to be educated on the connection between working capital efficiency and generating free cash flow to reduce capital needs or fund business growth.</p>
<h4 id="centralising-cash-management">Centralising cash management</h4>
<p>Another way in which treasury can drive working capital optimisation is by centralising cash management. “In a decentralised setup, subsidiaries tend to maintain high cash buffers, which in turn take the focus away from the need to reduce overall working capital levels,” says Mandhana. “Centralising cash across subsidiaries through pooling mechanisms, and transferring it back to the business as intercompany loans and deposits, not only helps in reducing overall cash needs but also drives business behaviour to optimise working capital utilisation.”</p>
<h4 id="institutionalising-policy-and-practices">Institutionalising policy and practices</h4>
<p>Mandhana adds that treasury plays a key role in institutionalising forecasting policy and practices across the organisation. “Effective implementation of the same has a direct impact on cash management and working capital optimisation,” he notes, adding that regular follow-up with subsidiary teams and the escalation of inaccurate forecasts can also help keep this process under control. Furthermore, Mandhana points out that treasury is assuming a leading role when it comes to arranging supply chain finance solutions for the business.</p>
<h3 id="getting-it-right">Getting it right</h3>
<p>There is plenty that organisations can do to optimise their working capital – and, equally, there are a number of challenges that can arise, and pitfalls that may need to be avoided. After all, a project which fails to meet its original goals – or which sees staff reverting to old processes over time – is unlikely to deliver the fullest possible benefits of working capital optimisation.</p>
<p>“When we implement these programmes, they are perennial,” says Vrontamitis. “It isn’t a case of implementing the deal and then having service reviews every six months. You’re constantly on-boarding suppliers onto the programme – and, of course, the purchasing needs of the company will change over time.”</p>
<h4 id="focusing-on-the-basics">Focusing on the basics</h4>
<p>For one thing, Vrontamitis advises that treasurers should avoid trying to run before they can walk. “My suggestion is to focus on getting the basics right,” he explains. “For example, if you are looking to increase payment terms from 30 to 60 days while adopting a payable financing programme, you first need to make sure that you have consistent processes in place for approving and paying invoices.”</p>
<p>Again, the need for robust processes extends beyond DPO. “Working capital improvements must be holistic across the order-to-cash cycle,” observes David Blair, an independent treasury consultant based in Singapore. Blair says that invoicing errors can represent a significant source of delays where accounts receivable is concerned. He also points out that it may be prudent for organisations to focus on the largest late payers who materially impact DSO in the first instance, rather than on smaller balances.</p>
<h4 id="collaborating-on-kpis">Collaborating on KPIs</h4>
<p>Also important is making sure that companies are applying key performance indicators (KPIs) consistently across divisions where working capital is concerned. “In an integrated world, we are better when we are connected,” says BofAML’s Venkat. “Each division needs to work together in order to support working capital goals across the enterprise as a whole. For example, whether there is an opportunity to negotiate better terms on the payables side, or reduce inventory, or collect payment faster, these things all need to be centrally co-ordinated – and treasury should play a key role in making that happen.”</p>
<h4 id="organisational-change">Organisational change</h4>
<p>Meanwhile, Mandhana points out that optimising working capital may require broad organisational change. Whereas treasury and finance teams may exercise more direct control over sources of capital through debt raising and capital markets, he says that “responsibility for managing cash, payables, receivables and inventory is spread unevenly across operational silos such as treasury, finance, operations, supply chain, sales and procurement.”</p>
<p>The entire organisation therefore needs to pull in the same direction when improving working capital – and this requires effective change management. However, as Mandhana observes, “most companies do not have a formal organisational structure to manage such initiatives.”</p>
<h4 id="securing-buy-in">Securing buy-in</h4>
<p>Also important is the need to secure buy-in and engagement from multiple parties. “You can’t just set these programmes up and expect them to run,” says Vrontamitis. “When you look at using techniques like payables financing and pre-shipment financing, it’s really important for all the different stakeholders to buy into the programme. Treasury needs to sign up, and so does the bank – but you also need procurement on board, and you need the suppliers themselves on board and seeing value in the programme.”</p>
<p>Likewise, Mandhana notes the importance of ensuring C-suite attention. “Considering the cross-functional nature of working capital initiatives, it’s important that companies set the tone at the top, with C-suite executives emphasising the importance of this topic while also setting annual targets to free up cash flow,” he comments.</p>
<h4 id="achieving-consistency">Achieving consistency</h4>
<p>For companies operating in multiple countries, local variations may also need to be taken into account. Vrontamitis notes that the regulations in Asia vary from market to market, meaning that solutions that work in some markets may present challenges in others. “For example, the use of insurance is more difficult in places like India, because you can’t use insurance-backed financing in that market,” he says. “And we’ve seen similar moves in China and Korea. So while you can achieve a broadly consistent strategy around a receivables finance programme, you might find there are some idiosyncrasies when it comes to what is or isn’t allowed by local regulation.”</p>
<h4 id="technology-and-data">Technology and data</h4>
<p>In addition, Mandhana points out the importance of leveraging technology and data. “Working capital optimisation requires visibility into various systems and tools capturing information on receivables, payables, inventory, suppliers and customer, business forecast and cash levels,” he says. As such, companies are changing the way in which they use technology: “Beyond the standard treasury and finance systems, corporates are starting to focus on data management and data visualisation tools that can provide them the required visibility and insights into working capital management.”</p>
<h4 id="further-challenges">Further challenges</h4>
<p>Aside from these issues, other obstacles can include a lack of visibility over key working capital metrics and processes, as well as challenges in getting non-finance people on board. Mandhana also says that the fear of harming customer or supplier relationships can slow down the process of payment term optimisation. “Instead of treating every customer or supplier the same way, companies need to take a more segmented and tailored approach to strike the right balance between price, service and cash flow,” he advises.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>As companies become increasingly focused on the benefits of working capital optimisation, it’s clear that there is much treasurers can do to drive improvements in this area. From promoting a cash focused culture to centralising cash management, treasurers can play an important role in creating the conditions needed for working capital success. Key to achieving success in this area is overcoming the possible obstacles by putting consistent processes in place, applying clear KPIs and gaining buy-in from everyone involved – as well as making the best use of the technology and data available.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Treasurers are increasingly playing a more central role within the organisation when it comes to optimising working capital. Where are the opportunities for treasurers to drive improvements in this area – and which challenges are likely to arise along the way?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/australian-money-aussie-currency-gears-ss275373254.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2018-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Unlocking the ties in working capital]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D3695B01A64D2258F9547844477F407B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5955AF207BC341E3F799BB9A3B85B3BB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=08D44B92AF8A25CEA4A1BF29EEE46936"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6590919E4ACEB56BDAD401BDAF214625"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=95E9A2B674AD3A3AB55C6EAD0BA4C193"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Close up of combination lock" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E0AB02DB9430349BDDD6419A5DB7D462" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E0AB02DB9430349BDDD6419A5DB7D462"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Not to be confused with simply releasing trapped cash, working capital optimisation is a dynamic process that can add value to the whole supply chain. With shrinking profit margins across Asia, corporates are focusing on the bottom line and looking at ways in which they can manage the cash conversion cycle to optimal effect.</em></p>
<p>Working capital (short-term current assets minus short-term current liabilities) is essential for a company to meet its obligations. Should the calculation result in a negative number, this could mean the company is illiquid – in other words, it has insufficient short-term assets to meet its obligations. Some organisations do operate with negative working capital where the business model means cash can be generated quickly because customers pay upfront, for instance. This enables these companies to collect cash normally but delay payment to suppliers. Dell Computers and Walmart are well-known examples of this model.</p>
<p>Generally speaking though, corporates want to optimise their working capital. This means that an excess of working capital could represent a wasted investment opportunity and the cost of carry may even be detrimental. Whilst holding onto cash certainly may increase a company’s flexibility in dealing with ‘stress’ events, it is a short-term strategy.</p>
<p>However, treasurers can extend their sights further by bolstering their supply chains with prudent investment in supply chain finance (SCF) programmes. By doing so, both short-term and long-term benefits can be felt, for example by unlocking trapped cash in emerging markets and securing the financial supply chain.</p>
<p>In order to enable the optimisation of working capital in this way, it is necessary for a business to measure the efficiency of its processes across the supply chain. This performance is typically measured by the number of days its cash is tied up in the different elements of the cash conversion cycle (CCC). There are three main metrics for treasurers to manage:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Days sales outstanding (DSO).</h5>
<p>The average number of days taken by a company to collect payment from a sale.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Days payables outstanding (DPO).</h5>
<p>The number of days a company takes to pay its creditors.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Days inventory outstanding (DIO).</h5>
<p>The number of days a company takes to convert inventory into sales.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With a solid understanding of these metrics, treasurers can hope to measure their working capital processes. As Percy Batliwalla, Global Head of Trade and Supply Chain Finance, Bank of America Merrill Lynch (BofAML) says: “Although we hear a lot in the market around shrinking trade volumes and how we are moving out of a benign credit environment, there are significant opportunities for working capital optimisation ahead.”</p>
<p>Technology, for instance, brings numerous efficiencies to working capital management, says BofAML’s Rakshith Kundha, Managing Director, Trade and Supply Chain Finance, South East Asia. “If you look at the impact of technology on the working capital cycle in a holistic manner, the benefits include efficiencies across processing, management and balance sheet.”</p>
<p>Indeed, in recent years specialist financial technology (fintech) companies have been increasing their presence in the traditional bank-dominated SCF space, offering platforms and software-based services. For treasurers, success in working capital optimisation will partly depend on their ability to determine which solutions are fit for their individual companies’ purpose.</p>
<h3 id="first-and-foremost-the-key-stages">First and foremost: the key stages</h3>
<p>As part of any review of working capital management, business consultancy The Hackett Group identified five areas on which to focus. Firstly, key stakeholders must be identified. These include local and corporate stakeholders including finance, procurement, accounts payable, supply chain, customer credit, order placement and billing, cash collection and dispute management.</p>
<p>Appointing working capital strategy leaders can help the organisation address the impacts of shared working capital issues. “Getting in front of all the stakeholders, explaining the value proposition to them – along with their suppliers – is critical because everybody needs to know what the end objective is,” Batliwalla says. “They need to know that any implementation is not something that is going to disrupt their business but increase the efficiency for them as well.”</p>
<p>Having this collaborative dialogue, more often than not, is the key to implementation of a successful working capital programme. Consideration should also be given to suppliers: every action is met with an opposite reaction thus it is not advisable to artificially adjust working capital levels by simply delaying payments to suppliers, for example, because whilst it may drive improvements over the short term, this practice is likely to damage price and relationships over the long term. Dynamic discounting, explored later, is one solution to this.</p>
<p>Next up in any review, treasurers should benchmark their current performance. The Hackett Group advises going back five years to benchmark working capital performance against a shortlist of appropriate industry peer organisations. Meanwhile, understanding which best practices and capabilities are making the difference in performance, in both your company and peers, is critical.</p>
<p>Aptly, the third of The Hackett Group’s key priorities is to understand your company’s environment – the processes, management framework and board objectives, for instance. “At the end of the day, different corporates are driven by different objectives,” says Batliwalla. There is “no one-size-fits-all solution” to optimising working capital and a lot will depend on the nature of the business model and the profile of the company’s cash flows.</p>
<p>This exploration should lead treasurers to determine the potential for improvement – The Hackett Group’s fourth stage. At this point, accurate and real-time information is essential to ensure that treasury is focused on the right actions.</p>
<p>The fifth process to focus on is for key outputs and the next steps to be identified using all of the knowledge that has been assembled. Again, it is important that the desired outcomes are articulated to all stakeholders. This allows the company to begin making informed – and tailored – choices about what strategies to implement next, which providers to contact and how much effort will be required to embed the changes throughout the supply chain.</p>
<h3 id="the-banks-role">The banks’ role</h3>
<p>Banks, of course, can provide some support here. BofAML’s Batliwalla emphasises the importance of “ensuring solutions are not concepts thrown at corporates but clearly something that meets their value expectations”. This means the bank elicits feedback from clients in terms of product development and how they would like to see the product evolve. “It always helps to understand, one, where the industry is going and, two, where the clients would like you to go,” he adds.</p>
<p>Currently, the client-centric approach is leading integrated developments in working capital products. Kundha says: “Corporates are realising that there is a lot of value in terms of looking at it in an end-to-end manner, not only in terms of cost savings and efficiency but also in terms of liquidity management, as well as from the perspective of risk management.”</p>
<p>Indeed, the current liquidity environment is emphasising not only the importance of optimising working capital, but the additional benefits, including strengthening of supply chains, which can be achieved. Value chains are becoming more integrated from a financing perspective, says Vivek Ramachandran, Global Head of Product and Proposition for HSBC. “Large companies are looking at working capital optimisation as a means to secure their supply chains and to mitigate risk so it is not just releasing capital, or the financing of the cash flow, it is more to mitigate risk on the balance sheet or to inject capital into the supply chain”.</p>
<h3 id="a-liquidity-failure">A liquidity failure?</h3>
<p>For Andrew Burns, Director of C2FO, an online working capital marketplace, it is important to understand why the current economic situation has led to an increased interest in large buyers looking to support suppliers through supply chain finance. “It’s a bit of a paradoxical situation because on the one hand there is too much liquidity and on the other hand, too little,” he notes. Central bank initiatives are, he says, putting more liquidity into the system but this is going towards the bigger buyers because the banks are doing their jobs through Basel III and pushing cash towards the less risky companies. “Which are, of course, the larger ones.” This he believes is failing the SMEs and the longer tail of the supply chain.</p>
<p>Whilst smaller suppliers wait for receivables, they might go to the banks to get a bridge loan. “They are finding it very difficult because there is a smaller pool of loans – and that pool of loans is at a higher cost for them.” The situation is particularly problematic in Asia with average payment terms of 120 days. “In the shadow banking market, it costs suppliers 30% to bridge those loans. In Europe, it’s around 60 days and can cost between 5-15% for those loans,” says Burns.</p>
<p>Ramachandran has seen a rising number of local corporates in India, China and Indonesia looking at supply chain programmes. His colleague, Stuart Tait, Head of Global Trade and Receivables Finance, HSBC adds: “In Asia, as the number of large conglomerate rises, there is more opportunity for them to arbitrage price.”</p>
<p>It is perhaps unsurprising that C2FO’s recent Supplier Finance Survey found that 96% of treasurers believe the role of supplier finance is growing. “Everybody recognises that there is a systemic failure of liquidity in the marketplace,” states Burns.</p>
<h3 id="how-treasurers-can-help-suppliers-and-themselves">How treasurers can help suppliers (and themselves)</h3>
<p>Of course, banks have offered SCF in the form of reverse factoring for a long time. They allow suppliers to be paid early by “essentially taking ownership of accounts payables and paying it earlier, taking the credit risk of the buyer to reduce the risk”, explains Burns. But this doesn’t reach into the longer tail because of the time and cost involved in on-boarding suppliers, not least due to KYC and anti-money laundering checks required by banks.</p>
<p>Ninety percent of SCF programme activity typically comes from about 20% of a corporate’s suppliers, says Tait. “If a corporate has this 20% on-boarded, the reasons for going through the bottom end of suppliers – such as your paper supplier – are limited.” Therefore, the bank has positioned itself to view the supply chain slightly differently and “supports all the segments, from some of the world’s largest companies right down to sole proprietorships in China or Japan”. This includes supplier pre-shipment financing, for example, and benefits larger buyers who want a stable and financially sound supply chain.</p>
<p>An alternative for treasurers may be found in the rising number of fintechs entering the SCF landscape. A McKinsey report, titled ‘Supply-chain finance: The emergence of a new competitive landscape’, noted that some have been offering innovative business models (C2FO; Taulia), others have improved the digital interfaces and tools on offer (PrimeSCI) and some have simplified implementation and on-boarding (Orbian).</p>
<p>Considering 67% of treasurers in C2FO’s survey believe their supply chain is currently suffering cash and liquidity challenges, solutions such as C2FO’s own marketplace, for example, offers voluntary models with potentially higher returns, Burns says, than the “narrowing options corporates have to invest”.</p>
<h3 id="finding-the-right-fit">Finding the right fit</h3>
<p>One problem, however, is the tendency to rely on legacy working capital metrics. If you relied on these in isolation, Burns says, you’d actually avoid dynamic discounting – despite the advantages discussed. “Metrics in working capital need to catch up with modern day,” he adds. “Because what early payment would do is slightly decrease your DPO and increase your CCC in terms of extending it – which doesn’t look good.” But quite clearly there is profitability in accelerating payments. Burns’ advice: “You can generate discounts, strengthen the supply chain and increase profitability but must make sure that it is offset as a separate metric.”</p>
<p>He believes there is an opportunity to be had that treasurers are waking up to. “But working capital optimisation needs to be done in a way that’s collaborative with the rest of the organisation, understanding how they can work together in order to modify the metrics and open up the opportunity to generate income and turn treasury into more of a profit centre.”</p>
<p>For BofAML’s Batliwalla, the potential is obvious. “Most corporates don’t treat metrics as the sole source of truth and look at the impacts of any SCF programme on working capital metrics, as per their individual situations.” This affords corporates with different priorities to select solutions, from fintechs or banks, which optimise working capital in a way that suits. There are exciting times ahead in terms of collaborative product development, he argues. But it remains vital for treasurers to make a consistent effort in working capital management – even in times when it feels there is less immediate need to do so.</p>



<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Case study</h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">Astro Malaysia Holdings Berhad</h3>

<img alt="Astro Malaysia Holdings logo" class="logo" height="26" src="/i/logo/astro-logo-2015-60x26.png" width="60"/>
<p class="management-summary"><em>Since 1996, Measat Broadcast Network Systems Sdn Bhd (MBNS), a wholly-owned subsidiary of AMH, has been providing satellite solutions to customers across Asia Pacific. It now has a reach that covers over 150 countries across Asia, Africa, Europe, the Middle East and Australia.</em></p>
<h3 id="the-challenge">The challenge</h3>
<p>MBNS offers satellite pay television services to consumers in Malaysia and the revenue is realised over the life of the equipment. Consumers will typically be bound by a contract for pay television with monthly fees via a commercial package lasting two or more years.</p>
<p>MBNS signed major contracts with its vendors to procure a full range of the latest set-top box technology and content licenses. These contracts were relatively significant amounting to around $100m payable over short tenors. Charles Chen, Vice President, Treasury &amp; Strategic Contracts explains: “This effectively created a fundamental mismatch between the purchases from these major vendors and the repayment source from our consumers.”</p>
<p>The key objectives for treasury included matching the financing with the life of the equipment, improving liquidity and avoiding the need to use its own funding to make the procurement payments, and meeting their KPI objectives to extend payment terms to its vendors and achieve the treatment as desired. This would result in the company’s payables aligning with its subscriber/consumer agreement packages.</p>
<h3 id="the-solution">The solution</h3>
<p>Deutsche Bank provided a first-of-its-kind solution to MBNS. It effectively allows the company to expand its payment terms on significant procurement contracts to compliment the revenue stream from subscribers and receivables, usually under commercial packages lasting two or more years.</p>
<p>Deutsche Bank provided a three-year account receivable purchase (ARP) solution, backed by promissory notes with recourse to MBNS, for the procurement of set-top boxes and satellite dishes for the reception of cable pay television (ASTRO) services in Malaysia.</p>
<p>The sales and purchase agreement between MBNS and its vendors clearly outlines the option of the promissory note as one of the instruments of payment between buyer and seller with a maturity date of up to three years from the purchase date.</p>
<p>Deutsche Bank’s implementation of this structure is an ‘off balance sheet’ solution, with recourse on the client, backed by a legally binding promissory note and factoring agreement. The solution created liquidity for MBNS while avoiding leverage. This improved the firm’s overall financial picture and indirectly helped MBNS to keep its financial ratios in-line with expectations while providing extended payable tenor of up to 36 months.</p>
<p>Key benefits included:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Risk mitigated.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Revenue enhancement.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cost savings.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Interest cost efficiencies.</p>
</li>
</ul>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Not to be confused with simply releasing trapped cash, working capital optimisation is a dynamic process that can add value to the whole supply chain. With shrinking profit margins across Asia, corporates are focusing on the bottom line and looking at ways in which they can manage the cash conversion cycle to optimal effect.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2016-05-06-tta-10-cm-combination-lock-ss234800383__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-04-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Cycle repairs]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E6D86B6E8DB2701C4DDC0099DE98B40B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E2BBB2DA5FE09D8F3C91C371E32BC024"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B0451E9F359D703BC8C5AC71AD4813A3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8498ABDB1572DB373AF3EFB0EC39F5A5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0E38573FB7FD9458CACE361ACF319D07"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Close up of classic guitar tuning mechanism " class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EDABD822775F4EBE0E4A9DC1AB8E0851" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EDABD822775F4EBE0E4A9DC1AB8E0851"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>The cash conversion cycle measures the speed that cash tied up in the buying, production and sales process can be converted back into cash again. This is perhaps one of the most important business metrics and its optimisation makes sound business sense. Treasury Today considers methods of improvement.</em></p>
<p>As working capital metrics go, the cash conversion cycle (CCC) must surely rate as one of the fundamentals. Most businesses preside over a complex web of suppliers and customers, and cash permeates that entire structure. The purpose of CCC is to measure the amount of time, in days, a company’s cash is tied up in the purchasing, production and sales processes before it is converted back into bookable cash through the collection of receivables. It can be expressed as equalling DIO + DSO – DPO (where DIO is Days Inventory Outstanding, DSO is Days Sales Outstanding, and DPO is Days Payable Outstanding).</p>
<p>Ultimately, the longer the CCC, the longer it takes to generate cash so even with a full order book, if this figure extends too far, it can mean insolvency. Conversely, when a company collects outstanding payments quickly, correctly forecasts inventory needs and pays its bills slowly, it shortens the CCC. Most companies understand the importance of cash and more are engaging with the issue. In the REL Europe Working Capital Survey 2015, analysis of the accounts of almost 1,000 of the largest companies in Europe found that the CCC had improved in 2014 by 5.5% (the equivalent of 2.1 days).</p>
<h3 id="fixing-the-cycle">Fixing the cycle</h3>
<p>A good starting point for companies wishing to optimise their CCC is to understand the gaps in each of the working capital components in the equation referred to above. By benchmarking these components it will be possible for a business to see where it stands in relation to its direct competitors. Of course, benchmarking should only ever be seen as an input to a broader discussion on cash, not an end in itself. For Greg Person, Global Vice President of Presales, Kyriba, optimisation requires a “holistic” view of processes and systems. Functions such as treasury, the controller’s office, accounts receivable, accounts payable, those on the operations side (such as manufacturing) and even banking partners, all have a role to play when discussing working capital management and free cash performance.</p>
<p>However, it is a big ask to rally the many and varied functions for such an initiative, so is it worth it? Increasingly, the cash conversion cycle is a metric that the CEO and Board will be interested in. The ability to maintain a liquid business plays a major role in the capacity to fund capital expenditure projects, M&amp;A activity, share repurchase programmes, dividend payments and a host of other significant capital allocation decisions that senior executives are tasked with, says Person. “Improving free cash flow and delivering an enhanced liquidity position is certainly going to help support those objectives.”</p>
<p>But company cash is increasingly of interest to external stakeholders too, he notes. The significance of a metric such as CCC is not lost on the markets, for example. Corporates, particularly those that are sensitive to cash flow (such as retailers), are often to be found giving guidance around their operating cash flow performance in earnings calls with analysts and the investor community. And well they might: if the capacity of the company to fulfil its capital allocation decisions is predicated on having the free cash flow and operating cash flow, then the ability to reduce its CCC is vital.</p>
<h3 id="cooperation-required">Cooperation required</h3>
<p>With multiple internal stakeholders involved, shortening the time that cash is tied up in operations is a major initiative. For Person, the first point to acknowledge is that the focus should fall on cash when business is good. Wait for a downturn and it may be too late.</p>
<p>To help embed the idea that ‘Cash is King’ into company culture – and to steer an initiative in the right direction and encourage support and cooperation between functions – there needs to be buy-in and sponsorship from the top. It is a ‘C-suite’ role (possibly that of the CFO) to make sure there is clear ownership of duties and that all actions are aligned with the overall objectives of the business.</p>
<p>From a finance perspective, the areas of focus will most likely be DPO and DSO, simply because there will be less immediate influence over DIO (although the project sponsor should tackle any resistance). In terms of DSO, aside from simply renegotiating payment terms (which can be fraught with problems, as we shall see), effective means of shortening CCC include schemes such as factoring and trade receivables securitisation programmes. These schemes typically involve close partnership with a bank or other FI to make the receivables available for early payment. “It’s not free but it is a way of accelerating cash collection and ultimately reducing the cash conversion cycle,” notes Person. Complementing these relatively common schemes (at least in the SME sector) are a range of best practice AR workflow tools (from the likes of Gresham Computing, Fundtech and Bottomline), that facilitate the streamlining of cash allocation.</p>
<p>As the REL survey, referred to previously, suggests, many big organisations do not seem to focus on getting the cash in quite as efficiently as they could or should. For these firms, it may be possible to drive the strategic value of their shared services operation on the AR side. But benefits can easily be wiped out by poor results. Some 44% of respondents to SunGard’s ‘Credit and Collections Global Benchmarking Study 2015’ stated just how complex dispute approval processes can be, particularly where multiple departments are involved. This, said the report, makes it very difficult to set up different resolution workflows for every type of dispute, so they are often handled manually as a result.</p>
<p>C.J. Wimley, COO for Receivables in SunGard’s Corporate Liquidity Business, wrote that “while disputes inevitably require human intervention and therefore need to be managed in a different way to routine collections, it is very easy to lose visibility, control and monitoring of these invoices if they are managed outside of the normal systems environment”. Instead, he believes that it is typically better to accept that disputes need to be handled “in a collaborative way”, adding that technology may be used to support this aim. If successful, stakeholders will have visibility over the status, responsibility for follow-up steps will be clear, and any insensitive or inappropriate intervention is avoided. “This ensures that disputes are handled quickly, improving customer relationships but also minimising the impact on DSO.”</p>
<p>Wimley also suggested that it may also be possible to carve out disputed parts of an invoice and pursue payment for the rest in the usual way, rather than holding up the entire invoice. However, the SunGard study demonstrated that 43% of companies choose to hold up the entire invoice. “This can have a material impact not only on DSO but also on the predictability of cash flow for working capital and cash flow forecasting purposes,” he noted.</p>
<h3 id="a-cycle-made-for-two">A cycle made for two?</h3>
<p>On the DPO side, one of the most common options is that of supply chain finance (SCF) where the buyer, often working in partnership with its bank, pays its supplier on shorter terms in exchange for a discount on those invoices. SCF is something of a catch-all phrase that includes schemes such as dynamic discounting and supplier finance. For the buyer, this extends DPO, shortening the CCC and, by providing the supplier with funding, lends a degree of continuity to its supply chain. SCF can come across as nothing more than a pretext used by large corporate buyers to coerce SMEs into accepting longer and longer payment terms and charging them a fee for the privilege. In fact, because the bank settling the invoice uses the buyer’s credit rating to determine the cost, it can be a ‘win-win’ offering as long as the supplier needs early settlement: it effectively provides them with finance at rates they could never achieve on their own. Convincing them that this really is the case is often the first hurdle in the on-boarding process.</p>
<p>SCF has been around in one form or another for a very long time but speaking at a session during the 2015 Annual ACT Conference, the issue of its sustainability was broached by James Kelly, Head of Treasury at Rentokil Initial. He asked, somewhat provocatively: “If we all just paid on 30-days wouldn’t the world be a lot simpler?” Although this elicited many nods of agreement, he admitted that whilst this would indeed be beneficial, the constant working capital tension between buyers and suppliers is unlikely ever to ease as no one was likely to break ranks first.</p>
<p>Of course, this tension is precisely why SCF exists. The ACT’s Peter Matza, playing Devil’s Advocate, asked why, if it is so good, so few are using it (a straw poll of the session revealed only around 2% had adopted it so far). Cranfield School of Management lecturer, Simon Templar was on hand to argue that although SCF has emerged as a practical solution, “it has not yet crystallised”. To be truly sustainable, Templar believes it must see large corporate buyers assuming the role of “stewardship” in the whole supply chain. He argued that few would tie suppliers into punitive and ultimately unsustainable contracts not least because sourcing and on-boarding good new suppliers costs time and money. In fact, Templar sees sustainable SCF as a truly collaborative effort. He applies the term ‘horizon scanning’ to the view a buyer should be taking right across its supply chain, from tier one down, seeking to understand the cash-cycle times of all suppliers in a more steward-like way.</p>
<h3 id="responsibility-and-reputation">Responsibility and reputation</h3>
<p>Indeed, as an alternative means of extending DPO (and as part of an effort to optimise CCC), SCF seems like a more responsible corporate approach than the easier alternative of simply paying late. The latter is a common practice which has earned much damning coverage in mainstream media in recent years. “Late payment is not sustainable and certainly puts a strain on business relationships,” comments Person. He adds, that it can also have an internal impact, especially where the AP department is forced to handle the backlash from suppliers and constantly fight fires. The negativity does not end here.</p>
<p>The promotion of voluntary industry initiatives such as the UK’s Prompt Payment Code, whilst offering a solution of sorts, serve to highlight the prevalence of late payment. As does more forceful legislation such as the EU’s Late Payments Directive which intends to put a stop to protracted payment times, limiting terms to 60 days (or 30 days for public sector firms). These initiatives are well-intentioned but could be better: a voluntary code is just that, and the EU Directive does not prevent large corporate buyers from strong-arming small suppliers into accepting new unfavourable terms. The call in the UK for a mandate to publish the late payment practices of public companies tackles the subject from a different angle. Should it happen, it will seek to impact corporate reputation by naming and shaming the worst offenders. A growing reputation for late payment could negatively affect investor behaviour and may even see more muscular suppliers enforcing certain types of guarantees to protect themselves, suggests Person. However, he continues, it need not be like this at all when seeking to optimise DPO and CCC “because there are more prudent and responsible ways of achieving this objective”.</p>
<h3 id="pay-by-the-book">Pay by the book</h3>
<p>One company that “lives within” the EU Payments Directive is global pharmaceutical player, AstraZeneca. “Quality and surety of the supply chain is absolutely paramount,” stated the firm’s VP Finance – Cash Generation, Steve Williamson at the ACT event. One of AstraZeneca’s key focuses is its strictly adhered-to ‘pay-to-terms’ metric. It always pays its suppliers on time, never late nor early. There is an exception process for immediate payments, but these must be approved either by the CFO or CEO. Generally the reason for such urgency is to rectify an error, explains Williamson. But rather than sanction such a need, he believes the best way is to correct the underlying issue that led to it so that it does not happen again. Effectively, this means there are very few exceptions: “The moment you have an exception you are sub-optimal”.</p>
<p>As part of his ‘cash philosophy’, Williamson understands the importance of it being seen as a matter for the whole business, not just finance. To this end he firmly believes in “communicating, educating and repeating” the message until it permeates the culture of the company. However, he adds, AstraZeneca is “not solely about the cash”, basing all of its plans and decisions “around meeting the needs of customers and suppliers”, the goal being to build long-term relationships. “We can generate as much cash as we like, but in a year’s time we might not have a business. We try to reflect what the commercial reality is,” he states. Cash optimisation for Williamson is thus all about “good internal housekeeping” and developing an understanding of how cash is seen and handled by other companies and industries.</p>
<h3 id="nothing-for-free">Nothing for free</h3>
<p>The intelligent deployment of technology is fundamental to the effectiveness of CCC improvement programmes. On the DSO side, for example, being able to electronically post and exchange receivables is a necessary component of reaching the market. And from an ERP/TMS perspective, the ability to automatically reconcile, apply cash and manage disputes more effectively will facilitate a shorter cycle. But regardless of how good a vendor or bank’s cash solution may seem, Person warns of the need for cost/benefit analysis.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The intelligent deployment of technology is fundamental to the effectiveness of CCC improvement programmes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Even low or non-tech solutions can have a cost. For the company, both factoring and securitisation have a P&amp;L impact because the full amount of the invoice is not collected. Although payment arrives quicker, which can support the company’s liquidity position, if the time-value of that cash does not meet or exceed the objectives of the business then there needs to be a rethink, warns Person.</p>
<p>Historically, only the larger companies have been able to exploit working capital initiatives such as SCF. But new technologies such as those facilitating the exchange of receivables in the public domain where the banks are not involved (such as C2FO and Taulia) enable even smaller firms to make incremental improvements to their overall cash flow and operational cash position. There is great potential for all businesses in gaining a consolidated view across a broad spectrum of commercial functions – including AP, AR, treasury, production, purchasing, the supply chain and even their banks – and the means to do so are readily available.</p>
<p>By acting on information drawn from this viewpoint to shorten the cash conversion cycle it could, for example, facilitate more aggressive paying down of debt or perhaps improve the company’s investment position. If sufficient gains are made – and the REL 2015 survey suggests that working capital realisations are there for the taking – then these could also allow the funding of important capital allocations, such as stock buyback or M&amp;A activity, without taking on additional debt. Whilst there is likely to be a cost attached to effective CCC optimisation, cash will always be an enabler so the arguments for getting the cash cycle to work more effectively remain compelling.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[The cash conversion cycle measures the speed that cash tied up in the buying, production and sales process can be converted back into cash again. This is perhaps one of the most important business metrics and its optimisation makes sound business sense. Treasury Today considers methods of improvement.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-11and12-tt-11-cm-a-close-up-of-classic-guitar-tuning-mechanism-ss153317051__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Working capital connections]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><img alt="HSBC" height="16" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/hsbc-logo-2013-90x16.png?la=en&amp;hash=E1C9F8245A5A409B80C70844FA194BDA" width="90"/></p>
<p><em>“As the newly appointed Head of the HSBC Payments and Cash Management business in Europe, I’m excited about the opportunities we have to help our clients to grow their business. With a presence in 33 European markets we are ideally placed to help clients across the globe expand into Europe and to help our European clients expand into fast growing markets in other regions.</em></p>
<p><em>We are seeing continued growth in multiple countries with increased investment in Spain, Poland, the Netherlands, Germany, Italy and Switzerland to name a few. Recently, we also became the first bank to implement a two-way RMB sweep between Europe (UK/Germany) and China. As the following article demonstrates, we have the international connectivity, presence and ability to facilitate working capital, supply chain, corporate card and liquidity management solutions flexibly, as part of our overall relationship with our clients.”</em></p>
<p><strong>Eddie Norton, Head of Payments and Cash Management, Europe, HSBC</strong></p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Eddie Norton, Head of Payments and Cash Management, Europe, HSBC" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-09-tt-12-st-eddie-norton-100x150.jpg?w=100&amp;la=en&amp;hash=8B51D31F56CED31426A0B7C0DB00A8EB" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 2em 0px; width: 100px;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Eddie Norton</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Payments and Cash Management, Europe</h5>
<h5 class="org">HSBC</h5>

<img alt="Brian Tomkins, European Head of Corporate Cards, HSBC" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-09-tt-12-st-brian-tomkins-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=53FC0701169739DD4F86B770D9D260F0" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Brian Tomkins</h3>
<h5 class="title">European Head of Corporate Cards</h5>
<h5 class="org">HSBC</h5>

<img alt="Stuart Rousell, Global Head of Working Capital Advisory, HSBC" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-09-tt-12-st-stuart-rousell-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=0EEE661836C43EC08FF7FB1759ED82C8" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Stuart Rousell</h3>
<h5 class="title">Global Head of Working Capital Advisory</h5>
<h5 class="org">HSBC</h5>


<img alt="Jennifer Doherty, Global Head of Commercialisation, Liquidity &amp; Investment Products, HSBC" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-09-tt-12-st-jennifer-doherty-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=EF2BD9FDE0249FE8255BBC23ED8DE82C" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Jennifer Doherty</h3>
<h5 class="title">Global Head of Commercialisation, Liquidity &amp; Investment Products</h5>
<h5 class="org">HSBC</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>In the working capital space, one of the current pressing themes is the state of connection between the physical and the financial supply chain. They have been interlinked in the past, particularly for international trade, through documentary trade solutions such as Letters of Credit (LCs). However, as trade has shifted ever more towards open account practices, a divide has appeared and can be problematic for a number of reasons.</p>
<p>To facilitate the finance element on open account trade, the market has seen increased take-up of solutions such as Supply Chain Finance (SCF). Particularly prevalent post global financial crisis, this proposition remains largely independent of the physical supply chain, notes Stuart Rousell, Global Head of Working Capital Advisory, HSBC. With the implementation of Basel III, the trend of widening pricing gap between highly rated and less well rated is set to continue. This is such that the great task today is to re-integrate the connectors between both sides whilst retaining their functional independence. Whilst the pressure point for that integration is the availability, or otherwise, of sufficient and sensibly-priced finance, the real stimulus for bringing both back together is buyer concern around the financial resilience of suppliers along their supply chain. “Solutions that enable the co-existence of both physical and financial supply chains provide robustness and better future-proofing,” argues Rousell. “Where we bring both together, solutions provide logistical reliance on the need for finance, but the visibility is available to financing banks and is equally available to benefit suppliers to help take out the real cost of the supply chain.”</p>
<h3 id="exclusive-systems">Exclusive systems</h3>
<p>The data flows that exist in the procurement process often exist independently of finance solutions, often via third-party web portals or directly through Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) systems. Indeed, says Rousell, “a number of e-Procurement platforms exist with payment, billing and even dispute management functionality. But these tend to be over-engineered for roll-out into smaller client sites, as are the majority of ERP systems; although tier one suppliers might have the resources to connect directly, the smaller tier 2 and tier 3 suppliers can often be left high and dry.” This, he notes, “usually creates a default to paper, adding unwanted costs.”</p>
<p>The real opportunity then lies in understanding the flow of procurement data and sharing it with banks more effectively at a transactional level, says Rousell. “There is no desire by banks to get in the way of a process that works between buyers and suppliers. What we want to do is supplement that process with perhaps a financing element; we can do that by capturing data from buyers and using that to identify suppliers,” he explains.</p>
<p>If the use of proprietary software means that at both ends of the chain there will be re-keying of data into different platforms, then the clarion call is for standardisation. This does not require a wholesale replacement of systems: many of the solutions that could be used already exist. These may be EDI (electronic data interchange) standards-based offerings capable of fulfilling an order straight through from purchase order to fulfilment.</p>
<p>EDI standards (such as EDIFACT and the US-centred ANSI) have been available for more than 30 years. However, one of the key issues for products using EDI-based software is still supplier on-boarding. “Many of the solutions in this space have been designed for the buyer not supplier,” notes Rousell. He feels there is also a lack of understanding amongst smaller businesses around what can be achieved with the existing toolkit. However, he does feel that there is at last “greater collaboration coming down the supply chain,” this being driven by an across-the-board need for efficient working capital management and a better view on where costs can be taken out. His ideal is clear: “We need to be heading towards common data being shared as an in-built process where, as soon as there is invoice acceptance, the next stage is automatic presentment of that invoice to the bank for financing; that is not an automated process today.” The most active users of EDI standards are the “logistically challenged” automotive and retail sectors. Even so, elements of the physical supply chain often act independently, with electronic delivery notes being followed by manual acceptance of delivery, frequently creating reconciliation issues for stock and payments. “But within the EDI environment, there is an opportunity to electronically pass that acceptance notice to a bank for financing.” Additionally, in the stock-control environment, across multiple sectors, universal GS1 Bar Code standards are being used to identity individual goods or parts so data can be captured at various points of the physical supply chain lifecycle. This can be shared between different stakeholders within that chain, including those in the financial supply chain.</p>
<h3 id="co-operation-with-leadership">Co-operation with leadership</h3>
<p>“If the parts of the solution already exist, then what is required to make it work is increased co-operation around working capital between business functions,” explains Rousell. Driving change internally thus rests with the fundamental question of working capital ownership. It could equally be claimed by operations, procurement, financial control or treasury, but each has a different agenda. This, he observes, means “too many silos leading to too many conflicting processes.” One way to break down these silos is to establish a head of working capital. Reporting to the CFO, the role should focus on driving efficiencies and costs through analysis of key elements such as Days Sales Outstanding (DSO), Days Payable Outstanding (DPO) and Days Inventory Outstanding (DIO) and aligning objectives.</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Payment risk ladder</h4>
<p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-09-tt-12-st-chart-01-payment-risk-ladder__967x353.png?la=en&amp;hash=3DACAACBE3656AD33FDB16E5D7D5CE19" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: Payment risk ladder" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2015-09-tt-12-st-chart-01-payment-risk-ladder__967x353.png?la=en&amp;hash=3DACAACBE3656AD33FDB16E5D7D5CE19" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: HSBC</em></p>
<p>In a wider context, (using the automotive sector as an example), the collaborative model will require a change of practice by some suppliers to enable acceptance of electronic delivery notes. “If we can get to a stage where there is further integration of banking into that process, we can get to a point of providing finance,” explains Rousell. “This would be self-liquidating at an individual transactional level, not merely on aggregated values.”</p>
<h3 id="the-value-of-virtual">The value of virtual</h3>
<p>Further to the above, a simple form of financed payment is a corporate card. When it comes to purchasing solutions a number of opportunities have opened up in recent years. Perhaps one of the most surprising developments in the business to business (B2B) space, and one not necessarily associated with the supply chain, is the rise of the humble card to a position of significant status within a treasurer’s tool box. Traditional Travel and Expense cards have evolved into broader B2B card programmes, for supplier payments. The ever-improving security and more sophisticated usage controls has seen payments values rise accordingly and can provide treasurers with the confidence to make card payments upwards of £1m. And perhaps the most significant development to arrive in the card arena – and facilitate the security of these larger payments – is the creation of virtual cards.</p>
<p>The ‘one-time use’ virtual card leverages the existing card network for acceptance and settlement in the B2B space, whilst effectively locking down the card number to a specific purpose or set of purposes, controlling factors such as purchase type, value, date and supplier. The inherent flexibility of virtual card numbers is complemented by an array of interfaces which can be used to generate them, for example, a traditional payment file can be used to create a batch of virtual card payments. The most recent evolution of the virtual card has even seen the cards being processed directly into the acquiring network so that the beneficiary need never touch the card data; the details are sent directly to its own bank where it will be processed and paid directly into the relevant account (usually within a day or two).</p>
<p>There are a number of reasons why the virtual card concept might appeal to a business. “Firstly, it is a very data-rich product,” explains Brian Tomkins, European Head of Corporate Cards, HSBC. “Once a payment has been settled with the supplier, having been processed through the card network as usual, the client can access real-time transaction information, making use of multiple client-selected data fields. This ensures clients can track and reconcile each payment made and offers stronger client oversight and control over spend patterns. In addition to this, as these are commercial credit cards, it also gives up to 56 days of interest free credit from the issuing bank. This heralds a distinct cash flow benefit: the supplier receives earlier payment and the buyer receives interest-free cash flow.”</p>
<h3 id="in-practice">In practice</h3>
<p>“There are a number of B2B payment scenarios where virtual cards add value,” observes Tomkins. One-off payments for new suppliers that have not yet been brought into a purchasing programme would suit this format, with rich payment and invoicing data still being provided by the bank. Even more traditional high volume, low value payments can be optimised using the virtual card concept. If paying a courier or a travel management firm for example, where there are many transactions per month, it may be beneficial to lodge a virtual card with that supplier so all transactions can be billed to just one account. Rather than processing multiple invoices, the dedicated virtual card account means just one payment per month, for many transactions, with the benefit of enhanced data available for reconciliation of each transaction. Tomkins also notes that “increasingly, cards are being used as a simple means to enhance cash flow. In any sector where a business is typically expected to pay its bills before it is paid (such as the construction industry) the effect on cash flow can be challenging. A card programme alleviates the pressure, allowing the business to effectively create a free ‘extended float period’ enabling up to an extra 56 days to collect on its receivables.”</p>
<p>Of course, the supplier has to agree to be paid in this way and will be charged a fee to accept a virtual card payment, similar to any other commercial credit card. The challenge lies in ensuring the fee does not outweigh the advantage of enjoying earlier settlement of receivables. For long-term core suppliers and for those where the payment value is substantial, the traditional supply chain finance programme might still be deemed preferable. However, a major benefit of using cards over the traditional model is that it removes the often complex three-way legal contract between buyer, bank and supplier, making the on-boarding process quicker and simpler as well as opening doors to the circa 38 million suppliers that accept cards today.</p>
<h3 id="the-perfect-mix">The perfect mix</h3>
<p>The simplicity of virtual cards, combined with commercial benefits, means that this is a focus area for card issuers. “There is big focus from HSBC on the B2B space because it is still a largely untapped area compared to the more heavily penetrated T&amp;E sector,” notes Tomkins. “This is really being driven by our clients and their level of interest on optimising payments within their supply chain” he adds. Rather than cards competing with our financed payment products, such as supplier finance programmes, virtual card programmes have complementary effect. “One of the biggest challenges in financed supplier payment products is that there is no ‘one-size-fits-all’; when we look at a client’s accounts payable file there are clearly different financing payment products that work better for some suppliers and their payment profile than others.” From international trade finance to local invoice finance solutions, the inclusion of a card programme helps to create the best possible, holistic, solution. “There is a harmonious balance to be struck between the different payment methods available. At the high end there is traditional trade finance, whilst supply chain finance is well suited to the middle ground. The fluidity of a card programme means it can effectively capture the high volume, smaller value transactions all the while providing the same benefits without some of the wider complexities,” says Tomkins. The virtual card concept will only serve to reinforce this and contribute to a wider acceptance and trust in the value and security of a card solution.</p>
<h3 id="the-impact-of-regulation">The impact of regulation</h3>
<p>The evolving regulatory landscape – particularly Basel III and its European interpretation, Capital Requirements Directive IV (CRD IV) – plays a significant part in the development of treasury solutions. Whilst Basel III may initially have been viewed by corporate treasurers as a challenge only for the banks, it is becoming increasingly apparent that what affects banks will indirectly be ultimately reflected in the corporate world. Today, whilst the concepts of account rationalisation, cash mobilisation, centralisation and yield optimisation remain core to most treasury operations, the arrival of Basel III – and the flurry of other major regulatory initiatives – has shifted their focus by a degree or two as treasurers need to consider the regulatory impact on their banking partners and on themselves.</p>
<p>Historically, banks have managed their balance sheets with a more asset centric approach impacting the scope and extent of lending decisions, says Jennifer Doherty, Global Head of Commercialisation, Liquidity &amp; Investment Products, HSBC and a speaker at Eurofinance Copenhagen 2015. However, as Basel III’s Liquidity Coverage Ratio (LCR), Leverage Ratios (LR) and Net Stable Funding Ratio (NSFR) comes into play, banks will need to look more holistically at the impact of their client relationship on both the asset and the liabilities side of their balance sheets. Compliance with the new liquidity and leverage ratios means that banks have already begun to assess the impact of nominal value of their assets as well as the deposits profile of the liabilities. For certain deposits that cannot be redeployed for lending, sufficient high quality liquid assets (HQLA) need to be held to maintain LCR. This in turn could impact the leverage ratio and capital cost.</p>
<p>One point to note is the increasing importance of the ‘Operational Deposits’. These are frictional deposits that help in facilitating clients’ payables and receivables activities. As Operational Deposits are linked to daily activities, they are deemed to be more stable from a longer-term funding perspective and they reduce the LCR requirement. As the Operational Deposit requires substantially less HQLA to be held against it, the deposit derived from operational business becomes more valuable to the banks. This will lead to a rise in the importance of the operational banking relationship. Unlike historic pricing trends based on higher interest rate and yield for larger balances, Operational Deposits must be ‘priced without giving an economic incentive’ as per the Basel III directive. From a stable funding and capital cost perspective, operational relationships are therefore growing in importance for banks. Economic value for moving cash to a non-operating bank or an over-lay structure may not be as rewarding for clients as in the previous regulatory environment.</p>
<p>“We need to work with our clients to find different ways to make it work for both them and the bank. Clients who not only understand Basel III but also engage with their banks will have the edge,” says Doherty. “It is more important than ever for clients to segment their cash and understand what will be considered as operational. Clients should work with their banks to understand the most suitable deposit and investment offerings for their segmented cash.”</p>
<h3 id="innovative-design">Innovative design</h3>
<p>The quest for a mutually beneficial position has seen the financial sector become more innovative with Basel III-compliant products such as the 30+ days Evergreen notice accounts offering. “Innovation in this space will also see current operational burdens being removed as clients can automatically and seamlessly move their cash into other suitable off balance-sheet instruments (such as money market funds or short-term cash investments) without the need for last minute placements that may not produce optimal returns,” notes Doherty. This requires an intelligent approach to liquidity investment. “Our subject matter experts are on the ground talking to clients, discussing the likely impacts of Basel III and other regulations,” says Doherty. “Although Basel III is still at a relatively early stage of its implementation (LCR will be finalised later this year and the net stable funding ratio (NSFR) follows in January 2018) HSBC is already fielding questions ranging from ‘how will the new regulations impact treasury management on a day-to-day basis?’, to specific questions such as how CRD IV will impact notional pooling.”</p>
<p>Commenting on the latter, Doherty says banks may take different views on how CRD IV will impact their pooling proposition depending on their regulatory and financial reporting (GAAP, IFRS etc) structure. Over time, she feels that there will be a shift in focus towards cash concentration solutions as banks become increasingly sophisticated with their offerings in this space. By offering the ability to calculate and post interest, for example, they enable the use of this model but without the additional administrative burden of an inter-company loan. However, Doherty does not see notional pooling disappearing altogether. She believes, “there is still an appetite for it,” but due to the leverage ratio implications, banks have already started engaging in deeper dialogue with clients for managing gross pool positions. “Clients will start closely monitoring their positions within their notional pools to ensure they are being used as intended, as a short-term working capital tool rather than as a source of long-term funding.”</p>
<h3 id="the-need-to-know">The need to know</h3>
<p>As the regulatory landscape becomes more complex, so too does the level of market concern. Corporates must keep in touch with these changes and understand how they may be impacted. They also need to understand the fundamentals of the regulation and how it impacts their operations and the relationship with their banks. “Regulation can be perceived as a challenge but with it also comes opportunities,” notes Doherty. “It ensures banks and clients re-evaluate their respective positions and ensure their solutions are fit for purpose.” She believes that treasurers are now well placed because most corporates have multiple bank relationships, they have access to a diverse range of advisory services and subject matter experts. “They should be using all that knowledge to enable them to draw their own conclusions and obtain the best outcome possible for their businesses in this new environment.”</p>
<p>In increasingly uncertain times, a strong treasury team will find new ways to make working capital work as hard as it can to contribute to cash flows whilst educating colleagues about good working capital management. But in the push for working capital optimisation, it is clear that treasurers need to work with banks who have a wide product offering with international connectivity and the ability to facilitate working capital and supply chain solutions flexibly, as part of the overall relationship.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[“As the newly appointed Head of the HSBC Payments and Cash Management business in Europe, I’m excited about the opportunities we have to help our clients to grow their business. With a presence in 33 European markets we are ideally placed to help clients across the globe expand into Europe and to help our European clients expand into fast growing markets in other regions.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Receivables: overhauling working capital management]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BF9EAB44464A416D41CE6421668656E9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=81F33AFAA5B780EA4A4A4AD4E0494002"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CD5353772AC7A470A0EAE95FEBE1591C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1D2D360E3E2A8AA130400627A61D0600"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4FE59C14384CCB02A1CDDD81D286CAC4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Sun halo in middle Thailand with ferris wheel" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4606BCCC84DE98789B59A5F08CC006C0" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4606BCCC84DE98789B59A5F08CC006C0"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>With billions estimated to be tied up in excess working capital, optimising the flow of funds through the financial supply chain will surely continue to be a top priority for European companies in the years ahead. But how are transaction banks, technology solutions and treasury itself, changing in the quest for ever greater working capital efficiency?</em></p>
<p>Since the financial crisis, corporates have been labouring to rebuild balance sheets to ensure short-term obligations can be met in future stress scenarios. It is a goal which has led, among other things, to a renewed focus on working capital management with some companies pulling down old, localised structures and starting again from scratch.</p>
<p>In a panel discussion at the 2014 Receivables Finance International conference in Warsaw in April, representatives from both the corporate and banking world debated some of the changes seen in recent years. Treasurers, the panel unanimously agreed, are now taking much greater ownership of working capital performance at group level – a trend most visible in the recent post-SEPA vogue for payments and collections factories.</p>
<p>“We are seeing more and more corporates now giving their treasuries the mandate to fully manage and optimise their working capital from end-to-end,” Eugenio Cavenaghi, Director of Trade and Working Capital at Barclays told delegates. In this new paradigm, treasury’s mandate to find efficiencies across the procure-to-pay (P2P) cycle is becoming less tacit and more formalised, he adds. “Consciously they have taken ownership of working capital and, as a bank, our challenge is to present a set of solutions that helps them as owners of working capital to meet the challenges they face.”</p>
<p>One of the ways banks are helping treasurers meet their working capital challenges is through the financing of receivables (see the fundamentals box at the end of this article for a reminder of common techniques). It is an activity which has seen spectacular growth in recent years. Since 2009, domestic invoice factoring across the globe has grown at a compound annual growth rate (CAGR) of 13.1%, while cross-border transactions have seen an even bigger upsurge, with a CAGR of 24.8%. Once considered as a last resort for companies that had become too risky for conventional loans, receivables financing is evidently much more mainstream now. Even large multinationals with investment-grade credit ratings are realising the benefits it can bring in terms of working capital optimisation (WCO).</p>
<h3 id="taking-control">Taking control</h3>
<p>One company that epitomises this fresh approach to working capital optimisation is Siemens. Friedemann Kirchhof, Head of Supply Chain Finance at Siemens began by telling delegates the journey his company has taken since beginning to explore working capital improvements over a decade ago. The company, he explained, decided a more centralised methodology was required. A split approach was taken; one unit was assigned responsibility for the physical supply chain while another brought in expertise to bolster the financial supply chain – both forwards and backwards.</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h4 id="chart-1-fundamentals-of-receivables-financing">Chart 1: Fundamentals of receivables financing</h4>
</figcaption>
<p><img alt="Chart 1: Fundamentals of receivables financing" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/2014-05-tt-05-cf-chart-01-fundamentals-of-receivables-financing__967x321.png?la=en&amp;hash=B947B48C0EBD824B0B103F5FFF5A740D"/></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: PwC 2014</em></p>
</figure>
<p>On the forward side, Kirchhof oversees the group’s efforts to improve DPO through extension of SCF facilities to strategic suppliers. But the most novel aspect of the system, perhaps, relates to the receivables side and the establishment of a ‘credit warehouse’. Siemens were dealing with large amounts of receivables data from its multiple business units and wanted to get a clearer picture of which companies posed extraordinarily high credit risk globally. The Siemens Credit Warehouse is an in-house unit that provides bank-like services to the company’s entities. Its principle function is to purchase and bundle the short-term trade receivables from subsidiaries and manages the Group’s credit risks by selling, securitising or hedging exposure to specific customers.</p>
<p>“For the moment, it is more of a risk management tool used to gain transparency on where our customers’ risks are,” said Kirchhof. “But there is the option on the receivables side, when it is needed, to turn them around very quickly into cash.”</p>
<h3 id="tools-for-the-job">Tools for the job</h3>
<p>New concepts such as Siemens’ Credit Warehouse have led banks and treasury technology specialists to develop up-to-date services and solutions to assist corporate treasurers with the evolving challenges they face. In fact, such has been the pace of technological advancement in treasury over the past few years there is an argument that solutions are now often leagues ahead of what processes can actually achieve, says Robert O’Donoghue, Managing Director and Global Head of Working Capital Management at ING.</p>
<p>O’Donoghue offers the example of a client that used SCF to extend payment terms only to see any benefits cancelled out by the time it took them to approve invoices. “Although I think it is clear that technology is an enabler,” he explained, “if you’ve got a SCF programme that extends your terms to 60 days, but it is taking you 45 days to approve an invoice, then you have a problem.”</p>
<p>Evidently, treasurers today need to focus on more than mere DPO improvements. Solutions that have the potential to speed up DSO, such as the Bank Payment Obligation (BPO), should, therefore see increasing acceptance in the coming years. That is provided bankers can overcome their initial hesitancy and begin building strong commercial propositions. Angela Koll, Product Manager International Business, Commerzbank believes that will be key to the success of the BPO, as it often is with treasury solutions. “We are trying to motivate everybody to look at this and encouraging banks to become more active in this space,” she says. “If we don’t, then there is a chance the instrument will fail to fully enter the market, and that would be a real pity.”</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Receivables financing: the fundamentals</h2>

<h4 id="factoring">Factoring</h4>
<p>In a factoring arrangement, finance is provided by a third party, the ‘factor’, who provides the supplier with a cash advance of (usually) up to 80% of the face value of the invoice. The factor then takes over the task of chasing in payment from the purchaser. Once payment has been received, the factor pays the supplier the remainder of the invoice value, minus a discount. Factoring may be done with or without recourse. Factors are frequently, but not always, bank-owned enterprises. Although traditional factoring only deals with the supplier side of financing, factors sometimes provide billing and collection services, so the buyer will be aware of the arrangements in place.</p>
<h4 id="invoice-discounting">Invoice discounting</h4>
<p>As in a factoring arrangement, payment is advanced to the supplier based on outstanding invoices. However, the invoices remain in the possession of the supplier, who is still responsible for collecting the outstanding payments. As such, the arrangement should not be visible to the buyer. Usually up to around 80-90% of the value of the invoice is advanced; however, some discounters will increase the advance against the security of assets including stock, machinery, land and buildings. Once these have been paid into a trust account, the discounter collects the payment and pays the supplier any outstanding funds minus the discounting fee. Invoice discounting can provide an effective method of improving or stabilising cash flow, though this may not be the most cost-effective financing solution for all firms.</p>
<h4 id="forfaiting">Forfaiting</h4>
<p>Developed in Switzerland in the 1950s, forfaiting is generally used to finance longer-term receivables and may be used by suppliers selling on extended credit terms of three to five years, although time horizons can vary from as little as six months to ten years. This flexible discounting technique can be particularly useful in turbulent times, as the uncertainties to contend with and consider when deciding whether or not to extend long-term credit now include heightened commercial and country risk.</p>
<p>Unlike a factoring or invoice discounting arrangement, which is based on the invoice itself, the forfaiter purchases drafts of letters of credit, accepted bills of exchange, promissory notes or other freely negotiable instruments on a non or without recourse basis, and for 100% of the value. The forfaiter then takes on the responsibility of chasing in the debt or alternatively sells the instruments to another investor. Finance can usually be arranged on either a fixed or floating rate basis. A guarantee or aval is usually required from the purchaser’s bank in support of the supplier’s obligation.</p>
<h4 id="receivables-securitisation">Receivables securitisation</h4>
<p>For larger companies, more complex financing solutions might be employed. One such technique is receivables securitisation, which involves the sale of a portfolio of receivables without recourse to a special purpose financing vehicle. In practice, most companies use a revolving pool of receivables as these are generally short-lived. This means that once receivables are paid, they are replaced with new ones. Under normal market conditions, the special purpose vehicle issues securities to the capital markets based on these receivables. Meanwhile, the company’s receivables are replaced with cash and are therefore not included on the balance sheet.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the financial crisis meant that use of the structured finance market, and securitisation in particular, was reined in for a period of time. However, efforts have been made by governments worldwide, particularly in the US, to re-open the securitisation channels and market opinion agreeing the concepts behind it are fundamentally sound, the unfairly maligned practise appears to be in the early stages of a comeback. It is the way that securitisation is put into practice that needs to be addressed, and the return of securitisation is expected to bring less complex and less opaque structures to the market. Where available, receivables securitisation can be a good source of alternative funding for those companies that have been subject to credit rating downgrades.</p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h3 id="going-mainstream">Going mainstream</h3>
<p>Given the evident success of the Credit Warehouse approach will others be following Siemens’ lead with their own centralised solutions? In the long run, almost certainly, says Barclays Cavenaghi. “We do expect that once corporates have done their homework then concepts such as payments and collections factories, and what Siemens is doing right now with their Credit Warehouse, are going to become much more mainstream.” SEPA, he adds, now makes all this easier to implement. “Once you have an overview of your receivables profiles across a number of countries those volumes will become much more visible and it will make more sense as a corporate to look at solutions that gets them off the books.”</p>
<p>Not every corporate has the resources to set-up its own in-house unit to sell-on receivables though. What steps can smaller, less technologically sophisticated corporates do to unlock greater efficiency within their supply chains? “For other companies, who lack the benefit of a “credit warehouse” like Siemens have, the important thing is to discuss the strategy on payables and receivables with the areas of the company that are buying and selling,” Anil Walia, Head of Supply Chain Financing at RBS told Treasury Today in a later interview.</p>
<p>Breaking down silos in the buying, selling and finance functions remains the biggest working capital challenge for many companies. Walia believes a large part of the problem is that the departments speak different ‘languages’; if procurement, sales teams and finance all understood each other’s objectives better greater efficiencies could be realised across the business. “The key performance indicators (KPIs) of the various business divisions are sometimes contradictory. If KPIs of the buying, selling and finance functions could be harmonised to a greater extent, that would be the first step in breaking down the silos,” says Walia. At Siemens, KPIs are already improving as a result of their centralisation efforts. However, Kirchhof cautions that treasurers should not expect miracles overnight. Making such changes naturally entails a lot of hard work and sometimes, he adds, it can take a while before the impact is seen. “It takes a lot of discussions, presentations, internal and external arguments to get there. But in the end you see more than a working capital benefit – you are bringing stability and structure into your supply chain.”</p>
<p>Maybe the benefits won’t be visible immediately. But that should not deter any treasurer from looking to garner longer-term working capital improvements.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[With billions estimated to be tied up in excess working capital, optimising the flow of funds through the financial supply chain will surely continue to be a top priority for European companies in the years ahead. But how are transaction banks, technology solutions and treasury itself, changing in the quest for ever greater working capital efficiency?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/cash-and-liquidity-management/working-capital/fantastic-beautiful-sun-halo-in-midday-thailand-with-ferris-wheel-139901272.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2014-05-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[All together now: integrating payments, trade and working capital]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFDF4ECC241CD011CE458A3E170E54A1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=69E5AF54A6052F2670FDCE0C1340ABEC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D453431E89174943914A1E9B77EEF04F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=13EF3DB5DEBC45694ABFCCA0015286D4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EE56E6C2D747C2EB4C0A26F5902BBE29"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Stack of coins" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>The complexity of modern business means that a client and solution focused mindset is increasingly necessary to meet a corporate’s daily transactional challenges. Integrated delivery, driven by this understanding, can help client organisations become more efficient in both their key business processes and in managing their finances.</p>

<h4 class="fn">Gerlach Jacobs</h4>
<h5 class="title">Global Head Transaction Services</h5>
<img alt="ING" class="logo org" height="22" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/ing-logo-2012-90x22.png" width="90"/>
<p>Gerlach Jacobs is Global Head Transaction Services at ING Commercial Banking since March 2011 and member of Commercial Banking’s Executive Team. Jacobs held various positions within ING in Hong Kong, Los Angeles, Mexico City, New York, London and Amsterdam.</p>
<p>Transactions Services includes Payments and Cash Management, Trade Finance Services, Working Capital Solutions, as well as ING’s specialised cash management subsidiary Bank Mendes Gans.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ingcb.com">www.ingcb.com</a></p>

<p style="font-size:108%;"><em>For ING, Transaction Services has brought three distinct but closely allied product domains into a single line of business, as a third product pillar of Commercial Banking, alongside Financial Markets and Lending Services. Transaction Services merges the core flow businesses of Payments and Cash Management, Trade Finance Services and Working Capital Solutions, together with the highly specialised cash management and pooling business of Bank Mendes Gans. How does this approach influence ING’s view of the world and more importantly, what does this mean for its clients?</em></p>
<h3 id="the-cash-management-challenge">The cash management challenge</h3>
<p>It is no secret that as a result of the financial crisis, the professional view of treasury departments in companies has become even more important. However, treasurers also have a number of new important challenges to meet. Gerlach Jacobs, Global Head Transaction Services, ING Commercial Banking, immediately focuses on the growing pressure to optimise working capital management (WCM). “More than ever it is vital to combine the financial and the physical operational supply chain, and to become as efficient as possible in managing working capital, because during the crisis many corporates had to face reduced availability of bank credit.”</p>
<p>Whilst Jacobs acknowledges that WCM continues to be a challenge, “because we are still living in difficult times and banks and the financial industry are still re-organising and responding to constantly changing regulation”, he believes that the more a company treasurer focuses on managing working capital, the more efficient that business will become and the less dependent it will be on traditional forms of lending.</p>
<h3 id="working-capital-staying-focused">Working capital: staying focused</h3>
<p>Of course, treasurers have always sought to manage their working capital; “it is part of their core remit”, says Jacobs. But pre-crisis, when there was ample liquidity available in the market, it was natural for them to focus on other, more pressing issues. “Now we are in the midst of another difficult economic cycle and companies must once more look to improve all their financial metrics,” he adds. And one way to do that is to ensure that their working capital is at peak efficiency.</p>
<p>It stands to reason that superior WCM improves key financial metrics including profitability, return on equity, risk perception and even access to funding. “What we see are companies focusing more and more on the different aspects of working capital – not just on cash and liquidity – and many are increasingly looking for tailor-made working capital solutions.” Using products that are designed to enhance the working capital position of a company, corporates are looking at those parts of working capital which can generate optimal financing; Jacobs notes for example the increased appetite for payable solutions, with supply chain finance (SCF) in particular having “finally really come to the market”.</p>
<p>It is easy to make bold statements of intent about improving WCM, perhaps by stretching payables or demanding quicker payment but Jacobs warns, it is essential to look deeper into commercial relationships across the physical supply chain than this would normally suggest. Corporates are focusing a lot on their core physical supply chain relationships but are so internally focused that it puts key suppliers under pressure. It is, he explains, vital to look at the right mix of products but also be very aware that the physical and the financial supply chain are very closely connected. “It is about making sure that you value your corporate supplier and buyer relationships, and ensuring that you have a good overview of your total supply chain and that it continues to work as optimally as possible. SCF is an obvious example where you can improve your working capital without creating a liquidity squeeze for your core suppliers.”</p>
<p>Difficulties can arise if a business does not have oversight of all the different aspects of WCM, especially if there are competing metrics for each department involved in the overall process. Jacobs believes that part of the reason why corporate treasuries are more important is because the business units really need that overall view, now more than ever. Technology has a role to play in delivery, he notes, but reporting on working capital and on liquidity “is becoming increasingly professionalised” requiring a deep skill-set to correctly understand results.</p>
<p>There is also a need for ever more timely data, so that companies know exactly what their working capital and liquidity position is, on a real-time basis. “In some large corporates where all these activities were run completely separately, perhaps out of the accounts receivables (AR) or accounts payable (AP) departments, the quest now is for a more harmonised approach; it has to align because they all support each other.”</p>
<p>But had there been a temptation to let WCM slip a little in times of easier credit? The focus may have shifted to other matters but Jacobs is adamant that treasurers have never “taken their eye off the ball”. There is a constant demand for more up-to-date financial information, “and that is not going to change”. Companies invest in technology, such as enterprise resource planning (ERP) systems, and that, he notes, is not going to change either. “All the measures that companies have taken to protect themselves against the financial crisis are going to continue and once they have started I do not think they are going to loosen their grip on WCM.”</p>

<h3 id="working-capital-solutions">Working capital solutions</h3>
<h5>Supply chain finance:</h5>
<p>ING’s SCF offering for suppliers and buyers combines outgoing payment services and a web-based portal. It features reconciliation functionality and full electronic trading of invoices. The ING concept aims to deliver a range of benefits to clients including access to transparent trade receivables and payables statuses and provision of automatic payments and faster funding. The bank’s broad global network enables local supplier support during on-boarding, and its robust SCF legal structure is based on current best practice. In addition, ING’s customised client support for programme rollouts can accelerate collaboration between finance, purchasing, sales and trade partners.</p>
<h5>Factoring:</h5>
<p>As a cash flow tool, accounts receivable financing, also known as factoring, has a long history. Within ING it has been offered for more than 40 years as a means of raising working capital by financing their receivables, inventory and purchase orders. If a business is concerned with adding fixed costs, has slow turnover of receivables, is highly seasonal or challenged by lengthy manufacturing cycles (or is just undercapitalised), factoring may be used to accelerate the monitisation of receivables, improve cash flow and act as a risk management tool.</p>
<h5>Trade receivables finance:</h5>
<p>The import and export business is full of financial and regulatory hurdles that can trip up the inexperienced. For clients who are looking to expand their export business ING provides its Trade Receivables Purchase Programme. An alternative solution to finance trade growth for exporting companies by purchasing large and diversified portfolios of their trade receivables. Customers generally have a focus on Europe, but are also active in the America’s, Asia and the rest of the world, where they are supported by ING’s local capabilities in 40 countries.</p>

<h3 id="cash-and-payments-sepa-is-coming-ready-or-not">Cash and payments: SEPA is coming, ready or not</h3>
<p>Another major cash management challenge for treasurers in Europe is the looming Single Euro Payments Area (SEPA) deadline. Jacobs believes that the whole industry still has reason to be concerned about its implementation. However, what he observes across ING’s client base is a growing desire to move on, particularly as the 1<sup>st</sup> February 2014 deadline is almost here. Many large multinational corporations have made significant progress, “certainly in their SEPA Credit Transfer migration plans”. On the SEPA Direct Debit side, he is less sure: “There still is a lot of work to do”.</p>
<p>“We see regional differences. Some countries are more advanced in their implementation preparations than others and domestically I see smaller businesses still having many of their SEPA migration projects ahead of them,” notes Jacobs. “There is no time to waste because the risk is that everyone waits until the last moment and then migration capacity is going to be under tremendous pressure.”</p>
<p>Despite all the press coverage, alarm bells and the fact that governments are now helping to create more awareness across Europe on the importance of being SEPA-ready, the banking industry feeling is that “things could speed up a bit” on the corporate side. However, ING is “working day and night” to accomplish the migration. ING has many core corporate customers that need to migrate and Jacobs points to the various ways in which the bank is helping them to do that, including offering its expertise and guidance on formats, testing and customer on-boarding. “We have an army of SEPA migration project managers working with our clients, helping them to get ready for implementation,” he says. ING also has a comprehensive website covering all aspects of SEPA preparation and migration at <a href="http://www.ingsepa.com" target="_blank">www.ingsepa.com</a>.</p>
<p>Despite the pressure, ING believes that it is still feasible to have its client base ready for SEPA. Of course, payments are a network business and it is one thing to be ready yourself, but you are also dependent on all other entities with which you do business being ready too. Smaller banks and SMEs may not realise the implications of not being ready and, says Jacobs, it will be tough for them to comply. “This is the common theme in our payments industry and everyone is putting their maximum resources on this. Time will tell if all parties will be ready in time.”</p>
<p>The inexorable move towards SEPA should be viewed as an opportunity for corporates to start considering the benefits it should bring. “At the moment that’s not happening; people are just scrambling to make sure they are ready,” notes Jacobs. Beyond February 2014, he suggests there will be a period “where we all catch our breath” and then the real opportunities will become more apparent. “Centralisation of liquidity is already possible, but I think centralisation of payments is the next step. We’ve always seen a delay in that for different reasons – too expensive, benefits outweigh the cost, and so on – but corporates are now going to look at these as real opportunities in SEPA phase 2.</p>

<h3 id="payments-solutions-the-payments-factory">Payments solutions: the Payments Factory</h3>
<p>ING offers clients a centralised Payment Factory (PAF) which operates as an overlay service, providing a single-point-of-entry interface between the client’s ERP system and the bank’s infrastructure. PAF provides end-to-end connectivity with clearing systems and helps clients achieve uniformity in distribution channels, file formats and processes. Harmonising processes reduces or removes treasury duplication, increases oversight of local offices and can deliver savings through economies of scale and can be combined with a collection factory to optimise working capital management.</p>

<h3 id="developing-trade-finance">Developing trade finance</h3>
<p>The likely impact of Basel III on some banking industry products is well publicised, including the possibility of increased costs for banks. In the trade finance space, there have also been some more positive effects of regulation, notes Jacobs. In certain markets, he says, some of the more stringent local regulations have eased slightly, as the regulators increasingly realise that the trade finance product set is fundamentally a safer product than some other forms of lending. Allied to this has also been a desire not to hamper trade by increasing the cost of a financial product that is a crucial “lubricant” in international trade. Jacobs is hopeful that this stance will continue.</p>
<p>Usually when costs rise due to increased regulation, the application of smarter product processing is often the solution. This can typically be implemented by either reducing processing costs by redesigning operations; or through more automation of business processes. “You would think that all that has been done, but there are still plenty of opportunities to centralise certain operations and create further economies of scale,” he explains. “Most financial institutions are looking into their processes to make sure that their cost of doing business remains competitive.”</p>
<p>In trade finance, this effort is nowhere better illustrated than by the advent of the Bank Payment Obligation (BPO). Although it has been around for a while, it gained a major boost in April this year when the International Chamber of Commerce (ICC) approved the uniform rules around the BPO (creating the URBPO). This, says Jacobs, goes a long way towards removing the process inefficiencies that are associated with paper-based letters of credit (LCs), whilst still retaining the desired level of risk mitigation to keep costs down.</p>

<h3 id="trade-finance-solutions">Trade finance solutions</h3>
<p>ING’s trade finance products include letters of credit, documentary collections and bank guarantees. These can be combined and shaped into a custom-built solution, according to client need. With a letter of credit (also known as a documentary credit), the buyer’s bank guarantees payment to the seller if certain criteria are met. Documentary collections, just as letters of credit, reduce the payment risks on international trade transactions, and with a bank guarantee obligations to third parties are ensured. All these products offer security and protection against risks if an international trade transaction does not go as planned.</p>
<p>Importers and exporters can also use a letter of credit to obtain financing. An exporter, for example, can obtain funding from its local bank to manufacture the goods as this bank is assured that payment will follow when the documents are presented under the credit.</p>

<h3 id="the-cash-and-trade-alliance">The cash and trade alliance</h3>
<p>Cash management and trade within the corporate space have always enjoyed something of a synergistic relationship, says Jacobs, noting too that “some of the products are substitutes for each other”. However, in the current economic environment, corporates are increasingly sensitive to the positions of their core suppliers and the other key participants in their value chains. Therefore they are ensuring they use the appropriate products to cover their risks and to ensure that their entire value chain continues to work efficiently. “I think there’s an even more proactive approach to make sure that there is access to sufficient liquidity throughout the entire supply chain” he states. “There is and always has been a close relationship between cash management and trade – and this will always be there.”</p>
<h3 id="an-holistic-approach">An holistic approach</h3>
<p>The corporates across the ING client base are, generally now much more interested in looking at an overall banking proposition, rather than taking a product-by-product view. “What I see is a more holistic approach, with corporates looking at their total value chain,” Jacobs confirms. This holistic approach is driven by the need to make their working capital position as strong as possible, including reducing funding requirements and to become better at self-financing. It means that more functions are involved in the financial processes of the business, including IT and procurement, but this is a welcome broadening of the discussion. “In the past we talked mainly to the treasurer or assistant treasurer and the conversation was often about a specific product. Now we tend to meet with a larger group of client staff, looking at the company’s overall financial position, how it all fits together and ultimately finding ways to improve working capital and liquidity.”</p>
<p>Considering the increasing importance of the treasury department across ING’s client base and the need for businesses to be on top of working capital more than ever, the bank has made some “quite dramatic changes” to its business model, says Jacobs.</p>
<p>It started by reviewing its core products; those seen as a key part of the working capital proposition for its corporate clients. It defined four overarching product domains: payments and cash management; working capital solutions; trade finance solutions; and a fourth product domain which is operated via ING subsidiary, Bank Mendes Gans, providing specialised overlay propositions (including cash pooling on a global basis handling close to 40 currencies). “I guess it’s a sign of the times and also proof that companies are becoming better in managing their working capital, as we see that these products are in demand, with many customers having a growing interest in them,” states Jacobs.</p>
<p>ING also created a client solutions group specialising in looking at the working capital of customers, coming up with “total solutions” (rather than focusing on a single product) to address the whole physical and financial supply chain of its customers. “We continue to develop our technology, investing in our portals, our centralised services for treasury and centralised data management,” Jacobs states. “We are also looking at harmonising processes and our client service model. We are a large international bank with extensive market presence internationally but we want to make sure that our customers feel that we are a harmonised organisation, with all the efficiencies that a seamless consistent service can bring.”</p>
<h3 id="keep-delivering">Keep delivering</h3>
<p>Treasury presents a dynamic environment in which both corporates and banks must respond to and increasingly anticipate events. Right now, SEPA is top of mind and will stay there until at least 31<sup>st</sup> January next year. ING is mindful that it must give its clients time to implement and comply, but will also continue to work closely with clients to provide innovative solutions to improve their liquidity management. “Having gone through the SEPA implementation, in the second half of 2014 I expect many corporates will be seeking advice on what will happen in the post SEPA era – ‘SEPA 2’ – and how SEPA can improve their payments and cash management processes “ Jacobs says.</p>
<p>The continual stream of regulatory change will absorb a lot of industry time and effort. The European Commission’s proposal for a revised Payment Services Directive (PSDII), for example, was published in July 2013 and if approved by the European Parliament, will have to be transposed into law in each Member-state before being implemented. Such changes will continue to demand “a lot of the bank’s attention” but, Jacobs adds: “We will continue to look outwards, servicing our customers and making sure that we continually make things easier for them and deliver the best solutions that fully meet their requirements – in the end this is what really matters to both us and to our clients.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[For ING, Transaction Services has brought three distinct but closely allied product domains into a single line of business, as a third product pillar of Commercial Banking, alongside Financial Markets and Lending Services. Transaction Services merges the core flow businesses of Payments and Cash Management, Trade Finance Services and Working Capital Solutions, together with the highly specialised cash management and pooling business of Bank Mendes Gans. How does this approach influence ING’s view of the world and more importantly, what does this mean for its clients?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2013-10-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Optimal working capital: making aspiration reality]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFDF4ECC241CD011CE458A3E170E54A1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=69E5AF54A6052F2670FDCE0C1340ABEC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D453431E89174943914A1E9B77EEF04F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=13EF3DB5DEBC45694ABFCCA0015286D4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EE56E6C2D747C2EB4C0A26F5902BBE29"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Stack of coins" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B97EDB6FB9985B8C0A682C1D13914B13"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Efficient working capital management is not about achieving a universal 'right answer'; what works for one corporation may be irrelevant for another.</p>
<h3>Optimal working capital: making aspiration reality</h3>
<h3>优化营运资金: 让愿望成为现实</h3>
<p>Please click on one of the images below to view the full PDF.</p>
<a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/advertorial/jp-morgan/2012/01/11/jp-morgan-optimal-working-capital-making-aspiration-reality.pdf?la=en&amp;hash=3E81C8E40EADF978C7522AA5ABBB9A94"><img alt="Optimal working capital: making aspiration reality | J.P. Morgan" height="431" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/advertorial/jp-morgan/2012/01/11/jp-morgan-optimal-working-capital-making-aspiration-reality-t.png?la=en&amp;hash=B6C3D04CFB750F81A34FBE31428B916A" width="625"/></a> <a href="~/media/255C2DAA37724E76881D692D2F5417E8.ashx"><img alt="优化营运资金: 让愿望成为现实 | J.P. Morgan" height="431" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/advertorial/jp-morgan/2012/01/11/jp-morgan-optimal-working-capital-making-aspiration-reality-zh-t.png?la=en&amp;hash=20F391F633FDC86C396F88648617E67C" width="625"/></a>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/default-hero-image__euro-coins-stacked-on-each-other-382756216__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2012-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Working Capital]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
