<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Women in Treasury Global Study 2021]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Oct 2021 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><div style="float:left;text-align:center;width:200px;margin:1em 2em 2em 0;">
<img alt="Treasury Today Group Women in Treasury Global Study cover" height="283" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/supplements/women-in-treasury-global-study-2021__400x566.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=4503785FA67D7CBD09F3D4C7273BB48C" style="height:283px;width:200px;" width="200"/><br/>
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="mailto:wit@treasurytoday.com?subject=Request%20PDF&amp;body=Please send me a PDF of Women in Treasury Global Study 2021.">Request PDF</a>
</div>
<div id="publication-contents-editorial" style="float:left;width:75%;padding-bottom:1em;">
<p>In this year’s Women in Treasury Global Study there are a number of new elements. Most significantly, for the first time we have opened up the study to participants of all genders to take part. This is in response to the importance of everyone’s views on gender in the workplace to be heard and for us to actively engage with allies.</p>
<p>Men have an important role to play in progress and we wanted to assess their insights and opinions alongside monitoring the lived experiences of women and non-binary people, as we assess gender from a new perspective. Over the course of the last two years the world has changed irrevocably, powered by human rights movements and by a pandemic which has drastically altered the way in which we live and work.</p>
<p>Flexible working has long been a central component in discussions around female representation and inclusion in the workplace. Access to parental leave at equal levels for both genders is another area of ongoing significance. Although many organisations that may have been previously resistant to flexible working have evolved their attitudes through necessity, that doesn’t necessarily translate to flexibility in the number of working hours expected from staff.</p>
<p>We have noticed when looking at the results of the study and anecdotally from our conversations with women over the past 18 months within our Women in Treasury platform, that the burden of domestic responsibilities tends to have fallen more heavily on female members of households. The pandemic has meant a different reality for different individuals that is just as dependent on their domestic situation as their professional one. In previous years of conversations around improvements to female representation and gender equality, we have spoken about the universe of the office and the boardroom as if it were entirely cut off from the universe of society and of our personal lives.</p>
<p>They also reflect the seismic shifts in society around broader issues of racial inequality that have been occurring over the past year. When we closed our Women in Treasury Global Study 2020, the ripple effects of the murder of George Floyd and the galvanisation of the Black Lives Matter movement had not yet fully resonated. In 2021 we are able to truly assess the impact that such movements have had on our respondents’ organisations and their commitments towards diversity, equity and inclusion across the board.</p>
<p>We hope you will find this year’s results enlightening. We believe this new approach offers a fully rounded and comprehensive look at the state of play regarding gender equality in corporations across the world.</p>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury Today Group Global Sustainability Study 2021]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Aug 2021 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><div style="float:left;text-align:center;width:200px;margin:1em 2em 2em 0;">
<img alt="Treasury Today Global Sustainability Study 2021 cover" height="283" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/supplements/2021-08__global-sustainability-study-2021-cover__400x566.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=0421422FDD4CD8084B8FD91E33821C59" style="height:283px;width:200px;" width="200"/><br/>
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="mailto:memberservices@treasurytoday.com?subject=Request%20PDF&amp;body=Please send me a PDF of Treasury Today Global Sustainability Study 2021.">Request PDF</a>
</div>
<h3 id="heading-in-the-right-direction">Heading in the right direction</h3>
<p>Treasury Today Group’s second Global Sustainability Study reveals a swathe of encouraging progress on ESG integration. Indeed, in one standout statistic 61% of our 2021 respondents are new to the survey and didn’t participate in 2020 in a reflection of the growing importance of ESG amongst the treasury community. Elsewhere, we saw a spike in responses from Latin American corporates and find treasury everywhere is spending more time on sustainability.</p>
<p>Our 2021 cohort are integrating new KPIs or targets in their ESG strategy. Companies continue to prioritize emissions, energy consumption and their use of technology, but recycling and working to integrate issues brought to the fore via societal action like the Black Lives Matter movement have also pushed center stage.</p>
<p>Treasury is increasingly tapping the growing number of ESG products. In a marked jump compared to last year, nearly a quarter of 2021 respondents said they are planning to issue a green bond compared to just 12% of our 2020 cohort as frameworks, liquidity and investor demand gathers steam. Indeed, every 2021 respondent had signed up to the ICMA’s voluntary Green Bond Principles in comparison to 63% of respondents last year.</p>
<p>In this year’s study, we draw on new data revealing the key impetus behind sustainability with 47% of respondents saying that stakeholder pressure now drives ESG strategy to “some extent.” Of this, respondents list consumer demand as the primary driver with investor and regulatory pressure close behind.</p>
<p>The latter two influences are certainly set to grow. Like groundbreaking legislation about to arrive via courtesy of the EU’s new taxonomy which will list what constitutes a sustainable activity, with unprecedented consequences for corporate behavior and investment in the years to come. Elsewhere, updated sovereign emission targets and new pledges likely to emerge in Glasgow from COP26 this November, will also increasingly shape treasury strategy.</p>
<p>Elsewhere pressure on treasury and finance teams from investors to integrate financially material ESG data is also growing, with 57% of respondents saying they now include ESG metrics in their annual report.</p>
<p>Of course, not all our findings are positive. 2021 responses reveal treasury’s role in integrating ESG is still unclear. For example, we find some sustainability teams report directly to the CFO bypassing treasury altogether, and although some treasury departments are closely intertwined with colleagues in sustainability (20%) more (25%) reveal they do not work closely with sustainability teams despite the need to pool expertise, processes and rigor. Elsewhere many 2021 respondents say sustainability has lost out to COVID and other more pressing everyday treasury priorities.</p>
<p>But despite one of the most difficult years on record and slow progress in some areas, the survey shows progress nonetheless. Treasury is heading in the right direction.</p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury Today Group Global Sustainability Study 2020]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><div style="float:left;text-align:center;width:200px;margin:1em 2em 2em 0;">
<img alt="Treasury Today Global Sustainability Study 2020 cover" height="283" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/supplements/global-sustainability-study-2020__cover__400x566.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=0A7BDAE19BD845E7F91E2038FCAD7E38" style="height:283px;width:200px;" width="200"/><br/>
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="mailto:memberservices@treasurytoday.com?subject=Request%20PDF&amp;body=Please send me a PDF of Treasury Today Global Sustainability Study 2020.">Request PDF</a>
</div>
<div id="publication-contents-editorial" style="float:left;width:75%;padding-bottom:1em;">
</div>
<h3 id="turning-opinions-into-action">Turning opinions into action</h3>
<p>There is a sense that the concept of sustainability – the idea that through positive action now, we can ensure a viable future for generations to come – is so vast that surely the individual can have no meaningful impact on the outcome. There is a corresponding feeling that, as a truly global issue, isn’t it best just to let ‘other’, better qualified, agents take care of it?</p>
<p>The problem is that persistence of these opinions will lead to not enough action being taken, and the planet and its future inhabitants being left, at best, to some rather unfavourable odds.</p>
<p>Of course, ‘sustainability’ is nothing new. Irish physicist, John Tyndall, demonstrated in 1860 what we now call the greenhouse effect. In 1896, Swedish scientist, Svante Arrhenius, identified human industrial activity as the main source of new CO2 into our atmosphere.</p>
<p>Although Arrhenius believed global warming to be benign – benefitting agriculture in colder climes – his view set in motion a train of research that, 120 or so years later, gave rise to one Greta Thunberg who set about invoking mass consciousness of the problem as we now understand it.</p>
<p>Thunberg draws upon the science of outstanding, but largely anonymous, researchers. By virtue of being a typical awkward teenager, she stops people in their tracks. Through her unwavering belief, she has the ear not just of the good and the great, but of regular people too. This is not ‘others’ making a difference; it is one person.</p>
<p>And when we set out to see what the world of treasury is doing to make a difference, we quickly found plenty of individuals, from a wide range of corporate sectors, sizes and geographies, quietly getting on with activities that are making a positive difference. By engaging with their stakeholders – such as banks, vendors and internal teams – treasurers are raising the volume of the conversation so that many more in their circle are now taking notice.</p>
<p>However, for treasurers active in this space, despite organisational proclamations of support for sustainability, there are still frustrations. Whether finding the time to incorporate more sustainable activities in their day-to-day role, or experiencing limited relevant dialogue with their financial institutions and vendors, this is holding some back from seeing how they too can make a difference.</p>
<p>Climate scientists and activists are pressing home the need for an immediate mass response to global warming. Many more individuals are taking climate change seriously, realising that they can make a difference. They know that the cumulative effect of all our actions, no matter how seemingly small, will always surpass waiting for ‘others’ to do something.</p>
<p>This, the first Treasury Today Group Global Sustainability Study, delivers a positive sign that increasing numbers of treasurers are taking measures – sometimes with support, sometimes without. And whilst it also shows that not everyone is clear about what they can do – with an indication that financial institutions and vendors need to be engaging more with their clients on sustainability – there is clear evidence that treasurers and their organisations are willing to do more to help us on the road to a sustainable future.</p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[The definitive guide to sustainability in corporate finance]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2019 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=04A34F0E1F8C163E90786986307B604F]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=75EA3E7098E74939E869E787CF6818E7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=386522CC337466C3A7D1202A56F2D346"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=076FFB4BD0C6E3936B224FD0A4F683B0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5281E654E865087B5CE326D48812B934"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E2822CCBCF7EB0B1721600E26DB6FEE4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Group photo of the participants" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=04A34F0E1F8C163E90786986307B604F" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__group-photo__ttf-ldn-2019-040__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=04A34F0E1F8C163E90786986307B604F"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>Most modern organisations visibly promote sustainability in some form or other. It’s what their stakeholders – from employees to investors – expect of them, and it’s increasingly what the public demand. For many, it’s also the right thing to do.</em></p>
<p><em>For treasurers sitting at the financial heart of these businesses, ensuring the organisation is financially sustainable remains sacrosanct. But with many now seeking to uphold the principles of sustainability too, does it have to be a battle of value versus values? In this Talking Treasury Forum, a panel of experts, drawn from the worlds of finance and treasury, explore this theme.</em></p>
<div style="padding-bottom:1em;">
<p><strong>Listen to the audio teaser below</strong></p>
<p><audio controls="controls" height="30px" id="audio-teaser" preload="none" src="https://tt-static.s3.amazonaws.com/tt-2019-09-25__talking-sustainable-treasury-forum__audio-teaser.mp3" type="audio/mp4" width="625px"></audio></p>
</div>
<p style="text-align:center;"><a class="button-block button--red-stroke" href="mailto:memberservices@treasurytoday.com?subject=Talking Treasury Forum 2019&amp;body=Please send me the PDF version of 'The definitive guide to sustainability in corporate finance' Talking Treasury Forum." style="margin:0 1em 1em 0;">Request PDF download</a><a class="button-block button--red-stroke" href="#video" style="margin:0 1em 1em 0;">Watch video</a><a class="button-block button--red-stroke" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/pdf/2019/treasurytoday-talking-treasury-forum-sustainability-2019-certificate.pdf?la=en&amp;hash=9C059A25451A08907FC5A1E01B383075">View ClimatePartner certificate</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Participants</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><div class="person n1 vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Adam Richford, Group Treasurer, Renewi" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__adam-richford__ttf-ldn-2019-007__150x200.jpg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=42B2AC9D4646AF9FE596C5661BE7328F" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 1em 0px; width: 150px;" width="150">
<h4 class="fn">Adam Richford</h4>
<h5 class="title">Group Treasurer</h5>
<p><img alt="Renewi logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/renewi-logo-2018-75x55.png?w=75&amp;la=en&amp;hash=8320C23B714FF53071D3874B6CAAA363" style="margin-top: 1.5em; width: 75px;" title="Renewi" width="75"/></p>
</img></div>
<div class="person n2 vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Henrik Lang, Managing Director, Global Head of Liquidity GTS, Bank of America" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__henrik-lang__ttf-ldn-2019-009__150x200.jpg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=627759BDCD7D9C214620D04D7F05E43E" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 1em 0px; width: 150px;" width="150"/>
<h4 class="fn">Henrik Lang</h4>
<h5 class="title">Managing Director, Global Head of Liquidity GTS</h5>
<p><img alt="Bank of America logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/bank-of-america-2020.svg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=79758BC37AA5E30315192F9ECEF4DFCE" style="margin-top: 1.5em; width: 150px;" title="Bank of America" width="160"/></p>
</div>
<div class="person n3 vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Tom Callahan, Head of Global Cash Management, BlackRock" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__tom-callahan__ttf-ldn-2019-026__150x200.jpg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=7EAF7E290BEE3AD23AAA41E359DA03DA" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 1em 0px; width: 150px;" width="150"/>
<h4 class="fn">Tom Callahan</h4>
<h5 class="title">Head of Global Cash Management</h5>
<p><img alt="BlackRock logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/blackrock-logo-2019__120x17.png?w=120&amp;la=en&amp;hash=54DE0C0A43D38086C6B502E4D7F5D968" style="margin-top: 1.5em; width: 120px;" title="BlackRock" width="120"/></p>
</div>
<div class="person n4 vcard" style="clear:both;">
<img alt="Inês Faden da Silva, Treasurer, Tideway" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__ines-faden-de-silva__ttf-ldn-2019-034__150x200.jpg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=DA67510093EDB10E2C1D7C19FAFE380D" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 1em 0px; width: 150px;" width="150"/>
<h4 class="fn">Inês Faden da Silva</h4>
<h5 class="title">Treasurer</h5>
<p><img alt="Tideway logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/tideway-logo-2019-70x79.png?w=70&amp;la=en&amp;hash=6AF57046D1A33C22507E7FD7B20D908E" style="margin-top: 1.5em; width: 70px;" title="Tideway" width="70"/></p>
</div>
<div class="chair" style="clear:both;">
<h3 id="chair">Moderator</h3>
<div class="person n0 vcard" style="min-height: 200px;">
<h4 class="fn"><img alt="Sophie Jackson, Joint Publisher &amp; Head of Strategic Content, Treasury Today Group" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__sophie-jackson__ttf-ldn-2019-017__150x200.jpg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=31C36737CF3EBD35A6FCB5B414339098" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 2em 0px; width: 150px;" width="150"/>Sophie Jackson</h4>
<h5 class="title">Joint Publisher &amp; Head of Strategic Content</h5>
<img alt="Treasury Today Group logo" class="logo" height="30" src="/i/logo/treasurytoday-group-logo-2016-130x30.png" style="margin: 2em 0 0 0;" title="Treasury Today Group" width="130"/>
</div>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4>Welcome everyone. Sustainability often has some very personal values attached so let’s start by looking at what it means to you, and how it manifests itself in your treasury department.</h4>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Treasurer, Tideway:</strong> Our company was created to address a sustainability issue, so it was natural for us to align the financing and the treasury function with that mission. We started with financing and have now turned to our cash investments. On a day-to-day basis, we also have many activities that we do as team, to be more sustainable. We’ve implemented paper-free meetings, and we have organised team volunteering sessions, with litter-picks on the river.</p>
<p>In a huge city like London, we need an acute awareness of the entire ecosystem in which we operate. We look at it as needing both a license to operate for construction and a social license too. We have a long-term view of reconnecting London with the Thames. As an example, in order to build the tunnel, we had to bring tunnel boring machines and other equipment onto the sites, and then remove the spoil from the tunnel. Normally, this would have required about 600,000 two-way heavy goods vehicles trips across London. Our solution was to implement a “more by river” strategy. We now transport about 90% of all equipment and spoil by river for sites on the river. Because we are trebling freight traffic on the river, we worked with the Port of London Authority to establish an academy to train 300 new pilots, for now and for future use of the river.</p>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Group Treasurer, Renewi:</strong> Renewi is a recycling and waste to product company. Sustainability is one of our core values and we have been able to align treasury activities so that we are now entirely green-financed. It’s about making sure that we reinvest into the circular economy. We are focused on finding new, sustainable solutions for waste issues that don’t yet have solutions. Last year we invested in PMC, a joint venture in reprocessing asbestos-contaminated steel which previously would have gone to landfill. We’ve also entered into a joint venture with firms such as Ikea to find ways to recycle old mattresses. In treasury, our focus is supporting the business to continue to invest in the circular economy.</p>
<h4>On the financial institution side, what has the sustainability journey been like for your organisations?</h4>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, Head of Global Cash Management, BlackRock:</strong> Journey is the right way to describe it for us at BlackRock. Today we have a centralised division called BlackRock Sustainable Investing which focuses on identifying drivers of long-term return associated with environmental, social and governance issues. The team looks across all of our products, considering how we can integrate ESG into our investment processes and create solutions for our clients to achieve sustainable investment return.</p>
<p>Two years ago, in the cash management world, few were talking about sustainability. Through increased investor interest in these issues, we had to work out how we could overlay basic ESG metrics on our existing products, making sure that we were fully capturing the exposure to ESG risks of individual companies. It was a fairly modest beginning, but the world has evolved and sustainability is resonating even more deeply, at a personal and corporate level with many of our clients. We found we weren’t being ambitious enough; there was a void in cash and liquidity management in terms of dedicated sustainable strategies which we have now turned our attention to. Earlier this year we launched a family of green money market solutions to stunning market reception.</p>
<p>One of the main challenges for our clients was the ‘value versus values’ debate, which is something we’re seeking to address. Our job as a fiduciary is to deliver the best risk-adjusted returns. Many felt under pressure from their board and investors to incorporate sustainability, yet were concerned about the risk of underperforming benchmarks. Now we can take a lot of those worries away.</p>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Managing Director, Global Head of Liquidity GTS, Bank of America:</strong> So not dissimilar to what Tom described. I think that Bank of America has been a market-leading institution in terms of green financing for a long time, and we try to build on that success. Responsible growth is a cornerstone of our corporate strategy, and we try to do that also through ESG leadership in the broader market.</p>
<p>Where I sit, within the global transaction services, we work together with treasurers. And what we found over the last few years is that there is an increasing demand from them to try and turn their treasury departments into more sustainable and greener operations.</p>
<p>Also what we realised, I think, was that in the past we, as a bank, did a really good job focusing on ourselves and making sure that we are doing things in a sustainable way, and the right way. But I do believe that that there is a great multiplication impact to be had once we start extending that approach to our client base, simply because across the globe we deal with thousands of corporate clients.</p>
<p>In my view, the greatest impact for us on the broader economy and in wider society can be gained once we can work together with our clients and turn their treasury departments and businesses into sustainable and greener functions; it creates a far greater impact than if we just focus on ourselves.</p>
<p>It’s because we can impact our clients’ life within their treasury departments across the board, from the point that they make a payment, take out the loan, invest their excess cash, or even get their statements. We realised that we actually provide our clients with a very clear set of actions that they can take back to their businesses and start executing them. And it doesn’t take a lot, honestly; it just requires a little bit of focus and the willingness to move forward with their sustainable agenda.</p>
<h4>And do you notice different regional appetites for this amongst your clients?</h4>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> At BlackRock, absolutely we have and this is reflected in the US$5bn of assets already raised in our green money market strategies in Europe. There has been enthusiasm and energy in Europe that we have not quite seen yet in the US; this is partly due to regulators and governments expanding their focus on incorporating sustainability into investment information and decision making and corporate treasurers are often engaged on the topic through their pension fund or internal sustainability teams.</p>
<p>In Asia, demand has been primarily driven by investors in Hong Kong and Singapore. We are also seeing the ESG investment theme starting to emerge from Chinese investors.</p>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> I would say no real differences between the regions except perhaps for product choice but there is a difference between the size of the company. Larger corporates, with greater resources might be able to dedicate more people to creating a wider scope of ESG-friendly treasury, whereas I think smaller companies tend to focus, for example, on moving away from paper statements to electronic statements, or they stop using cheques in favour of electronic transfers. Across the globe though, the consistent theme is that clients are really interested in discussing their ESG agendas with us.</p>
<h4>Let’s move on now to thinking about some of the best practices that treasury departments can adopt. What best practices have you adopted, and are putting in place for KPIs?</h4>
<figure class="portrait right" style="float:right; margin: 0.5em 0em 0em 2em;">
<img alt="Adam Richford, Group Treasurer, Renewi" height="225" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__adam-richford__ttf-ldn-2019-074__200x225.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=889CE6F4BB795AF04DBAAA67ABF5F792" title="Adam Richford, Group Treasurer, Renewi" width="200"/>
<figcaption>
<h6>Adam Richford</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> We have introduced a sustainability-linked loan which has various KPIs. As we meet those targets, the price of facility is reduced correspondingly. One of the things that was really important to us was that the KPIs that we chose were also important metrics for the organisation. We were very keen to ensure that we could leverage the same measures that we were already using for our CSR reporting. By putting them into banking documentation they gain importance, they have a monetary value linked to them and they have a specific target linked to them each year over the five-year life of the loan. They need to be realistic and achievable because we don’t want to miss our sustainability targets but they need to be sufficiently challenging to deserve reward from our lenders.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> When I first took a green-financing strategy to the board, I was mindful that I didn’t want to create a mini-industry on the side, just producing reports. Although treasury has to look at what we are doing, how we measure it, and what we are reporting, we also have to align with the rest of the company in this respect. It brings more discipline because once we got treasury involved, the metrics were no longer optional. We formed a great relationship with our sustainability colleagues because it meant we are supporting the efforts that they lead.</p>
<p>I’d add that, like many things you do first time, you can find resistance, but with us, once we went through the cycle and the business saw the final product, those barriers quickly dissolved.</p>
<p>And what I would say on KPIs, it is important to be very candid about it with stakeholders. We have 54 legacy objectives – many in terms of employment – of which about 37 are live, with 90% on-track. Investors like to hear about those targets we meet as well as those we are still working towards and it makes the rest of our performance much more credible.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote><p>Sustainability is one of our core values and we have been able to align treasury activities so that we are now entirely green-financed. It’s about making sure that we reinvest into the circular economy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Adam Richford, Group Treasurer, Renewi</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4>What about external measures such as the Dow Jones Sustainability Index or the Global Green Finance Index. Are any of those of relevance for either of you?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> ESG ratings are broadly relevant. There is a lot of commitment to the UN PRI Principles for Responsible Investing from equity investment managers, and it is certainly a topic of conversation on the equity side of the equation. Many ESG ratings are unsolicited and un-consulted so the veracity of them is questionable sometimes. But I think that the ESG rating industry is maturing and is becoming more relevant as a benchmark; as their understanding of the idiosyncrasies of individual companies improves, the level and quality of their ratings improve.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> We are on some of the green bond indices but have minimal exposure to ESG ratings. Some of the unsolicited ratings providers show companies what they have drafted, giving them a chance to provide feedback, others don’t. There is an ongoing discussion in the investor community about the general lack of transparency of the methodology. One view is that they should all have the same methodology, and all be transparent, with companies publishing their data just once a year. I think it is fine for each to have different approaches because it allows for indices to be valued in different ways by investors but consistency in the data procured would be welcomed by corporates.</p>
<h4>From a financial services perspective, what are your thoughts on the use of metrics?</h4>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> Clients have different priorities. One could be interested only in having sustainable vendors and suppliers, and would like to offer different supply chain models and price points to suppliers that meet certain sustainability criteria. Another could be interested in having diversity on their board or be interested in moving completely away from paper-based payment instruments. Rather than focusing on and trying to follow the sometimes confusing methodologies by the rating agencies, we would rather engage on a bi-lateral basis, then work with them to really dig deep, and then try to tailor our solutions and advisories to those specific objectives.</p>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> There are issues that have to be talked about, especially the metrics, when creating portfolios. We often see wildly diverging ratings on the same company so we created our own ESG credit methodology approach, taking into account Sustainalytics and MSCI metrics, and other third-party data. It is confusing for clients and we do find a lot of inconsistencies. We have had times where the treasury department can’t buy our funds, but their charitable foundation can, because of different policy guidelines. And there are different standards for what qualifies as a green bond for certain clients, so it is hard to create a one-size-fits-all product when there are so many conflicting demands. We can bring the breadth of our experience, having gone through this journey ourselves, and can create custom solutions for clients. But there needs to be a dialogue because it is more complicated than I think many of us appreciate.</p>
<h4>Let’s turn to the practicalities of using green finance tools such as green bonds and green loans. Can you talk us through your experience?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> Renewi issued its first green bond in 2015, which was a Belgian retail bond. We did a more substantial green financing in 2018, where we converted our main banking facility into a green finance document. That involved creating a green finance framework, which we worked closely with our banks to prepare, with Sustainalytics reviewing and providing a second opinion.</p>
<p>Our banking group is a syndicate of lenders, and a couple of those banks were our ‘green advisors’. They were able to sound out the other banks on the documentation, making sure that what we were proposing was acceptable to all parties.</p>
<p>Somewhat unusually for Renewi, we were able to create a ‘perpetual’ green framework that documents our asset position versus our liability position. This meant it was fit for purpose for another bond issuance that we did earlier this year; we didn’t need to create a new framework for the new instrument.</p>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float:left;margin:0.5em 2em 0em 0em;">
<img alt="Inês Faden da Silva, Treasurer, Tideway" height="225" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__ines-faden-de-silva__ttf-ldn-2019-064__200x225.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=BABB171A8AD759FFD79680C6EB4CFDE7" title="Inês Faden da Silva, Treasurer, Tideway" width="200"/>
<figcaption>
<h6>Inês Faden da Silva</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> Both Renewi and Tideway are pure-play sustainability businesses and so it may not be quite the same for other companies. I make that caveat because sometimes people say it is easy for you, because you are a pure-player, but we have still taken a green finance strategy to the board and then created our green finance framework.</p>
<p>We are often asked how much work it involves. Our framework offers a short description of the company, a section describing what we do from a sustainability perspective – all that information already exists – and then we just follow the simple four IMCA Green Bond Principles: Use of Proceeds, Process for Project Evaluation and Selection, Management of Proceeds and Reporting. It is relatively straightforward.</p>
<p>Since 2017, all our financing has been green. We have issued seven green bonds – much of which is done on a deferred basis – and in August this year we closed our first green US private placement, also deferred.</p>
<p>We are now going a step further. Our green evaluation by Standard &amp; Poor’s now covers all our bonds issued since the inception of our EMT programme, and we will be transferring all to the London Stock Exchange Green Exchange, greening all of our bond financing.</p>
<p>And then of course there is the reporting. Anyone designing a green bond framework should pay attention to how they plan to report; as they are reporting on the allocation of funds, that has to be very straightforward. In terms of the impact, just don’t design things that will require a lot of work later on!</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote><p>Like many things you do first time, you can find resistance, but with us, once we went through the cycle and the business saw the final product, those barriers quickly dissolved.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Inês Faden da Silva, Treasurer, Tideway</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4>What benefits have these instruments brought to your organisations?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> We get a financial benefit: that is clear, and a strong sell in and of itself. But we are also linking one of Renewi’s core Values, ‘Sustainability’, with multiple teams internally. Our treasury and finance teams are more closely connected with the ESG function and together are driving a stronger dialogue with the board as a result. On the equity capital markets side, it has been a helpful additional part of our narrative; offering proof positive to investors that we are entirely focused on sustainability.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> We are very similar; it has definitely helped in aligning the company’s sustainability mission with financing. It has changed the dynamics inside the company. It has brought financing closer to some other functions. Finance is generally misunderstood but we made it much more understandable, so others could link what the company is doing with what finance is doing; it started a number of conversations. It also started conversations with our shareholders; they are delighted! We are one of the most advanced portfolio companies and so they use a number of our sustainability case studies, including financing, in their reporting.</p>
<p>I’d add that there is a lot of discussion as to whether you get better pricing or not. I think there is some evidence that you may, but I think that it is still early days. It was not our main motivation.</p>
<h4>Tell us about Bank of America’s approach to sustainable financing and investments.</h4>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> We have heard a lot about green bonds and green financing. Within global transaction services, we like to extend the spectrum of products we are offering in the financing space. One particular solution that we are getting a lot of interest in is sustainable supply chain finance. It’s a very simple yet powerful concept because of the multiplication impact again.</p>
<p>We give tools to our clients that allow them to offer preferential payment terms to certain suppliers who meet specific sustainability targets. Clients love the flexibility that it is not just about their green bonds and loans and facilities but also that they can extend the ESG concept across their entire supply chain model. It remains that the most important incentive for clients, across, all products, is that it enables them to achieve their ESG goals.</p>
<h4>And how is BlackRock adjusting its products to keep ahead; are you responding to clients or doing so on your own initiative?</h4>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> We respond to clients and also to market structures. The essence of any money fund is of course liquidity and preservation of capital. Just because a fund is green does not relinquish that requirement. The challenge that any asset manager moving into this space has is that there is very little – next to zero – issuance of short-dated green bonds. Multi-billion dollar liquid portfolios of green bonds just don’t exist!</p>
<p>In time, as market structure changes, our portfolios will change. But as with many sustainability projects, you have to start where you are, not where you wish you were. And right now we are at the front end of the market, where 80% of issuance comes from financials which are not green entities. At BlackRock, our approach is ‘best of breed’. We have many financial names and we filter and rank them based on publicly available green criteria.</p>
<p>As we become successful and these funds grow, it is going to change issuer behaviour. Since we have launched these funds, we have issuers talk to us about green CP programmes and green CD programmes. The short end of the market is always the deepest, most liquid and most cost-effective part of the curve to issue, but right now that is not available to choose a green project. As firms like BlackRock create the products and the demand, supply should follow, making it cheaper and more efficient to finance green projects.</p>
<h4>And do you see a time when we will stop using the term ‘green’ because it will become ubiquitous?</h4>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> What I would love to see is that, whether you call it green or whether it just becomes a more ubiquitous term, that the green issuance will trade at a premium to non-green issuance, ie the market will pay more and issuers will finance more efficiently for green products than for non-green products. When we get to that point, it becomes the ultimate incentive for issuers to create these products.</p>
<h4>We hear a lot about how technology is revolutionising corporate treasury so would you say that it is enhancing your sustainability agenda?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> I don’t personally see, at the moment, technology playing a major part in our sustainability activities. Obviously using a treasury management system concentrates the activity and makes it more efficient, but that’s really driven by efficiency and how we want to operate.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> I agree that system integration can help – we have in our procurement policies a number of ESG KPIs that can be centrally managed.</p>
<h4>How is Bank of America using technology, in terms of driving your own sustainability agenda, and as a service for clients?</h4>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin: 0.5em 2em 0em 0;">
<img alt="Henrik Lang, Managing Director, Global Head of Liquidity GTS, Bank of America" height="225" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__henrik-lang__ttf-ldn-2019-110__200x225.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F3E58CFE233560C5032EBD7C064E95C7" title="Henrik Lang, Managing Director, Global Head of Liquidity GTS, Bank of America" width="200"/>
<figcaption>
<h6>Henrik Lang</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> We believe that technology does have a very important role in driving the sustainability agenda and are trying to look at different ways to innovate around this. An example of what I mean is the idea of ‘digital disbursements’. This allows corporates to make payments based on an email address. There are two very important sustainable aspects to this.</p>
<p>Because it is all electronic it replaces the need for anything paper-based, removing a lot of transportation and paper costs. Also, where we work with a number of US charities, we have found that in areas impacted by natural disasters, for example, by hurricanes, often the physical infrastructure is damaged; using digital disbursements helps get immediate aid to people. For us, it’s about challenging ourselves, using technology in innovative ways, helping drive the sustainability agenda.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote><p>The greatest impact for us on the broader economy and in wider society can be gained once we can work together with our clients and turn their treasury departments and businesses into sustainable and greener functions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Henrik Lang, Managing Director, Global Head of Liquidity GTS, Bank of America</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4>And how is technology being used within the asset management space in the context of sustainability?</h4>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> Our company is built around a single best in class risk analytics and order management platform, called Aladdin, which enables us to efficiently manage our own US$6trn in assets. Our approach is to fully integrate sustainability and ESG metrics into Aladdin so that we are able to operate at scale.</p>
<p>Anytime a portfolio manager purchases an asset in one of our green funds, it goes through the same filters as any other class, ensuring that we are being consistent with our investment philosophy and that non-green assets don’t end up in green funds securing their credibility.</p>
<h4>Let’s turn now to how this space might evolve over the next five years. How much further forward do you think your company’s approach to sustainability will be?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> We completed our conversation to all-green finance earlier this year; it was a major milestone for us. We have got our CSR targets too, so in five years’ time I would hope that we have met all of those. But that won’t be the end of the journey. We will need to define the next stage of the journey for the organisation, and from there continue to focus on the positive impact of sustainability.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> We started with financing and so all our financing going forward is green and sustainable. We are now turning our attention to our cash deposits, and in particular money market funds. It’s very early days in this market. There are probably only two or three companies that have suitable products available, and even explaining how these work is still difficult.</p>
<p>We’re also focusing on the ESG performance of our counterparties. They may have a great fund, but if the organisation is not committed, we’re not so interested. We’ll either replace them or engage them in dialogue. We know that it’s difficult in the very short-term investment space, where 80% of holdings are financial institutions, to create a product that is different from what exists already. But we are watching that space.</p>
<p>Generally, I think for all companies sustainability is quickly becoming central to their business. It’s not something on the side, it is essential to their strategy. Most of the business opportunities and most of the risks will come from this space and soon it will be second nature to everybody, treasury included.</p>
<h4>Are either of you working towards any other kind of sustainability agenda at the moment, with specific goals?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> Becoming an entirely green-financed company was our primary focus but in the longer-term maybe there are more products to consider as the banking market evolves, and as Renewi itself evolves. Hopefully we can participate in some of those developments.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> Corporates have traditionally been under-represented in bodies where frameworks and guidelines have been created but these will ultimately have to be implemented by corporates so it is vital that we have a voice. That’s why we are a group member of the Corporate Forum on Sustainable Finance, and we are very keen to share our experience and best practices with others at event such as this.</p>
<h4>As corporates, will you increasingly expect green credentials from your suppliers?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> I think that would be a logical extension. Obviously, it depends on the nature and scale of your organisation and the nature and scale of your suppliers. In our industry, we work with businesses of all sizes, and the requirements are going to be different for a ‘mom and pop’ business versus a massive global corporate.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> We have three main work contracts of around £2.6bn and they have to report on a quarterly basis on all of those commitments. We try as much as possible in our procurement policies to extend our commitments to other suppliers, but we have to be realistic.</p>
<h4>How do you see this space evolving over the next five years from a financial services perspective?</h4>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> Just based on what we have seen in the last few years, I think it is just going to be more front and centre for our clients. In August, more than 180 CEOs signed, as part of the business roundtable, a new statement making sustainability part of a common core strategy, with common goals that we are going to work towards in the next five years. This topic is not going away, it is just going to become part and parcel of our everyday life.</p>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> My hope, ambition and expectation is that in the coming years, as it relates to liquidity investment, sustainability goes from a niche strategy to the default choice for liquidity management. That might sound ambitious, but I think that there is a generational shift that is happening in the world, and certainly in corporate treasuries where the up-and-coming generation care passionately about these issues.</p>
<h4>What are the key sustainability initiatives that your organisations are working on for next year and beyond?</h4>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> I think we have managed to get to a point now where ESG in Bank of America is not just a group of experts sitting somewhere in New York. ESG principles are embedded in all our lines of business. Our product managers are thinking about the kind of products we should bring to market. We are, for example, looking at bank-deposit products which could align with ESG principles. We are looking at broadening our digital solutions, helping treasuries to become more sustainable.</p>
<p>We are also spending a lot of time on training our sales force and our coverage bankers, educating them on the importance of ESG, giving them the confidence to open up that discussion with their client base and adding another dimension to that relationship.</p>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> At BlackRock, our focus right now is on broadening and deepening our investor base and our product line-ups. We have been very encouraged by the market reception of our approach to sustainable cash investing. We will see where we go from here, based on investment demand, but we feel on the evidence so far, we are on the right track.</p>
<h4>As experienced practitioners, what advice would you offer to treasurers who are just getting started on a sustainability project?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> Just talking to people. You can hear from the other side of the table that this is a conversation that the banks are very happy to have. I think there are other treasurers who have experience, such as myself and Inês, who are happy to share that – and there is a growing body of that experience.</p>
<p>I would say to treasurers contemplating it, that as well as discussing it with your banks and your peers, also make a point of connecting internally if you are not already, with your teams responsible for managing CSR and sustainability. Do make sure that you understand these themes within your organisational context because it will help you explain it when you are having those conversations with the banks and the investment community.</p>
<p>More and more treasurers are interested and engaged, and they are curious as to my experience of sustainable finance, and how they can translate that into their own organisation. As we have said, each organisation will be different in its application, and they may be very different in their Purpose and Values, but that doesn’t mean that they can’t find the parts of the organisation where they can have a positive impact and find eligibility in the way that we have.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> Have a go! And I think have a go now whilst it is optional, because regulation will soon catch up. There are risks and opportunities involved, but I believe that one day this will become central to all corporate treasuries, finance being at the heart of all of companies.</p>
<p>As treasurers, we may not know everything about sustainability, but we can bring a lot to the table alongside our specialist internal partners. In fact, we bring a wealth of experience in communicating with investors and in reporting, and that is valuable to other areas of our organisations.</p>
<p>There is a lot of information out there to fill the gaps. As an example, A4S, the Accounting for Sustainability Project , published a very practical guide, with lots of case studies, earlier this year specifically for treasurers, explaining how to raise sustainable finance.</p>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> From a bank perspective, I agree with Adam, encouraging clients to speak with their financial providers, and also to challenge them because we need to be proactive in bringing these solutions to our corporate clients.</p>
<p>But I would also encourage treasurers to think as broadly as possible. For a number of years it has all been about green finance and green bonds. We’ve heard today that there are so many other possibilities, from how diverse their treasury department is, to what extent they incorporate green and sustainable principles into their investment policies or into their broader treasury policies. But also think about rating vendors and suppliers from a sustainability point of view, and even to what extent it is possible to eliminate paper from treasury.</p>
<figure class="portrait right" style="float:right;margin:0.5em 0em 0em 2em;">
<img alt="Tom Callahan, Head of Global Cash Management, BlackRock" height="225" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/2019-11-12-tt-00-ttf__tom-callahan__ttf-ldn-2019-081__200x225.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=D540F9DD32B52F35D771CCA09D46645D" title="Tom Callahan, Head of Global Cash Management, BlackRock" width="200"/>
<figcaption>
<h6>Tom Callahan</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> I agree with what everyone else has said, but perhaps the most important advice that I would give to corporate treasurers is to understand the power that they have. This is a new and evolving market. It may not seem so important in terms of sustainability for the treasurer to think about where they allocate their cash, but the power that they exercise through their investments will change the products that the asset management brings to market. And those products will change issuer behaviour, and issuer behaviour will have a direct impact on green and sustainable products. Treasurers should never underestimate the upstream impact that they have at this very early stage of this market in terms of how this market will evolve. It is incredibly powerful. They should appreciate that power and exercise it!</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote><p>My hope, ambition and expectation is that in the coming years, as it relates to liquidity investment, sustainability goes from a niche strategy to the default choice for liquidity management.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Tom Callahan, Head of Global Cash Management, BlackRock</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4>Sustainability has a naturally strong human element so, to finish, I wanted to ask you all if there was a moment for you personally when you knew it was something on which you needed to focus your attention?</h4>
<p><strong>Adam Richford, Renewi:</strong> For me certainly there was less of a focus on sustainability before being part of Renewi. But it particularly became front and centre as we went through a merger and created a new organisation and got to re-define our sustainability purpose as an organisation. The personal resonance that this has for me became very obvious and apparent as well, and that has been a driving force to want to push the agenda within the organisation.</p>
<p><strong>Inês Faden da Silva, Tideway:</strong> I previously worked in banking and in the emerging markets energy sector. In 2003, a small group of banks, including mine, launched the Equator Principles, a risk management framework to help banks assess and manage environmental and social risk in project finance, based on IFC’s Safeguard Policies from 1998. Because of that, I became very much aware of critical environmental and social aspects affecting the projects on which I was advising.</p>
<p>But it was only since joining Tideway, a company created to address a major sustainability issue – and where the whole company is enthused by what we are doing – that I really knew I had to do something, to the point where I decided to study sustainable business whilst working.</p>
<p><strong>Henrik Lang, Bank of America:</strong> For me, it all started with volunteering, early on in my life. Later, when I had a family, I realised just how important sustainability is. At Bank of America, culturally, it is just ingrained within the organisation. Everybody is aligned with our sustainability cause and works together as a team. Importantly, we enjoy talking about these topics. ESG discussions are very personal so it becomes interesting and easy for everybody to engage.</p>
<p><strong>Tom Callahan, BlackRock:</strong> Engaging with our clients around sustainable cash investing has been personally transformative in terms of how I think about this and how I live my life.</p>
<p>The world is changing, and so are our clients. BlackRock holds charity events throughout the year and our beach clean-ups have quickly become the most popular and over-subscribed.</p>
<h4>Thank you all very much for taking part.</h4>
<p id="video" style="text-align:center;">
<img alt="Renewi logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/renewi-logo-2018-75x55.png?la=en&amp;hash=97705B300A371EF74660ABD37E8BC3D5" style="margin-right:3em;" title="Renewi" width="75">
<img alt="Bank of America logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/bank-of-america-2020.svg?la=en&amp;hash=28821131E4FA58414B38435B112B6A03" style="margin-right:3em;" title="Bank of America" width="160">
<img alt="BlackRock logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/blackrock-logo-2019__120x17.png?la=en&amp;hash=98A0797FE22C19D5217D4274AECB8FF4" style="margin-right:3em;" title="BlackRock" width="120">
<img alt="Tideway logo" class="logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/tideway-logo-2019-70x79.png?la=en&amp;hash=BCA87C646A8C3FF8CFBA36D3AB4CCC59" style="margin-right:3em;" title="Tideway" width="70">
</img></img></img></img></p></div>
</div>
<div class="video-panel v-spacing--bottom" data-component="video-panel" data-height="" data-videourl="https://vimeo.com/516712557" data-width="">
<div class="video-panel__item">
<a class="video-panel__link" href="#video-player">
<img src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-practice/sustainability/tt-2019-09-25__talking-sustainable-treasury-forum__video-cover.jpg"/>
<span class="video-panel--overlay">
<span class="icon-play">Watch video</span>
</span>
</a>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Business without borders: treasury in the digital age - Barclays supplement]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 0001 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h3>Crossing borders together</h3>
<p>We are living through a period of unprecedented change driven, primarily, by the continual advancement of technology. The biggest impact has undoubtedly come from the proliferation of internet access, which has given rise to the hyper-connected world that we live in today. For businesses, this has created a tremendous opportunity to tap into a bigger consumer base and find new and substantial pockets of growth by selling goods online. Today, with the power of the internet, any business can be a global business.</p><br/><a class="btn btn-danger" href="http://treasurytoday.com/barclays-supplement-2017-business-without-borders.html" target="_blank">Free PDF</a>
<div class="css-layout-v2">
<img alt="Barclays" class="logo right" height="20" src="/i/logo/barclays-logo-2012-120x20.png" width="120"/>
<h3>Crossing borders together</h3>
<p>We are living through a period of unprecedented change driven, primarily, by the continual advancement of technology. The biggest impact has undoubtedly come from the proliferation of internet access, which has given rise to the hyper-connected world that we live in today. For businesses, this has created a tremendous opportunity to tap into a bigger consumer base and find new and substantial pockets of growth by selling goods online. Today, with the power of the internet, any business can be a global business.</p>
<p>This fact has made the business landscape more competitive than ever. It is no longer enough to have quality goods and competitive prices. To win in today’s world, businesses must operate globally but in a local way, offering a seamless user experience customised for their local market. They must also act with speed, providing near real-time delivery of goods and services.</p>
<p>To facilitate these market demands, regulators are responding by upgrading infrastructures to support real-time commerce. This is perhaps most evident in the payments space where ‘instant payments’ systems are becoming ubiquitous. These payment systems are creating a host of opportunities for banks and fintech players (facilitated by open banking regulation such as PSD2). They are revolutionising payment processes for corporates and their customers. It is a revolution that might signal the end of the road for bulk and batch processing.</p>
<p>In many ways, the journey is just beginning. Developments such as open banking and Faster Payments may be seen as merely laying the foundations for the second wave of digitisation. This is where technologies such as blockchain, the Internet of Things, APIs and Artificial Intelligence will completely redefine how businesses operate, creating many new growth opportunities.</p>
<p>We at Barclays are excited by the potential of these technologies and the way they can revolutionise banking services and the role of banks in providing access to finance. We are leading the way, innovating internally, supporting fintechs and working with the entire financial community, as an enabler, aggregator and partner. We are building ground-breaking solutions that will help support our clients as they continue to evolve in this brave new world.</p>
<p>The opportunities created by technology are bountiful but it would be remiss to overlook the ongoing geopolitical flux. The recent backlash against globalisation, which arguably manifested itself in Brexit and the election of President Donald Trump, has made it harder for some businesses to enter certain markets. There are also ever-present risks, such as cyber threats, that corporates should never take lightly. Elsewhere, regulation will continue to both support and prohibit corporate activity.</p>
<p>When all is considered, there is a lot for corporate treasury professionals to take in as they help guide their organisations through all these changes. Throughout the pages of this supplement, our experts provide insight into these topics, highlighting the impact on your business and offering potential solutions.</p>
<p>At Barclays, we pride ourselves on over 325 years of supporting our clients with their banking needs, across cash, trade, lending and foreign exchange, in both good and bad times. It is our aim to continue to be a thoughtful and reliable partner, thinking ‘beyond the technology’ and working with our clients and partners to help us all redefine the way we do business.</p>
<p><a href="http://treasurytoday.com/barclays-supplement-2017-business-without-borders.html" target="_blank">Download your FREE report to business without borders</a></p>
</div>
<style type="text/css">
	#Supplement .btn.btn-danger
		{
			background: #ca140a none repeat scroll 0 center;
			border: 0 none;
			border-radius: 0;
			box-shadow: none;
			color: #fff;
			display: block !important;
			font-family: Arial&#44;"Helvetica Neue"&#44;Helvetica&#44;sans-serif;
			font-size: 18px;
			font-weight: normal;
			left: 0;
			line-height: 1.4em;
			margin-top: 1.4em;
			position: absolute;
			text-shadow: none;
			top: 198px;
			width: 121px;
		}
	#master_2_left_1_addToBasket_linkAdd
		{
			display: block;
			height: 34px;
			margin-top: 4em;
			width: 145px;
		}
	#previousEditionsList&#44;
	#publication-contents&#44;
	#master_2_left_1_addToBasket_NoPriceContactUsButton
		{
			display: none;
		}
</style></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[21st century treasury: risk and reward in the digital age]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 0001 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h3>Understanding the drivers of change</h3>
<p>Technology and digitisation is having a profound impact on all of our lives. We now live in a world interconnected by bits and bytes, and one in which personal handheld devices – often boasting more computing power than NASA had for the Apollo missions – now outnumber people.</p>
<br/><a class="btn btn-danger" href="http://treasurytoday.com/barclays-understanding-the-drivers-of-change.html" target="_blank">Free PDF</a>
<div class="css-layout-v2">
<img alt="Barclays" class="logo right" height="20" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/barclays-logo-2012-120x20.png" width="120"/>
<h2>Understanding the drivers of change</h2>
<p>Technology and digitisation is having a profound impact on all of our lives. We now live in a world interconnected by bits and bytes, and one in which personal handheld devices – often boasting more computing power than NASA had for the Apollo missions – now outnumber people.</p>
<p>This connectivity is also driving big changes in the global business landscape. With the ability to connect instantly with people around the world, businesses have opportunities to find new customers, move into new geographies, and tap new areas of growth. For both individuals and businesses, technology is making what was once unimaginable, possible.</p>
<p>Have we already seen most of the benefits digital technologies can offer? At Barclays we believe we have just scratched the surface.</p>
<p>In the rather staid area of credit underwriting, for instance, the process has remained unchanged for an age. But Artificial Intelligence and machine learning engines have the power to fundamentally change this by allowing banks to harvest an incredible amount of data on a corporate in real-time, enabling banks to more effectively work with their clients to adjust credit limits and even take on data as a form of collateral.</p>
<p>Take blockchain by way of another example. There are already many ideas around how this nascent technology could be applied to cash and trade services. Arguably, though, what is really exciting about this technology is how it is driving people to think out of the box when it comes to developing solutions.</p>
<p>Trade finance, in particular, has the potential to be greatly improved through digitisation and technology. Indeed, there are already a variety of solutions in the market that enable corporates and banks to remove the reams of paper traditionally required for trade finance transactions. Additionally, Barclays is also looking at ways to ensure that these benefits permeate right through the supply chain, working with organisations such as the UK government’s UK Export Finance to help build a digital platform that will help UK exports expand and grow. In light of the recent Brexit vote, these initiatives will arguably become ever more important.</p>
<p>There is little doubt that technology represents a great opportunity for corporates to drive efficiencies across all areas of their businesses. But treasurers also need to be conscious of the fact that the proliferation of technology has also exposed businesses to a range of new risks. Cybercrime is fast becoming the curse of the digital age and a risk that all businesses must face with eyes wide-open. The threat is not insurmountable though. Businesses should instead look to ensure that cyber-security is part of their business and product strategy, transforming it into a business enabler.</p>
<p>Throughout this supplement we explore these issues, while offering insights into what each development may mean for your business. Barclays strives to be at the forefront of digitisation in transaction banking, not only by delivering digital solutions to our clients, but also supporting them with their own digital transformations and forging deep relationships, as we navigate the evolving technology landscape together.</p>
<p><a href="http://treasurytoday.com/barclays-understanding-the-drivers-of-change.html" target="_blank">Download your FREE report to risk and reward in a digital age</a></p>
</div>
<style type="text/css">
	#Supplement .btn.btn-danger
		{
			background: #ca140a none repeat scroll 0 center;
			border: 0 none;
			border-radius: 0;
			box-shadow: none;
			color: #fff;
			display: block !important;
			font-family: Arial&#44;"Helvetica Neue"&#44;Helvetica&#44;sans-serif;
			font-size: 18px;
			font-weight: normal;
			left: 0;
			line-height: 1.4em;
			margin-top: 1.4em;
			position: absolute;
			text-shadow: none;
			top: 198px;
			width: 121px;
		}
	#master_2_left_1_addToBasket_linkAdd
		{
			display: block;
			height: 34px;
			margin-top: 4em;
			width: 145px;
		}
	#previousEditionsList&#44;
	#publication-contents&#44;
	#master_2_left_1_addToBasket_NoPriceContactUsButton
		{
			display: none;
		}
</style></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Your gateway to SIBOS 2015]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 0001 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The first SIBOS event was hosted by SWIFT in 1978 in Brussels, five years after the society was founded. There were just 300 participants. In 2012, the last time the conference was held in Asia, over 6,000 delegates travelled to Osaka in Japan. Back in Asia this year, Singapore is a perfect venue for the conference as the country celebrates 50 years of independence.</p>
<br/>
<p><a class="button-block button--red-stroke" href="mailto:subscriberservices@treasurytoday.com?subject=Your gateway to Sibos 2015&amp;body=Please send me a PDF copy of 'Your gateway to Sibos 2015' handbook">Request PDF</a></p>
<h3><br/>Introduction</h3>
<section class="logos boxed">
<h4 style="font-size:18px;margin-bottom:2em;color:#173E6D;">Sponsors</h4>
<a href="https://www.anz.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><img alt="ANZ" class="logo" height="30" src="/i/logo/anz-logo-2015-93x30.png" width="93"/></a>
<a href="http://www.baml.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><img alt="Bank of America Merrill Lynch" class="logo" height="33" src="/i/logo/bank-of-america-merrill-lynch-blue-2014-130x33.png" width="130"/></a>
<a href="http://www.swift.com/corporates" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><img alt="SWIFT" class="logo" height="50" src="/i/logo/swift-logo-2015-50x50.png" width="50"/></a>
</section>
<p>The first SIBOS event was hosted by SWIFT in 1978 in Brussels, five years after the society was founded. There were just 300 participants. In 2012, the last time the conference was held in Asia, over 6,000 delegates travelled to Osaka in Japan. Back in Asia this year, Singapore is a perfect venue for the conference as the country celebrates 50 years of independence.</p>
<p>Much has happened in that time and Singapore has been rated by the World Bank as the easiest place in the world to do business; an impressive accolade indeed. That theme of making it easier to transact transcends all of the streams at this year’s SIBOS event as banks, vendors and corporates come together to discuss ways to do exactly that.</p>
<p>Against this backdrop, the Treasury Today Group’s SIBOS supplement analyses five key agenda items for corporates and the wider banking community to be thinking about throughout the conference season and into 2016, namely:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>SWIFT for Corporates: increasing accessibility</h5>
<p>SWIFT has been handling financial messaging since 1977 yet it took another 24 years to announce the availability of corporate access. Find out about the various access options now available.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Disruptive banking technologies and new entrants</h5>
<p>We are hearing much about FinTech but what does it all mean in practice for treasurers? Is the banking industry as we know it being reshaped by technology, or is it more a case of evolution than revolution?</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Navigating the APAC payments market</h5>
<p>Do you know your FAST from your IMPS in the payments space? How about NPP in Australia and CIPS in China? Turn to page 24 to discover more.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Innovations in trade</h5>
<br/>
<p>Paper documentation has been the mainstay in the trade space for a very long time. But in recent years, the conversion to digital formats of some trade elements has gradually taken place, so is paper really on its way out?</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>RMB developments</h5>
<p>As the Chinese authorities take bigger and bigger steps to internationalise the renminbi, we ask: where next for the redback? And what do developments in this space really mean for corporates trading in and with China, against a backdrop of stock market volatility?</p>
<p> </p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This year’s conference again included a Corporate Forum on 14<sup>th</sup>-15<sup>th</sup> October entitled ‘Shaping the future of treasury and trade’ and it picked up on many of the above themes, as well as looking at emerging treasury models and centralisation practices in Asia – a session moderated by Treasury Today Group’s Managing Director, Richard Parkinson.</p>
<style type="text/css">
    a#master_2_left_1_addToBasket_NoPriceContactUsButton&amp;#44;
    .flagged
    {
    display:none;
    }
    #Handbook #previousEditionsList
    {
    display: none;
    }
</style></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Supplements]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Technology and innovation: redefining the rules of treasury]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 0001 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h3>Seizing the digital advantage</h3>
<p>Technology is changing the way we live, the way we communicate, and the way we do business. In fact, technological innovation is changing the world as we know it and at an extremely rapid pace. Year-on-year growth in the 12 months from January 2014 saw the world population increase by 1.6%, yet over the same period, the number of active internet users soared by 21%, whilst social media accounts accessed by mobile devices increased by 23%.</p><br/><a class="btn embed-page" href="http://treasurytoday.com/barclays-technology-and-innovation.html" target="_blank">Free PDF</a>
<div class="css-layout-v2">
<img alt="Barclays" class="logo right" height="20" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/barclays-logo-2012-120x20.png" width="120"/>
<h2>Foreword</h2>
<h3>Seizing the digital advantage</h3>
<p>Technology is changing the way we live, the way we communicate, and the way we do business. In fact, technological innovation is changing the world as we know it and at an extremely rapid pace. Year-on-year growth in the 12 months from January 2014 saw the world population increase by 1.6%, yet over the same period, the number of active internet users soared by 21%, whilst social media accounts accessed by mobile devices increased by 23%<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>For companies in all sectors, the impact of this increasingly digital operating environment is both significant and exciting. And it’s not just about embracing mobile payments and collections, or further automating day-to-day treasury tasks – the impact runs much deeper. Take trade, for instance; the very nature of supply chains is changing as a result of technology and innovation.</p>
<p>As an example, 3D printing is on the cusp of becoming a disruptive and potentially transformative technology, notably in the manufacturing space. Historically, supply chains have revolved around logistics – often moving goods half way round the world – and warehousing. Today, manufacturers can use 3D printers wherever they choose, rather than being tied to low-cost manufacturing locations in the emerging markets.</p>
<p>This could change the global supply chain quite dramatically and forward-thinking businesses are already reviewing their supply chains with a view to re-shoring. With manufacturers able to print certain components on demand, inventory levels and warehousing requirements should also be able to be reduced. Given these cost efficiency opportunities, developments such as 3D printing could also significantly alter corporates’ working capital and supply chain finance (SCF) requirements.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, the buyer-seller relationship is steadily evolving, with cloud technology providing new collaborative opportunities. These range from creating and managing extensive networks of supplier relationships more effectively via a shared cloud portal, to sharing data as a means to improve processes such as stock control, inventory management, forecasting and replenishment – and secure pricing and working capital benefits.</p>
<p>So, with digital innovation and evolution comes significant opportunity. But there are also associated operational, reputational and financial risks which corporates must plan for too – whether that be cybersecurity or the risk of losing competitive advantage by continuing to use outdated technology.</p>
<p>Barclays recognises this and is at the forefront of the ongoing journey of innovation and development. This supplement provides an overview of some of the latest trends and innovations in the treasury space, and outlines how we can work with companies to make the most of the digital opportunities available, whilst managing related risks along the journey. We look forward to the exciting times ahead!</p>
<div class="footnotes" style="font-size:10px;">
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="http://wearesocial.net/blog/2015/01/digital-social-mobile-worldwide-2015/" target="_blank">http://wearesocial.net/blog/2015/01/digital-social-mobile-worldwide-2015/</a> <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<style type="text/css">
	#Supplement .btn.embed-page
		{
			background: #ca140a none repeat scroll 0 center;
			border: 0 none;
			border-radius: 0;
			box-shadow: none;
			color: #fff;
			display: block !important;
			font-family: Arial&#44;"Helvetica Neue"&#44;Helvetica&#44;sans-serif;
			font-size: 18px;
			font-weight: normal;
			left: 0;
			line-height: 1.4em;
			margin-top: 1.4em;
			position: absolute;
			text-shadow: none;
			top: 198px;
			width: 121px;
		}
	#master_2_left_1_addToBasket_linkAdd
		{
			display: block;
			height: 34px;
			margin-top: 4em;
			width: 145px;
		}
	#Supplement #previousEditionsList&#44;
	#Supplement #publication-contents
		{
			display: none;
		}
	#Supplement #publication-contents
		{
			display:none;
		}
</style></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
</data>
