<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury professionals sitting tight despite hirer demand]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2022 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=1DDF54669718F8427ED6337E63A40EC1]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>High job vacancy levels across many sectors are reflected in the treasury recruitment sector, where corporates are finding it challenging to fill senior finance roles.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=99E8833C293796C18CC2F02DEA1A46DB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3FB5E85B5CEDE369E86085388B47CD6E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8D625C90A479B1B3587496A100F25295"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9AB867E3658E253E20AF05CD5E09440C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AF219529F765AACE3BB3C6220C1FBEB3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Magnet attracting metal figures" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1DDF54669718F8427ED6337E63A40EC1" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2022-01-02-tt-00-tt__high-angle-view-magnet-attracting-traffic-694643950__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1DDF54669718F8427ED6337E63A40EC1"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>The number of unfilled jobs continues to rise in countries recovering from the worst effects of the pandemic. UK vacancies reached a record high in November, the number of available positions in Japan was at its highest level of the year in October, and even in the US – where job creation figures were below expectations in November – demand remains high for finance professionals. In this context it is hardly surprising that companies are facing considerable challenges in finding the right people for senior roles such as chief financial officer, treasurer or financial director.</p>
<p>At the end of the summer the market was full of vacancies and senior finance leaders were confident about moving jobs. However, as summer passed to autumn potential candidates were thin on the ground – those who had been ‘waiting out’ the pandemic before they moved had done what they needed to and were now settled in new roles according to Refreshing’s Director, Charlie Jones. “Our work now is much more about headhunting and working hard to draw candidates from existing roles,” he says. “Responses to job ads are lower and we expect this to reduce further before the end of the year.”</p>
<p>Jones says it is not unusual for the best candidates to be considering three or more offers at a time. “There is huge competition to find the most talented people and companies who don’t work quickly and carefully consider the packages they are offering will lose out every time,” he adds. “Clients who have moved through the worst of the pandemic are ready to hire but until confidence returns and senior finance leaders feel happy enough to leave one stable job for another there will be an imbalance in the market.”</p>
<p>Bobby Lane, CEO of professional services consultancy Factotum, reckons it is more difficult than ever to find and attract the right people for senior roles as a result of a trend that was evident even before the pandemic. “The direction of the market pre-Covid was for chief financial officers and finance directors looking to take on a broader commercial role within a business rather than retaining a pure financial focus,” he says. “This means that many of those looking to change jobs are not looking to stay as a CFO or finance director but move into chief executive or managing director positions.”</p>
<p>Coupled with people taking time to reassess their personal goals and the way that they were working during lockdown, Lane says this has led to a contraction in the talent pool. “There are still people out there, but it is harder to find them and get them through the door,” he adds. “Existing employers are aware of the challenges of finding replacements so they are doing all they can to ensure that senior people do not leave, from increasing their salaries and loyalty bonuses to changing working conditions or job roles. Even if someone says ‘yes’ to you, nothing is guaranteed until they actually walk through the door on day one.”</p>
<p>According to Lane, the explosion of start-ups in the technology sector in particular has significantly increased the number of businesses looking for senior team members with financial experience. “There are technical candidates and people with commercial acumen in the market, but finding an all-rounder is not that easy,” he says. “There are suitable candidates available for employers who are clear about the role they are offering and realistic about what they are looking for, but the opportunity to work with a technology start up or fast-growing business has been more attractive than entering the profession and training over the last decade.”</p>
<p>Emma Ireland, recruitment consultant at Ten Percent Financial, agrees that there are fewer applicants for vacant roles, although she says mid-level positons have proved harder to fill than more senior roles since the end of lockdown. “We see fewer suitable candidates for roles than pre-lockdown in terms of both external applications and expressions of interest from candidates already registered with us,” she explains. “This is creating a shortage within the sector and has seen firms struggle to fill the roles they are recruiting for.”</p>
<p>Rej Abraham, Managing Director of ABPM, strikes a rather more positive note, suggesting that while potential candidates are fully aware of their value and reluctant to move unless the proposition is commercially appealing, merger and acquisition activity has seen some senior finance leaders enter the job market. On the topic of flexible working, he reckons the majority of CFOs/finance directors still anticipate spending most if not all of their time in the office while accepting that their teams don’t necessarily need to do the same. “The e-commerce, healthcare, logistics, homewares, construction and IT services and technology sectors have been notably active and there is a bias for recruiting from similar sectors,” says Abraham. “Competition is particularly noticeable where organisations are competing for finance professionals from their own sector.”</p>
<p>With a reduction in candidate numbers there is always going to be pressure on companies to offer as much as they can in terms of salary and improved working conditions. Unlike Abraham, Jones says candidates now assume that finance roles will allow for working from home at least two or three days a week and that any company demanding more time in the office than this is at a huge disadvantage.</p>
<p>“Salaries at newly qualified levels are up by 10% or more in the past six months,” he adds. “Those at the most senior levels have also seen their salaries rise, but to attract the best people companies are having to think more about the full package – bonuses and equity are less of a ‘nice to have’ than they were.”</p>
<p>Ireland also refers to increased demand for remote working roles, stating that for many this is now a non-negotiable factor. “For some, concerns about the pandemic are the reason stated for this, while for others it is a question of work-life balance,” she explains. “In many cases candidates are prepared to accept a lower salary if remote working is offered. But while working from home has become more common over the past two years some firms are still resistant to the idea, which can make recruiting more of a challenge.”</p>
<p>Lane agrees that the pandemic has prompted a reassessment of career objectives for many senior finance professionals. “The global experiment in home working gave them a real insight into what their work-life balance could look like,” he says. “I have spoken with a number of senior finance professionals who have subsequently decided that they would take lower paid roles in order to be able to work from home more often and not face the daily commute.”</p>
<p>Lane echoes Ireland’s observation that employers that do not offer flexibility are significantly reducing their chances of attracting the best talent. To make their task even harder, he says companies may also have to accept the need to pay higher salaries to tempt the right people away from their existing employers. Looking further ahead, Lane reckons the disparity between supply and demand for candidates with both technical and commercial skills will ease over the course of this decade.</p>
<p>“In recent years there has been a resurgence in people entering the profession and training to be a finance professional, so there will be a new wave of commercially minded, well-rounded finance professionals for the future,” he concludes. “However, this does not help the current position so employers have to recognise the challenges that they will face as post-lockdown, candidates may be happy to stay where they are or look for a total change of direction.”</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Case study</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/aceleron-logo-horizontal-colour__609x138.png?la=en&amp;hash=92E9DCA076C011E0B80E3B0A23818A09"><img alt="Aceleron logo" height="" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/aceleron-logo-horizontal-colour__609x138.png?la=en&amp;hash=92E9DCA076C011E0B80E3B0A23818A09" title="Aceleron logo" width="150"/></a></p>
<p>One of the obvious challenges in recruiting staff during a pandemic is meeting potential candidates in person rather than virtually.</p>
<p>“Fortunately the restrictions had been eased by the time we started the process so we were able to see quite a few people in person, but that might not be possible in the coming months,” says Amrit Chandan, CEO of clean tech company Aceleron, which recently recruited its first CFO through ABPM. “It is also important that the candidates are comfortable meeting this way.”</p>
<p>Because of the early stage nature of the business, Chandan was looking for someone with experience of venture fundraising as well as operational experience. “We promote a flexible working culture but for such a senior role it is vital that there is a willingness to get stuck in and do what is needed, including travel because some meetings are too important to do online,” he adds.</p>
<p>Chandan says he receives a large number of requests to connect on LinkedIn from recruiters looking to place people in the company on an ongoing basis, which he describes as “tiresome” when he is not looking to fill a specific role. The recruitment process for the CFO role started at the end of the summer and the chosen candidate was signed up in the second week of December. “We spoke to around a dozen people and my priority was to ascertain how they might fit into the business and whether they inspired confidence that they could do want I – and the business – need them to do,” explains Chandan. “Some of those we met had the potential to grow into the role, but just didn’t have the skills and experience we require right now.”</p>
<p>The company has a strategy of paying the market rate for new recruits, although Chandan says anyone looking primarily at the remuneration would not have been seriously considered. “For such a senior role we encourage working in person at least initially while the person is learning the ropes, but beyond that we enable staff to work around school runs and important life events,” he adds.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Case study</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/etz-logo-2022.png?la=en&amp;hash=D628F19278663B95B83AE97C36691CF9"><img alt="ETZ logo" height="" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/etz-logo-2022.png?la=en&amp;hash=D628F19278663B95B83AE97C36691CF9" title="ETZ logo" width="100"/></a></p>
<p>According to Nick Woodward, Group CEO of recruitment software vendor ETZ Group – which took on an executive financial director/CFO earlier this year – the biggest challenge in the recruitment process continues to be finding people with integrity. “We have talked to a lot of people who claimed to have certain skills and experience that they simply didn’t have,” he says. “Then you try to find candidates with real world business experience, people who have done something entrepreneurial or sales focused – and because the UK economy has become dominated by the service sector the pipeline of this type of candidate is drying up.”</p>
<p>The company’s latest recruit was found after a search that lasted around three weeks and was assisted by Ten Percent Financial. “We didn’t have as many options as we expected, although the candidates were all good quality,” says Woodward. “In terms of salary and working conditions, candidates want to be able to work from home – it is very hard to attract people if you make them come to an office when the work can be done equally well remotely.”</p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Rising Stars Roundtable]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Aug 2021 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=9B434AFD12F80E8115000ED2BFA9A3AD]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>The Adam Smith Awards is the industry benchmark for excellence in treasury. Every year phenomenal teams and individuals are recognised within the programme. We are now leveraging talent from the various years of the Adam Smith Awards global programme and bringing them together for focused roundtables around their winning categories and thematics. The first in our alumni series focused on our rising stars from across the world, who speak about their career journeys and aspirations.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4C9A70533A7D174348EB04AA4A967976"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0694FAFF7655AC8AE60592048D43436E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F4A9E257CF1AFB59CF923EAA528EB421"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=868A763979A6615126BF9EBA0B99EE75"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DC85FC15F7C45FB320F8BE4444C6E36A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Screenshot from the Rising Star Roundtable video" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9B434AFD12F80E8115000ED2BFA9A3AD" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2021-08-02-tt-00-asa__rising-stars-roundtable__1920x1080.png?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9B434AFD12F80E8115000ED2BFA9A3AD"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p style="margin-bottom:2em;"><a class="button--red-stroke" href="#video">Watch video</a></p>
<p>The Rising Star award is one of our individual awards and is a special recognition of those who are early on or new to their career in treasury and who are making real strides and an impression on the industry as a whole. Previous winners have gone on to enjoy tremendous careers with a variety of different paths taken. We were lucky enough to be joined in April for our Rising Stars Roundtable by:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Adam Smith Awards 2020 Rising Star, Tian Song of Baker Hughes</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Adam Smith Awards Asia 2020 Rising Star, Pulat Yunusmetov of Danone</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Adam Smith Awards 2019 winner Gino Gude of Honeywell</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Adam Smith Awards Asia 2019 winner, Jason Weiguang Han, ex treasury at General Electric who has now moved to  a Banking, Finance and Fintech Industry career consultant role at Nanyang Technological University, Singapore.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Gino Gude joined the conversation having been recently promoted from Senior Treasury Analyst to Treasury Manager at Honeywell. Pulat Yunusmetov is Regional Treasury Manager for Danone in ASAPME &amp; GC. Tian Song is leading Strategic Treasury Projects at Baker Hughes in London and Jason Han, who has 15 years in the industry working across corporates and banks and who was most recently at Michelin and General Electric before moving across to a role at Nanyang Technological University.</p>
<p>Sophie Jackson, Treasury Today Group’s Publisher &amp; Head of Strategic Content, was delighted to moderate our discussion on the day.   The conversation focused firstly on what winning a Rising Star award means, why recognising talent is important, the value of mentoring and coaching and the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic for the rising stars and their organisations.</p>
<p>When asked what had been helpful for his development, Pulat shared the following, “Support from seniors is so important. Senior management have supported projects of automation and digitisation. Mentorship is also quite important to recognise the talent within the company. Winning the award helped even just internally. This is how our higher management in Danone can assess the success through the awards.”</p>
<p>Tian shared some of her insights around talent recognition, “Each company’s internal rewarding programmes form an important part of talent recognition. It helps to boost near-term career development and incentive talents to work harder. The Rising Star award offers an external perspective, which helps us to build brand and obtain recognition from the industry. It’s a great scheme to support longer term career development in the treasury space.”</p>
<p>Gino shared his take on the importance of the award for him, “When I joined Honeywell, Marie-Astrid Dubois and Séverine Le Blévennec and the team were very committed to winning awards and to being able to showcase our successes to the US. From my perspective, applying for an award and winning motivates me to work harder. On a daily basis you don’t always get recognition or thanks, but when they see globally that you are being recognised that matters.”</p>
<p>Jason Han spoke about mentorship and senior inspirations that have helped him. “I have been invited to  university events in Singapore. The industry partners and friends are so willing to share. There is such a lot of industry support for mentorship and nurturing talent in APAC and in the treasury industry.”</p>
<p>On the importance of being part of a broader treasury community, Jason shared the following, “‘In terms of community support we have one basket that would be treasury. Treasury professionals getting together. Then there is the basket of banking, fintechs and start-ups. Both communities are happy to share information and support. It’s important to be connected to different communities now. In my role, I hope to bring across that passion for finance and treasury to the student community and connect that with the other communities to support.”</p>
<p>When it comes to their plans for the future, within the next five years Pulat would like to move into commercial finance. That is his mid- to long-term plan but in the short term “there is so much to be done within treasury. The skillset that treasury offers is immense, cash is king and treasury rules that!’ As Gino says of the skillsets developed and the support offered within treasury, “Treasury is no longer such a niche industry. In France there are now three universities offering a Masters in Treasury. I was a member of the French ACT and they are pretty big. If you reach out to other treasurers and ask them how they solved certain problems they will normally help. The industry is normally not secretive.”</p>
<p>Tian spoke of the beginning of her career at General Electric within its finance graduate programme, doing rotations. This is where she started in treasury with the GE China Treasury team. After two years on the graduate programme and moving to GE’s executive development programme, Tian became part of the global GE corporation, helping the company to go through its finance transformation. “This allowed me to learn different elements of treasury, both from a country level in China and at the GE corporate level, to understand how treasury is connected to broader finance processes and business operations. Treasury was the place I wanted to go and then I joined Baker Hughes as it separated from GE and set up its own standalone treasury team.”</p>
<p>Overall, beyond their technical skills, as Pulat says “We should not forget our soft skills and on developing them, focusing on leadership and storytelling. These skills should be being developed by any professional that wants to succeed.” Pulat then added, “As Gino and Tian have both touched on, a lot of times you learn from the different stakeholders that you work with and your bankers, accountants and controllers, and by taking more responsibilities outside of your job description you can be exposed to a range of skills.”</p>
<p>The buzzwords of the moment for our attendees were ESG, understanding green bonds and green products. The second were diversity, equity and inclusion and the efforts that companies are putting in. As Gino said, “I hope this is not just because this is fashionable. Now at Honeywell we have a working group and when we open a new position, we have to have a diverse slate of candidates and of interviewers.”</p>
<p id="video">Focusing on issues that our Rising Stars found inspiring, and exploring things that they are passionate about, were clear trends. We look forward to seeing where they go next!</p></div>
</div>
<div class="video-panel v-spacing--bottom" data-component="video-panel" data-height="" data-videourl="https://vimeo.com/582043462" data-width="">
<div class="video-panel__item">
<a class="video-panel__link" href="#video-player">
<img src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/tt-2021-08-02__asa-asaa-rising-star-roundtable__video-cover.png">
<span class="video-panel--overlay">
<span class="icon-play">Watch video</span>
</span>
</img></a>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Education for all]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=D7AD664DE317028DB9C41296D5591339]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C207A63CC6345B70F5776F697DD9DC72"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=06E10E1596F4DE51EE29C19489CDEC96"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=43C3747114BA0E3B1C54A2BD45C5111D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=60B708BA5A67936B44E97DBFF6FBDE33"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=47D5383F5B802A3145C45E2D6E25DDB0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Exam room with tables and chairs" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D7AD664DE317028DB9C41296D5591339" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa__school-empty-cold-exam-class-room-779279428__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D7AD664DE317028DB9C41296D5591339"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue's question</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“What are the benefits of taking professional treasury exams?”</em></p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Alessandra Mogorovich, FCT, Head of Accounts Payable, YOOX NET-A-PORTER GROUP" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa-act-alessandra-mogorovich__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=58EA1B987B368E62C314DD7BCA0AA8F5" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Alessandra Mogorovich</h3>
<h5 class="title">FCT, Head of Accounts Payable</h5>
<h5 class="org">YOOX NET-A-PORTER GROUP</h5>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>Amongst finance departments, treasury professionals play a critical role that affects the financial health of any organisation.</p>
<p>Since the start of my career, by joining a treasury department, I’ve constantly felt that the team always wanted (and needed) to be one step ahead, not only by understanding and anticipating trends in the financial markets, but also in following the developments of a profession that is constantly evolving.</p>
<p>Even though I had graduated from a business school, I felt the need for a solid technical foundation for the skills that I was applying in my daily job. Through the Association of Corporate Treasurers (ACT) Diploma in Treasury Management (AMCT), achieved in 2015, I’ve gained a 360-degree technical knowledge on the five areas of treasury and the access to up-to-date treasury resources has supported the shift of my focus slowly away from operations towards improving processes, with a positive impact on the quality of the job for both myself and my team.</p>
<p>Since joining YOOX NET-A-PORTER GROUP, the leading online luxury fashion retailer, in 2017, my role as Treasury Manager has been to establish a more sophisticated working environment, by leading several projects necessary to build the operational backbone of the department.</p>
<p>In 2019 I was promoted to Head of Treasury and I felt that the expectation for the role in a fast-growing company required a new set of skills, to enable me to make a bigger impact in the organisation. In fact, in such an industry, I needed to become a forward thinker with a strong commercial acumen, able to face challenges at a more strategic level.</p>
<p>The ACT’s Advanced Diploma in Treasury Management (FCT), which I achieved in 2020, helped me to develop such competencies, not only by building on the technical foundation I had achieved through the AMCT, but also by training to become a “strategic treasurer” and “influencer”, able to use the appropriate leadership skills required in every business situation – particularly in the boardroom.</p>
<p>It was quite natural to change my approach in my daily job and the feedback that I have been receiving from my line manager both for the effort that I was putting into my studies and in the improved quality of the job I was delivering, was really rewarding. I’ve also started sharing the same approach with my team and the main benefit has been seeing them more involved in cross-departmental projects and becoming trusted partners in the organisation.</p>
<p>These achievements and qualifications helped build my confidence, to the point that I felt ready to accept a new challenge by moving into a role outside of treasury. In this role I have helped to redefine the operational processes and strategy, while implementing an innovative culture within the team, a change that was needed to redesign a department at the heart of the company’s business success.</p>
<p>Finally, the networking opportunities offered by professional qualifications are also invaluable: the peer group offers support not only during the preparation for the exam, dissertation and presentation but it also acts as a a platform to share problems, experiences and guidance due to the variety of the participants’ backgrounds.</p>
<p>As a treasury professional you need to accept that you will never stop learning: as the business evolves, you need to keep your knowledge up to date and the resources offered by professional qualifications make them a worthwhile investment.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Kunle Aladewolu, AMCT, MEng, MBA Manager Capital Markets &amp; Treasury, Actualize Consulting" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa_kunle-aladewolu__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=3652400DEA3737D257F7AE83AED493A9" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Kunle Aladewolu</h3>
<h5 class="title">AMCT, MEng, MBA Manager Capital Markets &amp; Treasury</h5>
<h5 class="org">Actualize Consulting</h5>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>Skilled and certified treasury professionals who have attained their qualifications through a recognised body are increasingly in demand for their particular knowledge set and ability to navigate through the critical financial, liquidity and risk management decisions facing organisations regularly.</p>
<p>Part and parcel of a certified treasury qualification, aside from the rigorous examination of the student’s industry knowledge, are a raft of benefits which further enhance the proposition for attaining a certification, including the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Demonstration of commitment to the treasury profession: a professional qualification is a significant undertaking consuming a substantial amount of time outside of one’s normal working hours. This is a sought-after attribute that employers view as a differentiator when recruiting for positions. A certification adds gravitas to your experience gained to date, in addition to demonstrating that you are well-versed in the principles and foundations of treasury.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Certain certifications are globally recognised, allowing qualified treasury professionals to migrate and work abroad more easily than their unqualified counterparts. There are abundant opportunities and rewards for those seeking challenges that will push their personal comfort levels and their limits of understanding when it comes to treasury careers and life goals where travel is concerned. Having a globally recognised professional qualification will speak volumes for you when seeking out such opportunities across the world stage, where the validation of competencies in treasury have been meticulously tested and certified.</p></li>
<li>
<p>Knowledge of good practice and current standards through continuous professional development (CPD): a key component of professional qualifications is the need to be up to date with current views on good practice, standards and relevant industry regulations via the accreditation requirement to recertify or enrol in CPD courses. It is paramount that we, as treasury professionals, are armed with the knowledge that can aid us in the ever-changing treasury landscape and keep us up to speed with the rapid evolutionary pace of banking, finance, and technology.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Industry networking and career-advancing opportunities: the ability to network amongst peers within the treasury community provides several advantages, especially given the treasury community is generally smaller and close-knit in comparison to other professional communities. Networking within the infrastructure that a professional association has built can prove more fruitful for discovering opportunities. If you’re in the professional services arena, you can obtain more client work. You will also have many opportunities to identify a mentor to aid in one’s career in treasury as well as uncovering other career-advancing or enriching prospects.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To those considering taking a professional treasury qualification, it is a highly rewarding experience that will significantly add breadth and depth to your knowledge, career, and professional network. The commitment demonstrated to the treasury profession through accreditation will undoubtedly pay dividends and is highly recognised by peers and employers alike.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Zarine Swamy, Head of Treasury, SOTC Travel" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-05-06-tt-08__qa_zarine-swamy__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=9454DB35DF1FC70BD342C78719DECB5B" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Zarine Swamy</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Treasury</h5>
<h5 class="org">SOTC Travel</h5>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>Attempting and obtaining a professional qualification is certainly beneficial. Here are a number of points I believe to be worth considering:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Professionals who are already in a particular specialised field of work can refresh their knowledge and upskill. In the corporate dynamic, it is beneficial: all things being equal, an individual with a professional certification will be considered over one without, for bigger responsibilities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Certification often helps individuals enter a certain field they wish to work in. I personally know of one individual who has been guided by her company towards Certified Treasury Professional (CTP) exams, awarded by the Association for Financial Professionals (AFP), so she can move into treasury.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All things being equal, it may also play a role in an experienced individual landing a better role outside their organisation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It gives a direction to professionals to better implement the theories they have learnt in practice. The CTP details regulations and processes around, for example, cash pooling. A treasury professional of a company with branches in several countries can certainly benefit from her prior knowledge gained from CTP when it comes to implementing cash pooling. The qualification may also help individuals create solutions to their company’s existing problems.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Obtaining certification is very beneficial if one wishes to enter the workforce of a different country. Many job listings for treasury roles in the US demand the CTP. Similarly, job listings in the UK demand an ACT qualification. While these may not be the only requirements for the role, the certification does give a certain edge.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Again, the CTP for example, gives one a detailed perspective of US regulations, functioning of US-based treasuries, and best practices. These will help treasurers who are already functioning in US treasuries.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My points 5 and 6 come with their own notes of caution. Prior to going in for a certification, it may be prudent to study the relevance of the certification in the environment in which one wishes to operate. If one wishes to work in a specific country, it may be wise to go in for the qualification most readily accepted there. Dubai, for example, holds the ACT in high regard when it comes to recruiting treasury professionals.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lastly, qualification/certification from a reputed body like the AFP has opened a lot of doors for me. I am talking about opportunities such as speaking at various finance forums, and the opportunity to share my knowledge in industry publications. These opportunities will also indirectly add weight to a resume.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lastly, going back to the drawing board to be a student does get those rusty cogs of the brain moving. It helps in keeping ‘over-30’ professionals like me agile and updated!</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“With the impact of the Covid-19 pandemic likely to be felt for some time, how should companies be examining the effectiveness of their treasury policies and approach to financial risk?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: The art of the interview]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=8CB2CCE7BE1FA80D77B05B560526D881]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=521CE6D49B53FAD8C98E4298B1F7AD12"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C4034931F004ACF2C2C6840FEF493AED"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=64085DE4555126ACD972254E9847869E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=924FEF2D24DAB2E62797FF7D62513012"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0F5FCBE464C9EF342B84F054B900E972"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Young person having a job interview" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8CB2CCE7BE1FA80D77B05B560526D881" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__young-woman-arriving-job-interview-business-561824056__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8CB2CCE7BE1FA80D77B05B560526D881"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“How can you interview effectively for a role in treasury?”</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Laura White, Operations Director, The Treasury Recruitment Company" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__laura-white__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=10C984CB6FB87085CEA6640719216727" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Laura White</h3>
<h5 class="title">Operations Director</h5>
<h5 class="org">The Treasury Recruitment Company</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The art of delivering a successful interview lies in the power of the questions. So, developing your questioning skills is absolutely critical to becoming a successful interviewer. One of the best questioning techniques is the funnel technique – you start by gathering broad amounts of information and then filter down to more specific details.</p>
<h5>Introduction</h5>
<p>This is key to setting the standards of the interview, what you want to get out of it, and putting the candidate at ease.</p>
<h5>Career history and experience</h5>
<p>This is where the bulk of the interview should be focused. This is your opportunity to establish as much information as you can about the suitability of the candidate for your role.</p>
<h5>Aspirations and goals</h5>
<p>It is assumed, based on the very fact that the applicant is there at the interview, that the role is what they’re looking for. But by making that assumption, many bad hiring decisions can be made. Asking the right probing questions will enable you to see if there are any shortfalls here or how genuinely suitable the candidate is for the role.</p>
<h5>Search status</h5>
<p>The next stage is information gathering around the applicant’s search so far. This section is often missed by interviewers, but it allows you to identify which individuals are at risk of being offered roles elsewhere, or counter-offers from their existing employer.</p>
<h5>Personal details</h5>
<p>This section focuses on the specific details around current salaries, benefits packages and notice periods, as well as additional information which may impact hiring decisions or processes.</p>
<h5>Job brief and sell</h5>
<p>In many cases, interviewers opt to start the interview by giving the applicant an overview of the role they’re recruiting and what they’re looking for. The debate here though is, how can you sell the specific aspects of the role that are relevant to that applicant, before you know what they are looking for?</p>
<h5>Next steps</h5>
<p>The final stage is what you do after the applicant leaves the building. It is very easy to focus your follow-up efforts only on candidates that you’re interested in. You never know when your paths may cross again. You don’t know who that person knows. Treat them how you would expect to be treated yourself, always provide feedback from the interview and follow up when you say you will.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Gary De Guzman, Director, Pure Search International" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__gary-de-guzman__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=C703C2A0C75702CC9DAA824C68990319" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Gary De Guzman</h3>
<h5 class="title">Director</h5>
<h5 class="org">Pure Search International</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED -->
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The process behind interviewing candidates for treasury roles is largely the same as for other areas. Being able to balance structured and technical questions alongside unstructured, more personal questions makes for a good interview and enables an interviewer to really assess and understand the individual.</p>
<p>For the structured side of the discussion introduce the company, the structure of the team, its culture, how things are run, the expectations of the role – really give the candidate a sense of what life will be like in the role. They will need to understand what the role requires and what skillset is needed to be successful. The structured part of the interview is a good opportunity to probe the suitability of the candidate’s technical skills.</p>
<p>Although structured, technical questions are expected, it’s always advisable to be mindful of ensuring the discussion doesn’t become robotic or one dimensional.</p>
<p>The less structured parts of the discussion can punctuate the necessary questions and start to build a more natural flow to the discussion. It’s a great opportunity to inject some personality into the interview and equally to find out more about the individual’s personality rather than only their skill set. This allows you to establish whether they’d be a good cultural fit for the team and the business as a whole. Take this opportunity to make a positive impression to a future team member as the overall candidate experience will continue to increase in importance.</p>
<p>The order of having unstructured and structured interviewing techniques depends on the style of the interviewer. Every interview is a two-way street and the interviewer is not the only one deciding if it is worthwhile to continue with the interviewing process given the interviewee will be assessing this as well.</p>
<p>Although obvious, it’s important to be mindful of unconscious bias when interviewing. Focusing on the individual and on their professional relevancy for the position is key. Asking the questions that can assess a candidate’s suitability and technical skills that can then be contextualised against others will allow for a fair and honest assessment of who best fits the requirements of the role.</p>
<p>For candidates, the best advice is to be well prepared and to stay positive. If you have been presented for an opportunity via a headhunter, utilise them. They will be a great source of information about the hiring manager, the culture of the team, the company in general and the skill set required for that particular role.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Portrait of Praveen Juyal, Treasury Manager, Amway India" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2020-01-02-tta-09-qa__praveen-juya__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=B359220E4E49A8F437121A2C1A3134D8" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Praveen Juyal</h3>
<h5 class="title">Treasury Manager</h5>
<h5 class="org">Amway India</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Many people say that treasury is the heart of finance, but I feel that if finance is ‘hardware’ then treasury is ‘software’. Without software, hardware is of no use. Accordingly, without proper treasury personnel, finance cannot succeed.</p>
<p>Making sure the right person is managing treasury is the responsibility of the person who hires for that position. So, based on my personal experience, the questions you should be asking are dependent on the way you ask them, and your understanding of that question: asking is an art.</p>
<p>Generally, there are two types of questions we ask at interview. One is structured and the other is unstructured.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Structured questions are the questions which can be answered in a specific way, such as yes, no, true, false, know, don’t know.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Unstructured questions are questions which can be adapted to suit the interviewee. It is a spontaneous conversation without a pre-determined set of questions. Asking questions based on the previous answer is the approach in this method.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I personally feel, a mix of structured and non-structured questions are required to know about the candidate. Again they are two sides of a coin and both are equally important.</p>
<p>Let’s start with:</p>
<h5>Introduction</h5>
<p>This is a way to get to know the candidate. This is an old technique, but ‘old is gold’. Ask lots of questions so that the candidate feels comfortable. The questions may be both structured and non-structured.</p>
<h5>Previous experience</h5>
<p>This is an area which has the potential to generate a lot of questions. In other words, the more you explore this area, the better you will know the candidate.</p>
<h5>Thinking ability</h5>
<p>Ask ‘out of the box’ questions. Keep the candidate going and you will learn their thinking ability – a core part of treasury.</p>
<h5>Analytical skills</h5>
<p>The candidate for this role should be good at analytics. Questions on forecasting, collections, payments and reconciliations can be asked. This will lead you to understand their micro knowledge of the work.</p>
<h5>Projects handled</h5>
<p>It’s important to know the assignments handled by the candidate in their previous organisation. It can help you to understand their work-handling capacity.</p>
<h5>Risk-handling capacity</h5>
<p>It is an important part of the treasury profile. There are a lot of risks we manage on a daily basis. It may be the requirement of working capital, the fund flow management, hedging, interest rates, surplus funds and so on. So, the questions should be framed around this.</p>
<h5>Future aspirations</h5>
<p>It is important to know the candidate’s future goals. If they say “I want to work with this organisation for a long time”, then immediately you can check their previous experience and how long they have been working with their present organisation. It can be a tricky question for the candidate.</p>
<h5>Feedback</h5>
<p>This is the final stage of the overall process. Tell them what you felt about their performance during the interview, and if possible, give some suggestions on how they can improve. At the same time, give them time for queries/questions arising from the interview. Accurate feedback comes from taking notes so make sure whenever you are interviewing, have pen and paper to hand and use them!</p>
<p>The progress of every interview is dependent on the candidate’s nature. Each of us is different, so the same pattern of interview cannot be followed for all for it to be truly effective. And I can guarantee no one can fully understand a person in a few hours; you need to spend more time with them.</p>
<p>Finally, these steps are just an indication of how to conduct the interview based on my own personal experience.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“Does the move to digitisation cause more problems than solutions?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[From treasurer to CFO]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2017 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=3CAE72858E7B009C9195E8BAC6844352]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7BCA10CBD30987D31609D0C31B4FF5DE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=00F402FB4794D63E111BCEC2A330ACD7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8D26E343648E90D1892E6AF86E61D0F6"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B6C8FE20982EDA05C7D8EF068DC4C6FF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C55548BFE81F642273B64E9B883F4902"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Person using fingers as a symbol of someone walking up steps to become CFO" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3CAE72858E7B009C9195E8BAC6844352" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/hand-walking-his-fingers-up-wooden-steps-on-the-way-to-success-and-aspiration-451007416-cfo.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3CAE72858E7B009C9195E8BAC6844352"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>Treasurers often aspire to move to a CFO role – but what obstacles should they be aware of and what steps can they take to improve their chances of success?</em></p>
<p>While many treasury professionals may aspire to the role of CFO, there are no guarantees that even a highly experienced treasurer will be successful in achieving this goal.  While the two roles certainly share some common ground, treasurers should be aware that they may need to overcome some gaps in their skills and experience in order to be considered for a CFO role.</p>
<p>Mike Tucker, Managing Director of Cadence Search, points out that the responsibilities of the CFO are broad, encompassing all areas of financial management as well as a significant stake in leadership.  “The role of the treasurer is increasingly varied but ultimately limited to the various financial risks the group is managing, be that cash, liquidity, FX, counterparty, etc,” he says.  “Insurance and pensions are also (often) found on the treasurer’s table these days – and sometimes tax – but the profile is and always will be narrower than the CFO.”</p>
<p>Jennifer Ceran, CFO of Smartsheet and the former treasurer of eBay, similarly notes that the biggest obstacle treasurers face is that of being viewed as too narrow in their experience.  “The board and the CEO want a CFO with broad experience,” she explains.  “Sometimes you not only manage finance but also legal, IT and HR.  If you have been a treasurer your entire career, not having other experience may hold you back from being considered.”</p>
<p>Nevertheless, many treasury professionals do go on to become CFOs.  While every individual’s career path is unique, there are a number of steps that treasurers can take if they want to become CFO, from gaining business exposure to building confidence.</p>
<h3 id="how-the-roles-differ">How the roles differ</h3>
<p>Naturally there are a number of differences between the roles of treasurer and CFO.  As Tucker points out, “at CFO level, you’re more often than not sitting on the board with a key stake in the strategic decisions the group is taking or going to take.  Whilst the profile of the treasurer has undoubtedly risen in recent times, your strategic influence at the top table is currently limited and your responsibilities directly affected by strategic decisions above.”</p>
<p>According to Ceran, a treasurer needs “deep technical skills in the financial markets, a keen sense for risk and how to manage it, and a great partnership with the CFO.”  A CFO, meanwhile, “needs broader technical skills beyond just treasurer, a strong grasp of business operations and an ability to translate strategy into execution”.  She adds that all CFOs must also have a great partnership with the CEO.</p>
<p>Mustafa Kilic, CFO of Groupe SEB in Turkey, was previously head of regional treasury for Indesit.  He cites a number of differences between the roles: “There are different skills and expertise required – yes, treasury is one of them, but planning, controlling and knowing the regulations and the environment is also quite important.”  He notes that the CFO role is more strategic, with greater interaction with other departments, from marketing to logistics.  Treasury, in comparison, is “more isolated”.</p>
<p>On a practical note, Kilic also points out that a CFO role requires more travel.  “When I was working in treasury, I would not be meeting clients or suppliers very often – I was not that much involved with the other contracts that the business was signing,” he says.  “Right now I spend almost 10% of my time with clients, suppliers and representing the company with different platforms.”</p>
<p>Nevertheless, there are also a number of similarities between the roles.  Ceran says that both roles require an ability to sense risk around the corners and great communication skills – “particularly if one is a treasurer or CFO of a public company”.  She adds that both roles require the ability to recruit and retail great talent.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><h3 id="making-the-move-points-to-consider">Making the move: points to consider</h3>
<p>Pieter de Kiewit, Owner of De Kiewit Treasurer Search, says that the following points are often discussed in conversations about making the move from treasurer to CFO:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If there are nine controllers for each treasurer, the treasurer has a less than 10% chance of making it to CFO.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Being a treasurer within company A and becoming a CFO in company B is virtually impossible.  So take care if you are in an organisation that enables such a promotion.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>There are many examples of treasurers making it to CFO, so it can be done.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If treasury has been your single job type, consider a lateral move to accounting or control before moving up again.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In board meetings, topics around management accounting, reporting and analysis get more attention.  From a technical skill perspective, the aspiring CFO should cover these well to avoid being disqualified.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>From a personal skills perspective, the competition – group controllers and chief accountants – are often more experienced people managers and have experience in multi-disciplinary management team meetings.  These skills are appreciated in a CFO.</p>
</li>
</ul></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h3 id="preparation-is-key">Preparation is key</h3>
<p>Jason Wang, Group CFO of the largest Chinese baby nutrition company Biostime, previously held roles in treasury, including regional treasurer for Asia Pacific at Henkel.  However, the leap from treasury to a CFO role did not happen in a single step.</p>
<p>“Before I became the CFO, I actually moved from a treasury role to a controller role, becoming the financial controller for China and Hong Kong at Henkel,” he explains.  “It was a very important and critical experience to gain direct exposure to the accounting and controlling work, and also to gain closer contacts with business and operations colleagues.”</p>
<p>As well as taking the financial controller role, Wang also concurrently took a business role as interim general manager for Henkel’s detergent business in China – a move which he says was invaluable as a means of gaining direct business management experience.  He was subsequently appointed CFO, Greater China at Henkel.</p>
<p>Wang says that when it comes to moving to a CFO role, there are several steps that treasurers can take to acquire valuable skills, knowledge and experience.  Firstly, he says that treasurers should make sure that they have the required professional accounting knowledge.  “In my case I had both the AICPA and ACCA qualification, which was very helpful,” he explains.  “On the one hand, this put me in a better position when it came to making decisions about financial and accounting questions.  It also enabled me to show a higher level of credibility in the organisation.”</p>
<p>Wang also regards controlling experience as important for treasurers who are looking to make this type of career move.  “Within the financial organisation, as well as traditional finance functions such as treasury, tax, purchase-to-pay and order-to-cash, I think the controlling function is very important right now.  To me it’s almost a must that you have this experience before you become the CFO.  I have already encouraged all my treasury colleagues who want to become CFO to obtain this type of experience.”</p>
<p>In addition, Wang recommends that treasurers should make sure they have business exposure – either directly or indirectly.  “Indirect exposure could be involvement in working capital management, supply chain finance or FX hedging within the treasurer role – all of these areas include interactions with the business, which is valuable experience when it comes to understanding the whole company’s value chain,” he says.  “If possible, it is also valuable to have direct experience, for example by moving into a business controller role where you are in charge of financial planning and analysis (FP&amp;A) and you become like a chief of staff for the business manager.”</p>
<h3 id="expanding-horizons">Expanding horizons</h3>
<p>Ceran agrees that treasurers should get their hands on experience in other areas, such as Accounting, FP&amp;A, IR or a BU CFO role.  “The IR and FP&amp;A roles I held have helped me understand the bigger picture of the CFO role and prepared me to take on the role,” she says.  “I would seek out mentoring from other CFOs, who may ultimately help you land that first job, or make you realise it’s not the job for you.  I would also start building relationships with your potential future partners like auditors and legal firms.”</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Kilic adds that while treasurers have a strong understanding of a company’s cash flow, they should look beyond this to gain a better understanding of topics such as working capital, P&amp;L and balance sheet management.  “Most treasurers unfortunately may not have time to focus on the balance sheet and P&amp;L side of the business, but this should be seen as essential,” he says.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Stepping outside the comfort zone</h2>
<div class="copy__body">
<h4 id="">Jennifer Ceran, CFO at Smartsheet</h4>
<p>“I graduated college in 1985 and spent my first two years on Wall Street as a financial analyst.  After attending business school and graduating in 1989, I joined the Sara Lee Corporation as a Senior Financial Analyst in Corporate Development.  I did not know what I wanted to do back then from a long-term career perspective so every 12-18 months or so, I moved to a different role in finance to explore the opportunities.</p>
<p>“In 1992, I rotated into the treasury department, and it was there I discovered my passion for the role.  I loved that the treasury team had the visibility and responsibility for taking care of the company’s capital structure including its financial assets and liabilities all around the world, and associated risks.  Essentially, I learned that the right capital structure is critical to a company functioning well in both good and bad economic times, and maximising shareholder value over the long term.  Companies can have different optimal capital structures depending on their business model so it’s a balancing act of many factors and I loved the challenge of trying to figure out how to optimise it.</p>
<p>“I made the decision at that time that I aspired to be a treasurer someday.  So I spent the next ten years rotating within treasury and doing two international treasury assignments.  I wanted to learn everything I could to be ready for an opportunity when it came along.</p>
<p>“In early 2003 a recruiter contacted me for the treasurer role of eBay; at that time the company had just surpassed $1bn in revenue.  I felt this was the perfect opportunity for me to take my experience and scale.  For the next seven years, I was their treasurer and revenues grew to $14bn during my nearly ten years there.  It was an exciting time.  We were helping the company expand globally, making bold acquisitions like PayPal and Skype, managing sizable and growing FX, interest rate and operating risks, and dealing with an unplanned global financial crisis in 2008.  After seven years in treasury, and navigating through the financial crisis, I asked our CFO to consider me for other finance leadership opportunities as I was ready to learn something new.  When he offered me the investor relations and financial planning and analysis roles in 2010, I jumped at the opportunity.</p>
<p>“Then in 2012, after spending 25 years at big, multinational companies and now living in Silicon Valley where start-ups were offering challenging opportunities in emerging technologies, I got the start-up bug.  A chance meeting with the co-founder of Box led me to moving to the then $50m revenue, fast-growing start-up.  I joined as a VP of Finance to help them scale and get ready for an IPO.  Box went public in January 2015, and I had the opportunity to help the founders and leadership team ring the bell at the NYSE.</p>
<p>“For most of my career, I never thought about being a CFO but I sometimes wondered if I was selling myself short by not stepping out of my comfort zone.  It was around the time Sheryl Sandberg’s book ‘Lean In’ came out.  She encouraged women to lean in and stop holding themselves back.</p>
<p>“In the summer of 2015 a recruiter contacted me about becoming the CFO of a sub $1bn market cap public company.  I interviewed and got the job.  Then nearly a year later, a recruiter called me about being the first CFO of Smartsheet, a small but fast private SaaS business in the emerging collaborative work management space.  I loved the Smartsheet technology because it made it so much easier to do the work I do every day with my colleagues and partners.  I joined Smartsheet to help them fulfil growing customer demand in a large market and to work with a very passionate and collaborative team.”</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>In addition, while technical skills and experience are crucial, soft skills may also play a role in determining whether an individual is suitable for the role of CFO.  Ceran points out that the board and CEO must see you “as a CFO”.  “There is an element of strong leadership, someone who can inspire and motivate,” she notes.  “It is a perception thing but it’s important how you carry yourself.</p>
<p>“For me, I have also had to work on my self-confidence.  You need to prepare yourself a bit for the discomfort of new things coming at you as a CFO and not having the answer right away.  I have built a large network of former colleagues and other CFOs and rely on them for advice when I need it.  They have been invaluable for me, and that is why I regularly help others when they call on me.  It is a two way street.”</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Treasury professionals can certainly make it to CFO – however, it is clear that they may first need to overcome some obstacles.  By making strategic lateral moves in good time, and by taking the time to gain the right sort of skills and business exposure, treasurers can greatly improve their chances of becoming CFO.</p>
<p>Indeed, with treasury becoming more visible over the last few years, treasurers are arguably in a better position to achieve this than in the past.  As Tucker remarks, “in my opinion the group treasurer is increasingly well equipped to move into a CFO role.  The nature of their work means they are forward thinking.  In an increasingly unpredictable world, I believe this is a huge asset as they are often better equipped to deal with rapid change – unlike those who are approaching the CFO role from a more traditional background.”</p>
<p>Finally, while many treasurers do have aspirations to advance to CFO, in the meantime it is worth remembering that the role of treasurer can itself be highly rewarding.  As Ceran concludes, “the treasurer role is an extremely important and fulfilling one.  Of all the functional roles below CFO, it was my favourite.  It was my favourite because a lot of CFOs don’t really know treasury that well so they really value you.  It was also a role where you can make a very positive impact, while potentially having a better work/life balance than the CFO.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury talent: managing your career]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Sep 2016 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=0AA4E654C77528F41DADC68B5F5BF8A3]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AF2D1754025EF85CBD1D8AA07A95C9B6"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7C2BEE7719D86E5CA4831BFA1D07B1FB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=020D0FBF6EC2F545B1E9CD1D0F099EC4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D5A154CE58D95D9BCAA8B90E60634FD1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=801FC7FA4EA8FD0E4FC174F0F146A4B7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Man with backpack on rocky peak" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0AA4E654C77528F41DADC68B5F5BF8A3" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/touristwithbackpackandpolesonrockypeaklookingintosunsunnydaybreakinmountainsdreamyss4117594661920x10.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0AA4E654C77528F41DADC68B5F5BF8A3"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>The world of corporate treasury is full of talented people. But how can treasury departments make the most of their teams and what can individuals do to progress? In this article, we propose some tips for climbing the career ladder, as well as highlighting the benefits of embracing, and supporting, a diverse, ambitious treasury team.</em></p>
<h3 id="diversity-and-equality">Diversity and equality</h3>
<p>Diversity is a topic close to Treasury Today’s heart having run the successful Women in Treasury initiative for four years now. The motivations are simple: despite concrete evidence that having more women in senior roles is good for business, equal opportunities are still a long way off. For example, Treasury Today’s Women in Treasury Global Study 2015 found that 33% of female respondents believe they are paid less than their male counterparts and 45% did not feel their career prospects are the same as male colleagues.</p>
<p>Yet evidence has proven that gender-diverse companies perform better. In fact, companies in the top quartile for gender diversity are 15% more likely to outperform other companies, a report, titled ‘Diversity Matters’, from McKinsey &amp; Company indicated. But diversity isn’t limited to gender – the same research showed that companies in the top quartile for racial and ethnic diversity were 35% more likely to have financial returns above their national industry medians.</p>
<p>What’s more, it’s not just that bottom-quartile companies are not leading – they are lagging. For both gender and ethnicity and race, the least diverse companies are statistically less likely to achieve above-average returns.</p>
<p>Diversity in terms of age, gender, ethnicity, sexuality, background and so on creates diversity of thought which is a strength in business because it ensures different ways of approaching the same problem are suggested. “Alternative ideas allow us to come up with the best solutions,” says Debra Todd, VP, Global Treasury Services, BP.</p>
<p>Therefore, when corporates are hiring they should consider the dynamic of their existing treasury team – and consider which aspects could need more prominence. As Todd says: “It’s important that we look at whole teams, rather than just at individuals. If you consider six people that are the same and have similar strengths, that team would be a lot weaker than six very different people who boast diverse strengths.”</p>
<h3 id="talent-management-tools-and-techniques">Talent management tools and techniques</h3>
<p>In order to develop such strengths, talent needs to be nurtured. As corporate employers reap the rewards of a successful treasury team, it is in their favour to support the progression of individuals’ careers. Internal and external training programmes are beneficial, as well as supporting those who are studying for additional qualifications. Ones of note include: the Association of Corporate Treasurers (ACT) qualifications, the Certified Treasury Professional (CTP) or the Association of Chartered Certified Accountants (ACCA). Some professionals also look into the Chartered Institute of Management Accountants (CIMA), but it is important to be aware, as the title suggests, this is not as treasury focused as the first two.</p>
<p>In terms of encouraging a team who want to succeed, senior executives are responsible for providing a good example. The CEB Corporate Leadership Council™ analysed data from more than 150,000 employees and identified that senior executives acting as good role models for developing employees is the single most important factor for driving leadership quality. What’s more, excellence here increases an organisation’s probability of being a top-tier leadership organisation by 84.1%.</p>
<p>Top-tier leadership, the CEB Corporate Leadership Council™ says, is characterised by managers who prioritise and act on employee development needs. Whether this is further training, support for flexible working or backing for a career change perhaps, these are some of the areas good managers keep an eye on. Not only that, but it is often recognised that professionals don’t leave jobs, they leave managers. A Gallup poll claimed that 75% of workers who voluntarily left their jobs did so because of their bosses and not the position itself. As the graphs below confirm, a competitive salary is rated as the least influential factor in a treasurers’ happiness (<a href="#chart-01">Chart 1</a>), whereas a poor boss or manager is the most influential factor in their unhappiness (<a href="#chart-02">Chart 2</a>).</p>
<h4 id="chart-01">Chart 1: Why treasurers are happy in their roles</h4>
<p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-09-10-tt-15-ttal-chart-01-why-treasurers-are-happy-in-their-roles-967x499.png?la=en&amp;hash=8D494E102D789E75FAF9540E522EED5E" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: Why treasurers are happy in their roles" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-09-10-tt-15-ttal-chart-01-why-treasurers-are-happy-in-their-roles-967x499.png?la=en&amp;hash=8D494E102D789E75FAF9540E522EED5E" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: MR Treasury Recruitment Global Treasury Salary Survey</em></p>
<p>Whilst it may have become somewhat of a cliché, the most important company resource is its people. Supportive working environments and the opportunity for career progression are key to attracting and retaining great talent.</p>
<h4 id="chart-02">Chart 2: Why treasurers are unhappy in their roles</h4>
<p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-09-10-tt-15-ttal-chart-02-why-treasurers-are-unhappy-in-their-roles-967x492.png?la=en&amp;hash=DFCA9D99C0522C2179FA041D0C39D43F" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 2: Why treasurers are unhappy in their roles" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-09-10-tt-15-ttal-chart-02-why-treasurers-are-unhappy-in-their-roles-967x492.png?la=en&amp;hash=DFCA9D99C0522C2179FA041D0C39D43F" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: MR Treasury Recruitment Global Treasury Salary Survey</em></p>
<h3 id="formal-mentoring-informal-mentoring-and-sponsorship">Formal mentoring, informal mentoring and sponsorship</h3>
<p>Mentoring frequently comes up as a springboard for success; many corporates cite mentoring programmes as critical in helping them navigate new organisations and supporting them with different perspectives throughout a career. Mentees can gain a lot from the experience of those around them, picking up new skills and knowledge. It is an opportunity to have conversations in a risk-free way as a key aspect of mentoring is confidentiality.</p>
<p>There are some myths to debunk, however. Mentoring isn’t necessarily restricted by gender. Males can mentor females and vice versa. Also, mentoring doesn’t have to be formally ‘set up’ by a programme or organisation. What is perhaps less emphasised is informal mentoring. Rather than going through an established mentor programme (as not all companies have them), similar relationships can evolve in a more natural way, within the same company or from outside. Senior executives have a wealth of knowledge others can tap into and the recurring thoughts Treasury Today hears suggest that most professionals are more than willing to share their understanding – and time – with others.</p>
<p>For informal or formal mentoring to be successful though, mentee and mentor must have commonalities, meet regularly and have areas of experience identified which the mentee wants to gain from. For the mentor, it can be hugely rewarding to see someone develop and progress. Fifty-eight percent of respondents to Treasury Today’s Women in Treasury Global Study said they would be interested in being a mentor to others.</p>
<p>Moreover, successfully leveraging networks is a great way of meeting other professionals, making friends and learning. You may also hear of suitable vacancies and are more likely to receive recommendations from those who have worked alongside you in the industry.</p>
<p>Indeed, sponsorship is said to be another – potentially more lucrative – way of progressing your career. It is a case of ‘who knows you, not who you know’ as a sponsor is essentially an ally who will be your advocate when it comes to staffing decisions. It is worth noting that employees of all seniorities can champion colleagues.</p>
<p>To attract sponsors, Catalyst, an organisation with a mission to expand opportunities for women and business, recommends the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Be seen.</h5>
<p>You – and your work – must be visible. If your achievements aren’t seen, how can colleagues or managers champion you?</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Take risks.</h5>
<p>Sometimes you need to go outside of your comfort zone to progress – for instance, applying for positions you don’t yet possess the entire skill set for.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Ask for what you want.</h5>
<p>So long as you have a clear understanding of what you want, don’t hold back on articulating these career ambitions.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>More than anything, though, your work should speak for itself.</p>
<h3 id="preparing-for-career-success">Preparing for career success</h3>
<p>Indeed, it is the responsibility of individuals to manage their careers. Seeking out an informal mentor or attracting a sponsor could be part of this. According to Singapore-based recruiter Megha Khare, Manager, Accounting &amp; Finance, Page Personnel: “For somebody who is very keen and passionate about treasury, if they plan it well, they can have a good career ahead of them.”</p>
<p>But don’t run before you can walk. The emphasis here is on planning – knowing where you’d like to progress to and the best methods to help you get there. A career road map can help to boost your mobility.</p>
<p>A common piece of advice Treasury Today hears from the industry is to put yourself in the right place at the right time so that you are having the right conversations with the right people. Martha Pierce, Senior Consultant at UK-based recruitment firm Hays Treasury says that a common gripe made by candidates to recruiters is that there aren’t sufficient opportunities within their current company. “But I will be having a conversation from the other side and line managers will say ‘they are great at their job, but are not showing much eagerness to learn’.”</p>
<p>It is the responsibility of all employees and managers to start having conversations which ensure staff know their employers are willing to invest in them. “In my experience, it’s difficult to recruit at the moment so businesses, most of the time, are going to give you that opportunity to gain more experience,” Pierce adds.</p>
<h3 id="c-suite-ambitions">C-suite ambitions</h3>
<p>For some treasurers, the ultimate goal is to become a member of the C-suite. There are, of course, certain things a treasurer can do to improve their chances of this happening. Making themselves more visible (for the right reasons), getting closer to the operational side of the business and expanding their scope of responsibilities, for example.</p>
<h3 id="chief-financial-officer">Chief Financial Officer</h3>
<p>The CFO role necessitates the capability of translating business decisions into numbers and explaining the impact on the company’s bottom line. Looking into the future – and all the time translating reality into numbers and numbers into reality – is a vital part of the job. As Maciej Müldner, Finance Director, Skanska Property Poland says: “There is no ‘safe haven’ for a CFO, so whilst many talk about it, the role isn’t for everybody.”</p>
<p>Typical financial qualifications are good to have, as well as a Master of Business Administration (MBA) or alternative forms of management study. Working in the treasurers’ advantage is the fact that they are already, in their current role, exposed to some of the most critical contacts within the CFO’s reach – financial institutions (FIs) and suppliers, for instance.</p>
<p>Additionally, it is “second nature for a treasurer to look for financial risk; they understand how operational, financial and strategic risks are all linked and can trigger each other”, says Mustafa Kilic, CFO and Member of the Board of Directors, Candy Group Turkey. “In their existing roles, treasurers have already built up a good perspective of credit and market risks too.” All of which are key components for a CFO.</p>
<p>Indeed, the skills valued in the role are all within the reach of the corporate treasurer who can “add these abilities to their current skillset and maximise their chances of becoming a CFO”, says Kilic. Desirable skills, he says, include an in-depth understanding of an individual company’s business operating environment, risk management skills, and the ability to communicate well with people from governments, banks and also local populations.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body">
<h3 id="ten-top-tips-for-climbing-the-career-ladder">Ten top tips for climbing the career ladder</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Don’t be afraid to ask for help or advice.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Experience may not be found where you expect. Taking on roles or projects outside of the department can give you fresh and valuable perspectives.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Try and make sure you stand out by going the extra mile for colleagues.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Plan where you’d like to be, and how best to get there – but don’t expect it to always be a straightforward route. You can learn from bumps in the road.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Know where your strengths lie, and keep a record of accomplishments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Maintain a healthy balance between your work and home life.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Don’t expect your colleagues or bosses to be telepathic. You’ve got to communicate well in order to achieve common goals.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Keep up-to-date with current trends, technology and industry developments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Avoid getting dragged into finger pointing and blaming. It is important to keep your integrity, even in challenging times.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Understand the manual processes behind the treasury systems you use. If – or when – they break, you will be in the best position to cope.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h3 id="chief-executive-officer">Chief Executive Officer</h3>
<p>According to the ninth annual Robert Half FTSE 100 CEO Tracker survey, more than half (55%) of today’s FTSE 100 CEOs have a background in finance and accounting or financial services, compared to just 21% in retail, 15% in engineering and 14% in technology. Almost one in four (23%) CEOs are qualified chartered accountants.</p>
<p>Although formal qualifications are not usually specified for the CEO role, having a university degree and even a post-graduate qualification helps. The majority of FTSE 100 CEOs have at least one university degree, and more than a quarter have either an MBA or a PhD. Nevertheless, it is worth noting that some very high profile chief executives either dropped out or never went to college. This list includes luminaries such as Richard Branson, founder and CEO of Virgin Group, Michael Dell, founder and CEO of Dell Computer and Bill Gates, co-founder and former CEO and Chairman of Microsoft.</p>
<h3 id="communication-skills">Communication skills</h3>
<p>CFOs and senior treasurers will be far ahead of their bosses in financial acumen, and at least on par in terms of decision-making, thinking strategically and taking a global perspective, wrote Gary Burnison, CEO of executive recruitment firm, Korn Ferry, in a recent white paper. However, he says CEOs “have a clear right-brain advantage that wins the day on the leadership front”. This, he argues, means they are “better at building relationships and at influencing, engaging, and inspiring others; they are more courageous and optimistic; and they have a stronger customer focus”.</p>
<p>The firm’s analysis of current CEOs in the global Forbes 2000 list 2015 reveals that only 13% moved into that position from the CFO role – somewhat at odds with the Robert Half UK observation. In addition, Forbes 2000 CEOs who previously held senior-level financial officer positions (controller, treasurer, chief accounting officer, senior vice president/vice president of finance, chief tax officer, vice president of investor relations, or CFO) accounted for only 18% of the total. It adds that little has changed in the past few years. The most noticeable gap for CFOs seeking to take the CEO chair is in their ‘people skills’. The need, says Burnison, is to develop “more social leadership skills to influence, engage, and inspire others”.</p>
<p>Similarly, Pratibha Advani, CFO of Tata Communications, told Treasury Today that for a financial executive to succeed in leadership it requires balancing the responsibilities of stewardship with those of business partnerships. “We cannot just be number-crunchers; we should also be able to communicate the logic behind those numbers. Today’s finance professionals are not like old-fashioned bean counters – we have a much more proactive role to play as business partners in drafting and implementing business strategy.” From this point, the well-rounded treasurer has every chance of becoming CEO.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body">
<h3 id="the-recruiters-perspective">The recruiters’ perspective</h3>
<p>In working at the ‘coalface’, recruiters have a unique view on what the treasury jobs market will look like in 2017 and beyond. Treasury Today talks to Martha Pierce, Principal Recruitment Consultant, Hays Treasury and Mike Richards, Managing Director, MR Recruitment, about what to expect:</p>
<h5>Current state of play.</h5>
<p>Although the pace has slowed down somewhat of late, Pierce says, “the treasury recruitment market has become increasingly busy over the last couple of years”. This has been largely driven by transformation projects within treasury functions requiring corporates to bring in project people or increase headcount and it is a trend she sees continuing into 2017.</p>
<p>SMEs have been increasingly realising the value of a treasury function too, she adds. “In general, treasury has been improving in terms of vocalising the value it can add to a business. As such, organisations are just more aware of the value-add it can provide, even in cases where a dedicated role didn’t previously exist.”</p>
<h5>Brexit.</h5>
<p>For Richards, Brexit and the volatility it has helped to create will put treasury in the spotlight again and, as such, the recruitment market will get busier, he predicts. “On Thursday 23<sup>rd</sup> June, there was only a remote chance of stormy times but as soon as the results [of the UK EU referendum] were announced, treasury was placed in the eye of the storm,” he says.</p>
<h5>In demand.</h5>
<p>In fact, candidates are in the driving seat at the moment. As Richards says: “Two years ago, companies were in charge but the balance is more in favour of treasury professionals now.” For corporates in the process of recruiting, this means focusing on what the role offers and communicating the reasons why candidates would enjoy coming to work for you. “Do not put obstacles in their way – such as tests – before they have even walked in the door.”</p>
<h5>Qualifications.</h5>
<p>Nonetheless, according to Pierce, qualifications are “hugely important” because “businesses are more risk-averse and they want those qualifications to confirm what level that individual sits at”. A Hays survey, titled ‘DNA of a Head of Treasury’, surveyed over 100 senior treasurers across the UK and found that 38% held the ACT qualification, 21% the ACA and 20% CIMA.</p>
<h5>Cross-training on the job.</h5>
<p>In addition to qualifications, professionals will need to expand their “toolboxes” in order to progress in the future, says Richards. “Those who would like to move into slightly different roles can look at shadowing others to learn new skills on the job. This is a great way of getting different tools in their toolbox to be able to then apply for different roles.”</p>
<h5>Salaries.</h5>
<p>Whilst salaries have stagnated in recent years, says Richards, the treasury community might finally see increases as the demand for their specialist skills “will increase in these tough times”.</p>
<h5>Communication skills.</h5>
<p>It seems whether you are in a junior or senior role, the way you communicate is a factor that drives progression. Both Pierce and Richards agree that softer skills will continue to be valuable in 2017. “Understanding the core workings of an organisation and how treasury benefits the company’s objectives as early on in a treasury career as possible is advised,” says Pierce. “In the process, individuals will increase their visibility too.”</p>
<p>It is that visibility, and being able to communicate what value you add in your role, which enables treasurers to command higher salaries too, adds Richards.</p>
<h5>Keep in touch.</h5>
<p>Whether looking for a new role in 2017 or not, it is important for treasurers to keep an eye on the recruitment market and think about long-term career paths. Few professionals are better placed to help with this than recruiters – so keep in touch. “After all, treasury professionals at any stages of their career will have similar concerns about where best to go next to benefit their careers,” concludes Richards.</p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[An assisting role]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jul 2016 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=B76BF520DC4B47C90C1CA31AD083991F]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A622A8162C91EB99D71B17C94D0888A4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AD0DC0F082DE1A4BA9FD638179DE9652"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=615574E77C8E6E6424449D692CE0AED4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D8521AE2C2A44B9F07561EAABB07F149"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2B774B654C2C4C08548435D54A54A1C1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="View inside a safety ladder tower" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B76BF520DC4B47C90C1CA31AD083991F" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2016-07-08-tt-09-cpr__safety-ladder-inside-the-tower-water-supply-422354536__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B76BF520DC4B47C90C1CA31AD083991F"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>What skills and experience are necessary for treasury assistants? How do successful candidates progress? Treasury Today asks these questions and more to shine a light on the role in the first of this new series focused on the different rungs of the treasury career ladder.</em></p>
<p>Treasury assistants perform an array of tasks which support the daily operations of a treasury department. These could include: multi-currency cash management, bank reconciliation, settlements and the review of payments and receipts, amongst many other responsibilities. Although generally considered an entry level position, they have an important role to play in ensuring operations in treasury run efficiently – so what makes a good treasury assistant?</p>
<p>In this article, Treasury Today talks to recruitment experts, as well as former treasury assistants themselves about the key aspects of a successful candidate. What quickly becomes clear is that the answer to the preceding question is not a straightforward one. A range of skills and wealth of knowledge to build upon, as well as practical ability and softer skills, need to be demonstrated by any professional who wishes to fulfil the role of a treasury assistant.</p>
<h3 id="gaining-exposure">Gaining exposure</h3>
<p>The world of treasury is generally very supportive of new entrants, according to Martha Pierce, Senior Consultant at UK-based recruitment firm Hays Treasury. “Early on, you should be able to get the opportunity to gain exposure to the various elements needed to make a good treasury assistant.”</p>
<p>A common gripe made by candidates to recruiters, she says, is that there are not sufficient opportunities within their current company. But employers, on the other hand, sometimes feel like junior staff are not working hard enough to seize opportunities. “I will be having conversations with line managers, who will say ‘they are great at their job, but are not showing much eagerness to learn’.” Conversations need to start occurring then which ensure employees know their employers are willing to invest in them and, conversely, that employers know their employees are keen to develop professionally. “In my experience, it’s difficult to recruit at the moment so businesses, most of the time, are going to give you that opportunity to gain more experience,” Pierce adds.</p>
<p>Making the most of such opportunities will help individuals counter a mistake Pierce sees occurring too often at the beginning of a career. “I see a lot of people moving from roles too quickly for the wrong positions and a very small wage increase.” Rather, they should, she believes, be making the most out of their current position. “People that are very eager and asking their managers for more responsibility are getting it.”</p>
<p>As a result of such a conversation, Jennifer Gillespie, now Head of Money Markets at Legal &amp; General, started her treasury career at Scottish Widows Bank as a treasury assistant, before later becoming a treasury manager. “As I had no finance or treasury experience, this didn’t come into play at all. It was more who I knew and the conversations I was willing to have – I talked my way into the job!”</p>
<p>A willingness to get involved is also necessary to fulfil a key part of the treasury assistant’s remit: liaising with banks and other senior people outside of the treasury department. For these activities, efficient communication skills – as well as a genuine enjoyment working with others – are absolutely necessary. “As a treasury assistant, you are not a silo. You are reliant upon other people, such as IT, so maintaining good relationships with other areas of the business is incredibly important,” clarifies Gillespie.</p>
<p>What’s more, according to Hays Treasury’s Pierce, being able to show your personality is a necessary part of the recipe for success. “Quite often at this level, personality is what gets somebody the job. Going into an interview and saying the right things – showing how keen and personable you are, for instance – and having the right foundational experience are components for success.”</p>
<p>Nadine Dannenmuller, now Treasury Analyst at Nokia Oyj, notes that when she initially joined the company (formerly Nokia Siemens Networks Finance B.V.) back in 2008, her treasury assistant role consisted of 70% administrative and logistical tasks and 30% treasury tasks. But, by showing a desire to progress and learn, she attracted the attention of a member of the team who believed she could make the step towards a more treasury-orientated role – and offered informal training and guidance. Dannenmuller does point out, though: “The treasury assistant role can be varied so you have to be flexible and ready to accept some uncertainty in the definition of your role which can evolve and develop over the course of time.”</p>
<h3 id="the-foundations">The foundations</h3>
<p>But what are the necessary building blocks from which to grow? First of all, the right attitude is important. “Clients looking for treasury assistants don’t want someone to try and run before they can walk. Rather, showing an eagerness to get stuck in and learn will hold you in good stead,” says Pierce.</p>
<p>Initially, those who tend to be successful have experience with multi-currency bank account and loan administration, for instance. They will also be familiar with settlements and confirmations. But the beginning stages of involvement with risk management and forecasting could help further their career development, says Pierce.</p>
<p>When you look at the more manual treasury functions, rather than those at departments with TMSs in place, treasury assistants must have intermediate level Excel skills: experience with pivot tables, the VLOOKUP function and the ability to trace back macros. “Requirements do depend on the company in question, however,” says Pierce. Therefore, treasuries with more automated processes will be looking for familiarity with these systems. However, a fundamental understanding of the underlying processes remains necessary. As Gillespie says: “It’s like understanding the mathematics behind something. We all had to learn multiplication tables. Understanding the processes behind the systems means you can cope if – or when – they break.”</p>
<p>For those interested in the role, it is pertinent to remember that treasury assistants are expected to work extremely hard – and this often involves taking responsibility for some of the department’s more administrative tasks. Treasury assistants will be involved in both the day-to-day operations, such as processing payments and receipt posting, as well as having month end responsibilities which could include reviewing the balance sheet or reporting the group currency month end rates. A list of further possibilities duties include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Bank reconciliations.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bank account management.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cash book maintenance.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Answering payment related queries.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Preparing and processing payments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Compliance activities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Posting of bank transactions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Maintenance and reporting of standing orders and direct debts.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Analysing funding needs</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ad hoc projects, as required.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>A certain level of knowledge regarding international payment processing and time zone differences will need to be maintained too. As Dannenmuller said, the role will evolve and, currently, her main role is to ensure “EMEA cash centralisation and repatriation to avoid local currency devaluation and a better use of this cash centrally. For example, for repaying the central debt or for centralised deposits.” This involves booking inter-company loans and deposits, for instance, and providing the relevant documentation.</p>
<p>Treasury assistants will also be expected to ensure treasury policies are followed during every process and raise liquidity concerns to managers; a strong relationship between these two members of the team is invaluable. “Seeking and sharing macroeconomic knowledge is also about finding solutions to add value,” adds Dannenmuller.</p>
<p>Gillespie, for instance, says that it was perseverance and hard work that helped her gain treasury experience. “Practical experience is the most beneficial. That, and learning when to ask for help.” The role, for her, acted as a springboard for success somewhat. During 14 years at SWIP, Gillespie held various positions – the most senior of which was Investment Director, Money Market Funds where she helped to successfully launch SWIP’s global liquidity funds to bring the assets under management (AUM) from £3bn to £12bn. It would seem that the treasury assistant role provides sufficient exposure to the areas necessary to progress in different areas. “From the position you can build yourself out and boast a broader wealth of knowledge,” says Gillespie.</p>
<h3 id="beyond-expectations">Beyond expectations</h3>
<p>As with any position, the most successful employees bring something additional to the table. For the treasury assistant, one of the most valuable extra skills is experience with cash flow forecasting. According to Pierce, this will see your salary rise and more opportunities come your way.</p>
<p>Treasury-specific education is not a ‘must have’ at this level – as Gillespie’s success demonstrates – but employers do now tend to require graduates with a degree in a financial field. Those that are enrolled, or are close to sitting or have sat, their first paper of a treasury qualification are the ones in the strongest position. For instance, the Association of Corporate Treasurers (ACT) qualifications or the Association of Chartered Certified Accountants (ACCA). Some also look into the Chartered Institute of Management Accountants (CIMA), but it is important to be aware that this isn’t as treasury focused. “For a foot in the door, and to really show your interest in treasury, I think the ACT is the one that helps people massively,” says Pierce.</p>
<p>Training courses over shorter time frames also offer opportunities suitable for working life. Dannenmuller, who attended one of Eurofinance’s programmes, typically no longer than a week, says: “Although they are intense, you aren’t away from your daily tasks for too long. This training helped me see how my work is linked together with the work of other departments, and injected me with motivation and confidence through theory, real life case studies and group exercises.”</p>
<h3 id="when-it-all-goes-wrong">When it all goes wrong</h3>
<p>As with any career, however, there are bound to be stumbling blocks along the way. As treasury assistants tend to be more junior, making mistakes can be daunting. “But it will come out that an error was made,” says Gillespie. “Therefore, make sure you have integrity.” This entails, she says, owning up to mistakes and, most importantly, thinking about how you are going to amend them. Being able to fix something is far better than hiding your head in the sand, pretending you weren’t at fault. “What this does mean is that when other responsibilities come to the forefront, people will trust you to do it correctly – and if you don’t, they feel confident that you won’t try and hide problems that need amending quickly.” Even the most senior executives, Gillespie continues, started from somewhere – and that isn’t a bad thing. In a recent conversation Treasury Today had with BP’s VP, Global Treasury Services, Debra Todd, she mentioned a remark which she makes to her team: “I’m not telepathic.” If they require something, or spot a problem, they need to tell her about it, Todd says. “Then I can either sort something out, or work with them to fix the problem.”</p>
<p>Senior colleagues also have a wealth of knowledge others can tap into. An official mentoring programme doesn’t need to be in place for employees to be able to ask those senior to them for advice. The reoccurring thoughts Treasury Today hears concur that most professionals are more than willing to share their understanding – and time – with others. And aptly so, as Dannenmuller says: “Treasury can be a mysterious world for a novice.”</p>
<h3 id="moving-sideways">Moving sideways</h3>
<p>Gaining further experience could involve a sideways step. There are, of course, many different roles within the treasury function. What’s more, there are other departments where transferable skills can be applied – record-keeping skills or bank fee analysis, for instance. “It’s the people that have done their research and know what their transferable skills from their current role are that are the most successful,” says Pierce. For example, those in an accounts payable (AP) position that have gained exposure to relevant cash flow analysis could begin to transition into a treasury assistant role. “Over the last year or so, there has been an increasing emphasis on personal development in treasury,” says Pierce. This makes it a great time to consider how to progress your career, whilst bearing in mind this might not be immediately in an upwards direction.</p>
<p>A sideways career move will build out your breadth of knowledge in treasury which, higher up the ladder, could make all the difference. “You have to figure out what you are good at and you are only going to do that if you try different things,” says Legal &amp; General’s Gillespie. And the opportunities are out there. According to her, treasury is a great place to meet other professionals, make friends and learn from others. You also hear of suitable vacancies and are more likely to receive recommendations from those who have worked alongside you in the industry.</p>
<p>This comes as a result of being someone who has a cooperative approach particularly important, as referenced earlier, to the treasury assistant. “It works both ways, however. If you ask AP people, for instance, for help, they are much more likely to do so knowing you’d do the same, rather than if you had sat in an ivory tower,” says Gillespie. People remember those that are willing to go out of their way to support the overall progress and efficiency of the whole organisation.</p>
<h3 id="staying-put">Staying put</h3>
<p>Whilst the preceding focus has largely been on progression and how professionals can expand their breath of experience, treasury assistants can generally be split into two kinds. There are a number that have found their place in this position – and are achieving great things for treasury departments.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>Practical experience is the most beneficial. That, and learning when to ask for help.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Jennifer Gillespie, Head of Money Markets, Legal &amp; General</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>“Corporate clients do highlight succession planning as a key criteria, but they are always looking for stability and candidates that want to stay in the role for the next five to ten years,” says Hays’ Pierce. “These professionals tend to prove themselves in one company, rather than move every year or so.” During which time, of course, they will see their responsibilities grow. More experienced treasury assistants will, for example, liaise with treasury managers about the company’s funding responsibilities and will be more involved in the decisions which ensure effective use of cash than those at an earlier stage of their career. Dannenmuller, for example, controls and monitors the excess cash, instructing and facilitating local entities on cash repatriation, as well as optimising the liquidity of EMEA entities in accordance with local regulations and treasury policy. Also, the earlier operational skills gained will allow senior treasury assistants to manage and guide others at this later stage.</p>
<p>The department, in fact, relies upon the treasury assistant to be able to collaborate and communicate developments to all of the affected parties. It is well documented that treasurers today should act as strategic partners to the business, and these lines of communication are crucial to the meeting of this goal. A successful treasury assistant should have their finger on the pulse of all of the department’s activities. “You have to be a good communicator and coordinator. By talking to colleagues and interacting with multiple stakeholders, you can visualise where you stand in the chain and figure out where and how you can help,” says Dannenmuller. “It develops responsiveness and reactivity, traits that often prove valuable.”</p>
<h3 id="in-the-midst">In the midst</h3>
<p>This supporting skill, acting somewhat as the seam between parts, is particularly in-demand when employers are looking for a treasury assistant on a contractual basis. For example, over busy periods, large treasury departments may need additional support. These new recruits will have to fit in fast – and keep up multiple communication links to ensure efficient operations. They will not be afforded a lengthy adjustment period. “When recruiting for contractors, employers will typically seek an experienced candidate who can hit the ground running rather than somebody who will need extensive support or training,” says Pierce. Contracting also provides greater exposure to a variety of different areas, she adds.</p>
<p>But regardless of whether someone is new to the role, a seasoned professional or taking on contractual work, the conventional activities treasury assistants undertake form key cogs in the treasury machine. A smoothly run department rests on a treasury assistant that can deliver.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body">
<h3 id="top-tips-for-climbing-the-career-ladder">Top tips for climbing the career ladder</h3>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Do not be afraid to ask for advice.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Experience may not be found where you expected. Taking on short-term roles or projects outside of the department can give you new perspectives.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Try and make sure you stand out by going the extra mile for colleagues.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Plan where you’d like to be, and how best to get there – but don’t expect it to always be a straightforward route. You can learn from bumps in the road.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Know where your strengths lie, and make sure to keep a record of accomplishments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Maintain a healthy balance between your work and home life.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Mind the gap]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=8A24CF53D510F80B9FFC86AA6590398E]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>As the end of the year fast approaches, some may be thinking about New Year resolutions, or perhaps how yet another year has passed by without those determinations being fulfilled. Treasury Today looks at the best advice for making 2016 the year for climbing up the career ladder.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=491BE8CCDB938DE430D53CB75CAA630A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9DBE7707BA769DC3B28E107924B03C14"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E28532EEAD9C2C09ABAA54E6DB18B330"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2478CFD55CB913153AD9F217A59CECDD"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=008ECA083FE784411E7F8E0D78C0B824"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Ant bridge" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8A24CF53D510F80B9FFC86AA6590398E" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ant-bridge-unity-232113886-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8A24CF53D510F80B9FFC86AA6590398E"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Whilst making resolutions for the upcoming year isn’t an activity everyone takes seriously, it is always pertinent for corporate treasurers to reflect on their personal successes to date, and then consider how they can continue on a fulfilling career path. The treasury community is full of ambition and drive, the pinnacle of which was showcased at the Treasury Today Adam Smith Awards Asia 2015 very recently. Amidst such talent, how can the individual stand out? Rising up the career ladder certainly involves increasing visibility at every available opportunity, but for treasury professionals on the starting rungs of the ladder and for those boasting more experience, equally, it is essential to discover ways of maximising potential.</p>
<h3 id="what-are-you-missing">What are you missing?</h3>
<p>“It is always a good idea to start enlarging your scope of responsibilities,” advises Maciek Müldner, Financial Director for Skanska Property Poland. In order for candidates to boost their employability, they need not only to make themselves highly visible within the company, but they should also show willingness to engage with aspects that are not directly connected with their day-to-day role. As an example, Müldner explains that employees should be inviting themselves to meetings. In turn, this will expand a worker’s understanding of a broader range of topics as well as serving to distinguish them from the crowd – after all, not everyone is willing to give up their time.</p>
<p>As Mike Richards, Managing Director of treasury recruitment specialists MR Recruitment, explains: “Once you develop excellence within a particular area of finance, why wouldn’t you utilise that to your advantage?” Financial reward is on offer and, in these challenging economic times, he asks who could blame an expert for wanting to be rewarded as such?</p>
<p>But, for those with broader ambitions, “they need to appreciate what experience they are lacking,” says Müldner. This involves deep thought on all achievements (or lack of) throughout what has been a challenging economic period. Richards suggests asking the following questions: Have you achieved what you set out to achieve? Where have you fallen short? What have you done to achieve your aims? “After all, these questions will be asked of you at your next job interview,” he says. “If you are satisfied with the answers then you are on the right track to achieve your next move.”</p>
<h3 id="specialise-or-cross-functionalise">Specialise or cross-functionalise</h3>
<p>When answering these questions, the responses will of course largely depend on an individual treasurer’s background. As Chris Robinson, Director at TransactionBanking.com and Senior Tutor EuroFinance explains: “Where candidates come from tends to have implications on how they move up the career ladder in terms of which skill set gaps they want to fill in.” For instance, an assistant treasurer with a background in accounting will need to broaden their treasury perspective. Someone who is focused on treasury operations would clearly need to learn more front office skills. How high an individual potentially wants to rise in the treasury world is also a factor, he comments.</p>
<p>It is worth reinforcing Richards’ belief that diversification of skills isn’t the only way to the top. Indeed, many argue that having a specialised set of skills is more beneficial to the treasury function. In short, it depends on personal circumstances, and opinion remains divided on which path is the best to take in light of current economic difficulties.</p>
<p>Direction does seem to be intrinsically linked to seniority. Given that the world’s various and ongoing economic crises have expanded the scope of the treasury function considerably, it is often desirable to have a cross-functional skillset. But for Müldner, this is more applicable for the more senior roles. For instance, he explains that to be a CFO, you need “to harness a combination of skills, including – but not limited to – accounting rules and processes, financial controlling and operational understanding.”</p>
<p>For junior positions it can be more beneficial to have a specific skillset – whether that’s technology, project financing or another niche area – from which the incumbent can build on as they assume more responsibility. Ultimately, for the hiring company, it is about commerciality and what value the employee can bring to the role; a broad range of low-value and poorly executed skills has never been in demand. This is increasingly the case as corporate treasurers now occupy a prominent strategic position. So what historically was seen as a supporting role was turned by the onset of the financial crisis into a more prominent and proactive position to the extent that senior management pay much closer attention to the skills the treasurer brings to the table. Indeed, Martha Pierce, Senior Consultant at Hays explains: “Employers can be quite demanding when it comes to finding the right candidates that fit all the requirements of the role.”</p>
<h3 id="add-to-your-skills">Add to your skills</h3>
<p>The need for corporate treasurers to be well-prepared for every eventuality is clear, but this gives rise to the perennial argument about whether experience or education prevails as the preferred route to a successful application. A good treasurer, of course, needs to have a solid understanding of the fundamentals and this can come through study. “Businesses are increasingly risk adverse and now use qualifications as a standard to identify people suitable for the job,” says Pierce. “Those individuals that are both accounting qualified and ACT qualified – before later moving to the MCT qualification – are now faring best when it comes to progressing in their career.”</p>
<p>But classroom-based learning holds little credibility if a candidate cannot then apply it effectively in the real world. “It is about a balance,” states Robinson. “On one level, qualifications demonstrate academic capability but a lot of treasury is not necessarily learnt, it’s gained from experience.” It is without a doubt that professional qualifications are necessary to secure certain roles but vocational study is generally best kept part time if balance is to be achieved. Indeed, whilst additional qualifications do go a long way towards developing a career (it demonstrates commitment, sending a strong signal to employers about future ambitions), exiting the labour force, however temporarily, can be ill-advised, particularly when the economic climate is depressed or changing quickly. There is also the thorny issue of age. “For younger employees, taking one or two years out to study for an MBA might not be a problem,” notes Robinson. For those of more mature years, and likely having taken on more commitments, “going off to get those qualifications is going to be a challenge.” This does not mean further education beyond a certain age is inevitably problematic. Robinson suggests that training courses running over a few days, or one working week, can offer corporates a workable option. Continuing Professional Development accreditation can be given for training courses and attendance at certain events, conferences and webinars add to the overall experience.</p>
<p>What’s more, such courses are often used to avoid treasury departments becoming siloed. “When you do the day job, treasury can be quite isolated,” he explains. “It is easy to end up specialised in one area of treasury and not be exposed to others. Training can get you up to speed relatively quickly.” The goal for a treasurer, he argues, is to be sufficiently well-educated to know the right questions to ask the experts, “but they should also be experts in a few things themselves.” In this way, the inquisitive treasurer will secure a broader – and well-developed – treasury experience for him or herself.</p>
<p>One way of matching mature experience with enthusiasm is to consider mentoring. Mentorship is a personal developmental relationship in which a more experienced or more knowledgeable person helps to guide a less experienced or less knowledgeable colleague. The mentor may be older or younger, but will have expertise that the mentee seeks. Some firms have a formal approach to this, setting up schemes for introductions and progress monitoring, whilst others may sanction an ad hoc approach. However it is approached, its value as a career-booster is acknowledged. Pui Yee Lee, Vice President and Treasurer of Singapore-headquartered Kulicke &amp; Soffa Industries, is a case in point. She was mentored by Marie-Astrid Dubois, Assistant Treasurer, EMEA and Asia for Honeywell and was happy to endorse her experience when Dubois was recipient of the 2013 Treasury Today Woman of the Year Highly Commended Award. “I worked for Marie-Astrid for over eight years as a Treasury Director in Brussels, Shanghai, and Singapore. She was my greatest advocate and continuously provided me with the encouragement, experience and responsibility necessary to succeed and to develop. Marie-Astrid’s mentorship has been invaluable to my current success.”</p>
<h3 id="ideal-traits">Ideal traits</h3>
<p>Contrary to common belief, the most successful corporate treasurers aren’t necessarily the ones who appear to dedicate all the hours in the day to their job, taking little time for anything other than career progression. In fact, coping with a tough day at work is made a lot easier with a balanced lifestyle. Working longer hours when needed but going home on time (or early) when it is appropriate shows confidence in the individual’s own abilities. Good employers seek professionals who manage a sustainable work/life balance, enabling them to think and function efficiently.</p>
<p>A key part of that process for treasurers is to be able to function socially. “Businesses are always looking for candidates that are personable and able to develop relationships within the business and with the banks,” notes Pierce. This is a skill which can to an extent be learned by individuals immersing themselves in such situations (even public speaking, which many would view with horror). But there are certain traits which are even more desirable, and which can be honed to optimise the suitability of a candidate for a role. This includes the ability to bring solutions instead of just problems to managers (showing this type of foresight and commitment to a collaborative working environment is likely to be rewarded). Also, a tendency to avoid finger-pointing or blame-shifting is appreciated. It gives colleagues confidence that they will not be attacked when their backs are turned. According to Pierce, “at the treasury analyst level, personality and cultural fit can often be the difference between whether or not you get the job.”</p>
<p>However, recent research from Robert Half in the UK reveals that accounting and finance professionals increasingly need to fine-tune the so-called soft skills. Reflective that finance operations can no longer work in isolation, learning to interact with and manage a variety of personalities and conveying financial information in non-financial terms were identified among the most common cross-departmental challenges. But the skills that contribute to the success of professionals most were: leadership skills (60% of 200 CFO and FD respondents agreed), strong technical skills (47%), effective communication (33%), a competitive nature (32%), futuristic outlook (30%), strong interpersonal skills (17%) and risk taking (16%).</p>
<p>In order to succeed, corporate treasurers can’t rest on their laurels – instead, they must demonstrate a range of skills that contribute to treasury’s position as a strategic partner to the business.</p>
<h3 id="a-case-in-point">A case in point</h3>
<p>For Jiameng Teah (JT to her friends and colleagues), Assistant Treasurer at Vodafone, “having an open mind and being resourceful and innovative” is essential when building a life in treasury. Speaking at this year’s ACT conference in the UK, JT told how when she moved to England from China several years ago, she had to overcome certain immigration and work permit complexities to forge a successful career. By making several intelligent tactical moves away from her intended law career, she was able to ease herself into the right place at the right time in order to start climbing the treasury career ladder.</p>
<p>With an initial move into accountancy with Deloitte, she progressively undertook professional studies for ACA, CTA and MCT. “The MCT qualification came about by chance,” she reports. Having been co-opted onto a tax audit project for a US-listed company, she found herself being introduced to the world of derivatives. With her interest in the treasury space piqued, she moved out of tax into a corporate finance and treasury advisory role, joining her firm’s transaction services team. “But at my level, I was no more than a spreadsheet monkey,” she recalls. “I was working 11 hours a day and had no life.” With four hour commute on top of this, it was time for a major change.</p>
<p>“With the help of a few recruitment agencies, I discovered the world of corporate treasury,” says JT. She moved to her first position at Tate &amp; Lyle where she had “the time of my life.” The role was “very broad” allowing her to take on every aspect of treasury. Unlike the “static profession” of tax, bound as it is by rules in books, treasury was more in line with her outlook and personality, being essentially fast-paced and “forward looking.”</p>
<p>Her next move came quite by chance, JT finding herself sitting next to the Group Treasurer of Vodafone during the conversation-heavy lunch break of an S&amp;P presentation on ratings. Six months later the call came through to talk more and in another three months the always opportunistic JT was on the move once more. Her new role gave her the broad sweep of treasury experience she craves, but with the added attraction of a truly global scope, travelling right around the world in a treasury day, but always tackling something different. It sounds full-on, especially when giving the treasury view to the business units, “but the way to deal with this and not completely lose my life is to develop the skill of picking what’s relevant.” By deciding what is applicable to each situation, and often with just a few minutes to give a response, she states the important skill is not to give “the War &amp; Peace version of everything.”</p>
<p>JT also speaks passionately about career development for women in treasury, commenting on certain challenges, including the often “confrontational” nature of male financial professionals. “It’s important for women to develop a thick skin; but just by digging your heels in and being firm at the negotiation table it does not mean you are aggressive,” she says. Although she feels the industry is making significant inroads (Treasury Today champions and organises a successful series of international events around this theme, for example) she stresses the importance of mentoring and making connections to strengthen the career opportunities for aspirant women in treasury.</p>
<h3 id="move-on-up">Move on up</h3>
<p>With economic volatility now the new normal, it is important for all treasury professionals to stay ahead of the curve, and rather than hoping for the best, making the best for themselves. Proactivity is essential, keeping a record of accomplishments and communicating them where appropriate. In order for candidates to fill in the gap in their experience, Pierce advocates asking the line manager for more responsibility or the opportunity to get involved in other areas. “Most managers are more than happy to say ‘yes’ if employees demonstrate eagerness to learn,” she notes. “But when organisations cannot offer opportunities, we are seeing candidates looking for new roles that allow them to fill in the gaps in their experience.”</p>
<p>This is advice treasurers with high aspirations can ill-avoid to ignore. Job opportunities at the higher echelons of corporate treasury have always been few and far between but there are numerous ways to improve career prospects, and being proactive should be seen as compulsory for progression right to the top.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Maximising your potential]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Sep 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“What can a treasurer do to maximise his or her chances of one day becoming CFO? Are there any particular qualifications or experiences that might be beneficial?”</em></p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="Maciej Müldner, Finance Director, Skanska Property Poland" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2015-09-tt-01-qa-maciej-muldner-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=0EBDE5CC2E6C327202A40E4FCFF884C8" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Maciej Müldner</h3>
<h5 class="title">Finance Director</h5>
<h5 class="org">Skanska Property Poland</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Whilst it may seem obvious, it is important to point out that in order to become a CFO, first and foremost, you have to want to. It should be part of your career plan because any aspiring CFO must understand the capabilities, knowledge and experience needed to fulfil that role. You can find a lot of ideas and descriptions of what the role entails on the internet (posts on LinkedIn, for instance). My personal view is that a CFO is a business partner; they are the person that ensures the president or owner of a company is comfortable with what the organisation does and the financial impact of all of its business activities. This involves business decisions that are properly considered and presented and ensuring, as much as possible, that decisions show the expected result.</p>
<p>There are, of course, certain things a treasurer can do to improve his or her chances of becoming a CFO. It is often the case that the treasury function, and those working in it, are rarely seen by the rest of the organisation so they need to make themselves more visible in the company. Employees can invite themselves to meetings even if these meetings are not 100% connected to their day-to-day role. This is one way of gaining the desirable understanding of the business beyond a current role, for a CFO needs to get much closer to the operational side of the business – understanding the consequences of their decisions and how operational processes work, for instance. For those who wish to gain such skills, first, they need to appreciate what experiences they are lacking. A few typical areas where treasurers need to gain knowledge are accounting rules and processes and controlling. Controlling can refer to financial controlling, an area which treasurers usually work quite closely with, and business controlling. This is where a treasurer could boost their marketability: how to do a budget, how to forecast, the best way of following up on a forecast and the key performance indicators (KPIs) that drive a business, for example. It is also a good idea to start expanding your scope of responsibilities.</p>
<p>In a way, a CFO lives in two worlds – the operational world and the financial world – so it is crucial to build up good communication skills in order to explain difficult and complicated concepts in a way others can understand and relate to. Whilst this is a challenge on the one hand, on the other if you can build up this skill, it is invaluable in fulfilling the CFO’s role of being an operational voice. Moreover, this involves having the capability of translating business decisions into numbers, both seeing and explaining the impact on the company’s bottom line.</p>
<p>To summarise, as a CFO you need to harness a combination of skills. Typical financial qualifications are good to have, as well as a Master of Business Administration (MBA) or alternative forms of management study. Treasurers will develop the relevant skills when focusing on transactions within a given benchmark or certain value to achieve. Accountants, will reflect on what has happened by analysing the accounts. But, as a CFO, you need to combine both – as well as looking into the future, all the time translating reality into numbers and numbers into reality. There is no ‘safe haven’ for a CFO, so whilst many talk about it, the role isn’t for everybody.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="Mike Richards, Founder and President, MR Recruitment" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2015-09-tt-01-qa-mike-richards-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F3583E033AA6B34B6D17EC23E8F831CF" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Mike Richards</h3>
<h5 class="title">Founder and President</h5>
<h5 class="org">MR Recruitment</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>For the ambitious, it is always a good thing to look towards the future and, with regards to maximising your chances of one day becoming a CFO, I have the following advice. Of course, it is extremely useful for corporates to have a background in a wide range of business functions (rather than have spent their entire career within treasury), although I do find that many treasurers tend to have developed their treasury or finance expertise within just the treasury ‘stream’. This isn’t always intentional, however. It is often by accident rather than design: once you develop excellence within a particular area of finance why wouldn’t you utilise that to your advantage? Financial reward is on offer and, in these challenging economic times, who could blame an expert for wanting to be rewarded as such.</p>
<p>This being said, of the CFOs that I know with a background in treasury, all have also worked in other areas within finance as part of their career path, eg they have become experts in the treasury area and have moved into other senior business roles or senior finance positions. Thus, they have made active choices to move into financial controller or planning roles in order to experience finance as a whole, enabling them to better sell themselves when applying for CFO and/or FD positions.</p>
<p>In short, for a treasurer looking to move up the career ladder, take a moment to reflect on what you have and have not achieved through the challenging economic period we have seen over the past three to five years and ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Have you achieved what you set out to achieve?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Where have you fallen short?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>What have you done to achieve your aims?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>After all, these questions will be asked of you at your next job interview. If you are satisfied with your answers then you are on the right track to achieve your next move. If you are not happy with your answers, why would anyone else be? A track record of success within the treasury function is simply the precursor to achieving the next role. In order for corporates to enhance their chances, all business related qualifications are beneficial. Professional treasury examinations are extremely useful as a benchmark of expertise and an MBA gives a wider business view. Whether business experience overrides professional qualifications, however, depends on the audience.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="Mustafa Kilic, CFO and Member of the Board of Directors, Candy Group Turkey" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/2015-09-tt-01-qa-mustafa-kilic-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=2A9250F0CDB2465ABACAA658B2981236" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Mustafa Kilic</h3>
<h5 class="title">CFO and Member of the Board of Directors</h5>
<h5 class="org">Candy Group Turkey</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>It goes without saying that the environment for all finance professionals is changing and, with that, the role of a CFO has also evolved. Within the last ten years, the CFO has started to become more of an integrator and co-ordinator in addition to the more traditional operator and protector tasks. There is also more competition in the business environment. This is pushing CFOs to gain new skills and the ability to sustain and continue business performance is more important than ever. Against this backdrop, and in order for a treasurer to maximise his or her chances of becoming a CFO, it is important to understand the capacity of your organisation’s business operations. Each and every company will have individual operating systems and their own ways of working with them. A CFO first needs to understand the range of areas the business operating system interfaces with in order to run effectively. This, of course, is a prerequisite for writing and applying policy.</p>
<p>Moreover, with the state of the current regulatory environment, expectations to understand the impact of such regulations, are higher than ten years ago. Understanding these procedures, and the company’s exposure to risk, is crucial in a CFO’s role. I cannot even begin to compare the tools we are using today to measure risk with those from say ten years ago. But this isn’t all a would-be CFO needs to be aware of. The world is now more connected than ever before and news spreads fast: crisis management and communication skills are important in order to fulfil the expanded role of a CFO in today’s world. In this position, you need to learn how to deliver both good and bad news.</p>
<p>One of the positives is that, as treasurer, you are already in touch with some of the most critical contacts within the CFO’s reach – financial institutions (FIs) and suppliers, for instance. Treasurers have the added advantage that they’ve worked with cash flows and have experience with this element of a company’s business operating system. It is also second nature for a treasurer to look for financial risk; they understand how operational, financial and strategic risks are all linked and can trigger each other. In their existing roles, treasurers have already built up a good perspective of credit and market risks too.</p>
<p>In addition, treasurers are always in touch with the key working capital management components: cash, payables, receivables, inventory, funding and profitability. Thus, they develop the key skills which allow them to contribute to the liquidity, transparency and general effectiveness of the organisation’s cash management. The skills that are becoming increasingly valued in CFOs I would summarise as follows; an in-depth understanding of an individual company’s business operating environment; risk management skills; the ability to communicate well with people from governments; banks and also local populations. Such skills are all within the reach of treasurers who are ideally placed to add these abilities to their current skillset and maximise their chances of becoming a CFO.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“What’s new in the Latin American treasury space? Are there any cash management or payment innovations treasurer should be aware of, for instance?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>
</div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[A day in the life: interim treasury]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=BC41B59D084FEBFA64C952A572053806]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AE2CB90FAFF289DBD53AF4257377770A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EC4D18B3ACB55763EEF7A8481F954DBB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=475DC195FFFE9237B98D6075B26228AF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=709BE8284196B863E0D8F3D2A8CB8C42"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=383769BBE2146F90230F25D53E32A6F8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Bunch of red matches with a green match sticking out in the middle" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BC41B59D084FEBFA64C952A572053806" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/ss-one-match-standing-out-from-the-crowd-leadership-difference-concept-253710055.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BC41B59D084FEBFA64C952A572053806"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>For the interim treasurer, a number of skills must fall into place to be a success. It can be hard work finding the next assignment but the rewards both financially and in terms of job satisfaction can make it all worthwhile. What pleasures and pains does the role hold for practitioners?</em></p>
<p>There is no doubt that the life of the interim treasurer has its up and downs and would not suit anyone who needs security in their working life. But the very nature of interim is such that change is inevitable and from one assignment to the next the exponent will never really know what to expect until that assignment is agreed. But for those that make a living this way, this is part of the attraction.</p>
<h3 id="finding-the-next-assignment">Finding the next assignment</h3>
<p>The next assignment – whatever and wherever it may be – could arrive in a number of ways and for the seasoned professional it could even be just a news item away. All treasurers need to understand the relationship between business and the rest of the world and paying attention to the news can inform of sudden developments in other regions or countries that require immediate attention to protect the company from on- and off-balance sheet financial risks (such as FX risk). But for the proactive interim treasurer, a news item could be the cue for the next assignment.</p>
<p>Although around 50% of his work comes via major recruitment agencies such as Michael Page or Krongaard, interim treasurer, Thomas Stahr says many of the assignments he takes are the result of regularly searching news items, looking for signs of a treasury in need of assistance. “If I read the comment of a CFO who says his company improved sales but, because of exchange rates, it actually reported a loss, I see that as a signal to get in touch,” he explains.</p>
<p>Sometimes this speculative approach yields a new assignment, sometimes not – a claimed ‘hit rate’ of around 20% seems like a positive result and Stahr agrees that it works well for him. The news is but one alternative source and Stahr reveals that he also keeps a watching brief on the job advertisements for permanent treasurers. “If I see the same advert for three or four weeks I will contact the company and offer my interim services.”</p>
<p>It is this level of resourcefulness that keeps the interim in the game but cannot be the only source of assignments. Being in a position to trade on a solid reputation and owning an impressive contacts book also plays an important part in securing the next job, says Erik Teiken, an interim treasurer also of many years’ experience. Of course, it takes time to build a reputation, so for the new interim he suggests working closely with the main recruitment bureaux that have a stated interest in the interim world, such as the two mentioned above and the likes of Robert Walters and MR Recruitment. The larger players, he notes, will have more locations and corporate connections and more staff to work on behalf of its clients but he says do not dismiss contacting the smaller agencies that handle treasury recruitment as these will potentially offer a more personalised approach to your search. “When I’m looking I call them all, frequently. If I’m on an assignment I always tell them when I will be available again. Once you’re in their system everyone in that bureaux should know it.”</p>
<p>It will be presumed that the prospective interim has accumulated a number of years’ professional experience in various branches of treasury and finance before deciding to take the new route. To get started it will be useful to begin calling upon contacts made over the years – in the corporate, banking and technology sectors and even through the national associations of corporate treasurers (ACTs). A concerted effort in this respect will alert the community to the fact that the new interim’s services are now available for hire. It is a good idea also to keep notes on each contact and build a file of what was said and when; it makes it easier when approaching them again.</p>
<h3 id="stand-out">Stand out</h3>
<p>There is an element of competition in seeking an assignment, warns Teiken. Whoever submits the application first will stand a greater chance than all the others – so speed is of the essence. But the right match of skills is the final decider. It is very hard and perhaps even impossible to become an interim treasurer without first having solid experience on the payroll of a corporate. The addition of relevant professional and academic qualifications count almost as much as experience in this highly competitive space. In terms of their education, training and event opportunities, the various national treasury associations can help all treasurers broaden and validate their skills.</p>
<p>The bad news is that with the banking industry losing many jobs over the past few years, there are entrants now from this arena too. These people may not be treasurers per se but, as Jean-Claude Jossart, an interim with 13 years’ interim experience under his belt says of this situation, “the main enemy of the banks today are former bankers.” Knowing most of the tricks of the trade and the constraints that the banks face will stand them in good stead in the interim world.</p>
<p>Indeed, Jossart worked for 20 years as a corporate banker (in front, middle and back office) before entering group treasury. He knows only too well that a business looking to manage its banking relationships would be well-armed indeed with such inside-knowledge on-board. But the point to understand here, he says, is that treasurers need to acquire a broader range of skills and knowledge than ever before to stand out. The more widely experienced and qualified the individual, and the better the contact list, the better the chances of securing the best paid and most interesting assignments. “Interims need to work out their own approach to the market,” he says, but adds that today, being known as a very good professional is no longer enough. “Flexibility is important and you need to be ready to work on the international market if you want the most interesting mandates.”</p>
<h3 id="the-first-days">The first days</h3>
<p>Having secured a new assignment, depending on the actual mandate (it may be operational or more strategic), one of the first duties of the interim is to be introduced to immediate colleagues and then to extend this out as far as possible to those within the wider group that have connections with treasury. The arrival of an interim treasurer may, says Jossart, be best initially announced via internal messaging/intranet so that even staff who are not immediately connected with the assignment are fully aware of what is happening. This can help establish the interim with the necessary authority, setting forth the plans and avoiding potential conflicts and misunderstandings.</p>
<p>The first practical task should be to carry out an assessment of the structure and culture of the organisation, to get a feel for how things are done and how they could be done under the auspices of the assignment and in line with the competences of the people involved. It may be necessary to try to map out the existing IT system and treasury-specific technologies at least as they relate to the reporting content and structure. Grasping the status quo is essential to secure the resources available for the assignment – including the co-operation of all external partners such as banks and technology vendors – and will almost certainly be part of any project-based mandate.</p>
<p>An assignment is not just a practical exercise. Interims “really have to care about the requirements of those above, below and around you in the hierarchy,” states Stahr. Managing change is almost inevitable for an interim but these changes should, wherever possible, be seen as “new opportunities.” He acknowledges that change is not always seen in such a positive light by existing employees and as such the work of an interim may face some resistance. If this is the case it will usually appear at lower levels of the company hierarchy. “You frequently have to take care of these people first because they are the basis of the business – you cannot work without their support,” he advises.</p>
<p>Although he acknowledges that “everybody knows you are only temporary” and that the regular employees will always assess interims as such, Teiken believes that most of the time the individual will be accorded the professional respect they deserve. Whilst never having had any real confrontation to deal with, he notes that if someone does not want to co-operate, for whatever reason, there are always ways to “encourage” their involvement. “It is about getting everyone in line; after all, we are all working towards the same result.”</p>
<p>Contracts may last for a few weeks or extend to a year or more. A short-term assignment can sometimes develop into a longer-term involvement if project scope is allowed to creep (as distinct from necessary additions to allow the work to be executed fully). “Many times at the start it is not clear what the exact scope of the assignment is,” notes Teiken. “It will be discussed with the management on day one but an interim has to widen and deepen that conversation, finding out where the boundaries are, defining the goals and expected results.”</p>
<h3 id="handing-over">Handing over</h3>
<p>As an interim, there will come a time when an assignment must end. An experienced and effective operator will frequently be approached by the employer with an offer of full-time employment. This may be of interest but really, says Stahr, the focus from the outset should only be on completing the task at hand. “Don’t think about starting work that you know you have no chance of completing within the agreed time; the project must always come first.” In any case, he says, most professional interims would probably prefer to live with “all the advantages and constraints” of their chosen path.</p>
<p>There is thus a clear need to define an end-point and prepare for the handover. “Do not underestimate the effort required for this very relevant exercise,” states Jossart. In fact, preparation for handover should commence right at the start: setting up documentation that tracks progress, including any changes will enable the interim not only to check that the assignment has been fully met but also aids handover to a successor at the end.</p>
<p>Writing very clear guidelines and explaining what has been achieved in the project is part of the procedure. Detailed notes should aim to re-assert the goals set at the beginning, offering analysis and advice on all changes that have been implemented. For Jossart, this document should be submitted at least four weeks prior to the end-date, allowing time for additional meetings with relevant parts of the business to ensure everyone understands the impact of the work carried out and that there is agreement that it has been executed effectively.</p>
<p>Once an assignment has concluded it is quite common for an interim to keep the dialogue going with the company. “In most cases it does not end with the last day; I always remain in contact with my successor and with the people who hired me,” says Stahr. References from each assignment (assuming it was successful) will build up credibility and aid the process of securing each new job. But be warned: “You’re only as good as your last three years or five assignments,” says Teiken.</p>
<h3 id="advice-from-the-professionals">Advice from the professionals</h3>
<p>Enthusiasm for, and a deep and ever-expanding knowledge of the subject is an essential part of successful interim work. “Try to define your own level of competence versus market needs; treasury is subject to constant evolution so try to propose the optimal match,” advises Jossart. Up to the minute technical skills and broad practical experience are vital and should be augmented with formal study (industry and academic) and additional certification such as PRINCE2 for project leadership is a bonus. Development of soft skills, such as change management or negotiation skills, are also a necessary part of continued success if this field, he says. The interim must also be able to listen attentively but never be afraid to ask the client for a clear profile of what they want: the success of the assignment is paramount.</p>
<p>When tackling an assignment, always be open-minded and see every change as a new opportunity, “but don’t try to change too much in the first few days and weeks,” advises Stahr. He believes that it is essential to respect the employees and that the interim should always try to put themselves in the position of every colleague, regardless of the function in which they are employed. “Try to put yourself in the position of the people around you, what they might think about you, the work you do, the organisation and so on,” he says. “Understand that communication is everything.”</p>
<p>The chance to work in many different types of businesses, meet new people, constantly learn new skills and, potentially, earn more than a salaried treasury position suggests that interim is the ideal treasury job, and for some it is. It comes with one major caveat: “It can be a risky job, with sometimes no assignment for several months,” warns Stahr. Under normal circumstances a gap of a couple of weeks might be engineered purposefully by the interim to refresh before starting the next role; this is not always an option, especially in mainland Europe. “It was a really hard time just after the financial crisis hit,” admits Jossart. Today, as the Eurozone crisis continues unabated, there is still market caution on the continent. “It’s tough at the moment,” he muses.</p>
<h3 id="market-pressure">Market pressure</h3>
<p>Conditions are exacerbated by the flood of cheaper resources on the market. Indeed, with many non-treasury corporate finance professionals and corporate bankers having lost their jobs due to cutbacks they are naturally seeking a living from what they know; the interim space is a natural attraction. For every interim, staying competitive is essential and this means keeping contacts, skills and knowledge up to date and remaining proactive and flexible in the search for work. “You must remain active in the market otherwise people will forget you,” urges Jossart. “But you must consider that there will be times when you are not being paid.” However, with fewer jobs and more candidates, the rates of pay have dropped by up to 35%, at least in mainland Europe, he warns.</p>
<p>A typical rate for an experienced and well-qualified interim would be around half of the rate for partner-level advisory services from one of the Big Four consultancies, says Stahr. Curiously, working for a large and well-known business can actually see the daily rate drop slightly: “the better the reputation, the lower the rate,” he comments. These companies know that they can pay slightly less because the interims they employ are subsequently able to leverage the credibility afforded to them by such an assignment. The reverse is true of course for less well-known corporates and slightly higher rates may be commanded.</p>
<p>Despite the risks and uncertainties, the lifestyle of the interim treasurer is one that its best exponents swear by. “You can achieve great success in a very short time; you can improve something and make many people happy – not just those in the department but even up to shareholder level – and this can be a great feeling,” says Stahr. Permanent treasurers may also experience the joys of success, of course, but as an interim you have a ready-made goal and the mandate to go ahead and make a difference.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Upgrade or delete]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Feb 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=47D35BBE9F4920F3475798E7FBAF65B2]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>At a time when the role of treasurer has taken on a new level of importance, up-to-the-minute technical knowledge is vital. But, as the rest of the business wants to hear what the treasurer has to say, it is time to evaluate the so-called ‘soft skills’ too.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A7CBDBEF8E3B616ABF7E8FCE5CB0336D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4D94715257C500B99D0295C884B92BA5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=02515260EC8C1462DAE3E228D9E05076"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8B178BC81E75224A720076A65CCAF771"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=402C5E293B3970955D83A87B1E06BFE0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Snow level lift" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=47D35BBE9F4920F3475798E7FBAF65B2" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/careers/snow-level-lift_228951160-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=47D35BBE9F4920F3475798E7FBAF65B2"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>For fans of the long-running UK sci-fi drama series, Doctor Who, the phrase “upgrading is compulsory” will summon images of the fearsome Cybermen. Their intention is to delete all human memory and emotion, turning victims into highly-focused cybernetic killing machines. The notion that humans can ‘upgrade’ by improving their knowledge to specialist status is nothing new and is one to which many would readily subscribe, especially in a professional context.</p>
<p>Indeed, as the treasurer’s role diversifies, there is an increasing demand for in-depth training in specialist areas such as tax, covenant loan agreements, accounting standards and technology. But as treasurers move further into the business the need is for highly intelligent professionals who are also able to communicate clearly with colleagues from other functions. Ruthless ‘cybernetic’ efficiency is one thing, but the value of the so-called ‘soft skills’ of relationship building and people management must also now come to the fore.</p>
<h3 id="expanding-horizons">Expanding horizons</h3>
<p>The perception that treasury is a highly specialised function hidden away from the rest of the business was never a helpful view, said Jan-Martin Nufer, Director Treasury &amp; Funding for multinational petrochemicals firm, Borealis Group, speaking at the 2014 EuroFinance conference in Budapest. He has watched the role develop with growing confidence since he started his first assignment back in 1994 when “hardly anyone knew what we did”. Now, as it sits astride risk management, funding and cash management, Nufer sees treasury as “one of the central functions in the company”.</p>
<p>It is, he argues, high time treasury practitioners started positioning themselves even closer to the business so that they can take advantage of every opportunity to expand their understanding of the wider organisation. Those that have the technical and personal skills and who can combine broad market experience, contract negotiation experience and a lot of analytical know-how will, he believes, find themselves in a very good position to take their careers forward too.</p>
<h3 id="learn-from-the-locals">Learn from the locals</h3>
<p>Progress may involve tackling assignments requiring skills not covered by traditional academic and professional study. These can be loosely incorporated under the banner of ‘cultural awareness’. Hennie de Klerk, CEO of South Africa-based treasury services provider, Treasury One, says treasury and finance functions entering the country for the first time will really need to get to grips with the diversity of approaches likely to be met when tackling fundamentals such as cash management, forecasting and bank operations. The norms of banking in Germany or Spain, for example, are often quite different from those of South Africa. There are, he comments, “many technicalities around the South African market which corporates from outside will not be used to”.</p>
<p>South Africa is increasingly the stepping stone for corporates moving into other parts of Africa and the country’s Big Four banks (Absa, Standard Bank, Nedbank and FirstRand) provide services across much of the continent. Despite this, for any business seeking to expand beyond South Africa, de Klerk notes that it is unwise to expect basic treasury functions to be handled in the same way as their European or US operations. Whilst more sophisticated economies such as Kenya and Tanzania may meet treasurers’ needs, the level of technology and connectivity may be less well-established in other jurisdictions. “Every country is different,” he states. Even South Africa is not as standardised as the European market, he notes. “But if you then work with a different bank, such as [the pan-African] Ecobank to reach further into Africa, it becomes a whole different ball game.” In many cases, he warns, “as soon as you cross the border from South Africa there is a ‘technology cliff’”. A means of working around each situation must be found or cash and liquidity management and forecasting quickly become major issues.</p>
<p>In terms of everyday operations, de Klerk also warns of a steep learning curve, even for experienced corporates, when building up their understanding of processes and procedures as they move out across sub-Saharan Africa. For those that are new to the region, the curve is far steeper and seeking help on the ground is advisable, either from the Big Four banks that dominate the transaction banking space across the region or from well-versed local consultants and solution providers.</p>
<h3 id="never-forget-the-soft-skills">Never forget the soft skills</h3>
<p>Despite near-constant development, the principles with which treasurers work have broadly remained the same over the years, noted David Dunkerley, former Group Treasurer of Cable &amp; Wireless Communications in the UK, another speaker at the 2014 EuroFinance Budapest conference. Its best exponents have always possessed a mix of business skills, people skills and technical knowledge. But where in the past the emphasis was on the technical, in recent times, particularly since the financial crisis, he feels treasurers have had to be “more front of house”, becoming “a little more outgoing” in their approach.</p>
<p>The ‘soft skills’ of building relationships, managing people and expectations are, it seems, in demand in the treasury space. Nufer refers to the nurturing of these relationships as being part of a “business partnering” exercise where the expansion of treasury can be explored.</p>
<p>Soft skills, for Nufer, are “extremely important”, especially when working in a culturally diverse operation. Borealis’ centralised treasury operation deals with people from many cultures and countries across the world. There needs to be “sensitivity” to those differences but the company’s leadership supports the notion of inclusivity and is keen to develop its staff. It has invested a lot of time and effort in personal development and has a programme that primarily encourages leadership skills and the raising of individual profiles within the organisation. People from across the business meet to exchange ideas and get to know each other, developing the all-important softer skills. “It’s one of the ways in which we can come out of our Ivory Tower,” acknowledges Nufer.</p>
<p>“Communication is the key to success,” states Karen van den Driessche, Director Treasury EMEA at Avnet Financial Services in Belgium. “A computer can crunch the numbers better than most people but as treasurers we can build relationships – with the CFO, with the business, with the team – and I don’t think anything can replace human contact and communication.” But, she adds, regardless of the industry or company setting, people need to feel “at home” with the process because if there is any discomfort the communication quickly breaks down into“noise” and. “Being open and transparent is vital, not just in treasury, but in any function.”</p>
<p>Communicating in an open and honest fashion can bring together a wider view and appreciation of the finance agenda. A critical mass can be attained within a larger operation where this approach becomes the norm. It may be that treasurers feel they do not have the time to reflect on the context and position of their function within a business; the demands of consistently delivering a high quality service are surely many. But, says Dunkerley, “if we are blessed with that time, then we should step back and look at the development of our role and that of our treasury team” because doing so can yield some worthwhile results.</p>
<h3 id="live-the-brand">Live the brand</h3>
<p>One of the career buzzwords currently doing the rounds is ‘personal brand’. Many people don’t know what their personal brand is or what it says about them – or even that they have one. The fact is that, in one way or another, everyone has a brand and yet few do anything to develop it (Gene Simmons, bass player with the rock group KISS – and a serial entrepreneur – once famously said: “I don’t want to be in a band, I want to be in a brand”).</p>
<p>Perhaps the concept of developing a ‘personal brand’, as espoused by many career gurus (and Gene Simmons), may be too much for some people. But if ‘brand’ is substituted with ‘reputation’ then a clear-cut case can be found for taking up the challenge because reputation and success are tightly bound together.</p>
<p>According to author and entrepreneur, Kevin Daum, there are three key steps to building a powerful personal brand. Daum urges followers of the programme to remain authentic, consistent and harmonic. Being authentic requires the individual to be true to themselves, sticking with their core values, skills and history. “Being self-aware helps a lot here,” he suggests. Consistency requires the individual to decide what is truly important to their image and then to “give concerted effort to practice what you preach”. Finally, an individual needs harmony. This may be achieved in a professional context by managing time, activities and the people around you. Living in chaos may suit some, but he advises the individual to “surround yourself with people who celebrate and enhance your life”. In this way it will be possible to carefully manage your time and resources “to support the reputation and lifestyle that will result in your preferred future”.</p>
<p>If that still sounds too much like New Age nonsense, Dunkerley has a more prosaic approach. “In establishing a notable treasury reputation there is a need to deliver on the short-term goals of the treasury and the business but there is also a need to take on increased responsibility and to develop that too.” Reputation-building is, he says, “about constantly chipping away at the stewardship role”. This is what got him interested in treasury in the first place; that principle remains the same. “What gets most treasurers out of bed in the morning is the knowledge that the buck stops with us. We are in charge of those risks and financial assets, and their stewardship is at the forefront. In building upon your reputation, take it back to basics and work on that.”</p>
<p>Understanding other people and processes is important, but the ‘authenticity’ that Daum talks about plays an important role for van den Driessche too. “Throughout my career, the companies have changed but I haven’t,” she says. Of course, she has learnt and developed personally but the core of who she is remains intact. “What you see is what you get; I’m open, honest, I work hard and build on trust,” she asserts. This approach has seen her rise up the ranks. But it is not an approach she has cultivated per se; it is simply the firm acknowledgement of who she is. “It’s too difficult to play games, trying to remember what you said to play a role.” Although an individual’s rough edges may be filed away over the years, van den Driessche ultimately promotes the need “to be vocal, be yourself and deliver what is expected of you”.</p>
<p>Building a solid personal reputation (or ‘brand’ if you prefer) is obviously beneficial, but then Nufer argues the case for avoiding being “labelled”. Rather as some actors risk being type-cast in a particular role and then forever struggle to be taken seriously in any other part, it may not be healthy in career terms for treasurers to specialise too much, at least not too early in their careers. In smaller organisations it may be possible for individuals to shape the space around them, absorbing many skills, but for many it may be more prudent to find a point somewhere between ‘specialist’ and ‘jack of all trades, master of none’, “without compromising the authentic self”. Indeed, van den Driessche points out that it is advantageous to have a level of cross-functional knowledge that enables the treasurer to be able to talk knowledgably with colleagues from other departments.</p>
<p>For Dunkerley, “an emphasis on flexibility”, where the individual is able to adapt to unforeseen changes and disruptions, is the key to progression. “As treasury professionals, we have an inherent skillset,” he notes. “While some people are happy to remain in a transactional role for their entire career, others want to become specialists or adopt a more general outlook; we all know where we sit on that line,” he says.</p>
<h3 id="follow-your-heart">Follow your heart</h3>
<p>Treasurers can end up being the victims of their own success. They take on a new position, build a professional treasury around them and deliver a host of efficiencies by streamlining processes and implementing systems that automate many activities. But, after a few years, some reach a point where boredom sets in and they need a new challenge and the cycle begins again. It may be possible to move to a multinational where the scope of possibilities is wider, but most people in treasury work in smaller organisations where opportunities for spreading their wings may be few and far between. But even when you have risen up through the ranks, you have attained seniority and a decent salary but it is still not enough, what happens then?</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>A computer can crunch the numbers better than most people but as treasurers we can build relationships – with the CFO, with the business, with the team – and I don’t think anything can replace human contact and communication.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Karen van den Driessche, Director Treasury EMEA, Avnet Financial Service</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>In the case of Netherlands-based treasurer Philip Wielenga you start your own business. With more than 15 years’ high level international treasury experience under his belt, Wielenga had reached a point where he had pretty much “seen it and done it”. Repeating the pattern over and over by moving to yet another company did not appeal; being the master of his own destiny certainly did. Following a discussion with a career coach he realised something significant: “All my life I had been following the money, not my heart.” Trying to find a position outside of treasury mostly resulted in rejection on the grounds that he was a long-haul finance specialist.</p>
<p>Wielenga decided to get out of that “never-ending cycle”. In establishing Wieltec Treasury Services he felt he was now in a position to continue using his specialist skills but satisfy his own agenda and personal work ethic. Whilst he wishes he had made the move earlier, he acknowledges that he had to undertake many different treasury roles over the years in order to build up an understanding of ‘real-world treasury’ that would give his company credibility. To this end, he also undertook a range of academic and professional studies. But Wielenga has also had to work hard to build a contact list from across and beyond the industry.</p>
<p>“When I started, I had a phone, a Macbook and a piece of paper and started calling people in treasury 40 hours a week non-stop. Nine months later, I signed my first deal. When you call someone for the fifth time, people will start to respect your perseverance.” But having developed the business he says he still takes the time to go back to basics. “We pick up the phone to find out what the key challenges are within our business relationships. This underlines one of our core values: keep a personal approach.”</p>
<p>Many successful treasurers have a natural inclination towards the risk-averse; the kind of viewpoint that insists on return of capital not return on capital. Going it alone is a risk too far for some and Wielenga admits that in the beginning it can be difficult. “I’ve seen an empty refrigerator at home,” he reflects. This is a scenario that would dissuade many, especially those with a family to support. Everything he read about people who started companies said the same; there will be difficult times. But, he asserts, in the end it is worth it. “I used to read about how entrepreneurs have a vision of what they do,” he says. “For 15 years I didn’t get it. Now I know exactly what they mean.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Are you ready for the future?]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2014 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>From entering, approving and settling trades, to opening a new bank account, technology permeates almost every aspect of treasury work. And as treasurers look to 2015, many will ponder how advancements in the tools available to them will alter the function in the future. Here we speak to a number of treasury technology experts to find out what developments we can expect in the year ahead, and beyond.</p>
<p>We begin with mobile technology. It seems that no corporate treasury conference would be complete without a mobile treasury panel, although treasurers may sometimes wonder when exactly the promises of technologists will materialise into usable and useful solutions.</p>
<p>In the wake of a number of developments that could transform the mobile payments space, 2014 could be considered the year of mobile. In April, the UK’s Payments Council launched Paym, the first mobile payment solution with the ability to link between nearly every current account in the UK using only mobile numbers. Later in September, Apple unveiled plans for its Apple Pay digital wallet. However, while most high-profile mobile news has been on the consumer side, what about the mobile technology that treasurers can get their hands on?</p>
<p>“Pretty much every treasury RFP we receive includes an element where prospects want to know what our mobile capabilities are,” says Paul Bramwell, Senior Vice President – Treasury Solutions at SunGard. “Mobile is still at the novelty stage, where treasurers think it is interesting to have a strategy for it, but in reality its usefulness is still limited at present.”</p>
<p>The fact is, many key treasury tasks do not lend themselves well to mobile as a platform. Think about it: would you really want your treasury manager doing FX deals in the pub? Or buying commercial paper on the train to work? Probably not. It is for this reason that mobile penetration is unlikely ever to be as pervasive in corporate treasury as it is in the consumer space. “We don’t see there being such rapid migration to mobile as there has been in retail,” says Alastair Brown, Head of eChannels in the Global Transaction Services business at RBS. “There, the whole value chain is translated into a digital solution. In treasury departments it will supplement, rather than replace, what’s already there.”</p>
<p>That said, mobile can be a useful channel for monitoring and approvals, and it is here that technology could develop rapidly over the next few years. “The segregation of duties and the approval queue are key aspects of treasury. The ability to log in to your treasury application using a mobile device whenever you have some approvals waiting for you is a big draw,” adds Bramwell. “For payments which are high-value, low-volume, and critically important to the business, mobile approvals give far greater flexibility to the treasury department whose treasurer is often away from their desk.”</p>
<p>In future, the mobile medium could also greatly enhance visibility into cash and investments. “Dashboard components built into mobile treasury applications allow CFOs and treasurers to see what their current position is,” says Bramwell. “Valuable information such as how much cash they have, the mark-to-market position of their derivatives, and the number of deals that have gone through in a day, give them a snapshot of exactly where they are at a given time.”</p>
<p>The notion of flexibility that mobile solutions can offer treasurers is compelling. This flexibility is also inherent in another developing channel: the cloud.</p>
<h3 id="in-the-cloud">In the cloud</h3>
<p>Corporates are increasingly looking to the cloud for solutions to their treasury technology needs. “One of the big emerging trends is cloud deployment, which is becoming more accepted now as a deployment medium and methodology,” says SunGard’s Bramwell. “Treasurers were perhaps initially sceptical of the web as a medium in terms of security and usability, but they are becoming far more convinced now. There are several players who offer treasurers software-as-a-service (SaaS)/cloud solutions, and the market has adopted web-based services as a very viable option.”</p>
<p>Reval is one such player offering SaaS treasury solutions. “SaaS is a delivery model that allows us to create an environment in which a multi-tenant community shares the same version of application software to run their treasury risk management solutions,” explains Phil Pettinato, Chief Technology Officer at Reval. “The economies of scale and the accessibility of cloud and SaaS technology enable corporates to operate their global organisation on a platform that works across all their different locations.”</p>
<p>Pettinato says this kind of flexible solution is especially beneficial to growing companies and those that are acquisitive. “These are configurable, extensible and extendable solutions corporates can expand upon to accommodate their growth and meet regulatory changes in the marketplace,” he adds.</p>
<p>For corporates that are uncomfortable sharing data in a public cloud outside their own firewall, there is an alternative. “There is a significant minority of companies who want to control their data in a secure private cloud environment,” says SunGard’s Bramwell. “That means having the infrastructure dedicated to you as an individual company, with no shared elements, which then offers considerably more scope for customisation.”</p>
<p>Private cloud services are more costly than those in the public cloud, but they do give corporates the ability to bring the process back in-house at a future point should they so wish.</p>
<p>The increase in the use of cloud-based services within the treasury is linked to another technology trend worth watching – the rise to prominence of the Chief Technology Office (CTO) in the corporate world.</p>
<h3 id="the-rise-of-the-cto">The rise of the CTO</h3>
<p>Formerly the preserve of technology companies, now corporates in a variety of sectors, not to mention banks, are appointing their own CTOs and CIOs (chief information officers; they differ in that CTOs are typically responsible for technology innovation and development, while CIOs focus more on the organisation of technology) to keep pace with technology advancements.</p>
<p>In the UK for example, drinks group Diageo, hardly known for its technology credentials, has a dedicated CTO, and in May, Deutsche Bank appointed a CIO for its Corporate Banking and Securities and Global Transaction Banking business.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Mobile is still at the novelty stage, where treasurers think it is interesting to have a strategy for it, but in reality its usefulness is still limited at present.”</p>
<p><cite>Paul Bramwell, Senior Vice President – Treasury Solutions, SunGard</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This trend could be interpreted as a positive and proactive step in embracing technology outside the tech sector. However, the creation of a standalone role focused on technology can create challenges in treasury and finance if the CTO is not in close contact with other functions impacted by technology. For instance, if the implementation of a new TMS is led by the CTO with too little input from the treasurer or CFO, the project is likely to end in failure.</p>
<p>“The problem with the CTO role is that there is a separation of roles,” says Ian Pearson, a futurologist at futures consultancy Futurizon. “As more advanced technology is integrated into payments and cash management systems, if you’ve got a CTO that is distanced from the finance or treasury department, these need to be brought closer together. There should be some overlapping function that forces them to have regular meetings at the very least to make sure that adequate security is in place, that they are using the right technology, and that this technology is compliant with the company’s existing finance systems. Today this is too separated in many companies.”</p>
<p>This improved communication and visibility between functions is one evolution that could well take place in increasing numbers of MNCs in the years to come, but within the treasury function itself, visibility, particularly over cash and liquidity management, looks set to remain a challenge.</p>
<h3 id="moving-on-from-the-financial-crisis">Moving on from the financial crisis</h3>
<p>Following the turbulence of 2007/08, the way corporates manage their cash and liquidity has evolved, partly because many treasurers realised their control processes were overly lax, but also because they are more wary of relying on a single financial institution to handle all their transactions. The increasingly stringent regulation on banks has also had an impact. This has led to treasurers monitoring their positions more frequently and in more depth. It has also resulted in the expansion of the number of banking relationships a company has. As these two trends look set to continue, the role of technology should become ever more important to the treasurer.</p>
<p>“In the past, corporates would typically have a single bank providing all their liquidity needs, and the treasurer would view the company’s positions periodically. Now the active monitoring and management of their cash positions is more of a pressing business need, and for MNCs this is often across accounts at multiple financial institutions,” says Mike Jackson, Head of US Cash Management at Fundtech. “Even if a bank isn’t meeting all of a company’s liquidity needs, they still need to have a technology solution in place that allows their client to aggregate all the relevant information and closely manage their position.”</p>
<p>Just as the financial crisis forced treasurers to review their cash and liquidity management policies, it also made many corporates take a step back to look more closely at their risk management and mitigation. One key way to address this is by analysing the data arising out of treasury operations. But in order to analyse crucial data such as historical banks transactions, for example, treasurers are often hamstrung by the technology they have in-house: the typical reporting tool in a treasury management system (TMS) often limits analysis to a 12-month period at best, especially if the business has an annual, repetitive nature to its cash flows.</p>
<p>It is here that in the future banks could come to the aid of their clients with the wealth of data they collect on their behalf. “Treasurers in general probably don’t realise the potential benefits available from the data that comes from what we have transacted on their behalf,” says RBS’s Brown. “We have spent a lot of time thinking about the technology mechanics around handling big data, such as stitching data together, making sure the data set is consistent, and eliminating redundancy or duplication. The question is, what do corporates want to get out of this massive asset? Now we are working in close collaboration with our clients looking at the areas they are trying to get information on – this is going be a big differentiator over the next 12 to 18 months.”</p>
<p>He adds that as the pressures of regulation and resource constraints continue to impact treasurers, they are likely to seek outside help – notably, though not exclusively, from banks – to make use of their data. “Corporate treasurers are telling us that they are expected to do more and more – they have to take a bigger risk agenda and take a bigger role in the strategic decision-making of their firms, and they are under cost constraints. It is a role in change,” he says. “Based on the data from transactions we process, we as a bank are in the useful position of being able to provide an across-the-board view of the client’s business. The question we need to address is what will tomorrow’s corporate treasurers want from their data?”</p>
<p>So far we have looked at developments that, while they are ones to watch for the future, are nevertheless already starting to have an impact on treasury operations. Now we look at a more ground-breaking advancement.</p>
<h3 id="brave-new-world">Brave new world</h3>
<p>Looking further ahead, nascent technologies such as wearable devices and augmented reality could have a profound impact on corporate treasuries. As with many new technologies, wearable technology will likely make an impact on the consumer space before becoming widespread for use in treasury and finance.</p>
<p>Visor technology, such as the Google Glass, launched in May 2014, could be of use in retail by providing instant price comparisons and facilitating contactless payments. Futurizon’s Pearson says this comparability capability could also be of great use to some corporates. “Augmented reality and visor technology could potentially generate huge savings for companies that they can’t achieve at the moment,” he says. “For example, local stock managers could glance at an item in a warehouse and be given information on how much it cost, how much energy it uses, the alternatives available, and the savings that could be made. It is a very strong potential tool for optimising costs, and can go to a management level.”</p>
<p>Augmented reality could also impact negotiations. Imagine sitting down to negotiate with a supplier or banking partner armed with all the information you could ever possibly want. “This technology could offer every advantage possible in negotiation,” adds Pearson. “You can negotiate from a position of extreme strength knowing just about everything there is possible to know about a competitor – you will effectively be able to bring in an entire team to provide you with real-time figures.”</p>
<p>However, this could consequently create an ultra-competitive environment that diminishes trust in the negotiating room, similar to a chess player who might feel that playing an opponent backed by a supercomputer is neither fun nor fair. “There could be a backlash against using the technology in this way, as people might not want to feel under pressure all the time. Rules could be drawn up to ensure this kind of technology cannot be taken into the negotiating room,” he concludes.</p>
<h3 id="future-proofing-treasury">Future-proofing treasury</h3>
<p>As they look at the technology challenges and opportunities that lie ahead, treasurers must be careful to future-proof their businesses. If they pick the wrong technology, they could be confronted with the costly problem of obsolescence a few years down the line.</p>
<p>“Technology moves on and it moves on fast,” says SunGard’s Bramwell. “Corporates need a technology partner that can adapt very quickly and easily to make sure they don’t end up obsolete, using technology that is unsupported, not by their vendor but by the underlying supplier of the operating systems.”</p>
<p>He cites Microsoft’s recent decision to end support for Visual Basic 6 and Windows XP as an example of technology that will soon be unsupported. This termination of support can create a serious audit issue for treasurers. Similarly, corporate users of the Microsoft.NET framework were faced with the choice of HTML5 or Microsoft’s proprietary Silverlight plug-in. “Silverlight was picked by many vendors, but it is becoming far less prevalent now and at some point it will reach end of life,” he says.</p>
<p>“Corporates need a clear strategy for the future,” concludes Bramwell. “You need to be ahead of the game, otherwise you could end up with obsolete technology.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Just the job]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jul 2014 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>As companies lift their crisis-induced hiring freezes, the job market is coming back to life. What is more, with corporates expanding into new territories, exciting career opportunities are opening up across the globe for corporate treasurers. Competition for the top jobs will be stiff, however, as – let’s be honest – after a significant lull in treasury recruitment, there will be many professionals out there with proverbially itchy feet.</p>
<p>This is not a reflection of the loyalty of treasury staff; rather it speaks volumes about the nature of treasury positions. “In my experience treasury roles have a three to four year life cycle,” says Mike Richards, Managing Director of MR Recruitment. “The first year is all about learning the role, the second is about applying this knowledge and the third year is focused on refining your work and your role. At the end of this third year, I find that tedium begins to sneak in.”</p>
<p>Former corporate treasurer, now Chief Financial Officer at Skanska Romania, Maciej Müldner, agrees: “There is a moment when your role becomes repetitive and you feel the need to learn new skills and face a new challenge,” he says. “For me this happened three years before I became CFO. It wasn’t a conscious choice, it is just something that happens and you know once it does.”</p>
<p>Often this turning point comes once all of the objectives that you have set yourself for your current role are achieved. “If you are satisfied you have ticked everything off – and have a proven track record of success within the treasury function – then you are on the right track to achieve your next move,” Richards believes. “But if you haven’t, this needs to be fixed before thinking about stepping up,” he advises.</p>
<h3 id="ready-to-go">Ready to go</h3>
<p>Once you feel ready to move on or up, one of the most important questions you need to ask is: where to? And this isn’t just a geographical or company-specific question; it should address all of your additional career aspirations. What salary level would you like to achieve? What position do you wish to attain longer term? How can you secure a new role that will provide job satisfaction?</p>
<p>Each of these aspirations will be personal of course, but there are certain standards to work towards. The tables below, for example, provide a good indicator of the average level of remuneration attached to the various treasury roles, as well as a guide to realistic salaries in 2014, compared with 2013. This data, from the 2014 MR Recruitment Survey, is collected globally and UK Sterling is simply the current choice of base currency for the survey. Conversions can be made using the following rates: GBP £ = 1, AUD $ = 1.851, CAD $ = 1.845, CHF = 1.459, EUR € = 1.198, SGD $ = 2.106 and USD $ = 1.661.</p>
<p>The same survey also looks at the factors which contribute to job satisfaction. The level of job satisfaction is positive overall for the industry with 68% of respondents happy in their role, although there is a bias towards the upper echelons of the treasury department.</p>
<p>“From my conversations with treasury professionals,” says Richards, “the key reasons for job satisfaction are power and control. The higher a treasury professional moves within the department the more control they have over the environment and direction of the department.” Richards believes that this is why at junior levels there is less job satisfaction. “You are at the learning stage of your career and if this is not managed correctly then frustration can begin to creep in.”</p>
<p>This begs the question then, how can a treasury jobseeker improve their chances of landing their dream role?</p>
<h3 id="turn-the-tables">Turn the tables</h3>
<p>One of the most obvious and yet most effective tactics when answering this question is to think carefully about the skills and attributes that your potential new employer is actually looking for, rather than just focusing on what you have to offer. Often employers are not looking to take on someone who has the potential to step up into a role or to train someone internally – if the pressure is significant and there is an immediate skills gap, experience and the ability to hit the ground running are required. “Many clients I speak to want carbon copies of their previous treasurers and often want the exact same qualifications, backgrounds and level of industry experience,” reveals Richards.</p>
<p>Post-crisis, employers are also seeking treasury professionals who can understand the business as a whole; keep a cool head when the heat is on; and apply knowledge from previous roles or experiences, thereby adding value to the company from an operational and strategic standpoint. “Of course, the core competencies of a finance person are expected,” says Paul Pomroy Senior Vice President and UK Chief Financial Officer, North West Division Financial Controller for McDonalds. “But for those working in finance to be promoted they also need to have a strong personality and a variety of business experience.”</p>
<figure>
<figcaption>
<h4 id="chart-1-average-compensation-by-position">Chart 1: Average compensation by position</h4>
</figcaption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="6">Total</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Position</th>
<th>Responses</th>
<th>Average base salary</th>
<th>Average car allowance</th>
<th>Average bonus</th>
<th>Average total compensation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody class="td-right">
<tr>
<th>Treasury Assistant</th>
<td>6</td>
<td>£26,241</td>
<td>£0</td>
<td>£1,263</td>
<td>£27,504</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Treasury Analyst/Dealer</th>
<td>55</td>
<td>£38,964</td>
<td>£273</td>
<td>£2,839</td>
<td>£42,076</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Treasury Manager</th>
<td>131</td>
<td>£60,399</td>
<td>£1,403</td>
<td>£5,204</td>
<td>£67,006</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Treasury Accountant</th>
<td>7</td>
<td>£47,221</td>
<td>£2,386</td>
<td>£3,679</td>
<td>£53,286</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Treasury Consultant</th>
<td>34</td>
<td>£93,986</td>
<td>£1,520</td>
<td>£7,811</td>
<td>£103,318</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Assistant Treasurer</th>
<td>71</td>
<td>£83,912</td>
<td>£3,401</td>
<td>£15,578</td>
<td>£102,891</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Deputy Treasurer</th>
<td>39</td>
<td>£103,212</td>
<td>£4,084</td>
<td>£22,457</td>
<td>£129,752</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>International/Regional Treasurer</th>
<td>100</td>
<td>£102,129</td>
<td>£5,560</td>
<td>£19,228</td>
<td>£126,918</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Group Treasurer</th>
<td>173</td>
<td>£130,946</td>
<td>£4,270</td>
<td>£38,692</td>
<td>£173,907</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p class="source">Source: MR Treasury Recruitment</p>
</figure>
<h3 id="diversify-to-improve">Diversify to improve</h3>
<p>Diversification is the order of the day therefore. And while this may mean taking a difficult step outside of your comfort zone, it can give you the opportunity to learn new skills and can enhance your suitability for more senior and/or executive positions in the future.</p>
<p>Indeed, Pomroy is a fervent believer in the benefits offered by undertaking a variety of different roles in the business in your career – and he has first-hand experience of the dividends this can pay. In 2003, Pomroy was offered a promotion in the finance department; he chose instead to take a sideways step into the business strategy department. This allowed him to gain new perspectives on the business and also to progress more effectively once he returned to the finance department. “The more senior you become the more you are expected to understand the broader business,” he says “moving sideways is therefore as important as taking a forwards step sometimes. In my case I was giving up the immediate promotion for the longer-term view.”</p>
<p>Similarly, Müldner sees his experience in different roles of the business as vital to his career progress. “Treasury is a great job, the problem is that it is extremely specialised and you need to expose yourself to other elements of the business if you want to move up.” Without this diversification of roles Müldner believes that he “would have had substantial challenges taking up this new position [CFO]. It is something I would strongly advise to treasurers wishing to progress.”</p>
<p>If the opportunity simply isn’t there to move into another part of the business, undertaking some additional training may be another route to improving your career prospects.</p>
<h3 id="formal-and-on-the-job-training">Formal and on-the-job training</h3>
<p>Treasury training and qualifications allow you to develop your existing skills and learn new ones, whilst also keeping up with the latest development in treasury and business. Interestingly, Müldner believes that in addition to building up one’s technical skills, training has a more pivotal role to play in the development of a treasurer’s soft skills too. And these soft skills such as, how to manage staff, he says, are a now a key requirement for any treasurer looking to progress up the career ladder. Having taken part in an internal management and leadership programme at Skanska to improve his own soft skills, Müldner explains that “although you do not get a certificate for taking part in these kinds of courses, they offer you valuable insights which can complement your technical expertise and help you get ahead.”</p>
<p>For Pomroy, presentation and communication skills are also increasingly sought after in senior treasury staff. “You need to be able to bring what you are presenting to life and do more than say something is happening,” he says. To develop these attributes, Pomroy recommends a mixture of classroom style learning, where you can grasp the fundamentals, and on-the-job experience which allows you to apply and hone these skills in practical situations.</p>
<h3 id="stand-out-from-the-crowd">Stand out from the crowd</h3>
<p>Aside from improving your technical and soft skills, striving to add value to the business is another good way to get yourself noticed. It’s a cliché to say that you should go above what is asked of you in your role, however, if you are looking to move up the career ladder, this is certainly something you will need to do. Being an excellent treasurer is one thing, but becoming a strategic business partner to the C-suite will help you stand out from the crowd when vacancies arise.</p>
<p>To achieve this Pomroy suggests that treasury professionals begin to “develop a close relationship with all sides of the business and understand why the business is successful.” He believes this will “allow you to become an effective business partner and strategic advisor.” It might seem like a difficult task to accomplish, and one that is not easy to kick-start, but when a new job is at stake, proactivity is a must. According to Müldner, “you have to just invite yourself into other areas of the company. Treasury can often seem detached from other lines of the business, so you have to bridge this gap.”</p>
<p>Candidates that are shy or introverted must also make more of an effort to stand out from the crowd – personality is a key ingredient in the hiring process. “You need to show an inquisitive nature and explore why things are happening,” says Pomroy. It is also important to show leadership and a willingness to help those junior to you develop. “Nurturing the talent pipeline below you is vital as these will be the people you will rely on when you move up,” he adds.</p>
<figure>
<figcaption>
<h4 id="chart-2-2014-salary-shifts">Chart 2: 2014 salary shifts</h4>
</figcaption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Role</th>
<th>2013 Average Salary</th>
<th>2014 Average Salary</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody class="td-right">
<tr>
<th>Treasury Analysts/Dealers</th>
<td>£41,416</td>
<td>£38,964</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Treasury Managers</th>
<td>£64,487</td>
<td>£60,399</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Treasury Consultants</th>
<td>£87,812</td>
<td>£93,986</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Assistant Treasurers</th>
<td>£78,833</td>
<td>£83,912</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Deputy Treasurers</th>
<td>£109,303</td>
<td>£103,212</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>International/Regional Treasurers</th>
<td>£107,643</td>
<td>£102,129</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Group Treasurers</th>
<td>£136,477</td>
<td>£130,946</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p class="source">Source: MR Recruitment</p>
</figure>
<h3 id="plan-ahead">Plan ahead</h3>
<p>Finally, it is helpful to have a long-term strategy in place to decide what you want to achieve in your career – and how to get there. Moreover, having a plan should help to ensure that you progress up the career ladder in a logical way, allowing you to continually learn and gain new experiences. Müldner has successfully used a plan to shape his career: “My career path was a conscious decision,” he says. “Maybe not the places I have worked at, but the roles I have selected, I knew what I was looking for.”</p>
<p>Likewise, Pomroy also believes a plan is important when looking to define your career, however he believes that being ready to take advantage of opportunities as and when they occur is even more vital. “You need aspirations of where you want to go,” he advises, “but more importantly you need to make yourself the most attractive candidate when the opportunity arises. While there is a natural career path, you never know when the right moment to take the next step will present itself.”</p>
<h3 id="becoming-cfo-tips-from-the-professionals">Becoming CFO: tips from the professionals</h3>
<p>Today, those working in the corporate treasury function have a wider remit within the organisation than ever before, and are increasingly involved in business development and executive decision-making. The good news is that this experience is invaluable, in particular for any treasurer wanting to become CFO. So, when there is the opportunity to get involved in a project that will give you exposure to new parts of the business, or allow you to get involved in high-level decision-making, be sure to put yourself forward.</p>
<p>As outlined above, it is advantageous to have a wider business background when looking to advance to senior positions. The majority of CFOs that recruitment expert Richards has had contact with have previously had experience in other areas of finance, not just treasury, he says.</p>
<p>While research indicates that the treasury skillset is proving increasingly desirable in CFO recruitment, the career path from treasury to the C-suite is being made even smoother by the creation of roles such as Deputy CFO. This kind of opening offers a great opportunity for an aspiring CFO to hone their skills and learn the ropes before stepping fully into the CFO’s shoes. So don’t feel the need to aim straight for the top – often a slightly slower or more circuitous route can be beneficial for long-term career success.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
</data>
