<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Digital assets promise opportunity beyond bitcoin]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>So far, the treasury interest in digital assets has focused on investing, and mostly in bitcoin. Now, however, attention is turning to other kinds of digital assets and not just for investing; they have the potential to transform how treasuries – if not whole businesses – are run.</em></p> <picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E79BAB940957126B03452C99C2E13D94"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A0D15F020D1F6D3FF1D921BC731AA9DE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8E70E676E968D1896A831F5B167DBA89"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=95D498B3DEE547CC092582BCFE4A1F9D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2351CF203D0AA0D6F78E8E33376C93FF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Plant growing on stacks of coins" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1A90491DE7A48B4094670163C5BAB48B" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1A90491DE7A48B4094670163C5BAB48B"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Legendary rocker Rod Stewart once gave Elton John a fridge for Christmas. Not any old fridge, mind you, but the latest one at the time. He’d spent £600 on it – which was a lot back in the 1970s – but when his fellow musician reciprocated with his gift, it paled in comparison. “He gave me a Rembrandt painting! I’ve never felt so stingy,” Stewart reportedly said.</p>
<p>Now in the era of digital assets, such a mismatch in generosity could be solved with tokenisation. Now you could buy a portion – the equivalent of £600’s worth – of the painting and make an illiquid asset easily tradeable. Or perhaps you want to do away with physical paintings and venture into the world of digital art. A non-fungible token (NFT) of Melania Trump’s eyes, a digital watercolour that is selling for 1 Solana (approximately US$180), perhaps? This seems like a bargain when compared to ‘Everydays – The First 5,000 Days’ by Beeple, a collage of 5,000 digital images that sold for US$69m at Christie’s in March 2021.</p>
<p>When it comes to digital assets, treasurers aren’t looking to the art world for their investment strategy, but they are considering other types. “People are being cautious, but at the same time they are also curious about this asset class,” says Manoj Ramachandran, Principal of Digital Assets at BNY Mellon.</p>
<p>The US-based bank has got involved in this space – with its Digital Assets unit – in response to client demand. Also, Ramachandran says, “the timing is right” because there is now greater clarity around the custody of digital assets. And there is also an emerging ecosystem of fintech providers that can support the development of various digital asset products.</p>
<p>“I would not say everyone is thinking about it – they are at the very early stage with their allocation of this asset class,” says Ramachandran. “I think it will be a few years until this is mainstream from a corporate treasury perspective,” he adds.</p>
<p>So far, the interest has been mostly on investing in cryptocurrencies, and Ramachandran notes that corporate treasurers became more interested after seeing companies like Tesla and MicroStrategy investing in bitcoin.</p>
<p>Anatoly Crachilov, Founding Partner and CEO at Nickel Digital Asset Management, comments that it is natural – given the nature of their business – for treasurers to be conservative when it comes to digital assets. “They have to be mindful of liquidity,” he says. If it is their first foray into investing in digital assets, they are most likely to venture into crypto and its most liquid asset: bitcoin.</p>
<p>Such an investment is increasingly being considered by corporate treasurers. For example, Nickel Digital Asset Management found in December 2021 that growing numbers of listed companies were investing in bitcoin. Their analysis revealed that 20 listed companies with a market capitalisation of over US$1trn have approximately US$9.3bn invested in bitcoin, after originally spending US$5.8bn. Geographically, the bulk of these companies – 13 out of 20 – were in the US or Canada.</p>
<p>For many, an investment in bitcoin makes sense for a treasurer’s portfolio. In a previous interview with Treasury Today, Brad Yasar, Founder and CEO of EQIFI, had something of a rallying cry of “Buy bitcoin!!” Even for those who aren’t believers in the cryptocurrency, he argues, they should think of an investment in bitcoin as an insurance policy.</p>
<p>Crachilov makes a similar case for investing in bitcoin for treasurers who may still be reluctant: if you allocate a small portion – 1% – the upside can still be significant, without being too exposed to the volatility. “Sizing matters,” says Crachilov, when it comes to a bitcoin allocation. He illustrates by comparing a traditional investment portfolio of 40% bonds and 60% equities, which are invested in the S&amp;P500, to a portfolio that includes 1% and 59% equities. He tracks their performance over a nearly nine-year period from 31st December 2012 to 30th September 2021.</p>
<p>The traditional 40/60 portfolio had a cumulative total return of 144.3% (annualised return of 10.4%) over that period, an annualised risk standard deviation of 9.8%, and the maximum drop – or drawdown – was 21.6%. If the portfolio is adjusted to include 1% bitcoin, the cumulative total return increases to 170.8%, the risk is 9.9% (not much of an increase), and the maximum drawdown remains the same. This drop is the same because the biggest decline was in March 2020 when there was a sell-off because of Covid. Crachilov argues that a treasurer could enhance their portfolio by including bitcoin – an uncorrelated asset class – because historically it has behaved differently from the equities market.</p>
<p>If a treasurer is feeling braver and increases their bitcoin holdings to 3% there would be a cumulative total return of 232.2% – a much larger figure – but the risk increases to 10.1%. At this point Crachilov says, “The benefit outweighs the risk – that is the beauty of this.” However, he notes, as you allocate more and more crypto, “At some stage it is way too risky – a single digit allocation makes perfect sense,” he adds.</p>
<p>Also, Crachilov argues that bitcoin has a role to play in an investment strategy if you are looking to protect against currency debasement, where the value of the currency is lowered. He points to the figures for the M2 money supply, which increased by 28% between December 2019 and December 2020 to US$19.5trn as part of the US pandemic stimulus. The only other time the M2 indicator has been this high, he says, is in 1943 when the US undertook a stimulus programme as part of World War 2. At that time, M2 increased 27%. Initially, the impact of that stimulus had a subdued effect on inflation. However, it came with a three-year delay and by 1946 inflation was 18%.</p>
<p>“Bitcoin is the logical choice” for protecting against this scenario, says Crachilov. Bitcoin has a “non-discretionary immutable monetary policy” which means that no entity can affect its supply. Approximately 90% of bitcoin has been released and the remainder will enter circulation according to a fixed schedule over the next 120 years. Investing in an asset like this provides a hedge against the US dollar becoming devalued, says Crachilov.</p>
<p>And for those who are still reluctant to invest in bitcoin because of its volatility, Crachilov argues that you don’t need to be a believer in its value increasing. Instead, you can trade on its nature as a volatile asset and invest without taking a directional view, and rather harness its swings in volatility.</p>
<p>Beyond bitcoin, there are other cryptocurrencies that are of interest, such as Ethereum. This is a more dynamic asset as it is upgraded more regularly. Also, it has a whole infrastructure of smart contracts, and is an interesting investment for those looking to diversify, says Crachilov. And for the more adventurous, there is investing in decentralised finance.</p>
<p>This is the space that Yasar’s EQIFI plays in, which is positioning itself a leader in the field, with a single platform for banking, trading and lending for fiat and cryptocurrenices. The defi platform is connected to a regulated bank (EQIBank) so that high-net worth individuals and businesses are able to transfer their digital assets from the platform into the regulated banking system.</p>
<p>Digital assets have many forms, and corporate treasurers’ interest is now looking beyond the simple investment strategies of bitcoin or other cryptocurrencies. BNY Mellon’s Ramachandran comments that there is demand from treasurers in other assets, such as tokenised cash as well as tokenised bonds.</p>
<p>Also, with offerings like PAX Gold, for example, it is possible to buy gold as a digital asset where one token – on the Ethereum blockchain – corresponds to one ounce of physical gold that is stored securely in a vault.</p>
<p>Tokenisation means that a physical asset can be transformed into parts – tokens – that are digital and can be used as proof of ownership or traded. They can make assets that are typically illiquid, such as property or paintings, more liquid by making it possible to invest in a portion of them. If you need US$50,000 urgently, you could sell off a portion of your home – by dividing it into 50 US$1,000 chunks for example – and allow a new class of investors to benefit from its rise in value. You get the cash you need quickly without having to sell your whole home. And the blockchain can cut out the intermediary, making it possible to do such a transaction without an estate agent or a solicitor.</p>


<blockquote><p>People are being cautious, but at the same time they are also curious about this asset class.</p></blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Manoj Ramachandran, Principal of Digital Assets, BNY Mellon</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Tokenisation has already been trialled in the property sector and a September 2021 study by Hamburg Commercial Bank and the Frankfurt School Blockchain Center (FSBC) found that 41 companies in 17 countries had already started to pilot tokenisation.</p>
<p>Dr Philipp Sandner, Head of the FSBC, comments on how digital assets is a broad class, and can include digital securities so that stocks and shares can be transferred using blockchain technology – which makes it more efficient for trading.</p>
<p>Ramachandran also notes there is interest in tokenised securities. He notes that from a financial assets perspective, any securities instruments have the “potential to leverage distributed ledger technology (DLT) to make the issuance and the transfer process more seamless and transparent – that is driving some of the activity in the market,” says Ramachandran.</p>
<p>And aside from the transfer of securities, there are other more ground-breaking uses of the technology. Sandner explains how it is possible for corporations to tokenise industrial assets, such as machines, tractors, planes, or trains. In the past, a company would have probably involved a leasing company so that they could afford to have access to such equipment. Now that model can be revolutionised because of the blockchain technology: it is possible to slice up the asset and offer it to a range of investors. And the asset could be thought of as a profit centre, which is paid for on a per-use basis. Using the internet of things, the machinery could have sensors on it. These connect to the blockchain, which is also linked to a payments engine and accounting software, so a transaction occurs every time it is used. Such a way of doing things has the potential transform how corporate treasurers work, says Sander. “This transforms how they think about the financing of assets,” he says.</p>
<p>In this kind of innovation, Sandner says, treasurers have a key role to play. They often underestimate the role they have to play in innovation, he adds. “Blockchain is very often related to finance – this makes the CFOs and the treasurers the people to drive blockchain adoption in companies,” he says. For anyone thinking they may be too far behind, Sandner says, don’t worry it’s not too late – you haven’t missed out. “Everyone can be part of this journey.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[So far, the treasury interest in digital assets has focused on investing, and mostly in bitcoin. Now, however, attention is turning to other kinds of digital assets and not just for investing; they have the potential to transform how treasuries – if not whole businesses – are run.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2022-01-02-tt-00-in__plant-growing-on-money-coin-stack-1110854234__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2022-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Alternative Investments]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Schuldschein: international appeal of the German private placement market]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>With the LMA recently reporting cautious optimism for growth in domestic Schuldschein issuance, but less so for international deals, is the German private placement market at a tipping point? We explore the purpose and meaning of this funding option for international borrowers.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1BD6D867E5F0C17D53A8D5387B993189"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1C050698FA7FDC4EA43BD91785E04150"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7030511DA0846C1062F6199FE3260D3E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8D35F9A7CEE44D249B773154CA1DAD66"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=084EF2A695500F66DD1D80D198957EF2"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Open train doors" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8AB3913885016F7BFBFC67BC47E04FC7" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8AB3913885016F7BFBFC67BC47E04FC7"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>When it comes to corporate funding, most companies will head straight to their banks – they are, after all, a safe and reliable source of capital, certainly for everyday use. But whereas larger, rated firms might enter the debt capital markets when seeking a significant cash injection for a specific purpose (M&amp;A, for example), their smaller unrated or lower-rated counterparts do not necessarily have that option.</p>
<p>This may not be a problem per se, but having a diverse source of funding, at least as a backup, is something most treasurers would favour under any circumstance. Knowing that other funding doors are open for every use, from the operational to the strategic, can give much-needed comfort not just to treasury, but also to senior management, the board, investors, buyers, suppliers and employees.</p>
<p>Under such circumstances then, it may be prudent right now for treasury to explore all the options. One funding source that has been steadily building a fanbase for some years now is the Schuldschein market (plural Schuldsheine). Although predominantly used by enterprises across the size spectrum in German-speaking countries, it has been quietly building up its volumes across other parts of Europe in recent years.</p>
<p>That said, it is still very much a niche market. Up until about four years ago, issuance volumes hovered below €10bn. For the last four years it has been over €25bn. In 2019, it actually did slightly better, reaching about €28bn. Generally, levels are travelling in an upwards direction.</p>
<p>Based on actual issuance, without cancellations and exchanges, UniCredit (using Bloomberg data and its own curated corporate news) calculated outstanding debt in the market of €89.1bn, as of February 2019. This, it concluded, meant that “demand for corporate Schuldschein loans as a stable and less volatile source of funding should continue unabated”.</p>
<h4 id="easy-product">Easy product</h4>
<p>Schuldscheindarlehen loosely translates as ‘a loan evidenced by a certificate of indebtedness’, the note itself being the ‘Schuldschein’. The market is governed by German law, being the result of hundreds of years of development in that territory. The offer is typically a senior, unsecured, private debt product that is a hybrid between a loan and a bond.</p>
<p>Although in documentary terms they are closer to a loan, they share similar marketing tactics to bonds. However, they are quicker to arrange and often less expensive than bonds as there is no requirement for Schuldschein notes to be registered at a stock exchange, and no corporate or debt rating is required.</p>
<p>They can be fixed or floating rate, with tenors usually set between three to ten years. Beyond ten years, Schuldscheine become Namensschuldverschreibungen (NSVs), which are legally a different (although obviously closely connected) product. More than one maturity at a time is possible – with bullet repayments, the borrower builds up its amortisation schedule with different maturities.</p>
<p>Lending amounts range at the lower end of the corporate debt scale, somewhere between €50m and €500m. Different currencies can be used, even within one issue. Euro is by far the most common, but USD, CHF and GBP are increasingly featured, with slightly more exotic currencies, such as Polish Zlotys, making the occasional appearance. Deals can be bi-lateral, privately placed arrangements, but the growth in the market appears to be syndicated, with perhaps three or four arrangers.</p>
<h4 id="investor-view">Investor view</h4>
<p>The initial set-up process involves an investor call or roadshow to drum up interest amongst the predominantly bank investor community. In much the same way as bond issuance preliminaries proceed, an information package will be created about the company, its intentions and prospects, detailing the proposed deal.</p>
<p>Borrowers, notes Penny Smith, Head EM Corporate Debt Origination and non-German Schuldschein, Commerzbank, seem to like the fact that they do not need a rating. It certainly saves the financial cost and administrative effort but, she adds, smaller companies are often looked less favourably upon by the big ratings agencies, even if fundamentally sound, simply because they do not have the financial weight to justify investment grade. There seems little point in depleting resources to achieve a low rating when, in this market at least, each investor carries out its own credit assessment anyway.</p>
<p>Because Schuldscheine are relatively illiquid, the debt is typically seen as ‘buy and hold’ by investors, which, as a result of that illiquidity, are mostly banks, says Richard Waddington, MD, Head of Loan Syndications &amp; Sales, and Head of Private Debt, Commerzbank. However, with the market split between the domestic German and the International, investor bases are different, he notes.</p>
<p>In Germany, investors are, in the main, financial institutions – the Sparkassen and Volksbanken, with some Landesbanken and a few commercial banking players. Internationally, the investors are almost entirely commercial banks.</p>
<p>The institutional market (such as the insurers, pensions firms, and money market funds) do not seem to be overly interested, these players tending to be driven by investment policies that demand only highly-rated counterparties. If, however, a rated issuer is deemed a worthy target, Waddington says institutional investors will always weigh up the relative value of their Schuldschein versus bond options.</p>
<p>This is not to say institutions are not interested in unrated issuers. Indeed, he notes that some specialist investors will take unrated credit on an ad hoc basis, again making a call on the relative value of the asset versus other investment options. And some Schuldscheine are attractive in their own right. He cites a recent German state-owned rated corporate entering the market, offering an attractive pickup on German bund yield. With debt securities issued by Germany’s federal government currently negative, he says some institutional investors have taken the bait.</p>
<h4 id="diversified-funding">Diversified funding</h4>
<p>For the international treasury community, using Schuldschein just as a means of funding diversification could be a prudent move in itself, says Smith. But it also opens up a new investor-base for companies seeking an amount that would be too small (less than €500m) to warrant going to the bond market, and for those with no wish to get a rating. What’s more, she says, pricing is often favourable.</p>
<p>As privately placed debt, Schuldschein is only loosely aligned with the US private placement (USPP) market. As well as offering longer tenors, the US market has a totally different investor base, comprising mostly US-based (and a few Northern European) institutions.</p>
<p>For borrowers, there is a big difference. It’s difficult to pre-pay a USPP as it requires a ‘make whole’ exercise, notes Smith. This means that a business having issued a USPP when rates were high, has no easy escape as it watches rates go lower. “There is nothing they can do about it, because if they pre-pay, they have to pay all the interest that owed,” she explains. “With Schuldschein, a floating rate issue is pre-payable on an interest payment date at par – no fees, no penalties.”</p>
<p>Growing interest in Schuldschein has possibly bothered USPP players, Smith adds. Indeed, before Schuldschein started picking up volume around four years ago, USPP was very much a USD fixed-rate product. “Now it offers floating rates, euros, and much more flexibility in what can be done.” It suggests a USPP market responding to stiffening competition.</p>
<p>In 2016, Commerzbank placed the first ever ‘green’ Schuldschein. Worth €550m, and with terms of three, five, seven and ten years, with fixed or variable coupons, it was issued by German wind-power firm, Nordex. The proceeds were primarily used to finance the acquisition of Spanish competitor, Acciona Windpower.</p>
<p>Certification as a ‘green’ financial instrument by DNV GL Business Assurance opened up the market to ESG investors which accounted for around 25% of all subscribers. In total, just over 50% of funding came from international investors, the remainder mostly coming from domestic German savings and cooperative banks. Other green issuances soon followed.</p>
<h4 id="green-credentials">Green credentials</h4>
<p>When Royal FrieslandCampina – Europe’s largest dairy cooperative, and the second largest in the world – sought a new stream of funding, it knew that, as an unrated company, it would need to think on its feet. And so it did. It’s green Schuldschein programme scooped the Highly Commended accolade in the Best Financing Solution category of Treasury Today’s 2016 Adam Smith Awards.</p>
<p>With a requirement for €300m per year to support its Route2020 strategy, it was looking both at appropriate acquisitions and climate-neutral growth. Working with Rabobank as its green structuring advisor, the company issued in five, seven, eight, and ten-year fixed-rate tranches (respectively at 0.93% for €48.5m, 1.39% for €176.5m, 1.71% for €30m, and 2% for €45m).</p>
<p>The proceeds were aimed at eligible projects under FrieslandCampina’s green bond framework, in line with the Global Dairy Agenda for Action’s ‘Dairy Sustainability Framework’. Most of the funding went towards reducing the environmental footprint of the company’s factories, with sustainable farmer development programmes in developing markets, and the development of healthier products, absorbing the remainder.</p>
<p>Since then, Unicredit data shows more green corporate Schuldschein loans have been issued. In 2018 there were five, including Enercity (€100m for renewable energy), Volkswagen Immobilien (€100m for real estate), Encevo (€250m for utilities) and Verbund (€100m also for utilities).</p>
<h4 id="market-expansion">Market expansion</h4>
<p>Although green Schuldschein is far from a mainstream product, not taking off with as much vigour as has been witnessed in the regular loan and bond market, Smith nonetheless is seeing greater levels of interest. With the recent adoption of LMA Green Principles, Schuldschein is clearly making headway. Indeed, with issuances that reference sustainability and ESG KPIs when setting interest rate levels, it has provided yet more flexibility, with the potential to open up the market even further, adds Waddington.</p>
<p>Indeed, as the market grows, especially outside of Germany, and products develop, he feels that Schuldschein is maturing nicely on the international stage. With treasurers increasingly looking at diversified funding, especially as liquidity issues abound, it should surely be on the radar of continental European corporates. But with India’s oil-to-telecoms multinational conglomerate, Reliance Industries, setting up a US$170m deal in 2019, perhaps Schuldschein is set for entrance on the world stage in the not-too-distant future.</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[With the LMA recently reporting cautious optimism for growth in domestic Schuldschein issuance, but less so for international deals, is the German private placement market at a tipping point? We explore the purpose and meaning of this funding option for international borrowers.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/2020-09-10-tt-5-ba__taipei-mrt-night-209459104__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2020-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Alternative Investments]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Alternative investments join the mainstream]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BCC24A41615E5CFA4562A26687F33402"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2E3DD2B78BFDB78BC7F67E1A4D3DFE2B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F1FBF5D43F7D010B7C578FCA6378408E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2F091FCC9357EBEA6207733B16F94F95"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=27D44916E3FF175E7F2F29221F2DF859"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Blurred people in the city" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A4410F645ED54C7089E72FB9CB16E988" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A4410F645ED54C7089E72FB9CB16E988"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>If you are a corporate pension fund trustee, the chances are that your exposure to alternative assets has increased considerably in recent years.</p>
<p>Despite a challenging investment environment, in which large returns have become ever scarcer, alternative investment managers have continued to attract record levels of capital, research shows.</p>
<p>The 2014 Global Alternatives Survey by investment consultants Towers Watson shows pension fund assets held by the top 100 asset managers that deal with pension funds increased by over 5%, from $1.16 trillion in 2012 to $1.22 trillion 2013. Corporate pension funds have been big contributors to this growth. Like other institutional investors, they are continuing to diversify their portfolios away from traditional growth asset classes, such as equities, and into the world of alternatives, where they are able to insure their portfolios against the volatility of equities. It is a trend which has gathered pace since the financial crisis.</p>
<p>Investment trends will come and go, of course. But as tempting as it is to dismiss the recent shift in favour of alternatives as little more than a fad, the reality is that these investment tools are not simply growing in popularity; they are, in fact, becoming increasingly part of the mainstream investment landscape.</p>
<p>Already, most of these assets are such a common feature in investment portfolios that most asset managers will tell you that they no longer even think of them as ‘alternatives’, they are just another vehicle that can be used to secure stable, inflation-protected cash flows over long durations.</p>
<p>Not only does interest in alternatives continue to grow, but the range of alternative assets is also broadening. Direct real estate – the classic alternative asset – may continue to be the most popular type of investment for the time being, but we are also seeing increasing interest in other, formerly peripheral alternatives, such as infrastructure and distressed debt, in recent years too.</p>
<h3 id="beyond-yield">Beyond yield</h3>
<p>To understand why alternative assets have become more prevalent in corporate pension fund portfolios in recent years, it would be helpful, perhaps, to take a closer look at the different characteristics of these tools and at what pension fund trustees hope to accomplish when they invest in them.</p>
<p>Corporate investors are not only changing the weighting they are giving to alternatives within their pension portfolios – they are also taking different routes to gain access to the asset class. Traditionally, most corporate investors make their first allocations in alternatives via the “fund of funds” route. By using a fund of funds, a professionally managed investment vehicle that allocates capital towards multiple underlying managers, investors are able to get instant diversification across sectors and geographies. There is a catch, however. Using a fund of funds also means the investor gets, in the words of Julian Brown, Director in the Investment Consulting team at JLT Employee Benefits, “a double layer of fees.”</p>
<p>“You have the underlying fees of the funds themselves first of all,” he says. Then, if anybody is doing anything over the top – allocating between, performing operational due diligence, consolidated reporting – there will be an additional charge on the top. “In the old days, it would be two and 20 at the underlying, and then one and ten on the top. That would mean there is a 2% management fee and 20% of all your profits are taken by the underlying managers, plus a 1% management charge and 10% performance fee by the fund of funds manager.”</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Alternatives AuM variation 2009-2013</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2014-11and12-tt-08-cm-chart-01-alternatives-aum-variation-2009-2013.png?la=en&amp;hash=FB4E8E7FEDC88E63F17A964E01C4B072"><img alt="Alternatives aum variation 2009-2013" height="935" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2014-11and12-tt-08-cm-chart-01-alternatives-aum-variation-2009-2013.png?la=en&amp;hash=FB4E8E7FEDC88E63F17A964E01C4B072" width="978"/></a>
<p class="source">Source: Towers Watson Global Alternatives Survey 2014</p>
</figure>
<p>The weight of such fees on investment portfolios is not insignificant. It means that investors require, at the very minimum, a 5% rate of return just to cover their fees. Accordingly, most investors go into alternatives with the expectation of high returns and, in the good times, that was exactly what they got.</p>
<p>In the early years of the new millennium, Brown was working as the investments officer at the UK’s Nottinghamshire County Council pension fund, when he first began investing funds in private equity. At that moment in time, thanks to the buoyant economic backdrop, investors like Brown had return expectations for alternatives that were very often in the “high teens”.</p>
<p>“That sounds incredible now, doesn’t it?” he exclaims. “But that’s why people traditionally wanted to be in alternatives. It was always thought of as the sparkle in the portfolio; the investment which will give you some extra returns.”</p>
<p>Look around and you won’t see much in the way of yield these days, however. In the period post financial crisis, those stratospheric returns have all but evaporated as central banks around the world cut interest rate benchmarks to record lows and embarked on programmes of quantitative easing. In today’s low yield world, investors are naturally less prepared to accept the extra layer of fees above the individual funds, and are exploring alternative routes, such as single-strategy funds, for example. “I think its forced investors to become a bit savvier, and so those fund of funds fee structures – they are just not prepared to accept them now.”</p>
<p>Even if the days when turbo-charged performance was the main attraction are now gone for good, that has evidently done little to dampen the growth of the asset class. Investors today are turning to alternatives, for the most part, because they want consistent, risk-adjusted returns that insure them against volatility in other asset classes; those ever mercurial equities in particular. If they are able to find that protection in an asset class that also mitigates the risk to their portfolios of price inflation, then so much the better.</p>
<p>“That is why we are seeing so much interest in alternatives such as infrastructure, forests, and some of the real assets,” says Olivier Lebleu, Head of International Distribution at the investment fund Old Mutual. “It’s because they tend to mean a low notional investment upfront, coupled with regular inflation proof cash-flows.”</p>
<h3 id="what-are-the-alternatives">What are the ‘alternatives’?</h3>
<p>The label ‘alternative investment’ immediately raises the question: alternative to what? Most asset managers agree that an alternative investment is any asset that is not one of the traditional asset classes such as equities, bonds or cash.</p>
<p>As such, alternative investments are a very broad asset class that includes under its umbrella a set of products ranging from hedge funds and private equity, to infrastructure and private real estate.</p>
<p>Here we take a quick look at what each of these investments has to offer:</p>
<h5 id="private-real-estate">Private real estate</h5>
<p>Globally, the real estate market has recovered reasonably strongly, after taking a hit from the subprime mortgage debacle. In Europe, it remains the main attraction in the alternatives space, with investors now said to be holding $5.3 trillion worth of real estate assets across the globe. There has been a small shift of capital into other areas, however. “I am seeing a rise in allocations beyond property, and I’m sure many of my peers would say the same,” says Old Mutual’s Lebleu.</p>
<h5 id="hedge-funds">Hedge funds</h5>
<p>The key thing about hedge funds is that they are able to short-sell. This is attractive to pension investors since it should mean that the funds are able to secure some form of return, even in a bear market.</p>
<p>“Investors understand that equity markets go up and down, but what you want from a hedge fund is a stable, absolute return profile,” says JLT’s Brown. In the hedge fund space there are, of course, a range of different strategies for investors to choose between, which can be levered to meet higher return expectations. “But even those are relatively modest compared to the old days of ‘corporate raiders and red braces’,” he says.</p>
<h5 id="infrastructure">Infrastructure</h5>
<p>Infrastructure has been an increasingly common target for investment in the UK in recent years. There are two drivers behind this trend, says Old Mutual’s Lebleu. On the supply side, the need for private funding has grown as the UK government, constrained by fiscal pressures, has begun to step back from the financing of large infrastructure projects. Then, on the demand side, recent years have seen companies accumulate huge pools of capital that have a need for cash flows that are steady and inflation proof. “Given that governments have an incentive to push this agenda, we have seen infrastructure come to the forefront of discussions in the UK, relative to other asset classes such as forestry,” says Lebleu.</p>
<h5 id="commodities">Commodities</h5>
<p>“Commodities tend to be quite a specialist asset class for investors,” says JTL’s Brown. If a corporate is already familiar with a particular commodity – an energy company that trades in crude, for example – it certainly helps, as understanding the complexities of the asset class is often the first hurdle.</p>
<p>“The thing with commodities – and all alternatives for that matter – is that there has to be an adequate level of trustee understanding before an allocation can be made,” says JLT’s Brown. “So if you are a trustee for an energy company, you may be quite familiar with the spot and forward pricing for commodities, and if so you would know there is often a difference that can be traded. Trustees should not invest in anything they do not understand, thus it is helpful for an understanding to already be there when we come to provide specific alternative asset class training for trustees.”</p>
<h3 id="the-regulatory-challenge">The regulatory challenge</h3>
<p>Like most corners of the financial universe, the alternative investment industry has had to manage significant regulatory changes in recent years. In Europe, particularly, we have seen the deadline for compliance with the EU Alternative Investment Fund Management Directive (AIFMD) pass in July this year.</p>
<p>The new directive requires all managers based and managing funds in Europe to seek official authorisation once they pass a certain threshold. By the same token, funds that are outside the EU but plan to market to institutional investors inside Europe will have to have a number of organisational and transparency controls in place, providing investors, for example, with pre-investment disclosures and, throughout the duration of the investment, keeping treasurers informed about any material changes on risks, leverage and investment strategy.</p>
<p>For the corporate pension fund with funds in alternatives, building a more open and transparent market can be only a good thing, right? “It is indeed raising the bar on transparency,” says Heleen Rietdijk, KPMG’s global leader of AIFMD tells Treasury Today. Corporates and other investors now get the information that they need straight away and without any hassle. That will certainly help to reassure investors that their funds are being managed in the correct way.</p>
<p>For that reason, investors have been largely supportive of the regulation. That does not equate to wholesale approval of each and every detail, however. In particular, trade bodies representing the investment industry, namely the Alternative Investment Association (AIMA), the Investment Management Association (IMA) and the National Association of Pension Funds (NAPF) have voiced concerns around certain aspects during the consultation process. In 2010, for example, the three agencies wrote a joint letter to MEPs asking for leniency on the “third country” proposals that they believed threatened to effectively restrict investors to their domestic markets. “Compromise amendment ‘N’ is, we fear, unworkable,” the trade bodies wrote. “In practice it will not provide access for non-EU funds and fund managers, but will instead ban European investors from investing overseas.”</p>
<p>Thankfully for investors the words of the trade bodies did not fall entirely on deaf ears. Earlier this year, a compromise was proposed which would allow non-EU fund managers to obtain the same pan-European marketing passport as their European-based counterparts. The proposal is currently under review with the European Securities and Markets Authority (ESMA) and, if positive advice is provided, will be sent to the European Commission (EC) to become enshrined in EU law.</p>
<p>However, other concerns are not likely to be resolved as swiftly. The growing disparity around how alternatives are regulated in other jurisdictions is perhaps the biggest issue, says Rietdijk. In the US, regulation of alternatives is not as strict on certain organisational aspects such as the appointment of a depositary, the implementation of a remuneration policy and structuring a risk management framework as it is in the EU. One could argue that the steps taken by the EU are a positive, given the turmoil we all know can result from taking a too ‘light touch’ approach to regulation. Yet, as Rietdijk stresses, the authorities should still be very careful in that they do not “overextend our regulation to the extent that it makes it difficult for European fund managers to have access to the US market, because they are too expensive.”</p>
<p>Rietdijk concludes with a warning that could be equally applicable in a multitude of other areas in the financial services ecosystem. Regulation, when it becomes overzealous, often ends up doing more harm than good. “All of this compliance can, of course, come with a cost.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-investments/ss-blurred-city-and-people-urban-scene-173748197.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2014-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Alternative Investments]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[A closer look at tri-party repos]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><i>In an environment where banks continue to feel the impact of regulation, collateralised products open up a new world of opportunities for investors. Tri-party repos, for example, can offer investors both sustained revenues and lower risk – a genuine breath of fresh air for corporate treasurers in today’s low-yield environment.</i></p>
<p><img alt="Pascal Morosini portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/clearstream-0834-smarter-treasury-150x200.jpg?h=200&amp;w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=9456771102CDAFF63F3B7CE35F79E17E" style="width: 150px; height: 200px; margin-right: 2em; margin-bottom: 2em; float: left;" width="150"/></p>

<h4 class="fn">Pascal Morosini</h4>
<h5 class="title">Executive Director, Global Head of GSF Sales and Relationship Management</h5>
<br/>
<img alt="Clearstream" class="logo org" height="28" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/clearstream-logo-2014-170x28.png" width="170"/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<p>Pascal Morosini is Executive Director, Global Head of GSF Sales and Relationship Management, at Clearstream.</p>
<p>Pascal joined what was then Cedel Group in 1994 to work in collateral valuation operations. In 1997, he moved to triparty repo operations, and two years later he joined Clearstream Banking’s Customer Relations Department as a Global Securities Financing sales specialist. He is now responsible for sales and relationship management for all GSF products worldwide.</p>
<p>Pascal holds a Diploma in Banking Management from the “Centre Universitaire de Luxembourg” and has also participated in the Clearstream Banking Global Markets training programme.</p>

<p>Corporate treasurers could be forgiven for viewing tri-party repos as a complicated type of transaction. The reality, however, is not nearly as complex as some might think. Indeed, tri-party repos are one of the simpler forms of secured investment: they are essentially bank deposits secured by independently held and managed assets.</p>
<p>And in the current economic environment, that security could not be more welcome. Several high-profile bank failures in recent years have highlighted that unsecured bank deposits are not necessarily as safe as they were previously considered. Yet some corporates have more cash on their balance sheets than ever before – which presents them with somewhat of a dilemma.</p>
<p>Increasingly, corporates are thinking outside their traditional investment boxes and as a result, tri-party repos are falling into favour. A tri-party repo offers corporate investors the advantage of collateral (in the form of securities) in return for depositing cash for the duration of the transaction.</p>
<p>“It allows corporates to either diversify their counterparty network or lend more cash with their house banks if unsecured lines are already fully utilised”, says Pascal Morosini, Executive Director, Head of Global Securities Financing Sales and Relationship Management at Clearstream. “But the biggest and undisputable advantage is that tri-party repo is much more secure than cash deposits.”</p>
<h3 id="driving-the-market">Driving the market</h3>
<p>One of the key drivers of the growth in the tri-party repo market is regulation. For large corporates who have obligations under the European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EMIR) or Dodd-Frank to post collateral for OTC derivative transactions with central counterparties, tri-party repo offers a significant advantage over alternative products. “The collateral corporates hold against cash can be sold immediately should a counterparty default. This collateral can also be used to cover derivative liabilities that corporates have with their prime brokers and clearing members,” explains Morosini.</p>
<p>For this reason, tri-party repo is increasingly considered an alternative to money market funds (MMFs) for corporates with cash to invest in securities. Additional regulation in the MMF space is also causing corporate investors to turn towards tri-party repos.</p>
<p>Against the backdrop of regulatory pressure on investors, tri-party repo presents an opportunity for corporates, who to date have largely invested their cash on a unsecured basis, to invest in collateral-backed deposits.</p>
<p>“The low-yield environment, which continues to put a strain on investors, is another reason why now may be a good time for corporates to move into the tri-party repo market. Subject to the type of collateral investors are willing to receive in return for their cash, the yield on tri-party repos can even sometimes beat what they are earning on their current investments,” notes Morosini.</p>
<h3 id="role-of-the-tri-party-agent">Role of the tri-party agent</h3>
<p>Clearstream, a leader in the tri-party repo market, acts as collateral agent and securities depository (ICSD). In its custodian role it holds accounts for banks and global custodians, who in turn hold securities on behalf of their clients. More than €12 trillion of deposits are held within Clearstream by around 2,500 customers around the world. In its tri-party collateral agent role, Clearstream manages collateral worth more than €650 billion for more than 550 customers.</p>
<p>“Clearstream acts as a neutral collateral agent, handling all the administration related to the transfer of collateral from one counterparty to another,” says Morosini. “We value and allocate the collateral, monitor and process substitutions, execute margin calls, issue reporting and maintain and cross-check the eligibility criteria. In essence, our role is to ensure that sufficient eligible securities are transferred to cover any given exposure at any moment in time.”</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1-how-it-works-clearstream-tri-party-repo-service-flow-diagram">Chart 1: How it works, Clearstream tri-party repo service flow diagram</h5>
</figcaption>
<img alt="2014-09and10-tta-11-st-chart-01-how-it-works-clearstream-tri-party-repo-service-flow-diagram-967x431" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2014-09and10-tta-11-st-chart-01-how-it-works-clearstream-tri-party-repo-service-flow-diagram-967x431.jpg?h=431&amp;w=967&amp;la=en&amp;hash=9D918DA961085EC96AE4126DC4ECC27C" style="width: 967px; height: 431px;"/> </figure>
<p>The company’s role as tri-party agent is an important risk mitigation factor, as Clearstream is not directly part of the transaction. This neutrality guarantees – for both parties in a transaction – that should one default, the collateral will remain segregated and be immediately available for resale.</p>
<p>In addition, Clearstream’s tri-party repo service offers a number of unique features. The principal trading relationship remains between the counterparties, and only one signature of the Collateral Management Service Agreement (CMSA) with Clearstream Banking as the agent is required. Collateral profiles (either customised or designed according to industry standards) are predefined within the CMSA appendix, making it very easy and straightforward to sign up for the service.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the tri-party repo service presents distinct advantages to both the givers and receivers of collateral. Collateral givers can finance a broader basket of assets, tap into new sources of financing, use automatic asset allocation and unlimited substitutions, and be assured of optimal collateral allocation across products and locations. Receivers of collateral benefit from security of holding, an optimised balance sheet, low maintenance costs and full reuse of the collateral received.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, the outsourcing of back office operations to Clearstream provides corporates with access to a wide range of counterparties across the world. Clearstream clients have full control over their asset portfolio and benefit from efficient use of their cash and securities as well as from risk management solutions tailored to their individual needs. The solution is a flexible money market instrument at the heart of Clearstream’s Global Liquidity Hub which can form an integral part of a corporate’s wider liquidity strategy.</p>
<p>Clearstream offers a full suite of products under the Global Liquidity Hub, ranging from securities lending and borrowing to the posting of initial margin to central counterparties for cleared OTC derivative trades. The growing desire of corporates for greater security of the money they deposit with banking partners is reflected in the growth of the Clearstream platform, which now has more than 30 corporate users, with a combined $25 billion in cash.<story>
</story></p>

<h3 id="in-practice">In practice</h3>
<p>For a cash provider using Clearstream, once a tri-party repo deal is concluded, the user instructs its back office to pay the cash to its Clearstream account via its cash correspondent bank. Once this has cleared, Clearstream arranges the simultaneous exchange of the cash on the account for the securities from the counterparty. A core feature of the Clearstream platform is its delivery versus payment (DVP) functionality, which ensures that cash is not paid to the counterparty until the securities have been received, meaning the investor is never exposed.</p>
<p>Users must also inform Clearstream of the transaction with the counterparty; this can be carried out via various channels, including the 360T platform, the Bloomberg Professional service, or Clearstream’s own CmaX online communications portal. “Once you have deposited the cash in your Clearstream account and informed us of the transaction, you do not need to handle the collateral side of the transaction,” says Morosini. “Clearstream handles all the administration of the transaction, and the investor can remain passive until the transaction is automatically unwound.”</p>

<h3 id="whats-in-it-for-corporate-treasurers">What’s in it for corporate treasurers?</h3>
<p>Tri-party repo was initially created as a means for broker-dealers to maximise the use of small asset positions left in their accounts. Today it has expanded to cater to the needs of the larger corporate world. Though initially conceived as an inter-bank product, Clearstream’s platform is bringing tri-party repo to a much broader market. “Clearstream is opening the door for corporates to the tri-party repo market,” says Morosini. “We are facilitating and streamlining access to our state-of-the-art Global Liquidity Hub with our simplified legal agreements. Our goal is to industrialise and commoditise this product and offer it to a much wider audience so they too can reap the benefits.”</p>
<p>Indeed, greater numbers of corporate treasurers are starting to see the benefits of sustained revenues with lower risk that tri-party repo can offer.</p>
<p>In short the benefits could be summarised as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Access to a broader range of counterparties, thus diversifying risk and creating yield enhancement opportunities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Security: cash loans are secured by collateral in the form of securities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Simplicity: trades are negotiated like cash deposits.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Outsource back office workload: all the administration regarding the management of securities is done by Clearstream</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Simplified legal documentation for instant access to a large number of counterparties.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="evolution-and-innovation">Evolution and innovation</h3>
<p>But what makes Clearstream’s offering stand out? For starters, Clearstream’s tri-party repo product has matured with the market, meaning that since its launch in Europe in 1992, the service has become more flexible through the implementation of a streamlined signatory process. Users of the service have also benefited from the ability to re-use securities within the system, a feature that was put in place in 2006.</p>
<p>The company’s collateral management exchange engine (CmaX) has also been developed as a result of its longstanding industry experience and close market consultation.</p>
<p>Building on its core tri-party repo offering, Clearstream launched its GC Pooling product in 2005 in collaboration with Eurex Clearing AG, the central clearer of the Deutsche Börse Group. “This is essentially a tri-party repo transacted through a central counterparty with full counterparty anonymity. This product, which has on average €180 billion of outstanding, dramatically lowers risk to counterparties for corporates. It is currently unrivalled in the market and is now available for corporates,” Morosini explains.</p>
<p>In addition to these innovative products, Clearstream’s principal lending product ASLplus was launched in 2006. Through this service, Clearstream borrows securities (mainly high-quality assets such as government bonds) from its custody clients and re-lends them in its own name under a principal structure (as opposed to an agency structure). ASLplus, which is the market leader in terms of German government bond distribution, has around €50 billion outstanding.</p>
<p>A principal agreement is required to trade repos. This could be a Global Master Repurchase Agreement (GMRA), a document traditionally used for bilateral interbank repo trading which is negotiated with each counterparty individually. Some corporate treasurers have been deterred from trading repo as the negotiation process can be cumbersome and numerous provisions apply solely to bilateral repo, and are hence not relevant for those wishing to use tri-party repo.</p>
<p>Clearstream has sought to simplify the process by designing a standardised tri-party-only principal agreement, the Clearstream Repurchase Conditions (CRCs). Like the CMSA, this agreement is multilateral and only needs to be signed once with the agent. Counterparties do the same and the relationship is formed by acceptance of the collateral receiver’s eligibility criteria. The combination of the CMSA and CRCs effectively gives corporate treasurers membership to a club within which they can trade with other members without having to sign further agreements. The standardised nature of this setup saves both time and legal costs. This innovation alone can speed up the process for accessing tri-party repo counterparties by up to 12 months for corporates – particularly small and medium-sized companies.</p>
<p>Beyond innovation, Clearstream also prides itself on the level of service it offers its customers and the advanced technological portal through which this is provided.</p>
<p>And as more corporates start to appreciate the potential benefits of tri-party repo, these unique features, believes Morosini, will see Clearstream’s market share continue to grow. After all, Clearstream’s tri-party repo service offers the advantages of being secure and sophisticated, while at the same time being simple and transparent for corporates to set up.</p>

<h3 id="clearstream">Clearstream</h3>
<p>Clearstream is part of the Deutsche Börse Group and provides post-trade services to financial and corporate customers in more than 100 countries with access to 54 markets.</p>
<p>Our tri-party repo services through our Global Liquidity Hub provide corporate treasurers with a safe, flexible, collateralised money market product with innovative options including a unique ‘one time’ master repurchase agreement (CRCs) and end-to-end integration with vendors such as 360T.</p>
<p>With access to trade reporting services via REGIS-TR and OTC derivative clearing via Eurex, the Deutsche Börse Group offers a ‘one-stop-shop’ for all your treasury activities.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.clearstream.com">www.clearstream.com</a></p>
<img alt="Clearstream" class="logo" height="28" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/clearstream-logo-2014-170x28.png" width="170"/>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2014-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Alternative Investments]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Repurchase agreements]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Olivier de Schaetzen" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2014-09-tt-02-qa-olivier-de-schaetzen-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=26B9456D08B6ADB18722AE1818974B09" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="olivier-de-schaetzen">Olivier de Schaetzen, Director, Euroclear:</h5>
<p>During the financial crisis corporates were exposed to high levels of risk from the banking sector which they perhaps were not fully aware of. Since then, corporates have been actively looking to reduce their exposures to banking/deposit risks, using novel methods to invest their cash balances. One such method which corporates have adopted that has become increasingly popular, especially with multinationals with large cash pools, is repo agreements. A repo agreement allows a corporate to move from the unsecured to the secured world when depositing cash with counterparties; through receiving securities collateral which mitigates the credit risk of the counterparty. This collateral can be liquidated by the cash giver in the event that the counterparty is unable to repay the loan.</p>
<p>For a corporate, the beauty of a repo agreement is that the ‘risk-and-return’ equation on their investment can be adjusted and set to match their internal investment policy. This is due to the corporates’ ability to decide on the spectrum of assets, their quality and also what percentage of a haircut is required on lesser-quality collateral. For example, if a corporate wants to take minimum risk then they can request high-quality collateral, such as German Bunds. Conversely, if the corporate is looking to generate greater yield, it can broaden its universe of eligible collateral to include corporate bonds or equities.</p>
<p>Repos can also offer corporates operational benefits, particularly if they engage in triparty repos where a dedicated triparty agent like Euroclear Bank manages all of the operational burdens throughout the lifecycle of the repo agreement including margin management and collateral substitutions. Currently many corporates spread their deposits across many different banking partners as a way to mitigate the risk they pose. However, if a corporate enters the repo market and begins to deposit their cash on a secured basis, it can dramatically reduce the number of counterparties it has, reducing the number of relationship and the respective transactions. This can reduce operational work and also offer improved account management and oversight.</p>
<p>In addition to day-to-day cash pool deposits, the repo market is also used to support strategic corporate actions. For example, corporates who have acquired a large amount of cash to fund an investment or from the selling of business units are able to use the repo market as a way to deposit this cash on a secured basis. In doing so the corporate has the peace of mind that their money is secure while they wait to make the investment or decide how to reinvest the money in the event of a disposal.</p>
<p>Another benefit of the repo market, which has seen its popularity increase, is that corporates can use the collateral they receive from their reverse repo activity to create a pool of quality assets that can be tapped in order to cover their obligations for derivatives.</p>
<p>While the repo market can offer corporates many benefits, there are still a number of barriers which prevent wider entry. One such barrier is the challenge presented by the Global Master Repurchase Agreement (GMRA). While this agreement is referred to as an industry standard, lengthy negotiation with each individual counterparty can be needed in order to iron out the specifics within the agreement. Corporates with little knowledge of the secured financing world, legal capacity or expertise in the repo market can often find the process time consuming and off-putting. We are currently looking at the different ways in which the initiation process can be made simpler for corporates through a ‘true’ and simple industry standard derived from the GMRA in order to facilitate the entry of corporates into the repo market.</p>
<p>Another challenge for corporates entering the repo market is the levels of cash needed to participate. Because the banks are dealing with large amounts of cash on their side of the equation, corporates need to match these levels in order to become active trading counterparties. This is the primary reason why large multinationals are the most active corporates in the market and why it is often perceived as being closed off to smaller companies.</p>
<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Stephen Beill" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2014-09-tt-02-qa-stephen-beill-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=ADC6A2F82E83C598064224CA4731E6C6" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="stephen-beill">Stephen Beill, Director – Securities Finance, Citi:</h5>
<p>Since the financial crisis we have seen a large growth in the use of repurchase agreements by corporates. Before the crisis many corporates were placing money with banks on an unsecured basis. However, the rating downgrades which many banks suffered during the crisis saw a reduction in the amount which corporates could place on an unsecured basis, due to their investment policies. Corporates therefore began looking towards alternative investments, including repo agreements; more precisely reverse repo agreements, as a method through which they could place cash with a bank on a secured basis.</p>
<p>A reverse repo is a secured investment, where the corporate places cash with a counterparty who in return puts up collateral to at least the value of the cash, thereby providing two layers of protection: first and foremost to the counterpart; however should the counterpart default, the corporate takes ownership of the collateral which they can liquidate to retrieve cash back. The whole process is usually managed by a tri-party who ensures the collateral meets the criteria agreed at the outset of the trade and will margin daily to ensure the value of the collateral always meets the value of the cash plus any haircut agreed.</p>
<p>The return which corporates can achieve from a reverse-repo trade also adds to their popularity. This is driven by the type of collateral a corporate is prepared to take and the term of the trade. Surprisingly, returns to the corporate in investing their cash in a secured reverse repo trade can often exceed the return of an unsecured trade. This is because a reverse repo is essentially funding a bank’s assets and for the bank this can be cheaper than seeking internal funding. Banks therefore may be willing to pay a premium for this cash, particularly if the corporate is prepared to enter into a termed trade. This often leaves corporates thinking that a reverse repo is “too good to be true”, when really this is just another beauty of the product.</p>
<p>Despite all the positives which a reverse repo can offer to a corporate there can be significant barriers to entry which historically have proved off-putting. The most prominent of these is GMRA. Due to GMRA the corporate and the counterparty are faced with a lot of work and therefore the counterparty often is only prepared to enter into an agreement with a corporate if the terms of the likely trade meet certain criteria, such as adequate size and term. Repos have therefore historically been an investment tool only used by larger corporates with a significant amount of surplus cash.</p>
<p>Ultimately, I see corporate participation in the repo market continuing on its upward trajectory. The current uncertainty surrounding the Money Market Fund (MMF) industry reforms will be a driver, as will products which provide the corporate with quick and easy access to a very attractive investment alternative.</p>
<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Richard Comotto" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/funding-and-investing/alternative-funding/2014-09-tt-02-qa-richard-comotto-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=25EB180C736C6176AE31EE6161FE0228" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="richard-comotto">Richard Comotto, Senior Visiting Fellow, ICMA Centre at the University of Reading:</h5>
<p>There is little or no quantitative data about corporate involvement in the repo market but there is talk about more corporates turning to repo in order to reduce their unsecured exposure to banks and other financial institutions. Such non-financial institutions would be most likely to access the repo market using tri-party services to relieve them of the necessity for setting up bespoke clearing, settlement and collateral management infrastructures.</p>
<p>There are also an increasing number of electronic repo B2C dealing systems being rolled out to attract both non-bank financial and non-financial investors. A number of banks have offered proprietary bilateral systems for several years to their customers, who can see or request price quotes from the dealer. But there are also more commercial multilateral systems connecting individual customers to panels of competing banks who are signed up to support the system by providing competing price quotes. Typically, a customer makes a request for quotes (RFQ) and banks on the panel respond (without seeing the quotes entered by competitors). The customer accepts the best quote or can negotiate. Traditionally, the main customers were non-bank financials. However, the newest systems incorporate a tri-party back end, which makes them more suited to non-financials.</p>
<p>There is little doubt that the provision of liquidity by traditional financial intermediaries is being made more expensive by a wave of new regulation being imposed on banks, particularly the Basel Leverage Ratio and Net Standing Funding Ratio (NSFR). Leverage ratio exposure must be measured without being offset by collateral. Also exposures cannot be reduced by netting against opposite trades possibly except where this happens through a central clearing counterparty (CCP). The NSFR penalises maturity mismatches between borrowing by banks and on-lending to non-banks, including corporates, by imposing quotas on term funding. Banks have already started to reduce the size of their repo books and there can be little doubt that this will make the repo market more expensive and less liquid as a source of both investing and funding (albeit less disadvantageous than the alternatives). There is much talk of new non-bank intermediaries entering the market to take up the slack but no sign as yet. It is more likely that the disintermediation of banks will have to await new technology which can match non-banks.</p>
<p>The principal legal challenges for corporates are threefold. Firstly, they need to ensure that they have the general capacity and authority to transact repo with their intended counterparties but also the particular type of repos that they plan to employ (eg tri-party repo). Secondly, prospective corporate users need to conduct the legal due diligence required to ensure that the master agreements they sign with their counterparties are legally robust. It needs to be remembered that the providers of tri-party repo services are only agents, so there is a direct legal relationship that needs to be documented between the non-financial user and its bank counterparty. Fortunately, the most widely used model contract, the ICMA’s GMRA, provides a sound and well-tested foundation. Finally, corporate investors should check that, if the worst came to the worst and their counterparty defaulted, they would be allowed to accept the collateral onto their balance sheets before liquidating it (there are operational requirements here as well).</p>

<h3>The next question:</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“Now that the 1<sup>st</sup> August 2014 SEPA migration date has passed, does this signify the end of the migration process? What SEPA-related improvements should corporates now be working towards and what do non-EU companies need to think about?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2014-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Alternative Investments]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[SGAM Alternative Investments’ SG Treasury Plus Fund ]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h3 id="offering-attractive-returns-for-medium-term-sterling-investment">Offering attractive returns for medium-term sterling investment</h3>
<p>The role of the corporate treasurer has become increasingly demanding. Treasurers are expected not only to ensure the availability of funds as and when these are needed for operational activities, but also to earn a substantial return on any surplus cash.</p>
<p>The instruments of choice for the European treasurer and investment manager have so far often been the triple-A rated money market funds, due to their safe nature and low liquidity risk. However, the interest earned in money market funds reflects the low risk of this type of cash investment. Long-term investment (bond) funds, on the other hand, have the potential to earn significant interest, but are more risky and often tie up cash for too long to be able to meet the operational demands that most companies have.</p>
<h4 id="enhanced-cash-funds">Enhanced cash funds</h4>
<p>Enhanced cash funds, also known as liquidity plus funds, fill the gap between triple-A rated money market funds and long-term investment funds in terms of the risk and return of potential cash investments. Their objective is to offer a better yield than triple-A rated money funds. As such, they are a complementary investment product to traditional money funds, rather than a mutually exclusive alternative. The increased return is typically achieved by investing into slightly lower rated, riskier credits or by investing for longer periods of time and thereby increasing the credit duration and volatility of the fund.</p>
<p>It is important for the investor to realise that by investing into an enhanced cash or liquidity plus fund, the risk is higher than by investing in triple-A rated money funds. Each liquidity plus fund will also have a different maturity/duration, credit quality and liquidity profile. Nevertheless, the risk taken by the investor may still be relatively limited.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“We don’t compete with AAA funds. We provide corporates with a different solution for the use of their cash, as they are so far used to looking at their cash on a weekly basis, to the detriment of the return.”</p>
<p><cite>Vincent Lauwick, Sales Director Structured Products, SGAM Alternative Investments in the UK</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<h4 id="sg-treasury-plus-fund">SG Treasury Plus Fund</h4>
<p>Enhanced cash funds invest into the money market, but also into instruments that are outside the scope of traditional money funds. The SG Treasury Plus Fund invests into money market securities, deposits, fixed or floating rate securities – such as bonds and equivalents – asset backed securities and credit financial instruments, including credit derivatives and structured credit instruments. While the fund’s investment activity is not limited geographically, it only invests in the credit and money markets.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I think a lot of enhanced cash funds use mixed strategies of currencies, commodities etc. Here we are really focused on credit; the outperformance is generated by only investing in the credit universe.”</p>
<p><cite>Karine Seguin, Sales Director Structured Products, SGAM UK</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The fund owes much of its positive performance so far to its ABS position. Nearly 40% of the fund is currently invested in assetbacked securities, a market in which SGAM feels it has strong credit research, long-standing expertise and a successful track-record.</p>
<p>Asset-backed securities (ABS) are also an asset type that offers several advantages to enhanced cash funds. Interest rate risk and duration of ABS is similar to money market instruments. The rating volatility of ABS is relatively low compared to corporate or bank credit ratings and as a result credit spreads on ABS have a lower volatility. ABS will therefore yield a relatively safe premium over money market instruments.</p>
<h4 id="fund-objectives-and-investment-horizon">Fund objectives and investment horizon</h4>
<p>The SG Treasury Plus Fund has the target of outperforming the sterling 7-day LIBID by 30 basis points per annum net of fees. At the same time, it is the objective of the fund to provide daily liquidity and preserve capital.</p>
<p>In order to benefit from an enhanced cash fund, the investors must be prepared to leave funds invested for a longer time period than in traditional money funds. Given the nature of the invested instruments this means months rather than weeks. The minimum investment period should therefore be not less than three months with a typical investment horizon of six to twelve months.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“When you invest in a AAA rated fund you would expect that after one week redemption is at least equal to the cash that you have put in. Our fund, given the fact that we manage credit instruments and ABS among others, is not a recommended investment for only one week. It is possible that if you invest into this fund for two to three days you could have a slight drawdown. An investor needs to be aware that this fund has a different time horizon than the usual money market fund.”</p>
<p><cite>Vincent Lauwick</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<aside class="definition">
<h5 id="iboxx-and-itraxx">iBOXX and iTRAXX</h5>
<p>iBOXX and iTRAXX are indices for fixed income products and credit derivatives. The indices are provided by IIC, a company that was founded by 10 partner banks and Deutsche Börse AG and which operates out of Frankfurt. The indices represent the attempt to supply standardised, rulebased information on credit derivatives and bonds. While iBOXX indices comprise cash bond markets in various currencies globally, credit default swap (CDS) markets in Europe and Asia are covered by iTRAXX. Both indices are based on data supplied by licensed marketmakers.</p>
</aside>
<h4 id="investment-strategy-and-guidelines">Investment strategy and guidelines</h4>
<p>Liquidity plus funds aim to outperform cash targets by increasing the duration of the invested instruments and/or taking on a higher credit risk. In contrast to a triple-A rated money fund, the SG Treasury Plus Fund has the ability to invest into lower rated instruments and instruments of longer maturity. This obviously translates into a higher credit risk and a higher volatility of returns.</p>
<p>However, the fund’s internal investment guidelines provide for maximum limits to the overall credit duration of the portfolio, which is slightly under five years.</p>
<p>Interest rate duration of the fund is capped at three months and averages at 60 days. At the same time expected volatility should not exceed a target of 1% and currently averages 0.2 to 0.3%.</p>
<p>The fund does not carry any currency risk as non-sterling bonds are hedged directly. The credit risk to which the fund is exposed can be mitigated by buying options on the <strong>iBOXX</strong> and the <strong>iTRAXX</strong> or by directly investing into these bond and credit derivative indices themselves.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“We are always trying to optimise the performance of the fund whilst keeping a conservative profile.”</p>
<p><cite>Karine Seguin</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<figure>
<figcaption>
<h4 id="portfolio-breakdown">Portfolio Breakdown</h4>
</figcaption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Top 7 Sectors</th>
<th>%</th>
<th>Asset Class</th>
<th>%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody class="td-right">
<tr>
<th>Diversified Financial Services</th>
<td>16.7%</td>
<th>Financial Bonds</th>
<td>32.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Banks</th>
<td>9.2%</td>
<th>Corporate Bonds</th>
<td>27.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Engineering &amp; Construction</th>
<td>4.1%</td>
<th>MBS (Commercial)</th>
<td>23.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Iron/Steel</th>
<td>3.7%</td>
<th>MBS (Residential)</th>
<td>15.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Chemicals</th>
<td>3.7%</td>
<th>Consumer Loans</th>
<td>2.2%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Auto Manufacturers</th>
<td>3.5%</td>
<th>Cash</th>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Insurance</th>
<td>3.1%</td>
<th></th>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p class="source">As at October 2006</p>
</figure>
<p>Within these constraints, the fund has the ability to invest into the whole spectrum of the credit market and does not exclude any submarkets.</p>
<p>In terms of strategy, the SG Treasury Plus Fund replicates SGAM Alternative Investments’ euro funds, in which the asset manager has more than €11 billion under management. The fund diversifies not only by investing into a large number of instruments, but also by pursuing different strategies, such as combining long/short strategies and curve strategies. This corresponds to a recent trend in the credit market to move away from static long-only strategies, and is a point of differentiation for the fund from other enhanced cash funds.</p>
<aside class="definition">
<h5 id="synthetic-derivatives">Synthetic derivatives</h5>
<p>Synthetic derivatives are constructed or synthesised by combining other derivatives. For example, a synthetic collateralised debt obligation (CDO) is backed by a pool of credit default swaps. This is in contrast to a “cash” CDO which is backed by a portfolio of securities or loans.</p>
</aside>
<p>Another feature of SGTreasury Plus Fund is that it has the ability to use <strong>synthetic derivatives</strong> on credit instruments and options on credit indices. This strategy enables the portfolio manager to source additional value even when the market is quiet, but also to protect the portfolio against a downturn of the credit market.</p>
<p>The sterling fund is domiciled in the UK as an ICVC (Investment Company with Variable Capital) by SGAM UK and is FSA regulated. It is managed from Paris by SGAM Alternative Investments, a specialist division of Société Générale’s asset management unit. The fund benefits from SGAM’s size and the role that the asset manager plays in the market. As a result of this, the portfolio manager is guaranteed excellent allocation on primary deals, for example in the ABS market, as well as the fastest secondary market execution.</p>
<h2 id="interview">Interview</h2>
<h3 id="societe-generale">Société Générale</h3>

<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Portrait of Stephane Parlebas" class="photo" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2007/01/2007-01-tt-12-pp-stephane-parlebas-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h4 class="fn">Stephane Parlebas</h4>
<h5 class="title">Co-head of CDOs and credit management</h5>
<img alt="Societe Generale Asset Management" class="logo org" height="16" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/societe-generale-asset-management-logo-2007-120x16.png" width="120"/>
<p>Stephane Parlebas graduated from IEP Paris and he holds a Masters in Finance and is a candidate for CFA level 3. He has 14 years’ experience in credit markets including eight years at Commerzbank. He joined SGAM AI in 2004 as a Portfolio Manager and currently manages over £2.4 billion in total return credit funds. He is also in charge of managing equity linked CDO products.</p>

<h5 id="what-was-the-idea-behind-the-sg-treasury-plus-fund">What was the idea behind the SG Treasury Plus Fund?</h5>
<p>One of the driving ideas from my point of view as the portfolio manager was to launch a fund in the sterling market which we think offers interesting opportunities. As a general rule, there is a pick-up in spreads for similar risk for the issuers compared to both the global corporate and ABS markets. In particular, we believe there are a lot of opportunities for ABS in the sterling market. We thought the best vehicle was to have a direct fund for investing in those strategies which also give the performance in sterling. I expect also that some indices referencing sterling bonds will develop in the next years, so with this vehicle we will be prepared to capture these strategies in the credit market as well.</p>
<h5 id="how-does-it-differ-from-other-liquidity-plus-or-enhanced-cash-funds">How does it differ from other ‘liquidity plus’ or enhanced cash funds?</h5>
<p>There are several differentiating factors as far as the investment strategy is concerned.</p>
<p>It is not a fund that invests long only. Even at a time when the market is quiet, we still want to be able to do long/short trades. There is always adjustment in credit risk and there are some names where we think the fundamentals can deteriorate, and it is important to be able to express negative views. I think this ability to be short on selective names is a plus.</p>
<p>Secondly, we are also exploring curve strategies. So again it is not only being long, but long and short on an issuer on the credit curve. This is also interesting because it is a way to generate <strong>positive carry</strong>, which is the key factor when you launch a credit fund. At the same time, you are not too exposed when the market widens because you have a curve position. So for instance if you play with the steepening of the curve, which is usually the case when the market widens, you even have a positive mark to market and you have a carry. This is not common with all credit funds and I think we can differentiate in this area.</p>
<p>Thirdly, especially in the ABS market, we have a strong credit research here that is based in Paris. They started to analyse ABS ten years ago already and really have a strong knowledge in this area. We are buying ABS every day and include it in our fund portfolios. We think our analysis of the European ABS market is one of our key strengths.</p>
<p>And also since we are integrated into the Société Générale group, and SGAM is one of the largest asset managers in Europe, we have access to one on one meetings with group treasurers of large companies. There we can go into more detail on management strategies, potential threats and weaknesses, or business expectations in terms of results etc. Not all asset managers have this direct access to CFOs or Group Treasurers.</p>

<aside class="definition">
<h5 id="positive-carry">Positive carry</h5>
<p>Positive carry is generated when two offsetting positions are held and incoming cash flows from interest on investments are higher than the interest payable on borrowings used to make the investment.</p>
</aside>
<h4 id="fee-structure-minimum-investment-and-redemption">Fee structure, minimum investment and redemption</h4>
<p>The fund does not have any entry or exit fees. The all-in management fees are 25bp and include all fees (eg trading, custody, administration) related to the management of the fund. In addition, there is a performance fee of 30% of the net gain exceeding the notional 7-day LIBID benchmark.</p>
<p>There is no minimum initial or subsequent investment limit as SGAM is interested in diversifying customer types and investment horizons for the fund. However, the only available share class of the fund is an accumulation gross-paying share class. The target deal ticket is between £5m and £10m, but SGAM UK is able to accommodate tickets up to £50m.</p>
<p>Redemption of the fund is effective two days after the deal is placed (T+2), based on the NAV communicated at T+1.</p>
<h3 id="performance">Performance</h3>
<p>While past performance should never be taken as the sole indicator of potential future returns, the SG Treasury Plus Fund has exceeded its targets since the launch of the fund in June 2006. During this period, the fund outperformed 7-day LIBID by more than 82bp net of all fees (as at November 30<sup>th</sup>, 2006).</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="performance-chart-from-27-june-2006-to-31-october-2006">Performance Chart (from 27 June 2006 to 31 October 2006)</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2007/01/2007-01-tt-12-pp-diagram-01-performance-chart.png"><img alt="Diagram 1: Performance Chart (from 27 June 2006 to 31 October 2006)" height="206" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2007/01/2007-01-tt-12-pp-diagram-01-performance-chart-t.png" width="300"/></a>
<p class="source">Source for all performance: SGAM UK NAV to NAV net income reinvested, net of fees</p>
</figure>
<figure>
<figcaption>
<h4 id="performance-net-of-all-fees">Performance (Net of all fees)</h4>
</figcaption>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Dates</th>
<th>Fund</th>
<th>Annualised Rate</th>
<th>Index</th>
<th>Annualised Rate</th>
<th>Spread<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></th>
<th>Volatility</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody class="td-right">
<tr>
<th>October</th>
<td>0.50%</td>
<td>5.69%</td>
<td>0.42%</td>
<td>4.77%</td>
<td>0.92%</td>
<td>0.17%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Since 27 June 2006</th>
<td>1.91%</td>
<td>5.53%</td>
<td>1.63%</td>
<td>4.71%</td>
<td>0.82%</td>
<td>0.25%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p class="source">Annualised using daily data – Arithmetic method.</p>
</figure>

<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Fund less benchmark <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Liquidity plus funds like the SG Treasury Plus Fund offer a good opportunity for companies, local organisations and investment funds to earn enhanced returns on any cash surplus that is not required for operational use during an investment horizon of three to twelve months. Companies will therefore need to ensure that an investment into enhanced cash does not impede their cash liquidity needs and that it complies with the company’s own investment guidelines, in particular with regard to the use of derivatives by investment managers. As with any investment it is important to understand the investment strategies used by the portfolio manager, the risks that the fund is exposed to and how they are managed.</p>

<h3 id="societe-generale-asset-management">Société Générale Asset Management</h3>
<p>Société Générale Asset Management (SGAM) is the fund management division of Société Générale, the global French Banking and Finance Group. As at 30<sup>th</sup> September 2006, SGAM had £233 billion in assets under management through its four management centres in the UK, Continental Europe, USA and Asia, ranking SGAM as one of the largest fund management groups in the world.</p>
<p>Société Générale Asset Management Alternative Investments (SGAM AI) is the specialist alternative investment division within SGAM, specialising in developing and managing specialist structured products tailored for investors needs. SGAM AI has developed successfully by combining active management processes with a capital market culture that mixes innovation and risk management. As at 30<sup>th</sup> September 2006, SGAM AI had a total of £22 billion in structured asset management products including £8.9 billion invested in enhanced money market funds. Our enhanced money market funds are available in EURO, USD and GBP.</p>
<p>For more information on SGAM AI products in the UK, please contact one of the following:</p>

<h5 id="contact-details">Contact details:</h5>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Vincent LAUWICK</dt>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+44 (0)20 7090 2673</span></dd>
<dd class="fax"><span class="value">Fax: +44 (0)20 7090 2983</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:vincent.lauwick@sgam.com">vincent.lauwick@sgam.com</a></dd>
<dd class="url"><a href="http://www.sgam.co.uk">www.sgam.co.uk</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Karine SEGUIN</dt>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+44 (0)20 7090 2674</span></dd>
<dd class="fax"><span class="value">Fax: +44 (0)20 7090 2983</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:karine.seguin@sgam.com">karine.seguin@sgam.com</a></dd>
<dd class="url"><a href="http://www.sgam.co.uk" target="_blank">www.sgam.co.uk</a></dd>
</dl>

<img alt="Societe Generale Asset Management" class="logo org" height="20" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/societe-generale-asset-management-logo-2007-150x20.png" width="150"/>


<h5 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h5>
<p>No statement in this Product Profile is to be considered as a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell securities or other instruments, or to provide investment, tax or legal advice. Readers should be aware that this publication is not intended to replace the need to obtain professional advice in relation to any topic discussed.</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2007-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Alternative Investments]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
