<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Mauritius]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=68490E77C06380936DA34C18B950389A]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>The Republic of Mauritius occupies a key strategic position between Asia, Africa and Australia, making it an attractive treasury location for some companies. From the country’s banking landscape and cash management considerations to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic, here’s what treasurers need to know</em>.</p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4B7B2CD2177DD9CF4ECC5C742827F4B1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0BA7F2EA398F1D07C01DA03942FA5FE7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A972E49ECCAB93E56E446E2E718B500F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4E3EA97C14F6D6E72924606AC71B9649"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6B28FF5352F487377F22E7586F2862D4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=68490E77C06380936DA34C18B950389A" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2020-05-06-tta-04__cf_aerial-panorama-port-louis-mauritius-skyline-585884585__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=68490E77C06380936DA34C18B950389A"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>Situated 1,200 miles off the east coast of Africa, and 500 miles east of Madagascar, the Republic of Mauritius is part of the Indian Ocean’s Mascarene Islands. The island nation includes Mauritius as well as nearby islands Rodrigues, Agaléga and St. Brandon. Geographically, Mauritius occupies a strategic position between Asia, Africa and Australia. While its stunning beaches and coral reefs make it a popular luxury tourism destination, it also has much to recommend it from a business perspective.</p>
<p>“Mauritius acts as a gateway to Africa and provides an appropriate regulatory framework for global companies,” comments Anish Jain, Chief Treasury Officer at Export Trading Group (ETG), an agricultural supply chain group headquartered in Dubai which has operating entities across 40 countries. “International trading companies are finding Mauritius as a favourable destination to house regional treasuries to cater to African requirements. Moreover, international banks based in Europe or Africa are also quite acquainted with Mauritius laws to provide lending solutions to their clients.”</p>
<p>Mauritius has undergone a considerable transition in recent years. Sugarcane was originally introduced to Mauritius in the 17<sup>th</sup> century and became central to the country’s economy, with sugar representing a quarter of GDP in the 1970s. In recent years, however, the nation has achieved greater diversification, with sugar now only accounting for 3-4% of GDP. Three quarters of the economy is service-based, with industry accounting for 21% and agriculture 3%, according to the African Development Bank.</p>
<p>This transition is still under way. As the World Bank’s website notes, “Mauritius faces the challenge of managing its transition to a knowledge based high-income economy driven by innovation and productivity growth. This will require a concerted effort to remove bottlenecks to new sources of growth and private investment, such as a lack of connectivity, skills shortages, and misaligned incentives.”</p>
<p>In 2019, Mauritius’ top exports included clothing, seafood, sugar, fish, gems and precious metals, while imports include petroleum, frozen fish and cars. The island’s main trading partners include France, India, China, US, UK and South Africa.</p>
<h4 id="impact-of-covid-19">Impact of COVID-19</h4>
<p>Before the arrival of the COVID-19 pandemic, real GDP growth in Mauritius had been forecast to be 3.9% in 2020 and 4% in 2021, with tourism playing a role in contributing to this growth. However, with the pandemic continuing to affect countries around the world, a GDP contraction is now likely. The World Economic Outlook published by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) in April 2020 forecast a 3% contraction in real GDP for middle-income countries in Sub-Saharan Africa, in which it included Botswana, Cabo Verde, Eswatini, Lesotho, Mauritius, Namibia, and Seychelles.</p>
<p>In particular, lower demand for tourism from European countries, alongside ongoing travel restrictions, is expected to have a major impact on Mauritius’ economy during the crisis. “I think it is pretty obvious that the industries that will face the brunt of this slowdown or recession, which is due to the outbreak of this virus, are definitely the tourism industry and our textiles manufacturing industry,” commented Parikshat Tulsidas, Senior Executive – Treasury &amp; Markets at AfrAsia Bank in a video published by the bank in April. He also cites the construction sector as an area that is likely to see an impact, in light of the “high-end properties that we sell to foreigners.”</p>
<p>The government has introduced various measures to support workers and businesses, including the Government Wage Assistance Scheme (GWAS) and the Self-Employed Assistance Scheme (SEAS). The Key Repo Rate has been reduced by 100 basis points to 1.85%, and the Bank of Mauritius has likewise reduced the interest rate applicable on its Special Relief Amount under the COVID-19 Support Programme by 100 basis points. Other actions have included suspending capital repayments on loans for households affected by the crisis. Meanwhile, capital market activity has been suspended, as has trading on the Stock Exchange of Mauritius.</p>
<p>National confinement was introduced on March 20<sup>th</sup> and a curfew imposed on March 24<sup>th</sup> which has since been extended to June 1<sup>st</sup>. A report by Fitch Solutions Country Risk &amp; Industry Research on April 21<sup>st</sup> noted that Mauritius is well-placed to avoid a large domestic outbreak of COVID-19 in light of these measures, adding that even in the event of a larger outbreak “a robust social security system and free health care means that the country is one of the best placed in sub-Saharan Africa to deal with any potential pressure on healthcare and incomes.”</p>
<h4 id="banking-landscape">Banking landscape</h4>
<p>Mauritius’ finance sector is governed by two main regulatory bodies. Established in 1967, the Bank of Mauritius is Mauritius’ central bank. It oversees banking institutions, with the Banking Act 2004 providing a framework for the licensing, regulation and supervision of banks and other financial institutions. The central bank’s main objectives include maintaining price stability, promoting orderly and balanced economic development and formulating and executing monetary policy consistent with stable price conditions.</p>
<p>In addition, the Financial Services Commission, Mauritius (FSC) acts as the regulatory for non-bank financial sector and global business, and is mandated under the Financial Services Act 2007. The FSC’s goals are to:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Promote development, fairness, efficiency and transparency across Mauritius’ financial institutions and capital markets.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Suppress crime and malpractice in order to protect members of the public investing in non-banking financial products.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ensure the soundness and stability of Mauritius’ financial system.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>“The banking landscape in Mauritius is very inward-looking,” comments ETG’s Jain. “Most of the banks present locally are risk-averse and do not understand the international trading environment.” Jain notes that the credit risk assessment of clients is based on local operations, adding that only a handful of banks in Mauritius have really graduated to the extent where they compete with international banks. “I believe the smaller size of the balance sheet for Mauritian banks is also a limiting factor to compete with large powerhouse banks,” he comments.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">A short history of Mauritius</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Mauritius has had a varied history over the last 500 years. Arab traders referred to the island as Dina Arobi (Isle of Desolation) as long ago as the tenth century. The island remained uninhabited and in 1507 it was discovered by Portuguese sailors, who named it Cirné and used it as a refuelling base, although they did not build a settlement.</p>
<p>The Dutch claimed ownership of Mauritius in 1598, naming it after their head of state, Prince Maurice of Nassau. They embarked on the first of several attempted settlements in 1630 and subsequently abandoned the island in 1710 following a series of setbacks including droughts, cyclones and infestations. However, they left behind sugar cane, as well as domestic animals.</p>
<p>The island became a French colony in 1715, and was renamed Isle de France. Port Louis was established as a naval base and shipbuilding centre, and sugarcane was cultivated. The British attacked the island in 1810 following raids on British commercial ships by the French fleet from Mauritius.</p>
<p>In 1814, Mauritius was given to the United Kingdom as part of a treaty that saw the island of Réunion returned to France. After slavery was abolished, indentured labourers were brought to the island from India. Mauritius gained independence on March 12<sup>th</sup> 1968, and became a republic in 1992.</p>
<p>Among the nation’s other claims to fame is its former inhabitant, the dodo. The flightless bird passed into extinction in the late 17<sup>th</sup> century, likely as a result of being hunted by Dutch sailors as well as the ecological impact of animals introduced to the island by settlers, including pigs and dogs as well as ship rats.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4 id="company-considerations">Company considerations</h4>
<p>For companies operating in Mauritius, an important piece of legislation is the Companies Act 2001, which requires all companies to remain solvent and sets out company law both for domestic companies and for those conducting global business.</p>
<p>A key concept for the latter is the Global Business Licence (GBL), which is applicable to companies which are resident in Mauritius for tax purposes, but which conduct their core business activities outside of Mauritius. The conditions for a licence include employing suitably qualified people – either directly or indirectly – to carry out the business’ core activities, as well as a minimum expenditure level in line with the company’s level of activities. Companies with a GBL can take advantage of the country’s network of double tax treaties, corporation tax and withholding tax rates.</p>
<p>Until recently, the regime included the two concepts of Category 1 Global Business Companies (GBC1) and Category 2 Global Business Companies (GBC2). However, following recent reforms introduced in line with the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD)’s Base Erosion and Profit Shifting (BEPS) initiatives, these categories were discontinued on January 1<sup>st</sup> 2019.</p>
<p>As a result of the reform, GBC1 licences have been replaced with the GBL, while GBC2 licences have been replaced with the Authorised Companies (ACs) regime. This applies to companies which conduct business and have their place of effective management outside of Mauritius. ACs are not resident in Mauritius for tax purposes, but have a registered agent in Mauritius. ACs are required to file annual tax returns with the Mauritius Revenue Authority and are prohibited from business activities including banking and financial services.</p>
<p>Grandfathering provisions are in place for GBC1 and GBC2 licenses that were issued on or before October 16<sup>th</sup> 2017. After June 30th 2021, a GBC1 license will be deemed to be a GBL, while a GBC2 licence will lapse, with the company required to apply for AC or GBL status. For licences issued after October 16<sup>th</sup> 2017, the grandfathering period elapsed on December 31<sup>st</sup> 2018.</p>
<h4 id="treasury-challenges">Treasury challenges</h4>
<p>For corporate treasury professionals, there are a number of factors to consider when it comes to managing cash in Mauritius. Claudinette Permal, a Mauritius-based Treasury Manager at pan-African real estate company Grit Real Estate Income Group, cites a number of challenges that treasury professionals may face in this market:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Cash flow management</strong>. Keeping an eye on daily cash flows, which for most businesses is a manual activity involving spreadsheets.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Improving on the collections/debtor’s days ratio</strong>. “It is a real struggle to get funds out of corporate customers,” Permal notes. “It is like every company is pulling liquidity out of each other.”</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Real-time payments</strong>. “Treasurers must ensure sufficient liquidity, especially when it comes to debt repayments,” says Permal. “Any delay will impact as a breach in covenants, particularly under the COVID-19 crisis.”</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Currency fluctuations</strong>. In particular, Permal cites fluctuations in the US dollar and the euro, adding that most debt facilities are in those two hard currencies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Relationship management</strong>. Permal also notes the importance of maintaining good relationships with financiers during difficult times.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Where cash management is concerned, there are a few considerations to bear in mind. “Each company adopts a different method for cash management,” comments Jain. “Given the foreign exchange regulations in many African countries, cash pooling is not available across Africa. Companies can, at best, apply regional cash pooling.” He adds that besides bank solutions, many multinational companies deploy treasury management solutions (TMS) of their own choice that meets their specific requirements.</p>
<p>Grit Real Estate Income Group’s Permal says the company’s approach to cash management in Mauritius includes a clear working capital optimisation strategy, alongside daily cash flow monitoring and a well-defined policy with clear KPIs, metrics and approval limits.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote><p>We are currently moving towards the use of integrated systems which will speak to all the bank accounts, as well as to the accounting software.</p></blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Claudinette Permal, Treasury Manager, Grit Real Estate Income Group</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>“Most medium companies use Excel workbooks extensively, which is very time-consuming,” she adds. “We are currently moving towards the use of integrated systems which will speak to all the bank accounts, as well as to the accounting software. This will help improve the operational efficiency and better manage the cost of capital.” Permal explains the expected benefits will include the real-time availability of the cash position, with projections performed “in no time”, alongside eliminating the need for manual input and thereby freeing up time.</p>
<p>Where risk management is concerned, Jain says that ETG “has a comprehensive risk management policy that covers commodity trading and FX risk management.” For Grit Real Estate Income Group, meanwhile, Permal says that treasury forms part of the risk committee alongside representatives of other departments. From a treasury perspective, she says the main risks identified include liquidity risk, covenant risk, credit risk, FX risk and interest rate risk.</p>
<p>She adds that for each of these areas, the probability of occurrence and level of impact is assessed, monitored and discussed at monthly meetings. “Policies and procedures are clearly defined, and processes and systems are drafted and circulated,” she says.</p>
<h4 id="harnessing-technology">Harnessing technology</h4>
<p>As in other locations, technology has much to offer treasurers operating in Mauritius when it comes to streamlining processes and harnessing insights more effectively in order to improve decision making.</p>
<p>“Technology certainly plays a pivotal role in managing complex global operations,” comments Jain. “ETG continues to strengthen the existing technology base and adopt new platforms as the business needs.”</p>
<p>Looking forward, Permal expects technology will bring a number of opportunities for improvement. “In the first place, the automated cash flow reporting/forecasting will bring so many benefits,” she says, citing the freeing up of time, reduction in manual intervention and increased confidence in the data presented. She also expects technology will improve better cash management, enabling cash to be swept between accounts in order to increase interest revenue.</p>
<p>Other benefits will include greater oversight over FX exposures at any given point in time, the adoption of better internal controls and the building of scenario analysis, as well as the use of technology to improve monthly treasury reporting, including monitoring covenants, metrics and the expiry dates of facilities.</p>
<p>“I do think that technology will bring the treasury role to the next level, with more focus on strategic decision-making and building relationships with financiers, which is critical in our position,” she concludes.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Mauritius: quick facts</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><strong>Currency</strong>: Mauritian rupee (MUR)</p>
<p><strong>Capital</strong>: Port Louis</p>
<p><strong>Area</strong>: 791.3 square miles</p>
<p><strong>Population</strong>: 1.27 million</p>
<p><strong>Languages</strong>: French, English, Mauritian Creole and others</p>
<p><strong>Median age</strong>: 35.6 years</p>
<p><strong>GDP</strong>: US$14.8bn in 2019</p>
<p><strong>GDP growth</strong>: averaged 3.8% between 2015-2019</p>
<p><strong>Exports</strong>: fish, clothing, sugar, gems and precious metals</p>
<p><strong>Export partners</strong>: France, UK, US, South Africa, Madagascar</p>
<p><strong>Imports</strong>: oil, manufactured goods, capital equipment, food</p>
<p><strong>Import origins</strong>: China, India, France, South Africa, Japan</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Keeping an open mind: successful treasury operations in Africa]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2018 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=29208E0A4376EBC8F17BAA53A6833953]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C3611D86B22D8D85A40DC93FCFBCB6D1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D268D6ADAD475AB554A9E9931D40B59C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=43200215DBF01ECA5A5EB7B462121EA3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=85846612756295999EE20A692CEDFC79"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A39D2ECDA144B03F388F1B0BB58B2AD0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Coastal view of Cape Town" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=29208E0A4376EBC8F17BAA53A6833953" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/aerial-coastal-view-cape-town-city-ss383678785.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=29208E0A4376EBC8F17BAA53A6833953"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>It’s a long game for Asian corporates moving into Africa; is it worth it? Treasury Today Asia hears some real insights and country-specific textures from treasurers already operating in the region.</em></p>
<p>African economies are picking up. Some countries exhibit the kind of growth that seem a distant memory for European corporates, if not for Asian players. But it has not been an easy path to follow. Commodity prices have been on a roller-coaster ride, debt levels have risen, currency volatility (especially the South African rand) and the increasing costs of international capital have all burdened this continent in recent years.</p>
<p>There is optimism though. Investment in infrastructure is increasing – notably from China, keen to develop its Belt and Road initiative into East Africa, with Kenya a major beneficiary. In fact, Kenya is a hive of activity, having gone live with KITS (Kenya Interparticipant Transaction Switch) payments platform, offering real-time transfers.</p>
<p>Something similar is on its way in Zambia and Nigeria has also joined the global ‘immediate payments’ club with its NIBSS (Nigeria Interbank Settlement System). Indeed, Nigeria is moving from recession to growth and its leaders are beginning to loosen exchange controls. Meanwhile, oil exporters in sub-Saharan Africa (including Angola, Cameroon and Gabon) have seen encouraging real GDP growth of about 4%.</p>
<p>For corporates looking for a continental hub, it is no longer a case of South Africa or not at all. Other options have opened up, in countries such as Senegal, Kenya and Morocco, Côte d’Ivoire and Cameroon. The creation of unifying monetary zones too is adding momentum to corporate interest. The West African Economic and Monetary Union and the Central African Economic and Monetary Community are both delivering borderless banking and single payments within their zones for corporate treasuries.</p>
<figure class="left" style="width:500px;">
<img alt="Infographics Africa 1" height="417" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-05and06-tta-08__rt__infographics-01__500x417.png?la=en&amp;hash=2D2E2DA9ED9C67D7AB059D2A23E76A06" width="500"> </img></figure>
<h3 id="centralisation-rules">Centralisation rules</h3>
<p>But Africa is far from unified. With the markets being so different from one country to the next, the treasury decision to centralise or de-centralise is rarely clear cut, says Foluso Ayo-Olaiya, Head of Corporate and Public-Sector Product Sales, Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions at Citi Nigeria. Speaking at a recent EuroFinance event, she said even for a major bank operating in the region, it is necessary to consider the industry, sector and appetite for concentration of each business in detail before developing what is essentially a bespoke structure.</p>
<p>Whilst some local entities will be precisely directed on strategy and execution from a centralised position, others are granted full power to take decisions. There is no right nor wrong way, says Ayo-Olaiya. However, where decisions are made out of headquarters in other regions, sometimes escalating through multiple layers, it is possible that swift action is not possible on financial opportunities (such as the Nigerian central bank’s snap decisions to offer ‘bargain’ FX and FX forward deals). “It is matter of deciding what aspects of the business require agile decisions, leaving them to skilled locals, then centralising key decision making and strategic thinking,” she says.</p>
<p>If centralisation is a natural corporate inclination, Tracy Cooper, Assistant Regional Treasurer, EMEA at Cargill says “we’re driven to it from a cost and scale perspective”. With this comes the need to be sympathetic to the needs of the regions in which the company operates. This means putting the decisions about local activities “as close as is locally possible”.</p>
<p>Cargill is a privately-held company operating across food and beverage, agricultural, financial risk, and industrial products in 70 countries. Its treasury is focused on centralisation, building expertise in regional hubs. It has a treasury hub in Singapore handling Asia, with another in the UK for Europe and Africa. North America has its own operations and Latin America, whilst more of a co-operation of different country operations, is effectively another treasury hub.</p>
<p>Cargill is currently present in seven African countries, employing around 2,000 people. Although it has a multi-business approach in most other locations, here it is usually a ‘one business-one country’ model. It operates with what it calls ‘country tags’, giving the local business in each country a direct line into centralised treasury.</p>
<p>Understandably, centralisation is a key topic for GE too. However, adopting this structure is dependent upon whether the market permits it, says Vasu Reddy, Treasury Leader, Sub-Saharan Africa at GE. “In Angola, it is not possible to do offshore trading or hedging so companies need to have authorised local personnel,” he notes. For GE, although even its bank approvals are done at a central level, Angola does not allow this.</p>
<h3 id="fx-complexity">FX complexity</h3>
<p>GE itself is a combination of nine industrial businesses (covering power, water, oil and gas), and GE Capital, where the centralised treasury function resides. Its sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) operations are located in 25 countries, 19 of which are subject to cash restrictions requiring approvals for movement. A shared services centre (one has recently been established in Egypt) manages back office duties including accounts receivable, payments, bank account opening, trade execution and reporting.</p>
<p>In terms of its FX trading, below a certain trade-size this is standardised and automated for most GE entities. It uses an in-house platform connected to its banks through which entities request deals. However, with Angolan participation not possible, treasury must be flexible in order to discover the best possible solution that sits astride both global policy and local regulation, says Reddy.</p>
<p>In meeting its own FX needs, Cargill prefers multi-bank FX portals, says Cooper. Indeed, the scale and volumes of trade undertaken by the company means this technology is essential to facilitate straight through processing, from the point where the local business requests the trade, right through to execution.</p>
<p>“We can’t do this for many African currencies, but by streamlining and centralising the other geographies, it helps us to use our time and effort where it’s more complex,” she explains. That said, she adds that Cargill’s “technology driver” will still see the company rolling out the platform in Africa as far as it can.</p>
<h3 id="technology-the-saviour">Technology the saviour</h3>
<p>The adoption of such technologies will be a key means of supporting centralisation, says Ayo-Olaiya. With banks and other financial institutions and service providers distributing real-time information, and the use of multi-banking solutions, treasurers are able to take informed decisions despite the diversity of the African trading environment, she notes.</p>
<p>However, unless it is mandated, the real discussion for her is always whether centralisation adds value or not. For Cooper, technology and the information exchange it allows, offers the centralised treasury the agility it needs “without feeling too far away”, so the benefits are clear.</p>
<figure class="center" style="width:625px;">
<img alt="Infographics Africa 2" height="202" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-05and06-tta-08__rt__infographics-02__625x202.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=C1C09E6A5C105B2BF8671C3243D12630" width="625"/> </figure>
<h3 id="locally-aware">Locally aware</h3>
<p>Within this structure, the message is that streamlining and consistency of processes is advisable, even if the final execution with the local banks has to be manual. Not that centralising is without issue. Moving functions to a different region draws concerns, for example about local job security, lower volumes of trade and less local visibility, warns Reddy.</p>
<p>But then these issues have to be looked at in the context of a global business. “It’s nothing personal,” he says, “but when changes are made it’s all about cost-containment for us, operating in a much more streamlined environment in challenging times.” As such, he feels technology is going to play an increasingly important role in African treasury.</p>
<p>For Cooper, there is concern for local reaction too. Certain business managers in-country like to meet and talk directly with their banks, she notes. This allows them to feel in control of the relationship. Centralised intervention can, she admits, be seen as “controlling”.</p>
<p>But often the outcome of central intervention is that the local operation is steered in the direction of the right tools and even the right banking partner, she explains. “I think we allow them to focus on the business and take that workload off them; eventually they see the benefit.” As Reddy has said, ultimately it is about getting the best pricing and the best terms that local entities could not achieve on their own because they don’t necessarily have that insight and oversight. To a degree then an education process is necessary, Cooper describing this as an “ongoing partnership discussion”.</p>
<p>This constant communication and exchange of knowledge is important around a key topic such as FX because agility in responding to regulation and in accessing FX requires in-country expertise, even if the actual execution and internal processing is centralised.</p>
<h3 id="funding-options">Funding options</h3>
<p>The nature of funding in Africa can prove challenging too. This has led GE to undertake occasional capital injections. For Cargill this means promoting inter-company lending as far as possible. But if a local business needs local currency, Cooper says that treasury’s ability to inter-company fund can be more limited. If there is no access to currency, treasury may not be able to execute in a way that gives the local business its funding tool other than as an FX trade. “We will try to bring in as much capital as inter-company debt as we can, versus local bank debt, and then manage that relationship,” she says. In the majority of countries in Africa, it has been possible to manage inter-company loans although in some, such as Mozambique, other methods are required.</p>
<p>As a means of assisting its access to currency, treasury will often extend a corporate (parental) guarantee to its banks in-country covering the local subsidiary. Success here is of course contingent upon picking the right banking partner: “one that can respect and value the guarantee” which, Cooper adds, “is not always the case with local banks”.</p>
<p>GE’s method, depending on the cash structure and the jurisdiction in question, is to establish centralised offshore cash pools. It will also seek to issue commercial paper in the US. As such, much of what it does around funding is centralised. If the funded entity can pay back, then an inter-company loan will be made, otherwise it will be by capital injection. “We don’t take any debt from the local banks,” states Reddy.</p>
<figure class="center" style="width:625px;">
<img alt="Infographics Africa 3" height="223" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-05and06-tta-08__rt__infographics-03__625x223.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=EBE66FA0BD61CD664A5659BAF3F1AFD7" width="625"/> </figure>
<h3 id="banking-partners">Banking partners</h3>
<p>Seeing a combination of both funding models in the field, Ayo-Olaiya promotes the case for working with the right partner. “Having a bank that understands the culture of the corporate headquarters, and then knowing local personnel who can understand the dynamics and grasp the importance of flexibility, helps ensure success with the chosen structure,” she says.</p>
<p>Indeed, says Cooper, Cargill chooses to approach its banks on a ‘pari-passu’ basis. “With the banks knowing how we operate, it means we are able to get things done a lot quicker; we can be more agile when entering into a country.” Going to a new country and choosing a banking partner outside of the regular panel would, she notes, extend the lead time considerably.</p>
<p>With around 15 banking partners across Africa, and cash within those banks, GE has developed a robust risk team, says Reddy. Taking on a new partner requires extensive risk analysis on a global and country basis (considering credit ratings, balance sheets and so on). At times, banking group diversifications have necessarily been undertaken (in Angola, for example), on-boarding other banks to try to diminish risk.</p>
<p>The assessment of counterparty risk is a key part of GE’s global policy, this being reflected by its in-country activity. For Cooper, most of the countries Cargill operates in allows it to go with regional or global bank relationships, this making the assessment of the counterparty risk “a lot easier”.</p>
<p>Banking partners with muscle are closely bound with the corporate’s maintenance of relationships with local authorities too, especially with the central banks of Africa. Cargill’s team has met the authorities directly; in Zimbabwe, for example, the need for direct talk stems from the company’s status as a major exporter with deep historical roots. However, says Cooper, “normally our first port of call would be to our banks, to ask for their advice and support in going to the central banks”.</p>
<p>“We have a close relationship, but we don’t sleep in the same bed,” says Reddy of GE’s connection with the central banks of Africa. It too normally goes through its main banks, as a matter of policy. Indeed, he says, it is important to maintain a strong relationship with its banks, partnering with them to work with the central banks, not cutting them out of the loop in any way.</p>
<h3 id="open-mind">Open mind</h3>
<p>Whatever the corporate undertaking in Africa, its sheer diversity, for Reddy, means “there is no ‘one-size fits-all’ solution”. Indeed, the only constant for GE is change, he states. “We try to be flexible, we try to gain scale, and try to maximise local resources, and we always look to our banks as partners.”</p>
<p>It is the same for all companies entering Africa: no matter where they are from, there will be a steep learning curve. “But only when you go through it can you figure out if what you want to do works or not,” says Reddy. “Then you can look back and know that next time you can be better prepared.”</p>
<p>But, he warns, even what has been learnt can quickly become obsolete. “Structures and economies change so you have to keep abreast it. This is where local expertise can help.”</p>
<p>For Cargill, Cooper says it is vital to keep listening to what is happening in the markets. “I think we will move towards a more service-based approach to Africa, but it really depends on what countries we will be in, and what business lines we are going to be in.” The answers to such questions, she is certain, will in every case change the dynamics of the company’s approach. Indeed, Cooper is clear that treasurers should resist holding a set view of Africa.</p>
<div class="boxed">
<h3 id="top-tips-for-establishing-an-african-treasury">Top tips for establishing an African treasury</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Standard solutions for Africa are rare; a case-by-case approach will usually be required.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Centralisation seems to be the preferred model.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Before entering a new market, always involve treasury in planning.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Accept and plan for trapped cash.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Seek the advice of partners in banking, legal and tax to ensure full familiarisation with local rules and expectations, especially around repatriation of funds.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Build a strong relationship with the most appropriate banks to cover both current and future needs, especially for accessing FX liquidity and keeping up regulatory changes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Adhere closely to central bank regulations; build trust from the start.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Leverage technology to gain visibility.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Talk to those who are already there.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Treasury in Africa]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2018 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>What are the current trends in treasury management in Africa?
</em></p>
<h4 id="standard-bank">Idrees Kolabhai, Head, Cash Management, Transactional Products &amp; Services and Brendon Bouwer, Head, Liquidity Management, Transactional Products &amp; Services, Standard Bank:</h4><figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin: 0 2em 0em 0px;">
<img alt="Idrees Kolabhai" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-03and04-tt-11-qa__idrees-kolabha__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FC3A8768FAEA97D6C1405091B602C65A" width="100"/> 	<figcaption>
<h6>Idrees Kolabhai</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin:0 2em 0em 0px;">
<img alt="Brendon Bouwer" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-03and04-tt-11-qa__brendon-bouwer__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F9EA5414F43ED9598E02D88C2E8FC3C7" width="100"/> 	<figcaption>
<h6>Brendon Bouwer</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Corporates continue to focus on bolstering their balance sheets, increasingly so with the expectant increases in rates in the US and European markets. At Standard Bank, we have been strong advocates for corporates to better their cash conversion cycle, placing less reliance on term overdrafts and moving towards just-in-time funding to support their working capital lifecycle.</p>
<p>We continue to see consistent themes, but we are also seeing new themes emerging in the African context. Given the often slow and unreliable performance of correspondent banking models, having a single regional banking partner on the continent with a wide geographic footprint and extensive branch infrastructure and local clearing access has become critical.</p>
<p>Internal liquidity management has become a key source of funding, with companies looking to diversify their funding sources. Trapped cash is a reality for many businesses operating in Africa. Restrictive exchange control regimes mean that businesses can’t move money between their various operations easily. This presents challenges for the operation of regional and global treasuries, especially the repatriation of funds to parent companies abroad. While it is legislatively possible to remit funds in many African markets, businesses often have long waiting periods when sourcing foreign exchange in the domestic market.</p>
<p>Cash forecasting remains a concern. As is the case in markets across the world, it is critical for treasurers to have sight of their cash balances in order to optimise their working capital balances and manage their liquidity risk. Given the real-time nature of modern business, treasurers need intra-day liquidity information, enabling the management of cash flows, credit facilities and working capital quickly and responsively across multiple accounts and subsidiaries. Despite the growth of mobile banking in Africa, the continent remains reliant on cash as both a medium of exchange and store of value.</p>
<p>Corporate centralised payment factories and treasury centres have evolved to regional treasury centres with local payment presence. Businesses setting up in Africa can’t simply import the payment structure that they operate in their more developed markets. Instead, they need to understand what will work as a payment system in that particular country or region – and then be guided in terms of operating in these cash-based trading environments. To be effective, the regional treasury centre needs to be located in the region it supports and close to the key business operations in that region. Direct access to regional trade blocs like Southern African Development Community (SADC), West African Monetary Union (WAMU) and East African Community (EAC) provide an invaluable advantage to treasuries located there.</p>
<p>The digitalisation of traditional business channels has brought about unprecedented levels of access, automation and optimisation to corporates and their treasuries. The demand for Africa to be part of the digital revolution is as strong, with treasurers demanding tools and services from African banks to support their own digital journeys.</p>
<h5 id="citi">Geoffrey Gursel, Director – Citi Sub-Saharan Africa Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions Sales and Implementations Head, Citi:</h5>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin: 0.5em 2em 0em 0px;">
<img alt="Geoffrey Gursel" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-03and04-tt-11-qa__geoffrey-gursel__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=B5C613AA894B687533C532171B391024" width="100"/> 	<figcaption>
<h6>Geoffrey Gursel</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>With the downgrade of South Africa, coupled with several bank failures over the past 18 months and wider geopolitical risk through major elections, comprehensive reviews of counterparty exposure limits will continue to be a major trend throughout 2018 in Africa. While there are brighter economic forecasts for core markets like Nigeria and into West Africa, continued close management of FX and commodity risks remain critical, with certain industries managing exposure to oil prices closely.</p>
<p>Centralisation and automation are not entirely new to Africa and will continue via rationalisation of banking partners and accounts, but the physical locations of where to structure centralised payment hubs or SSCs is changing to new locations like Senegal, Côte d’Ivoire and Kenya. Automation is no longer just about cost efficiencies, it is now an enabler to effectively manage liquidity and risks in locations previously not considered.</p>
<p>The increasing number of centralised payment structures in Africa will inevitably evolve in 2018, with XML V3 now a standard and simplification a core objective with treasury teams being asked to do more-with-less. These new emerging treasury hubs, coupled with improved Central Bank policies and 2020/2030 visions, are helping to ensure the corporate sector buys into the economic future of the country – and this ties directly in treasury decisions.</p>
<p>The specific pressures, and therefore risk management priorities of corporates working on the continent, will have to be aligned to the digital adoption of the market as well, of which Nigeria and Kenya are good examples of upgrading their payment infrastructure to true real-time and the working capital efficiencies that organisations can benefit from. How treasurers in Africa adapt and maximise those enhancements that will increase STP and automation will also raise further questions on the understanding and readiness of cyber fraud. What are the ongoing roadblocks to protect the corporation in Africa? What role does your bank need to play in your internal playbook in the event of an attack? These types of questions are becoming more commonplace in Africa as organisations begin to implement contingency planning for specific cyber take-overs.</p>
<p>The continued evolution of the treasurer or treasury in Africa has to keep abreast with the new data-driven analytics that banks can offer now on the continent. Real-time visibility isn’t enough. It is real industry benchmarking, with examples like applied machine learning techniques to analyse clients’ payments data for outliers and enable clients to take action. Managing the associated risks with doing business in Africa will always be on the treasury KPI. But in Africa in 2018, if your bank isn’t being your catalyst for treasury innovation, you need to act on that. And fast.</p>
<h5 id="multichoice">Andre Olivier, Treasurer – Rest of Africa and Andrew Mills, Group Treasury Manager, Multichoice:</h5>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin: 0.5em 2em 0em 0px;">
<img alt="Andre Olivier" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-03and04-tt-11-qa__andre-olivier__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=22F2BB615D727BF67E594288BB9AFD6D" width="100"/> 	<figcaption>
<h6>Andre Olivier</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin: 0.5em 2em 0em 0px;">
<img alt="Andrew Mills" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2018-03and04-tt-11-qa__andrew-mills__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=C9D5A9019B79F6808E66D4C90428C401" width="100"/> 	<figcaption>
<h6>Andrew Mills</h6>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>When one refers to or thinks of Africa, it is generally the great unknown of this ‘dark continent’ that causes one to lump it into a single homogenous land (country). The truth of course is that Africa is a continent with a populace of over 1.2bn people living in 54 countries, making it a truly diverse place. African economies are equally diverse. The largest 12 economies make up over 80% of the continent’s GDP.</p>
<p>One of the great inhibitors to free trade and flow of cash in and out of many African states is exchange control – a mechanism which many countries use to manage the value of their currencies. Many central banks also still manage their currencies actively. However, the overdependency on foreign export proceeds, primarily from commodity-based revenue, to fund large import requirements has forced some fiscal and monetary challenges. Nigeria and Egypt are the most recent cases in this regard, with both having shown a positive effect of moving to free-floating or adopting a managed float, although Nigeria continues with a dual exchange rate. Foreign currency liquidity remains a key risk however, with forward cover often acting as a means of securing currency and not only a hedging method – and generally at a steep premium. The availability of effective hedge instruments, particularly in times of illiquidity, also remains a challenge, with treasurers often having to resort to quasi-hedges.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, these reforms have generally been well received from the investor community, resulting in increased foreign portfolio flows and foreign direct investment, enabling greater economic transformation, diversification and growth. Nevertheless, undiversified revenue streams, generally low tax collections and political will to implement budgets effectively continue to hamper structural growth.</p>
<p>Despite this, there are many multi-national companies operating throughout Africa who bring the need for some level of sophistication in treasury management. Given the low GDP per-capita across Africa, many collections-based businesses use relatively low-tech solutions which are often cash-based. These require extensive branch banking networks in order to be close to the customer. The notable exception to this is Kenya, where the electronic wallet – m-Pesa – has flourished and very much revolutionised banking in that country.</p>
<p>For large businesses, there is a trade-off to be had between the use of local banks, which often have very weak credit ratings, if any rating at all, and the use of banks with a strong international reputation who also operate in Africa. The former may indeed offer a wider footprint compared to the latter but with elevated risk, particularly around capital security and visibility.</p>
<p>One of the most basic tenets of treasury management would be concentration of cash – ensuring that your cash can be controlled from a single point to extract maximum returns. Given the exchange controls in many African countries, cash pooling across regions is often not possible, but within countries there are banking solutions that enable cash sweeping across various banks so that cash can be concentrated to a single point. Sweeps can be automated or manual, zero-balance or target-balance, so the system can be as sophisticated as you want it to be. Using SWIFT messaging for payments and balance and transaction reporting is generally feasible but very market and bank dependent. Many still have a very underdeveloped banking infrastructure where simple operation execution may be a challenge, but others like South Africa are mature and conform to international standards. Increasingly though, the influence of international and regional banks and indeed cross-state collaboration, is contributing to the development of the financial sectors in the markets with increasing availability for products and services.</p>
<p>Corporate treasury on the continent has undoubtedly responded to the ‘VUCA environment’ it operates in by being a strategic partner to the executive and helping it navigate the often volatile and unpredictable markets. Leveraging technology to provide valued-add through treasury management systems is no longer considered a nice-to-have but seen as an essential part of treasury’s armour.</p>
<p>From the ‘Africa Rising’ narratives at the turn of the decade to one of ‘Rebalancing’, the now seasoned treasuries across the continent are ready to embrace the next chapter of this exciting frontier, alive with possibilities.</p>
<div class="question">
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<div class="copy__body">
<p>“How can treasury best define the company’s optimal capital structure and what steps can it take to achieve this?”</p>
</div></div></div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Sub-Saharan Africa: regional insight]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2016 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=0FCB6E0D2A500675440368CD72B24910]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2981DB6EEE82944ACB446860CCECB402"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3C6C7C123E56CEF798CFB70D7A688ADF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B7C9EDFA88F735DB23882FFBD56A3017"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3B4FF6E00FEAE9C225DDADDB1DAE6C78"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AB637686782050336C29FF600275E69D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Victoria Falls" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0FCB6E0D2A500675440368CD72B24910" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/thevictoriafallsisthelargestcurtainofwaterintheworldmeterswidethefallsand2286646691920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0FCB6E0D2A500675440368CD72B24910"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>With increasing levels of investment in Sub-Sharan Africa, many treasurers here in Asia Pacific are now having to deal with the nuances and local market realities that are present in this part of world. Here, we take a detailed look at these are and what constitutes best practice in Sub-Saharan Africa.</em></p>
<p>The rapid growth of countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) has been one of the global economy’s success stories over recent years. Two-thirds of the region’s countries boast more than ten years of sustained growth, whilst a quarter have enjoyed more than 20 years of continual GDP growth – and this looks set to continue.</p>
<p>Real growth in SSA countries was forecast by the IMF to be above 4% in 2015, a faster pace than all other developing regions – except China. That pace of growth is below the 4.4% annual average growth rate of the past two decades, though. But, unlike previous resource-dependent booms, growth is now more diversified. The rapidly expanding middle class and its increased spending, for instance, have made SSA appealing to consumer goods firms. Between 2005 and 2015, consumer spending grew at nearly three times the rate of average SSA GDP growth.</p>
<p>Also, over the past decade or so, SSA has experienced a marked shift in trade flows from traditional partners (predominately in Europe, North America and the Middle East) to faster growing Asian countries. China is now Africa’s largest trade partner, representing about a quarter of SSA’s trade from just 2.3% in the 1980s.</p>
<h3 id="market-realities">Market realities</h3>
<p>That said, it has been argued that macroeconomic indicators are insufficient at capturing the reality in each market – especially when it comes to industry-specific data. Perception and reality often diverge when it comes to Africa. In a Harvard Business Review article, for instance, it was suggested that whilst Angola’s market size and spending potential look good on paper, operating there may be very challenging without prior experience.</p>
<p>Akin to the region’s physical landscape, the markets of SSA vary greatly from country to country. Corporates could be unaware of which of the countries retain the greatest prospects for their business and whilst they offer great potential, failure to understand the nuances will cause problems for corporates.</p>
<p>Therefore, according to Patrick Gutmann, Group Head, Transaction Services Group for Ecobank, “having access to local knowledge is an important aspect of creating efficiency in the treasury environment.” He adds that in as far as regulation and business practices in SSA are concerned, not everything can be found online. By appreciating eyes, ears and relationships on the ground are necessary to circumnavigate the challenges and opportunities, corporates can hope to combine available data with knowledge of the operating environment in each market.</p>
<h3 id="hit-the-ground-running">Hit the ground running</h3>
<p>Firstly, it is worth noting that action is underway already. The value of merger and acquisitions (M&amp;As) targeting SSA companies reached a record $41.4bn in 2015, the lion share of which (86%) went into South Africa. Nigeria, Kenya and Angola also attracted billions of dollars of M&amp;A investments into energy and power sectors. Indeed, countries are attracting investor attention as the continent’s natural resource sector further develops. Additionally, the Global Competitiveness Index (GCI) identified numerous SSA countries – including Mauritius, South Africa, Rwanda, Botswana, Namibia, Kenya and Seychelles – as having scores comparable to the averages set by other emerging regions. Increased infrastructure spending has been supporting the countries in lowering operating costs – highly encouraging for commodity exporters, for instance.</p>
<p>It would be wrong to ignore the challenges, however. Barriers to economic development include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The lack of job creation in line with development.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Poor infrastructure, especially electricity and transport.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Limited supply of skilled labour.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Socio-political challenges.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Headwinds also come in the form of plummeting commodity prices and volatility globally. What’s more, the increased participation of low-cost emerging and developing countries in global trade, combined with the fall in commodity prices, has accentuated the need to prioritise competitiveness-enhancing reforms.</p>
<p>Concerns in specific countries include the South African Central Bank’s defence of the rand, which is reducing the availability of hard currency in the country, subduing growth potential. In fact, local African currencies across the continent have been fluctuating against the dollar recently, causing many a corporate headache (<a href="#chart-1">chart 1</a>). “Treasury departments need to have the skills to deal with currency volatility,” says Artemis Galatis, General Manager, ACTSA (Association of Corporate Treasurers of Southern Africa). “The peaks and troughs can be far greater in emerging currencies than in sterling or USD.”</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: African local currency fluctuation against the USD</h4>
<p>Jan 2015 to date</p>
<p><a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2016-05-06-tt-08-rt__chart-01__african-local-currency-fluctuation__765x764.png?la=en&amp;hash=6F10E9AE0E112A3CB7FCFA6A50BE41D5" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: African local currency fluctuation against the USD" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/2016-05-06-tt-08-rt__chart-01__african-local-currency-fluctuation__765x764.png?la=en&amp;hash=6F10E9AE0E112A3CB7FCFA6A50BE41D5" width="400"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: Standard Chartered Research</em></p>
<p>As a result of some of these challenges, author of the aptly named ‘Africa: rich but poor’, Joseph Amamoo, laments the fact that Africa has an abundance of resources which remain unexploited. “You get situations in villages where there may be diamonds in the ground but the people, with limited education, do not know they’re there. Even if they did, they don’t know how to mine them, nor do they have the machinery to do so,” he says. “You need foreign investors to help in a joint effort to exploit these resources for the benefit of both sides.” Amamoo clarifies, however, that corporates cannot expect conditions to be the same as in developed countries. Power outages and untreated water, for instance, are common across SSA.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, there are strengths – a burgeoning and young labour force which is expected to increase dramatically just as the rest of the world starts ageing, for instance. Additionally, as Amamoo highlighted, there are untapped resources. For example, the agricultural sector represents an opportunity for growth: the region holds more than 60% of arable land globally yet only 15% is under cultivation. In a recent Citi Online Academy webinar, titled ‘Getting a Grip on Africa’, Peter Crawley, Managing Director, Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions Head, Sub-Saharan Africa at Citi estimated that in terms of global resources, SSA holds around 18% of gold, 42% of diamonds, 65% of cobalt reserves, 95% of platinum, 8% of natural gas and vast amounts of oil.</p>
<h3 id="leapfrogging-old-technologies">Leapfrogging old technologies</h3>
<p>In terms of adapting to local variances, treasury expertise has developed in accordance with different needs, which are perhaps uniquely prominent in the region; for example, when dealing with buyers and distributors that operate largely in cash. “The prevalence of physical cash is a challenge that corporates who embark on a journey on the continent will have to handle effectively,” says Gutmann.</p>
<p>Mobile has emerged as a solution to this challenge. It is well known that Africa leads the way when it comes to mobile money accounts – only 34% of adults in SSA had a bank account in 2014, but 12% have a mobile money account, according to the World Bank’s Financial Inclusion Database. “Because mobile banking has taken hold in many countries, there is a natural infrastructure from which to create less of a cash-based payment environment – and to eliminate the inefficiencies associated with handling cash,” says Gutmann. “Corporates can now leverage mobile infrastructure both in terms of making payments out into areas that otherwise might not be reached and accepting funds through a mobile wallet.”</p>
<p>Indeed, the arrival of electronic payments and mobile technology has been transformational in Africa, allowing the treasurer to ‘circumvent’ Africa’s poor infrastructure without being hamstrung by legacy technologies. For a continent that has long been dependent on physical cash flows, increasing digitisation has led to large gains in cash traceability, immediacy of notification and information visibility. Citi, for instance, has seen a 29% increase in host-to-host connectivity since 2012, with 20% of those clients using XML file format. This is supported by increased sophistication in the back end clearing of central banks. Nigeria, where advances in payments infrastructure has resulted in widespread uptake of NIBSS Instant Payments, was highlighted as an example in the webinar by Geoffrey Gursel, Director, Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions Sales Head, Sub-Saharan Africa at Citi.</p>
<p>What is less known perhaps is that Africa could leapfrog into a new era of power generation, responding to climate change related hazards prominent in the region, resolving some internal issues (such as power outages) and providing a competitive edge. The Africa Progress Report 2015 presents the case that “utility reform, new technologies and new business models could be as transformative in energy as the mobile phone has been in telecommunications”, as demand for modern energy is set to surge. In particular, renewable energy – including solar, geothermal and wind power – is making some remarkable advances in Africa, the report notes.</p>
<h3 id="banking-landscape">Banking landscape</h3>
<p>However, sustainable power will not be the panacea to Africa’s struggles. The banking sector plays a huge part in ensuring corporates can indeed operate in, invest in and finance such projects. Whilst acknowledging that the maturity of the banking sector across SSA can differ significantly, Gutmann says: “It is fair to say that across the continent, all of the countries are seeing significant development creating efficiencies within their banking landscape.”</p>
<p>Whilst in the past the reliance on local banks led to corporates having a large number of banking partners, the increasing adoption of SWIFT and host-to-host has resulted in a desire to have fewer banks, minimising the cost and administrative burden. For Philip Panaino, Regional Head, Transactional Banking, Africa and Middle East, Standard Chartered, technology has afforded treasurers regional advances in support. “If you are operating in SSA with global banks, you will have access to similar capabilities, platforms and technology found internationally,” he says.</p>
<p>What’s more, sophisticated technology won’t always be the reserve of the international banks. “The traditional challenge that local or regional banks in SSA do not have the same level of technological capabilities as multinationals in Europe or the US are used to is closing,” says Gutmann.</p>
<p>Ecobank invested considerably in infrastructure to support the use of less manual processes in its cash management system, Omni, explains Sonya Crites, Head of Cash Management Products at D+H, the solutions provider which worked with the bank. The single uniform online banking platform allows a treasurer visibility and transparency into all of their accounts across Ecobank’s entire footprint. They can also integrate other non-Ecobank accounts into that offering. “To give clients access to the entire Africa footprint through a single portal is quite powerful,” says Gutmann.</p>
<p>But whilst technology is allowing regional strategies to become a reality, local knowledge is a necessity for business operations. The questions treasurers must answer, such as whether to use SWIFT, mobile, TMSs, online banking platforms and so on, are eased by knowledge of each market and the risks to mitigate – particularly when it comes to regulation. Challenges include the widespread illegality of cross-border notional pooling to on-the-ground difficulties such as obtaining work permits for employees of certain nationalities. Exchange controls are particularly problematic as most countries don’t allow the free movement of funds cross-border. The underlying exchange control regulation in most SSA countries is that goods and services have to accompany foreign exchange, but this is at odds with notional pooling, the method treasurers would typical turn to in order to manage liquidity, concentrating funds for optimal interest returns.</p>
<p>In South Africa, stringent exchange control regulations shielded the economy somewhat from the credit crunch in 2008. “As a result, corporates in the country are less sceptical of banks. It is a trusting environment,” says Galatis. On the whole, she says, whilst on the face of it corporates may feel regulation is restrictive, SSA regulators are “listening to their needs and trying to accommodate wherever they can”.</p>
<p>Panaino concurs: “If clients experience challenges or queries around industry frameworks and regulation, we proactively engage regulators on the clients’ behalf. In 90% of the cases, we have achieved a flexible and sensible evolution on various complex issues, demonstrating the merits of facilitating two-way flow of communication between the public and private sectors.”</p>
<h3 id="the-silver-lining">The silver lining</h3>
<p>Treasurers of large multinationals in SSA are those weathering the current storm the best, despite the region’s varying rules, according to Citi’s webinar; Gina Schoeman, South African Economist, Citi spoke of listed companies in South Africa enjoying economies of scale, allowing them to perform better than SMEs. The metrics can reflect a slightly cloudier view, though. But whilst Citi predicts stagnated growth of 0.3% for 2016, the outlook over the longer-term moves “in the right direction”, says Schoeman, reaching 1.8% by 2018. This highlights that the African growth story is a long-term game. Potential remains attractive, but making it to that prosperous point depends upon a corporate’s ability to adapt to the current environment.</p>
<p>According to Frontier Strategy Group’s Sub-Saharan Africa Resilience to External Shocks Index, adaptation could be the key to success. Indicative of this, Google won a Treasury Today Adam Smith Award in the ‘Harnessing the power of technology’ category by implementing a scalable mobile payment solution, despite Africa’s diverse peculiarities and infrastructural inadequacies.</p>
<p>In fact, Panaino says that nuances “are what make Africa vibrant and exciting”, and it is this which has driven corporates to establish the region’s own set of treasury best practices, and support “the progression of the sector as a whole, encouraging the uplift of skills and expertise”.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Africa: perception vs perspective]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>The long-held perception that Africa is an opaque and challenging place to do business is changing, with investors flocking to the continent as never before. In this article Sneha Shah, Managing Director – Sub-Saharan Africa at Thomson Reuters, provides perspective on how investors are addressing risk, and why the opportunities outweigh the challenges.</em></p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard">
<img alt="Sneha Shah, Managing Director, Thomson Reuters" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/sneha-shah-thomson-reuters-150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=2B3C4F85843DB41C1D6488D078E1DB98" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Sneha Shah</h3>
<h5 class="title">Managing Director</h5>
<p><img alt="Thomson Reuters logo" class="logo org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/thomson-reuters-logo-2013-168x37.png?la=en&amp;hash=3B4AE0952CBF1042511D947CF87B57B9" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Thomson Reuters" width="168"/></p>
<p>Sneha Shah was appointed Managing Director of sub-Saharan Africa for Thomson Reuters in April 2015, with responsibility for developing strategy and executing operational plans in all business units.</p>
<p>Born in Kenya, Sneha is passionate about empowering Africa’s success, and has initiated partnerships with international market development, media and training providers, led regional and global mentoring programmes and worked with public and private sector organisations. She is a member of the African Leadership Network and the World Economic Forum’s Global Agenda Council on Governance.</p>
<p>Sneha joined Thomson Reuters in 2001, holding several global leadership roles in operations, product development and technology before moving to South Africa to lead the Financial and Risk business Africa in 2013. Prior to joining Thomson Reuters, Sneha was a commodities trader and traded money markets and FX. She chaired the Women@Thomson Reuters Global Advisory Council from 2012 to 2014. She holds a BA (Hons) degree in Politics with International Studies from the University of Warwick in the UK.</p>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Africa is home to five of the world’s fastest growing economies, with the youngest population in the world. Technology is thriving across the continent, especially in the mobile space, with pioneering solutions in healthcare, education and financial payments. Investors and economists are focused on the promise of the ‘next ten’ biggest cities in sub-Saharan Africa, whose population is projected to come close to doubling by 2030. Clearly all of these factors present significant opportunities and risks, and navigating these requires an understanding of the realities on the ground, beyond traditional views of the “dark continent”.</p>
<h3 id="fundamental-challenges">Fundamental challenges</h3>
<p>The challenges facing businesses, governments and individuals in Africa are undeniable – from infrastructure issues to a reputation for instability and corruption, the continent is not for the faint-hearted. In Kenya for example, it is estimated that 30% of the country’s budget is lost every year to corruption.</p>
<p>“Many of these illicit transactions are related to interactions between the public and private sector. In a high-growth environment, and with several large scale projects needing multi-stakeholder partnerships, some organisations are gaining market share in unethical ways” explains Sneha Shah. EY reported that one in three Kenyan companies surveyed had paid bribes to win contracts and PwC notes that tender fraud is the fastest growing economic crime in Kenya. “These types of interactions don’t just affect the stakeholders of the projects and countries involved. They also give rise to networks that facilitate corruption and crime into and out of the African continent,” adds Shah.</p>
<p>The issue is stopping many organisations from doing business on the continent. “Barclays, for example, believes that allowing remittances to flow to Somalia through their channels is too risky,” says Shah. “Multinational corporations are increasingly concerned with compliance with international financial regulation and the potential risk to the firm, both in terms of reputation and possible legal penalties from the US and other jurisdictions.”</p>
<p>Apart from fines, failure to proactively identify and manage risk can directly or indirectly have deadly consequences. The so-called White Widow – real name Samantha Lewthwaite, widow of the 7/7 terrorist bomber in London and suspected of involvement in the Westgate massacre, was able to open bank accounts with two major South African banks under an assumed name. Limiting access to financing and cross-border flows for suspected individuals is therefore a key measure in fighting terrorism.</p>
<h3 id="african-challenges-in-global-perspective">African challenges in global perspective</h3>
<p>“While Africa does have some extreme examples of financial crime and corruption, the issue is a global one and the need to assess risk realistically and maintain perspective is imperative,” explains Shah.</p>
<p>Many commentators and business people in the west see illicit activity as a problem that plagues the developing world far more than countries like the US. However, while that may be true in some cases, where citizens in Lagos, Accra or Nairobi for example may be more often asked to pay bribes to get things done than in New York or London, recent global financial scandals, and record fines paid by banks in Europe and America suggest that the problem may manifest differently but is common to most countries in the world.</p>
<p>Take for instance former New Orleans Mayor Ray Nagin, a US politician sent to jail for abuse of power – officials say Nagin took at least $500,000 in under-the-table money in exchange for several contractors being awarded several millions of dollars’ worth of city contracts. Nagin joins a long list of politicians who have been found guilty of abusing their office.</p>
<p>“In the US today, the concentration of wealth in private hands is at an unprecedented level and with many corporations larger than some governments, the perceived political influence of private companies is a cause for concern to citizens,” says Shah. “Movements like “Occupy” reflect the loss of trust by citizens in business leaders and public officials.” In 1964, 29% of voters said that they believed that the government was run by a few big private interests that were looking out for themselves. In 2013, 79% of voters felt this way.</p>
<p>A recent study, “Risky Business”, by the Combating Terrorism Center at WestPoint, using data from Thomson Reuters World-Check, showed that perceived connections between private and public figures are real and can be dangerous and far-reaching. In a sample of 2700 individuals across terrorism, crime and other illicit activity around the world, the report found many more connections across other types of crime and terror networks than was expected, and extensive global connections between suspicious individuals in developed and developing nations. What this means for banks and corporations, whether investing in Africa, other emerging markets or the US or Europe, is that understanding and managing who they are doing business with is critical, as the consequences of partnering with or funding a high risk individual can be significant to the organisation as well as society.</p>
<p>By its nature, illicit activity and corruption is a hidden phenomenon and we will never truly know the scale of the problem. What we can be sure of though is that the issue is broader than bribes, or a few high profile financial or political scandals. Crime and corruption networks are interconnected, global and impact everything from national budgets and resources, to citizen safety, and solving the issue is the shared responsibility of governments, corporations and civil society in Africa and around the world.</p>
<h3 id="change-on-the-horizon">Change on the horizon</h3>
<p>How do we effect change on this issue at scale in Africa? The demographics of the continent are unique: with 200 million people aged between 15 and 24, Africa has the youngest population in the world. The current trend indicates that this figure will double by 2045. This generation are technologically savvy, more globally aware, and have higher expectations of business and political leadership than their parents. Thanks to innovations in education, even those in rural areas will have more access to information and education, and like their millennial counterparts globally, they want to be part of a cause or mission, and are not held back by traditional views of authority, boundaries and controls. Engaging and harnessing this generation in the fight against illicit activity will be important.</p>
<p>“In addition to leveraging the demand from the millennials for change, there are many other factors in Africa that support increased governance and transparency,” says Shah. “Technology, connectivity, regional integration and institutions are key, as is the global push on supply chain transparency and financial regulation.”</p>
<p>Technology and connectivity are helping Africa to leapfrog traditional economies in several ways. According to a recent study on financial habits by the Gates Foundation, the World Bank and Gallup World Poll, the sheer number of people using mobile in Africa is the highest in world. “In the financial sector there is a push for a cashless society to ensure a consistent paper trail and reduce fraud,” explains Shah. “Mobile telecom players such as MTN, Vodacom and Airtel Africa, are investing millions of dollars in infrastructure, consumer education and awareness to broaden mobile money propositions and drive financial inclusion.” Most people are aware of the pioneering mobile money transfer service M-Pesa, the first of its kind in the world, launched in Kenya and now used by over 24 million people in East Africa, but, although less written about, newer mobile offerings such as M-Kopa (a pay-as-you-go energy provision to off grid homes) or M-Shwari (a mobile bank account offering a combination of savings and loans), are exciting developments driving innovation, financial inclusion and transparency. Availing mobile services to customers means they shift cash transactions into a digital ecosystem relatively cheaply, securely, and reliably. Some countries, like Nigeria, are going even further with a biometric ID and payments system plan for all citizens.</p>
<p>In addition to technology as a driver for transparency, the cause is helped by several African states actively pushing for greater regional trade and economic integration. For instance, many African states subscribe to the Financial Action Task Force (FATF) and choose to be peer reviewed. The African Peer Review Mechanism (APRM), is an instrument voluntarily acceded to by member states of the African Union (AU) as a self-monitoring mechanism for African states to ensure that policies and practices of participating states conform to the agreed political, economic and corporate governance values, codes and standards. Another example is the SADC (Southern African Development Community) Payments Project, which is creating and implementing standards and regional interoperable payments systems that will increase efficiency and automate transactions and verification process across the sub-region.</p>
<h3 id="a-region-of-endless-potential">A region of endless potential</h3>
<p>“African countries that foster an environment of transparency and governance will surely benefit from greater economic opportunities,” says Shah. “The demographics, a rising middle class creating great product and services demand, and increased focus on land rights, rule of law, education and the development of financial markets are all promising trends for Africa.”</p>
<p>“The risk of corruption and illicit activity exists everywhere, including Africa,” Shah concludes. “However, by proactively assessing and managing risks and supporting initiatives that drive transparency, corporations, banks, investors and governments will be able to successfully harness the enormous growth potential of this region.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Nigeria: the giant of Africa]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Oct 2014 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=7EF41284CDBE41F76DA3AAD43909DE6B]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B64639D6B41E0059DCB698E5E7FEC864"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BB038CC33263D3BB465AE4F393B1888E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1667FBC7F30AF4323BD8810D13F269BF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B57A12BCBF2EFEAE3E6D36B1D2197CCF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=49B414D873F5D763FB8A2517EFEF40E9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Two elephants touching each other, greeting" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7EF41284CDBE41F76DA3AAD43909DE6B" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/africa/elephants-touching-each-other-gently-greeting-addo-elephant-national-park-111119381.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7EF41284CDBE41F76DA3AAD43909DE6B"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>In April this year Nigeria, already Africa’s most populous country, overtook South Africa to become the continent’s largest economy. A long overdue rebasing of the Nigerian economy saw industries such as airlines, telecoms and e-commerce included in the country’s GDP figures for the first time. The statistical re-shuffle added 85% to the country’s GDP overnight, which now totals $510 billion, making Nigeria the 26<sup>th</sup> largest economy in the world.</p>
<p>Nigeria has come a long way since gaining independence from the United Kingdom in 1960. The initial signs were positive following independence and the country being awarded an ‘emerging economy’ label. However, political turmoil, which included several military coups and a civil war, and unfavourable economic events, have conspired against the country. Although some impressive growth was recorded during the oil boom of the 1970s, the adverse political climate meant the benefits were not passed down to SMEs, or to the general population, and the growth levels couldn’t be sustained. All this led to, at the turn of the century, Nigeria being one of the poorest economies in the world.</p>
<p>Since then, political reform and democratisation, has brought an end to over 30 years of military rule, putting Nigeria back on track to achieve its full economic potential. The country is now regarded to be a lower middle income emerging market. Oil still remains at the heart of the economy, and is the nation’s primary export to countries such as the US, India and the Netherlands. Nigeria’s main imports are primarily machinery, chemicals, transport equipment and manufactured goods from China, the US and India.</p>
<p>In recent years, the government of Nigeria has looked to move away from its dependence on oil. And the recent rebasing of the economy demonstrates the increasingly diverse nature of the Nigerian economy as the services sector now accounts for 52% of GDP, and manufacturing rose from 1.9% to 6.8%. At the same time, the oil and gas sector declined relative to GDP, falling from 32.4% to 14.4% after rebasing. Nevertheless, the oil and gas sector still remains the main revenue driver from the Nigerian government.</p>
<p>Due to these developments, and its large, youthful population, the long-term outlook for the Nigerian economy is positive. The nation was famously named as one of the high economic potential MINT (Mexico, Indonesia, Nigeria, and Turkey) countries, a term coined by Fidelity Investments.</p>
<p>To help the country fulfil that potential, the government introduced ‘Vision 20:2020’ in 2009 – an 11 year economic plan which looks to stimulate economic growth and place the country on a path of sustained socio-economic development. Five years on, although the message from the government is that the plan remains on track, Standard and Poor’s has revised its outlook for the country, downgrading from CreditWatch negative to negative, citing political in-fighting and political and institutional risks. The downgrade is a sobering reminder that, despite the positives of recent years, the country still has a number of pressing issues to resolve before it can fully step-up.</p>
<h3 id="key-challenges">Key challenges</h3>
<p>One of the key challenges facing Nigeria is poverty. The World Bank earlier this year stated that 33.1% live in poverty, 55.9 million of the 162 million population. However, the Nigerian National Bureau of Statistics estimates that 120 million of the 162 million people in Nigeria, 67% of the population, live in poverty. Whichever the amount, income inequality, political instability and corruption are largely regarded as the key reasons for the poverty levels and the government’s anti-poverty programmes are struggling to overcome the challenge.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, despite the political reforms, the political situation in the country still remains fragile, with in-fighting dividing the country’s ruling party, the People’s Democratic Party. In addition, sectarian violence is commonplace throughout the country and has caught the worldwide media’s attention in recent months through the actions of Boko Haram, a militant Islamist movement based in the North East of the country. This type of violence can bring challenges to businesses as some areas of the country are too dangerous to move goods through.</p>
<p>Little surprise, then, that Nigeria is widely regarded as a challenging place to do business. The World Bank ranks the country 147<sup>th</sup> out of 189 in its Doing Business 2014 survey, citing not only socio-political conditions but also infrastructural challenges. Basic services such as electricity are in short supply – the World Bank ranks the country 185<sup>th</sup> out of 189 in terms of ease of getting electricity. And when electricity is not an issue, transportation is: take the underdeveloped roads and transportation networks which often create delays in moving goods around the country, for example. This can cause supply chain, forecasting and inventory problems for corporates operating in the country which can significantly increase the cost of doing business, not to mention the effect on a corporate’s cash conversion cycle. It is also extremely difficult to register property in Nigeria and a weak rule of law and judiciary in the country mean that companies may be exposed to corruption and political interference.</p>
<p>Yet, despite all the challenges, many companies are thriving and Nigeria remains one of the top three destinations in Africa for foreign direct investment with inflows of $5.6 billion in 2013 according to the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development.</p>
<h3 id="a-revamped-financial-sector">A revamped financial sector</h3>
<p>As foreign investment and corporate involvement in Nigeria have increased, the country’s financial sector has undergone significant changes following years of underperformance. To modernise and strengthen the sector, the Nigerian government has sought to consolidate the banks, raise the levels of capitalisation required, adopt a risk and rules-based regulatory framework, while also strengthening existing laws. The reforms have had a dramatic effect on the sector which now exists with just over 20 banks compared to over 100 a few years ago. “If we look at the legacy Nigerian banking landscape and compare that to what we have today, it has improved vastly over recent years,” says Sam Ocheho, Head, Global Markets, Stanbic IBTC.</p>
<p>The sector is regulated by the Central Bank of Nigeria (CBN) and comprises mainly local banks and a handful of global banks. As is the case in many emerging markets, local banks dominate in the payments and collections space due to their expansive branch network which penetrates the furthest reaches of the country. The global banks on the other hand are primarily focused on the larger scale domestic corporates and international corporates offering more complex outward facing products and connecting these companies to the global financial system. “We find that multinational companies in Nigeria want to use one global bank in the country alongside relationships with one or two local banks,” says Segun Adaramola, Head of Treasury and Trade Solutions at Citibank Nigeria. “In doing so, they are able to leverage the international banks for their sophisticated outward looking business while also using a combination of local and international banks for their domestic collections and payments.” Corporate funding is widely available to all sectors of the economy and this is offered using an informal tier system. The large international companies will readily have access to the cheapest funding – in some cases it has been reported that these companies obtain cheaper funding than the government. The range of products which banks are offering to corporates is also increasing, especially as the nature of Nigerian businesses becomes more global and more complex products are called for.</p>
<h3 id="foreign-exchange-rules">Foreign exchange rules</h3>
<p>The banks also play a key role in assisting corporates to move capital in and out of the country. In order to keep the managed exchange rate stable, the CBN has regulated the foreign exchange market extensively and there are a number of rules corporates must follow to import and remit funds. “If a company is looking to bring funds into the country, it must seek a certificate of capital importation,” says David Adepoju, Head of Global Markets at Standard Chartered. “Only with this document will it be able to then convert the principle investment and capital gains from Naira to USD and repatriate.”</p>
<p>To make the process of both importing and exporting funds easier for corporates the CBN has empowered banks to grant a certificate of capital importation based on a set of guidelines, if these guidelines are not met then the corporate will need to seek central bank approval.</p>
<p>Additional documentation is also required to remove profits from the country. “A corporate is required to demonstrate the transaction history of the investment in order to repatriate the full amount,” says Adepoju. “The best way to do this is by leveraging a bank or custodian, because although the process isn’t necessary complex, a bank is well placed to help guide corporates through this area.”</p>
<p>A further headache for corporates looking to repatriate profits from Nigeria is that the country can sometimes lack dollar liquidity, despite petrodollars and remittances from abroad bringing $63.17 billion dollars into the country in 2013. The level of liquidity depends on what the CBN is doing at the time. But at times that it is limited, it can make taking money out fairly difficult for corporates.</p>
<p>Recognising the increasing importance of China to the Nigerian economy, trade between the two countries hit almost $13 billion in 2013, and the CNB announced plans to convert an additional 5% of its dollar reserves into yuan. In an interview with Bloomberg, CBN Deputy Governor Kingsley Moghalu, stated that “It was clear to us that the future of international economics and trade will shift in large part to business with and by China. Ultimately, the renminbi is likely to become a global convertible currency.”</p>
<h3 id="a-growing-hedging-market">A growing hedging market</h3>
<p>Hedging products are widely available for corporates in Nigeria, yet despite increasing global trade, they are still rarely used. “Very few companies have a hedging strategy in place,” says Ocheho. “For me this is either due to lack of capacity, prohibitive costs; lack of education or parent companies policies against hedging by multi-national companies across some jurisdictions. Companies are therefore leaving themselves open to exchange rate volatility as they develop into the global market – and also interest rate volatility.”</p>
<p>The primary hedging products which are available to corporates are vanilla forwards and swaps. But in a bid to increase the popularity of the derivatives market in Nigeria, the CBN has been hard at work. “The market in conjunction with CBN has developed a new OTC exchange (FMDQ OTC), a self-regulatory body for OTC transactions in Nigeria,” says Ocheho. “The company is expected to increase the level of transparency in our financial market and also build a credible platform where more complex derivatives trades can be done.” Standard Chartered’s Adepoju paints a similar picture: “As the amount of capital and finance which the country’s banks and corporates have expands, and the duration of banking books and corporate loans becomes longer, there will be much more activity around hedging and the market will start developing more quickly. This is something which we have already started to see in the oil and gas sector, for example.”</p>
<h3 id="the-end-of-cash">The end of cash</h3>
<p>A report released by MasterCard earlier this year showed that Nigeria spends $5.1 billion a year printing and handling cash, approximately 1% of its annual GDP. In order to reduce costs and mitigate the risks of such a heavily cash-based economy, the CNB introduced a cash lite policy in 2012 which looks to reduce the circulation of cash and move to electronic transactions. As part of the 20:2020 project, this began in Lagos and has since spread further across the country.</p>
<p>The main elements of this policy include a cash handling charge on daily cash withdrawals that exceed 500,000 naira for individuals and three million naira for corporates. “Two or three years ago, cash in Nigeria accounted for about 60% to 70% of transaction volume. As of today this figure has reduced to around 40% or less” says Citi’s Segun Adaramola. This shows the impact of the cash lite initiative and the growing importance of electronic payments in the country.” To facilitate the project, there has been an overhaul of the country’s payments and settlements systems. “The payments and settlements system in the country is now excellent,” says Standard Chartered’s Adepoju, “and this is positive for all corporates in the country.” The improvements have meant that corporates are able to make payments using the improved Real Time Gross Settlement (RTGS) Service within an hour and sometimes in less than ten seconds, depending on the value. “There has been a lot of work to ensure that this works smoothly,” adds Adepoju. “Also the CBN has put in place a process whereby cheque clearing has been reduced to one day, again helping corporate operations in the country.”</p>
<p>Having only been implemented across the majority of the country earlier this year, the jury is still out on how the project will work in the less developed cities and regions. Nevertheless, Adepoju doesn’t believe that there will be any significant challenges for corporates and that it is overall a positive development. “Most corporates would prefer to use electronic transfers because cash is expensive to handle. Using electronic platforms also allows corporates to have better real-time view of cash flows.”</p>
<p>The technological infrastructure, however, may hinder the development of the cashless policy. Despite significant improvements, broadband penetration across the country is low with an adoption rate of around 15% – the global average is 35%. This may prevent consumers and SMEs from readily adopting electronic payments, meaning that corporates will still need to handle a large proportion of cash.</p>
<h3 id="cash-management">Cash management</h3>
<p>When it comes to investing excess cash, short-term investment instruments in the market are also vanilla – with bank deposits, bankers’ acceptance and treasury bills being the most commonly used. Money market funds (MMFs) are available in Nigeria from the leading domestic banks and government treasury bills are often used by sophisticated corporates in the country.</p>
<p>It is expected that as further economic development attracts more international corporates to the country, the sophistication of cash management products will increase. “As the demand creates more financing to be required by corporates then more complexity will enter the treasury landscape in order to manage the additional risk. We expect to see many exciting developments in the coming years” says Adepoju.</p>
<h3 id="a-developing-market">A developing market</h3>
<p>In short, Nigeria is a country with giant potential and while on the whole the future looks bright, there are many challenges to overcome in the short term. It is predicted that the upcoming elections in 2015 will run smoothly – and after that, further improvements in political and social stability can be expected. Moreover, as Nigeria continues to improve its infrastructure and business landscape, the cost of operating in the country should decrease. This should drive more foreign investment into the country, which will generate greater opportunities for the young population. Organic growth such as this will help Nigeria to maintain its leading status in Africa, while also moving towards its global aspirations.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Africa: the final frontier]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2014 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Africa has huge economic potential. The continent, which is home to just over a billion people, has a wealth of natural resources, the largest share of the world’s uncultivated arable land, and now, also, a rapidly growing middle-class with a new-found penchant for consumer goods. It is, in a number of respects, the final growth frontier in the global economy.</p>
<p>Despite all this potential, Africa’s share of global trade remains very small, and is actually declining. Trade flows offer a convincing explanation as to why this is the case. African countries tend to trade much more with far-away lands such as China, India and Brazil than they do with each other. It is not a new phenomenon, by any means. Weak intra-continental trade has, in fact, hindered growth prospects for most countries in the region ever since independence.</p>
<p>The reasons are well-documented. In Africa, a century and a half of European colonialism had left behind an economic system and infrastructure focused on extracting the continent’s natural resources for export back to Europe. An absence of adequate road and rail connections is only part of the story, however. Trade between African countries is also weighed down by a near impenetrable plethora of bureaucracies, not to mention, the corruption found at border posts.</p>
<h3 id="trading-spaces">Trading spaces</h3>
<p>Until recently, very little had been done to encourage improved trade relations between the 50-plus individual economies of which Africa is comprised. That changed when the world’s trade ministers met in Bali at the end of last year for the biennial World Trade Organisation (WTO) conference. In a step which will surely have huge implications for the African continent’s future growth prospects, officials signed a trade facilitation agreement with the explicit purpose of cutting back the red tape that holds up the transfer of goods at national borders.</p>
<p>A study of the proposal carried out prior to the conference by the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) predicted enormous benefits from the deal for African nations. The measures would reduce total trade costs by 10% in advanced economies and by 13-15.5% in developing countries. Just a 1% reduction in global trade costs would increase worldwide income by more than $40 billion, most of which would be accrued by developing countries, the report found.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>African countries tend to trade much more with faraway lands such as China, India and Brazil than they do with each other.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Removing barriers to reduce the cost of trade is just the medicine Africa needs, says Jason Barrass, Head of Africa Trade at Barclays. “It’s a basic principle of economics,” Barrass says. “The faster economies can move goods and money around the greater their GDP will be.” Red tape at customs can seriously harm the competitiveness of African companies. The price of a product may be quite competitive at the point in which it leaves the factory gates, but it is often a very different story once it has gone cross-border. “I think there is somewhere in the region of 14 different customs unions on the continent. There’s very little in the way of conformity and it is totally inefficient.”</p>
<p>Tackling these issues will not be easy, however. A 2012 report by the African Development Bank reveals the sheer enormity of the transformation required to bring African trade up to speed. In most African countries, two sets of controls need to be completed on each side of the border post. An average transaction typically involves up to 20-30 different parties, 40 documents and 200 data elements which usually need to be rekeyed at least once.</p>
<p>It’s a bureaucratic nightmare; one which does little to negate Africa’s image as a difficult place for companies to do business in. “A lot of companies are not very enthusiastic about investing in Africa,” says Klaus-Dieter Ruske, PwC’s global leader for the transportation and logistics sector. On a number of occasions in recent years, Ruske has met with corporate executives and spoken of the huge opportunities for growth he sees in the continent. Many of them agreed, but their willingness to seize such opportunities was tempered by the absence of a secure, facilitative business environment. “They would tell me that there are a lack of stable political systems, and if they want to trade on the continent they know they will have to pay black money to customs officials.”</p>
<p>Tackling these problems will require enormous willpower from Africa’s political leaders. Finding it won’t be easy however, when the actions that need to be taken in order to secure improvements in intra-African trade are inevitably going to be very painful in the short term. “African governments with small tax payers are heavily reliant on import duties to make up for the lack of tax base,” notes Jerry Pearce, Head of Product Management &amp; Head of TPS at Standard Bank. It is, Pearce adds, one of the key reasons why economic integration initiatives in Africa across the years have so often failed to deliver. “Given the relative poverty of most African countries, it is difficult for governments to give up the small amounts of revenue they receive, and it is unlikely that they could easily shift the burden elsewhere.”</p>
<h3 id="fighting-back">Fighting back</h3>
<p>If anything is to change, businesses in Africa need to highlight the difficulties they encounter when trading with other African countries. In May 2012, a private sector advocacy and education group called the Borderless Alliance was established. The main work of the group is collecting and publishing data on trade inefficiencies throughout the region, to apply pressure on decision-makers to reform their policies and help develop their economies. Some of the figures published in the group’s quarterly reports are eye-opening; it is a litany of illegitimate checkpoints, lengthy delays and bribery, both on the roads and at border posts.</p>
<p>The group has also established a Border Information Centre on the Ghana-Togo border in order to help companies navigate the complex procedures involved in moving goods across West Africa’s borders. According to a recently published case study, 61 businesses – including the likes of Unilever – have already benefited from the service, and there are now plans to open a second branch at the Benin-Nigeria border later this year.</p>
<p>That private sector groups such as Border Alliance are now taking on a more prominent role in regional trade facilitation is evidently a positive step. The message seems to be getting across to Africa’s leaders too. “Change will come eventually,” says PWC’s Ruske. “Sub-Saharan nations in particular are now clearly seeing both the need and opportunity for improved trade with one another.” In February this year, South African President Jacob Zuma announced that talks being held between eastern and southern African nations to establish a tripartite free trade area were progressing well. It is still early days, but if the negotiations do succeed, the result will be the integration of 26 nations into a single market with a population of more than 600 million.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a step which will surely have huge implications for the African continent’s future growth prospects, officials signed a trade facilitation agreement with the explicit purpose of cutting back the red tape that holds up the transfer of goods at national borders.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="mind-the-gap">Mind the gap</h3>
<p>Since the cost of trade is extremely high in Africa, many companies – particularly SMEs – struggle to get the credit they require to get their goods to market. It is partly a product of the continent’s risk profile which, due to the aforementioned infrastructure and governance issues, looks very different from developed regions.</p>
<p>“Banks are not immune to the fact that corporate clients trading within the continent face a lot of difficulties,” says Barclays’ Barrass. But helping a greater number of companies in Africa to secure financing on their receivables would almost certainly provide a huge boost for intraregional trade. For a company trading into a new territory, such as Zambia or Ethiopia it can be difficult, initially, to understand the local requirements and what risks should be taken in those markets. “That is where a bank like Barclays steps in,” he adds. “It is our business to understand risk, to know how to get money out of countries, and to help them with their cash flow.”</p>
<p>Barrass acknowledges that a gap has emerged in the provision of trade finance in recent years. In the wake of the catastrophic events that hit financial markets in 2008, many financiers removed liquidity from peripheral markets, such as Africa, in order to cover positions in core areas. In addition local financial institutions found it difficult to access credit in international markets, and financing for a large number of SMEs began to retrench as a consequence. According to a report published in 2013 by the African Development Bank (AfDB), total unmet demand for credit across Africa now stands at $100 billion, of which $70 – $90 billion emanates from SMEs in Sub-Saharan Africa alone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Since the cost of trade is extremely high in Africa, many companies – particularly SMEs – struggle to get the credit they require to get their goods to market.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To fully close the gap, the report estimates that the provision of trade finance, along with other forms of credit such as loans, overdrafts and leasing, would need to increase by 270-300%. Even when some financing is available, the cost is usually prohibitive for a significant number of smaller businesses. For about one-third of countries, rates on trade loans offered on a non-sovereign basis exceed 10% and often require cash collateral of up to 50% of the value of the loan.</p>
<p>“I think it is fair to say that there are not enough banks in Africa providing this service,” says Barrass. He draws a comparison with Asia where, due to the region’s more accommodating risk profile, many more banks are willing to take on some risk and get involved in financing deals for companies. “It is clearly different from trading in other continents. It has a different risk profile, there are different on the ground facilities, capabilities and logistics.”</p>
<p>Barclays hopes it can fill some of the gap. Over the past year, the bank has been busy ramping up its trade finance coverage across the continent, focusing particularly on bolstering their strengths in structured commodities finance and developing new products in the receivables finance space. For trade finance in its ‘plain vanilla’ form, this will mean increasing counterparty lines around financial institutions in distant markets where the bank has little or no footprint.</p>
<p>“That will allow us to support more of our exporting clients around the world who are trading with Africa,” Barrass adds. “It is a key part of our strategy, and something you will be seeing a lot more of over the next few months.”</p>
<p>The difficulty is that, for commercial banks, only so much can be done to meet Africa’s rapidly increasing finance needs. Low country ratings and weak local banking systems mean there will often be times when such banks feel unable to justify deploying capital to support imports and exports in certain countries. It is here where multilateral development banks such as AfDB, play a useful role. Since 2009, AfDB has approved over $735m in trade finance facilities, through a combination of risk-sharing with international commercial banks and provision of credit to local financial institutions in order to facilitate their trade finance operations.</p>
<h3 id="the-opportunity-within">The opportunity within</h3>
<p>In recent years, there has been much talk of growth opportunities presented by China’s intensifying commercial interest in the African continent. Trade between the two has indeed been growing at a phenomenal rate, expanding from $10 billion in 2000 to an estimated $200 billion in 2013. This has already brought the continent many benefits. Chinese firms have made substantial investments in African infrastructure, particularly in key sectors such as telecommunications, transport and power generation. There is no denying that, given the scale of Africa’s infrastructure deficit, these types of investments could play a crucial role in the continent’s future development.</p>
<p>But stronger intra-African trade might just be an even greater catalyst for growth. Many of Africa’s small, landlocked countries encounter huge challenges when attempting to trade with countries in other continents. Yet through regional integration and the creation of larger markets, Africa might one day find itself able to compete on the same level as other low-cost emerging economies.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Many of Africa’s small, landlocked countries encounter huge challenges when attempting to trade with countries in other continents. Yet through regional integration and the creation of larger markets, Africa might one day find itself able to compete on the same level as other low-cost emerging economies.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What is more, there is a historical precedent for this. Europe’s decision to open its own borders in the years that followed the Second World War helped to rebuild the economic prosperity of a continent that had been all but decimated by six years of conflict. More recently, intra-regional trade has also been seen playing a key role in Asia’s rapid ascendancy. Although Asian economies are often thought of as workshops for the West, the truth is that more than 55% of its trade today is within the region. The fact that in Africa, that same figure currently stands at a mere 7%, reveals the sheer scale of the job that needs to be done to get Africa trading with itself.</p>
<p>It is a worthy goal to work towards, nevertheless. Over the past decade Africa has fared reasonably well economically. Real GDP rose by 4.9% a year from 2000 through to 2008; the point at which contagion from the US subprime mortgage crisis really began to pinch. But the continent’s success during this period was driven, if not wholly then at least in part, by a global boom in commodities that did very little to address structural unemployment. An economic restructuring that focuses on diversification and facilitating greater trade within Africa could well be the key, not only to more sustainable growth, but also to addressing some of Africa’s long-standing social challenges.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Egypt: from revolution to reform]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2014 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>On 25<sup>th</sup> January 2011, hundreds of thousands of Egyptians – many organised through social media – took to the streets across the country on the ‘Day of Anger’ to demand an end to police brutality, state of emergency laws, corruption and a lack of free elections. They were fighting for freedom of speech, greater employment opportunities and higher wages. The chants that filled Tahrir (‘Liberation’) Square in Cairo spoke volumes: “Bread, freedom, social justice” and “We won’t leave; he should leave”, referring to President Hosni Mubarak.</p>
<p>And leave he did. After 30 years, on 11<sup>th</sup> February, Mubarak’s rule came to an end following 18 days of nationwide protests. The Supreme Council of the Armed Forces took over and dissolved Parliament. After an extended election period, in which the Muslim Brotherhood won nearly half the seats, the presidential elections took place at the end of June 2012, putting Mohammed Morsi of the Muslim Brotherhood in power.</p>
<p>But the inability of the government to improve the everyday lives of Egyptians culminated in enormous demonstrations on the anniversary of Morsi’s electoral victory. As a result, Egypt’s military chief General Abdel-Fattah el-Sissi installed Chief Justice Adly Mansour as interim president. Mansour is currently leading a transitional government with ‘full powers’ until presidential and legislative elections can be held, possibly in March or April 2014. The current constitution will be amended at the same time.</p>
<p>Andrew Long, Deputy Chairman and CEO of HSBC Bank Egypt, believes that if the government can adhere to the proposed roadmap for a referendum and parliamentary and presidential elections, then this will be a major improvement and will have a positive impact on the business and the country as a whole.</p>
<p>It is clear that for many Egyptians the reforms are not moving fast enough, nor do the different governments inspire confidence that real change will happen. Tarek El Mahdy, CFO at Sphinx Glass, an independent float glass manufacturer based in Cairo, says: “We have had two revolutions in this country – the first phase in January 2011 and the second in June 2013 – in order to change things, but unfortunately things are not changing. The government aims are to stabilise the situation and not provoke anyone. Many people hoped that they would see a revolution in economic growth, regulations, tariffs, treasury, roads, culture and the mind-set of the people – but what was started on 25<sup>th</sup> January 2011 is not yet finished.”</p>
<h3 id="the-state-of-the-nation">The state of the nation</h3>
<p>The tumultuous political situation has not helped Egypt’s reputation in the eyes of the credit ratings agencies. On 5<sup>th</sup> July, Fitch Ratings downgraded Egypt to B- from B, with a negative outlook. Paul Gamble, a Director in Fitch’s Sovereign Group, says: “This reflects a high level of political uncertainty, a very weak fiscal position and a weakening of the government’s commitment to implement economic reforms. Egypt’s budget deficit is the highest of any country we rate and the authorities do not appear inclined to reach an agreement with the International Monetary Fund (IMF) that will involve measures – notably subsidy reform. Government debt has risen rapidly and shortages of foreign exchange (FX) are hindering the private sector.”</p>
<p>On 9<sup>th</sup> July 2013 Saudi Arabia announced a $5 billion aid package for Egypt that included a $1 billion cash grant, $2 billion worth of petroleum products and natural gas, and $2 billion as a deposit in the Central Bank of Egypt (CBE), free of normal financing costs. The same day, the UAE offered a grant of $1 billion and an interest-free loan of $2 billion. On 10<sup>th</sup> July, Kuwait followed suit with an aid package worth $4 billion.</p>
<p>But the IMF’s willingness to provide a lifeline for Egypt cooled considerably following Morsi’s removal. On 26<sup>th</sup> July, it stated that there were no plans to restart negotiations for a $4.8 billion loan until the country’s military-backed transitional government gained recognition from the global community. However, by this time three Gulf states had stepped into the gap.</p>
<p>Anthony Skinner, Director and Head of Middle East and North Africa (MENA) practice at risk analytics company, Maplecroft, says that at least the authorities know that they have the support of Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and the Emirates, which they didn’t have before. “The negotiations between former president Morsi, his team and the IMF were quite difficult. However, now the Egyptian authorities feel that they don’t really need to worry about the IMF and its conditions because of Gulf aid. In a sense, the authorities feel like they have more breathing room to engage in fiscal reform and stimulus to ease some of the economic pressure by generating growth. But this is misleading because painful structural reforms still need to take place.”</p>
<h3 id="economy">Economy</h3>
<p>Egypt’s real GDP slightly improved during the first nine months of fiscal year (FY) 2012/2013, growing by 2.3%, compared to 1.8% during the same period last year, according to the Ministry of Finance’s August bulletin. However, inflation has increased from 4.7% in December 2012 to 10.4% in October 2013.</p>
<p>Net inbound foreign direct investment (FDI) fell by 25% in fiscal year 2012/13 from the previous year, according to the CBE. Rising unemployment levels – at 13.3% in 2Q13 compared to below 9% five years ago – represent another obstacle to the government, while those living below the poverty line reached 25% in 2010/2011.</p>
<p>In the medium term at least, Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and the UAE will continue to provide enough aid to prevent a full-scale economic crisis. Egypt’s FX reserves have hovered just under $19 billion since July due to such support. However, although the loans and aids from Gulf countries are soft loans, with mild conditions compared to other sources of finance, they will still increase Egypt’s debt. According to the budget, it is expected to reach 89% of GDP in 2012/13, compared to 85% a year earlier.</p>
<p>On 31<sup>st</sup> August, the interim cabinet announced an economic stimulus plan worth $3.2 billion (later increased to $4.2 billion), which it said is aimed at creating a 3% growth rate over the current fiscal year, maintaining social justice and creating new job opportunities. On 11<sup>th</sup> November the government announced that a second stimulus package of $3.5 billion would be launched by the end of the year. A major share of the stimulus will be spent on infrastructure projects, such as electricity grids, roads, housing and public transport, as well as raising the minimum wage from $106 to $174 per month by January 2014.</p>
<p>In addition to shorter-term fiscal fixes, the government launched a long-term developmental vision, ‘Egypt 2022’, aimed at achieving a “sustainable and contained growth”, according to the Ministry of Planning. In tandem with the fiscal stimulus, this programme focuses on developing basic infrastructure – especially in Upper Egypt, New Valley, Sinai and the Suez Canal – in a way that serves industry, agriculture, trade and transportation.</p>
<p>“Having a fiscal stimulus in place is important in order for the economy to chug along, but it is just a stop-gap measure,” says Skinner. “The Egyptian economy is on a lifeline, which is being extended by Saudi Arabia, the chief provider of funds and aid, as well as the UAE and Kuwait. But by relying on this external liquidity, the authorities are just delaying the necessary economic reforms to get the economy back on its feet.”</p>
<h3 id="banking-and-markets">Banking and markets</h3>
<p>Over the past ten years the CBE restructured the banking market in Egypt and the number of banks were brought down to 40 from approximately 60. In addition, the central bank oversaw a recapitalisation of the banking sector. According to HSBC’s Long, this is why there haven’t been bank failures during the period post the January 2011 revolution nor has there been any evidence of large amounts of corporate provisioning during the past two and a half years of recession. Clearly, the banks have an appetite to lend and often have an average maturity of their lending book which is typically longer than seen in countries with debt capital markets.</p>
<p>Very few global banks have opted to leave the market. BNP Paribas and Société Générale (SocGen) sold their subsidiaries in Egypt but this was mainly to meet new capital requirements, rather than due to concern about the Egyptian market. Two Gulf Co-operation Council (GCC) banks stepped in: Qatar National Bank (QNB) bought SocGen’s National Société Générale Bank (NSGB) and Emirates NBD bought BNP Paribas Egypt. Both deals were done at the end of 2012.</p>
<p>However, the markets have not fared as well – since 2011 the amount of trade on the Egyptian Exchange (EGX), which has 234 listed firms, has nearly halved. As a result, the exchange is revising listing regulations, developing new mechanisms for exchange traded funds (ETF) and rights issues, and working to increase trade on its fixed income market. In addition, there is talk of a bond trading platform that has been ten years in the making potentially starting early next year.</p>
<h3 id="doing-business">Doing business</h3>
<p>Unsurprisingly, Egypt has dropped in ranking in the International Finance Corporation (IFC) and World Bank ‘Ease of Doing Business 2014’ report – but only by one place. It is now ranked 128<sup>th</sup> out of 189 economies. In the ‘ease of starting a business’ it dropped six places, while in ‘getting credit’ it dropped four places in comparison with last year.</p>
<p>The country has faced a number of specific challenges, which has caused Egyptian business activity to shrink for the 13<sup>th</sup> month in a row, as of October 2013. For example, most of Egypt has been under night-time curfew since mid-August, when security forces broke up sit-ins of supporters of Morsi. However, the seasonally-adjusted HSBC Egypt Purchasing Managers Index (PMI) for the non-oil private sector rose to 49.5 points in October, up from 44.7 points in September and moving closer to the 50 mark separating growth from contraction.</p>
<p>Whether business sentiment improves, comes back to the question of the government and its vision for the future, says Maplecroft’s Skinner. “It is the uncertainty of what Egypt will look like in a year or two as many businesses take a wait-and-see approach to making future investments, whereas others have decided not to push ahead with Egypt at all and are investing elsewhere.”</p>
<p>HSBC’s Long agrees. “If you are going to invest for the future, you need some sort of clarity as to what that future will look like. There is uncertainty at the moment, and this has persisted for a while, which is reflected in recent reports of the HSBC PMI which have been negative for some months. The good news is that we have seen a slight improvement in November’s PMI and I hope we see more improvement in the coming months, which would be a good indication for the future.”</p>
<p>When asked what he did to protect his business during the past few years, a regional treasury manager at a large multinational headquartered outside of the country, lists three things:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Tried to keep calm.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Obtained weekly updates from subsidiaries.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Obtained counter guarantees in sales.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Sphinx Glass’ El Mahdy says that his company focused on controlling its cost. “It is very difficult to control revenue, so we needed to be as efficient as possible to reduce our costs through in-depth cost analysis.” The company improved its working capital management by maintaining receivables as controlled and low as possible.</p>
<p>He explains that every time a new government minister starts to approach companies and manufacturers to get to know their problems, by the time he understands the business and what is needed, he is gone and another put in his place. Then the whole exercise starts over again with a different strategy.</p>
<h3 id="major-challenges-fx-and-fuel">Major challenges: FX and fuel</h3>
<p>FX is the biggest challenge facing the regional treasury manager of the multinational. At the start of 2013, the CBE imposed new monetary FX regulations, in order to help curb speculation on the US dollar in the domestic market and maintain a low rate of inflation. It also introduced a new mechanism to provide local banks with foreign currency through periodical auctions, aimed at conserving foreign reserves.</p>
<p>“There are shortages of currency for importers under traditional letters of credit (LCs) and collection bills, but also for those paying by direct transfer to their subsidiary or parent,” says HSBC’s Long. “There have been efforts by the central bank to provide foreign currency in the market through an auction process but the availability was less than what the inter-bank market used to offer 12 months ago. I remain hopeful that the situation will improve in the near future.”</p>
<p>El Mahdy agrees that FX is the one of the biggest issues “because it affects everything”. He says Sphinx Glass exports more than 50% of its products and therefore generates its requirements in US dollars. But he knows that the banks operate a priority list of companies in “essential” sectors, such as health care or food. Companies that can’t access foreign currency are forced to tap the black markets, which is costly and insecure. Although currently – specifically after the Gulf’s aid package – FX is stable and the banks are providing for the needs of almost all industry sectors, the question is how long this will last?</p>
<p>The limited availability of gas and electricity is another major challenge. According to Maplecroft’s Skinner, the government is struggling to pay companies in the oil and gas sector, where the state debt is estimated to be $5.4 billion. The state-run oil company, Egypt General Petroleum Corporation (EGPC), has entered negotiations with energy companies to restructure the resultant state debt. “This has been a significant challenge for oil and gas companies because a lot of gas has been diverted to the domestic market rather than being exported. Although there is a restructuring programme in place, it is far from ideal,” says Skinner.</p>
<p>El Mahdy agrees: “Energy is a problem in Egypt. Gas price, compared with other countries in the region where prices are much lower, is affecting our cost structure and our ability to compete.”</p>
<p>Although there were many power cuts leading up to 30<sup>th</sup> June and into July, these have now stopped. “The country runs quite close to its power capacity all the time, so it is important that part of the stimulus package is earmarked for building more power stations because manufacturers need power to run their machines,” says Long.</p>
<h3 id="the-future">The future</h3>
<p>Fitch’s Gamble is cautiously optimistic and believes that Egypt will become relatively more stable after a period of extreme uncertainty. “Financial inflows from the GCC should support the currency and with political tensions likely to be contained there should be a modest improvement in growth. Nonetheless, performance will be well below potential.”</p>
<p>El Mahdy highlights the opportunities present in a market that encompasses 90 million people. But he believes there must be a robust plan in place to take advantage of these opportunities. “They talk of 2022, but what will happen in 2014? In a developing country such as Egypt there are so many quick wins that can be achieved, but we need a strong administration that can take bold decisions. We didn’t lose three years of our lives in business just to go back to square one.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Doing business in Kenya]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2010 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Kenya’s capital, Nairobi, is generally considered to be the financial services hub of Central and East Africa. The country is a key member of the East African Community (EAC), alongside Uganda, Tanzania, Rwanda and Burundi. The aim of the EAC is to enhance co-operation between the member states in political, economic and social terms, for the benefit of all. This initiative has led to the establishment of a Customs Union in 2005, a Common Market in 2010 and will see the inauguration of a Monetary Union by 2012.</p>
<div class="country-facts">
<img alt="Map and flag of Kenya" class="flag" height="205" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-04-cp-map-and-flag-of-kenya-205x205.jpg" width="205"/>
<h4 id="key-facts">Key facts</h4>
<h4 id="geography-and-society">Geography and society</h4>
<dl>
<dt>Population:</dt><dd>39m</dd>
<dt>Population growth rate:</dt><dd>2.69%</dd>
<dt>Official languages:</dt><dd>Swahili and English</dd>
<dt>Capital city:</dt><dd>Nairobi</dd>
<dt>Time zone:</dt><dd>UTC+3</dd>
<dt>Land boundaries:</dt><dd>Ethiopia 861 km, Somalia 682 km, Sudan 232 km, Tanzania 769 km, Uganda 933 km</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="economy">Economy</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Currency:</dt><dd>Kenyan shilling</dd>
<dt>GDP per capita:</dt><dd>$1,600</dd>
<dt>CPI:</dt><dd>9.3%</dd>
<dt>Member of:</dt><dd>UN, WTO, IMF, UNCTAD</dd>
<dt>Fiscal year:</dt><dd>calendar year</dd>
<dt>Financial capital:</dt><dd>Nairobi</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="history-and-politics">History and politics</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Government type:</dt><dd>republic</dd>
<dt>President:</dt><dd>Mwai Kibaki</dd>
<dt>Independence:</dt><dd>12<sup>th</sup> December 1963</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="country-credit-rating">Country credit rating</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>B+/B</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="trading-partners">Trading partners</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Top five import sources:</dt><dd>Add, China, UAE, South Africa, Saudi Arabia</dd>
<dt>Top five export destinations:</dt><dd>UK, Netherlands, Uganda, Tanzania, US</dd>
</dl>
</div>
<h3 id="africas-financial-hub">Africa’s financial hub</h3>
<p>Kenya welcomes foreign investment, with a series of reforms having opened up the market and simplified the process. The Nairobi Stock Exchange (NSE) is Africa’s fourth largest in terms of market capitalisation. The service sector, dominated by tourism, is the largest contributor to Kenya’s GDP, followed by agriculture. The country’s key agricultural exports include tea, coffee and flowers.</p>
<p>2009 saw asset growth of 14% in Kenya’s banking industry, as a result of measures put in place by the Central Bank of Kenya in response to the global banking crisis. These measures included the Agent Banking Law, which allowed banks to authorise independent businesses to offer banking services on their behalf; and the creation of Credit Reference Bureaux, which allowed for the circulation of customer information amongst the country’s lenders, in order to prevent further bad loans.</p>
<p>Kenya’s financial sector is embracing new technologies, and was one of the first to test mobile payments, via M-PESA.</p>
<figure class="photo"><img alt="Photograph of an elephant" height="299" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-04-cp-photo-of-elephant-299x299.jpg" width="299"/></figure>
<h3 id="legal-and-regulatory-requirements">Legal and regulatory requirements</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The Central Bank of Kenya (CBK) was established in 1966 under the Central Bank of Kenya Act. The three core functions of the Bank are: to formulate and implement monetary policy with the aim of maintaining stability in prices; to adopt the liquidity, solvency and proper functioning of a stable, market-based financial system; and to support the economic policy of the government.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Maintaining low and stable inflation is the chief goal of the Monetary Policy Committee (MPC). Monetary policy in Kenya may be implemented in three different ways: by buying and selling securities in the open market; by altering the discount rate to encourage banks to seek funding in the market, and only turn to the CBK as a lender of last resort; and by adjusting the minimum reserve requirement level for commercial banks.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The CBK regulates commercial banks, non-bank financial institutions, mortgage finance companies, building societies, foreign exchange bureaux, deposit-taking microfinance institutions and credit reference bureaus.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>There are no foreign exchange controls; however a bank must report significant foreign exchange transactions (ie in excess of $10,000) to the Central Bank.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>IFRS accounting principles are adhered to. Financial statements must be prepared annually.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Permitted business entities include public/private limited liability companies, companies limited by guarantee, sole proprietorships, partnerships, co-operative societies and branches of foreign or local companies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kenya’s Proceeds of Crime and Anti-Money Laundering Act became effective in June 2010, and seeks to establish a Financial Reporting Centre (FRC) and Assets Recovery Agency. Under this new legislation, anyone found guilty of money laundering could face up to seven years imprisonment, and/or a fine of up to 2.5m shillings.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="taxation-framework">Taxation framework</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>A company is considered resident for tax purposes if it is incorporated under Kenyan law, if its affairs are managed in Kenya or if the Minister of Finance publishes a notice declaring the company to be tax resident in the Kenya Gazette.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All resident and non-resident entities are subject to tax on all income accruing in or derived from Kenya. Only expenses incurred exclusively in the generation of income are deductible for tax purposes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Capital gains legislation was suspended in 1985, and there is no capital gains tax in Kenya.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The general rate of corporate income tax is 30%, with foreign company branches paying a rate of 37.5%. Newly-listed companies benefit from a reduced rate of 20-27% for the first three to five years, depending on the percentage of capital listed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A 100% investment deduction is applicable on hotel buildings and buildings and machinery used in manufacturing. For manufacturing investment in buildings and machinery located in the towns immediately surrounding Nairobi, Mombasa and Kisumu, an investment deduction of 150% applies. Any companies located in Export Processing Zones have the benefit of a ten-year tax holiday.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Withholding tax is not imposed on dividends to qualifying Kenyan financial institutions, or where the resident recipient company owns more than 12.5% of the capital of the originator. In all other cases, a rate of 5% applies to residents and citizens of the East African Community, and 10% to non-residents. A lower rate of withholding tax may apply where a tax treaty is in force. Kenya currently has treaties with the UK, Germany, Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Canada, India and Zambia.</p>
</li>
<li>
<figure class="photo right" style="width:205px;"><img alt="Cityscape of Nairobi" height="288" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2010/11and12/2010-11and12-tt-04-cp-cityscape-of-nairobi-205x288.jpg" width="205"/></figure>
<p>The Kenyan law on transfer pricing requires transactions between related entities to be carried out at arm’s length, in accordance with OECD guidelines.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Thin capitalisation rules state that for controlled foreign companies (CFCs) where the controlling stake is at least 25% or more, interest expenses may be reduced when the CFC’s interest-bearing liabilities are more than three times the level of paid-up capital and revenue reserves/accumulated losses.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The standard rate of VAT is 16%. VAT is not charged on certain goods and services, in such industries as agriculture, health and education, computer hardware and software, international air travel and oil exploration.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Stamp duty is charged on certain transactions and financial instruments. For example, the creation and increase of authorised share capital attracts a stamp duty at a rate of 1%; 4% stamp duty is charged on immovable property; and 1% on the transfer of shares and securities. Any shares or securities listed on the Nairobi Stock Exchange (NSE) are exempt from stamp duty.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="case-study">
<h2 id="case-study">Case Study</h2>
<h3 id="bamburi-cement">Bamburi Cement</h3>
<p class="company-info">Bamburi is part of the French building materials giant Lafarge and is the largest cement-manufacturing company in east and central Africa.</p>
<h4 id="the-challenge">The challenge</h4>
<p>The objective of the programme was to assure continuous supplies to Bamburi by providing working capital support to Bamburi’s key suppliers. The programme also aimed to optimise Bamburi’s working capital cycle (by stretching the payment period from 15 days for some of the suppliers to 30 days) without increasing cost to its supply chain, and to improve relationships with its suppliers.</p>
<p>Bamburi had a tightly controlled supply chain designed to reduce borrowing costs. It continued to pay its suppliers and logistic partners on the invoice due date and tried to match its payments to its logistic partners and suppliers with receipts from customers in an effort to optimise working capital and reduce borrowing costs. As a result, payments to suppliers would only be made on the due date and on occasion get delayed. Suppliers had to finance their operations with bank borrowing at high costs, given their relatively small size and limited collateral, causing financial distress and high costs.</p>
<p>Ultimately, the suppliers’ additional cost of borrowing (due to increased days outstanding) led to them repricing their services to Bamburi.</p>
<h4 id="the-solution">The solution</h4>
<p>Citi proposed a supplier finance solution – the first of its kind in East Africa. Under the programme, it paid Bamburi’s suppliers on the due date of their invoices by drawing on Bamburi’s credit facilities. While the interest cost was passed onto suppliers, the financing cost was lower due to the substitution of the suppliers’ credit risk for that of Bamburi’s. The solution therefore enhanced suppliers’ loyalty to Bamburi. Citi has committed to providing timely and efficient service to ensure the success of the programme. Payment instructions received before 12 noon will be processed on a same-day basis; instructions received afternoon, on a next-day basis.</p>
<p>By supporting its suppliers, Bamburi was able to demand better payment terms and improve the efficiency of its working capital. Bamburi also benefited from improved cash flow; its days payables were effectively increased because the final liquidation of the supplier finance loans were an average 30 days after the due date of invoices.</p>
<p>The benefit of the increased days payables allowed Bamburi to extend enhanced credit terms to its distributors, giving it a competitive advantage.</p>
<h4 id="the-result">The result</h4>
<p>Citi began a pilot implementation of the supplier finance solution with one supplier in August 2008, after working extensively with it to identify and eliminate potential implementation problems. Following due diligence, a further 14 suppliers were added to Bamburi’s supplier finance programme. Bamburi estimates an opportunity for cost savings of over $200,000 a year, and it is considering expanding the programme to its subsidiary in Uganda.</p>
</div>
<h3 id="treasury-activities">Treasury activities</h3>
<h4 id="local-banking-sector">Local banking sector</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>There are 43 commercial banks in Kenya, of which 13 are foreign. The government has significant shareholdings in three local Kenyan banks. The biggest bank in terms of assets is Kenya Commercial Bank, with 226.15 billion shillings ($2.8 billion) in June 2010.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Banking in Kenya is governed by the Banking Act, the Companies Act and the Central Bank of Kenya Act.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kenya’s Microfinance Institutions (MFIs) provide financial services, such as credit, savings, insurance and money transfer services, to small and micro enterprises (SMEs) who do not qualify for access to traditional financial institutions. Deposit-taking MFIs are regulated by the Central Bank and are permitted to lend public funds; non-deposit-taking MFIs are only permitted to lend their own funds.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="payments">Payments</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Cash.</h5>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Cards.</h5>
<p>Card payment services have traditionally been provided independently; however, these are set to be centralised with the launch of a wireless platform by Paystream that will provide a single, central transaction interface for card payments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Cheques.</h5>
<p>The cheque payment process is undergoing improvements, with the cheque scanning introduced in the summer of 2010. This enables a digital image of the cheque to be forwarded electronically for clearing, thus simplifying the process and improving efficiency.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Electronic Funds Transfer (EFT).</h5>
<p>This is becoming increasingly popular, particularly for the payment of dividends which have traditionally been paid by cheque. Transactions are cleared once a day on a deferred net settlement (DNS) basis.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Mobile payments.</h5>
<p>Kenya was one of the first countries to use mobile phones for cash transfers, through a service called M-PESA, developed by Safaricom Ltd. Users of M-PESA do not require bank accounts; instead they must register at an authorised M-PESA agent. Once registered, users can buy digital funds at any M-PESA agent and send that electronic cash to any other mobile phone user in Kenya by SMS. An M-PESA-enabled mobile phone can also function as an electronic purse, holding up to 50,000 Kenyan shillings (€500).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="clearing-and-settlement">Clearing and settlement</h3>
<p>In July 2005 Kenya launched its first real-time gross settlement system (RTGS) for urgent, high-value payments – the Kenya Electronic Payments and Settlement System (KEPSS). The system is operated and owned by the Central Bank of Kenya, and all commercial banks within the country are participants. Messages are primarily carried via the SWIFT network. Foreign currency transactions may be processed in US dollar, euro and pounds sterling, with more currencies to be available when the East Africa Cross-Border Payment System (EAPS) is implemented.</p>
<h3 id="investment-opportunities">Investment opportunities</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Treasury bills.</h5>
<p>A Treasury bill is a paperless, short-term government security issued through the Central Bank of Kenya. These are available in maturities of 91, 182 and 364 days and are sold at a discounted price (to reflect investor’s return) and redeemed at face value.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Treasury bonds.</h5>
<p>Treasury bonds are medium to long-term debt instruments issued by the government. They are available in maturities ranging from one to 25 years. A number of different types are available:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Fixed coupon bonds.</h5>
<p>These are one of the most popular forms.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Zero coupon bonds.</h5>
<p>Alongside fixed-coupon bonds, these are the most popular.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Floating-rate bonds.</h5>
<p>These are no longer issued by the government, only by corporates.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Infrastructure bonds.</h5>
<p>These are used to fund specific infrastructure-related projects.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Stock market.</h5>
<p>The Nairobi Stock Exchange (NSE) is the fourth-largest in Africa and trades equities and bonds. Live trading on automated trading systems has been possible since 2006.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="url-list">
<h4 id="key-websites">Key websites</h4>
<dl class="websites">
<dt>Central Bank of Kenya:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.centralbank.go.ke" target="_blank">www.centralbank.go.ke</a></dd>
<dt>Ministry of Finance:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.finance.go.ke" target="_blank">www.finance.go.ke</a></dd>
<dt>East African Community:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.eac.int" target="_blank">www.eac.int</a></dd>
<dt>Nairobi Stock Exchange:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.nse.co.ke" target="_blank">www.nse.co.ke</a></dd>
<dt>Kenya Investment Authority:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.investmentkenya.com" target="_blank">www.investmentkenya.com</a></dd>
</dl>
</div>
<div class="profile">
<h3 id="citi-in-kenya">Citi in Kenya</h3>
<p>Citi began operating in Kenya in 1974 under the name “The First National City Bank of New York” and has since evolved to be known today as Citibank N.A. Kenya Branch (“Citi Kenya”). We have branches in Nairobi (Head Office) and Mombasa. Citi provides the full range of commercial banking transactions ranging from local and foreign currency advances, up-country collections, trade finance, foreign exchange, corporate finance, advisory, investment banking services and cash management. Citi has an East Africa Regional Business present in Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania and Zambia.</p>
<p>Citi is recognised in East Africa as international leader in end-to-end on-line financial services that provides state-of-the-art cash management and trade services, as endorsed by corporations who have voted Citi as the Lead Domestic Cash Management Bank in 2010 in the Euromoney Cash Management poll. In Kenya alone, Citi has been at the forefront of electronic banking solutions with the latest technology of internet-based banking solutions since 2000. Understanding the changing needs of our customers continues to be a strategic priority at Citi to provide innovative customer-centric solutions. We partner with our customers to help them transform their business and employ the latest technologies, which allow them to reach beyond traditional markets.</p>
<p>Other achievements</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Pioneer of web-based Electronic Banking in Kenya in 2000.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>First bank to be ISO 9001 2000 certified in Kenya.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>KIM Awards – “Best Bank in Kenya”. HR &amp; Technology, Professional Manager of the Year.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Euromoney Awards – Best Domestic Cash Management Bank in Kenya 2008, 2009 and 2010.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="contacts">
<h5 id="contact-details">Contact details:</h5>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Joyce Ann Wainaina</dt>
<dd class="title">Global Transaction Services Head East Africa</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+254 (20) 2754069</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:joyceanne.wainaina@citi.com">joyceanne.wainaina@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Mary Sabwa</dt>
<dd class="title">Sales Head East Africa</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+254 (20) 2754068</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:mary.sabwa@citi.com">mary.sabwa@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
</div>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-2012-70x40.png" width="70"/>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Doing business in Nigeria]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Oct 2009 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Nigeria is a country undergoing economic and financial reform. Looking to reduce its dependence on oil production, Nigeria is aiming to attract foreign direct investment through initiatives such as the creation of an international finance centre. This Country Profile looks at the requirements for doing business in Nigeria, as well as the country’s treasury landscape.</p>
<div class="country-facts right">
<img alt="Map showing Nigeria" class="map" height="154" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2009/10/2009-10-tt-07-cp-map-of-nigeria-205x154.png" width="205"/>
<h4 id="key-facts">Key facts</h4>
<h5 id="geography-and-society">Geography and society</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Population:</dt><dd>149.2m</dd>
<dt>Population growth rate:</dt><dd>1.999%</dd>
<dt>Capital city:</dt><dd>Abuja</dd>
<dt>Time zone:</dt><dd>UTC+1</dd>
<dt>Land boundaries:</dt><dd>Benin (773 km), Niger (1497 km), Chad (87 km) and Cameroon (1690 km)</dd>
<dt>Coastline:</dt><dd>853 km</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="economy">Economy</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Currency:</dt><dd>naira (NGN)</dd>
<dt>GDP per capita:</dt><dd>$2,300</dd>
<dt>FX regime:</dt><dd>managed float</dd>
<dt>Member of:</dt><dd>WTO, OPEC, IMF</dd>
<dt>Fiscal year:</dt><dd>calendar year</dd>
<dt>Financial capital:</dt><dd>Lagos</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="politics">Politics</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Government type:</dt><dd>Federal republic</dd>
<dt>Head of state:</dt><dd>President Umaru Yar’Adua</dd>
<dt>Vice President:</dt><dd>Goodluck Jonathan</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="country-credit-rating">Country credit rating</h5>
<dl>
<dt>AAA</dt>
</dl>
<h5 id="trading-partners">Trading partners</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Top import partners:</dt><dd>China, The Netherlands, US, South Korea, UK</dd>
<dt>Top export destinations:</dt><dd>US, Brazil, Spain</dd>
</dl>
</div>
<h3 id="one-of-africas-leading-economies">One of Africa’s leading economies</h3>
<p>With the largest population of any African country, Nigeria is the second major economy in sub-Saharan Africa and one of the world’s principal producers of crude oil. In 2007, when oil accounted for around 90% of the country’s export earnings and 78% of total gross revenue, Nigeria was producing oil at a rate of 2.3m barrels per day.</p>
<p>In the first half of 2008, Nigeria’s oil production dropped to 2.02m barrels per day, falling subsequently to below 2m, due to a large extent to unrest in the Niger Delta, Nigeria’s chief oil-producing region.</p>
<p>The country has undertaken numerous initiatives over the past decade to lessen the economy’s dependence on oil-producing sectors, as well as Nigeria’s international debt.</p>
<p>In 2000, the country entered into a $1 billion credit deal with the IMF and a debt restructuring programme with the Paris Club – a group of 19 international lenders, including the UK, German and Russian governments – to which Nigeria owed a total of $37 billion.</p>
<p>In 2005 debt relief was granted by the Paris Club and the country had almost $18m of debts written off in exchange for a payment of approximately $12.4m. The debt repayment was part of a plan to restructure the country’s economy. Nigeria has continued to work towards this objective in conjunction with the IMF.</p>
<p>The Financial Services Strategy (FSS 2020) is a proposal outlining the transformation of Nigeria into a major financial centre, and one of the top 20 economic powers of the world, by the year 2020.</p>
<p>The strategy was borne out of the identification of Nigeria by Goldman Sachs as one of the N-11, the next eleven breakthrough economies after the BRICs (Brazil, Russia, India and China), as well as the need for economic reform.</p>
<p>The main objectives of the strategy include strengthening domestic financial markets, enhancing integration with external financial markets and building an international finance centre.</p>
<p>Under this plan the country intends to attract $600 billion in foreign direct investment (FDI) over the next decade – compared to the estimated annual $9 billion that it attracts today.</p>
<p>An instrumental figure in the country’s financial reform has been Lamido Sanusi, who was appointed as the new governor of the Central Bank of Nigeria in June 2009. Vowing to crack down on banks with poor lending records, Sanusi began conducting an audit of all 24 of Nigeria’s banks.</p>
<p>So far five banks have failed Sanusi’s stress tests and the top executives of five troubled Nigerian banks have been sacked. The five banks in question were close to insolvency when the Central Bank of Nigeria stepped in, injecting capital in the form of a NGN 400 billion ($2.6 billion) rescue package in order to help the struggling institutions.</p>
<p>The move is a positive sign that Nigeria is actively managing its economy and addressing the increased systemic risk in troubled times.</p>
<h4 id="legal-and-regulatory-requirements">Legal and regulatory requirements</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The banking sector is regulated by the Central Bank of Nigeria (CBN), which was established in 1959. The four key roles of the CBN are: to preserve the value of Nigeria’s currency through the maintenance of the country’s external reserves, to safeguard Nigeria’s financial stability, to offer advice to the federal government on financial matters, and to operate as a lender of last resort to Nigerian banks.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In terms of central bank reporting requirements, banks are obliged by the CBN to report on matters relating to capital inflow and foreign exchange, as well as net open positions and interbank purchases and sales.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Other regulatory bodies include the Federal Ministry of Finance (FMF), the Nigeria Deposit Insurance Corporation (NDIC), the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), and the National Insurance Commission (NAICOM).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Banks must pay an insurance premium of 0.9375% of their deposit taking liabilities to the NDIC. The maximum claim a depositor may make in the event of a bank failure has recently been reviewed upward from NGN 50,000 to NGN 200,000.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Any new business must be registered with the Corporate Affairs Commission (CAC), which regulates the formation and management of companies in Nigeria, and the Nigerian Investment Promotion Commission (NIPC), which co-ordinates and monitors all investments in the country. The NIPC Decree of 1995 allows total foreign ownership of firms outside the oil sector and industries related to national security.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Foreign exchange flows into the country are regulated by means of the Certificate of Capital Importation (CCI), which must be obtained when importing funds for investment purposes. This document, issued by the bank receiving the funds, gives the investor the right eventually to repatriate those funds that have been imported into the country. All foreign exchange purchased must be for eligible transactions. For transactions exceeding $10,000, supporting documentation must be presented as evidence of eligibility.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Accounting standards in Nigeria are overseen by the Nigerian Accounting Standards Board (NASB). While most companies listed on the Nigerian Stock Exchange (NSE) conform to local accounting standards, some have now adopted IFRS to enable qualified disclosures.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Money laundering policies are enforced by the Economic and Financial Crimes Committee (EFCC). The Nigerian Financial Intelligence Unit (NFIU) is the branch of the EFCC that specifically handles crimes in the financial sector.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="taxation-framework">Taxation framework</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The standard rate of corporation tax is 30%. This is the same for all entities in Nigeria, regardless of turnover.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Companies granted ‘pioneer status’ can benefit from a five-year tax exemption (seven years in economically disadvantaged areas). Pioneer status must be applied for within the first year of commencement of business. To qualify, a joint venture or foreign-owned company must have sustained a capital expenditure of at least NGN 5m. This figure must be at least NGN 150,000 for Nigerian companies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Withholding tax (WHT) is deducted at a rate of 10% on dividends and interest. Interest on savings accounts is exempt, providing the deposit amount is less than NGN 50,000. A withholding tax of 10% is levied on royalty income.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The standard rate of VAT is 5%, although this is less for certain goods and services.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Nigeria has several double taxation treaties in place which offer the countries involved a 25% reduction in standard WHT rates.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>By way of a tax incentive for investors, Nigeria has export processing zones, regulated by the Nigeria Export Processing Zones Authority (NEPZA), where approved enterprises operating within these zones are exempt from all federal, state and local government taxes, rates, customs duties and levies. More than 20 zones are currently either operational or under construction.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="treasury-activities">Treasury activities</h3>
<h4 id="local-banking-sector">Local banking sector</h4>
<p>Prior to 2005, Nigeria’s financial system comprised 89 banks with 3,382 branches. As a result of the subsequent regulatory and market driven consolidation, however, there are currently 24 licensed banks in Nigeria. These institutions include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Discount houses.</h5>
<p>There are currently five discount houses in Nigeria. The concept was launched by the CBN in the 1990s, on the premise that these discount houses were to act as intermediaries between the CBN and other financial institutions, channeling excess liquidity by facilitating the trading of government short-term securities, such as treasury bills.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Commercial and merchant banks.</h5>
<p>Commercial banks accept deposits, approve loans and manage the payment and settlement system. Merchant banks provide medium and long-term loan financing, equipment leasing, loan syndication and debt factoring.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Community banks.</h5>
<p>The National Board for Community Banks handles applications for the creation of community banks, the first of which was set up in 1990. Community banks are self-sufficient financial institutions that are owned and run by the community to which they provide financial services.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Development Finance Institutions (DFIs).</h5>
<p>DFIs were set up to encourage the development of specific sectors of the economy. Among these are the Bank of Industry, the Nigerian Agricultural Co-operative and Rural Development Bank, the Education Bank and the Urban Development Bank.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="case-study">
<h2 id="case-study">Case study</h2>
<h3 id="nigerian-bottling-company-nbc-is-the-market-leading-soft-drinks-manufacturer-in-nigeria">Nigerian Bottling Company (NBC) is the market-leading soft drinks manufacturer in Nigeria.</h3>
<h5 id="the-challenge">The challenge</h5>
<p>NBC, a subsidiary of Coca-Cola Hellenic, the producer and distributor of Coca-Cola beverages worldwide, has a vast network of distributors across Nigeria. The company wanted a convenient, reliable and secure way of collecting receivables from its customers and an efficient method of managing its accounts receivables.</p>
<p>NBC also wanted to receive credit from distributors immediately and the ability to view distributors’ payments in real time. In order to achieve this, the company required reliable web-based access to detailed account information for control and reconciliation, together with real-time notification for credits made into its accounts.</p>
<h5 id="the-solution">The solution</h5>
<p>Citi created two integrated solutions – determined by the size of distributors – to meet NBC’s requirement to eliminate cash payments and give it an effective accounts receivables process.</p>
<p>For large distributors, a mobile POS terminal supported by Interswitch was proposed. This solution offers the same certainty as cash payments, with sales reflected in NBC’s operating account immediately following a transaction between a salesman and merchant.</p>
<p>For around 150 smaller merchants that do not have the volume of business to warrant the POS terminal-based system, an innovative alternative was proposed. Working with three correspondent banks, which have over 600 branches nationwide, smaller merchants are issued with cheques that are pre-filled with NBC’s payment details. These are collected by NBC’s deliveryman. This solution gives NBC the security of payment it needs because cheques cannot be issued on accounts with insufficient funds. Moreover, by using a book transfer between the correspondent banks and Citi, NBC receives the value of cheques on a same-day basis.</p>
<h5 id="the-result">The result</h5>
<p>The mobile POS terminal solution for larger distributors, which have been designated key account buyers, was implemented in 2008. The solution for smaller merchants using correspondent banks and cheques is being progressively rolled out with the ultimate objective of completing the implementation across NBC’s 13 plants in Nigeria, each of which manages a local dealer network.</p>
<p>NBC has gained visibility of its payments and balances through Citi’s two-part solution. Through Citi’s partnership with local banks, many small merchants – previously among Nigeria’s 40m unbanked people – now have the ability to make low-value payments.</p>
</div>
<h4 id="payments">Payments</h4>
<p>The main payment channels in Nigeria are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Cash.</h5>
<p>This is still the dominant mode of payment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Cheques.</h5>
<p>A common form of non-cash payment in Nigeria, usage of which has increased since anti-fraud measures were introduced in 2006 outlining imprisonment and/or fines for issuers of dishonoured cheques.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Payment cards.</h5>
<p>Payment cards suffered at their initial introduction, but the CBN’s guidelines on e-banking in 2003 encouraged further developments in e-banking, thus facilitating the wider use of payment cards. Types of cards available include debit cards, credit cards, ATM cards, smartcards and dollar denominated debit and credit cards. These foreign currency cards allow Nigerians to make payments in over 210 countries around the world.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Electronic Funds Transfer.</h5>
<p>Automated processing and settlement of fund transfer instructions is undertaken by the NIBSS (see below).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="clearing-and-settlement">Clearing and settlement</h4>
<p>The Nigerian Automated Clearing System (NACS) commenced operation in 2002. It was established by the CBN and operates within the infrastructure of the Nigeria Inter-Bank Settlement System (NIBSS). This system enables the transfer of funds electronically between NACS members. Once full automation is completed and NACS is activated nationwide, it is anticipated that the current T+3 clearing cycle for local and upcountry transfers will be significantly reduced.</p>
<p>The Inter-Bank Fund Transfer System (IBFT) allows banks and financial institutions to settle funds on a deferred net basis. Payments are then aligned with international best practice through the Real Time Gross Settlement System (RTGS). The CBN RTGS (Central Bank of Nigeria Inter-bank Fund Transfer – CIFT) System ensures safe and secure co-operation with Nigeria’s other payment and settlement systems, allowing continuous and immediate payment settlement in all securities transactions.</p>
<p>Different payment types are processed in the following manner:</p>
<figure>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Payment type</th>
<th>Payment instrument</th>
<th>Supporting infrastructure</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Paper</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li><p>Cheque</p></li>
<li><p>Other paper-based instrument</p></li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>Non-NACS clearinghouse<br/>
				NACS clearinghouse</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bulk electronic</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li><p>Electronic Fund Transfers</p></li>
<li><p>Other electronic funds from EFTPOS (electronic funds transfer at point of sale) and ATM</p></li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>NIBSS</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>High value</td>
<td>
<ul>
<li><p>Inter-bank fund transfers</p></li>
<li><p>High-value time sensitive third-party</p></li>
</ul>
</td>
<td>RTGS</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</figure>
<h3 id="cash-management">Cash management</h3>
<p>Foreign currency current accounts are available to both Nigerian residents and non-residents, and non-resident local currency accounts are permitted in line with CBN foreign exchange regulations. While the large international banks offer domestic physical cash pooling, cross-border cash pooling does not take place in Nigeria, due to exchange control regulations. Notional pooling is permitted for local currency accounts, subject to CBN regulations. Zero balancing services are offered by those banks with networks operating in real-time.</p>
<h4 id="short-term-investments">Short-term investments</h4>
<p>Although current accounts do pay interest in Nigeria, banks also offer business savings accounts which allow corporates to accrue interest at a higher rate. Term deposits are also available, usually over a period of 30, 60, 90 or 180 days. In addition to bank deposits, investment opportunities in Nigeria take the form of money market funds, treasury bills, government fixed income bonds and the stock market. Money market instruments may take the form of commercial paper, negotiable certificates of deposits, bankers’ acceptances and treasury bills. Foreigners are not permitted to invest in treasury bills that possess a maturity of less than one year.</p>
<p>Government securities are traded through treasury bills, which have a short-term tenure of 91-365 days, and through treasury bonds and Federal Government of Nigeria (FGN) bonds, both of which are more medium to long-term investments, with a tenure of between three and 20 years. Transactions are only possible through an account with the CBN. Equities, government debt and corporate bonds are traded through the Nigerian Stock Exchange (NSE) which was established in 1960 and now lists over 200 companies with a market capital of $35 billion. Transactions are conducted through the Central Securities Clearing System (CSCS), a subsidiary of the NSE, which was established to allow the automation of transactions in real time in a T+3 transaction cycle. Settlement is completed though means of the NIBSS.</p>
<div class="url-list">
<h4 id="key-websites">Key websites</h4>
<dl class="websites">
<dt>Federal Ministry of Finance:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.fmf.gov.ng/" target="_blank">www.fmf.gov.ng</a></dd>
<dt>Central Bank of Nigeria:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.cenbank.org/" target="_blank">www.cenbank.org</a></dd>
<dt>Securities and Exchange Commission</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.sec.gov.ng/" target="_blank">www.sec.gov.ng</a></dd>
<dt>Federal Inland Revenue Service:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.firs.gov.ng/" target="_blank">www.firs.gov.ng</a></dd>
<dt>Nigeria Deposit Insurance Corporation:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.ndic.org.ng/" target="_blank">www.ndic.org.ng</a></dd>
<dt>The Chartered Institute of Taxation of Nigeria:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.citn.org/" target="_blank">www.citn.org</a></dd>
<dt>Nigerian Stock Exchange:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.nigerianstockexchange.com/" target="_blank">www.nigerianstockexchange.com</a></dd>
</dl>
</div>
<div class="profile">
<h3 id="citis-capabilities-in-nigeria">Citi’s capabilities in Nigeria</h3>
<p>Citi celebrates its 25<sup>th</sup> anniversary of operations in Nigeria in 2009. Formerly operating under the name Nigeria International Bank Limited, it was renamed Citibank Nigeria Limited in 2008. Citi offers its clients a broad range of services in the areas of treasury, cash management, investments, loans, trade, buyer and supplier financing, capital markets, risk management and corporate finance, from 13 branches across the country.</p>
<p>In August 2008 Citi unveiled its Direct Custody and Clearing Services (DCC) in Nigeria. The DCC business is designed to enable transactions for investors looking to do business in Nigeria. Additional products offered by Citi include payment solutions to meet a variety of local and international payment needs, and a range of receivables products and liquidity management solutions which enable clients to make the most of the return on cash balances in local foreign currency accounts.</p>
<p>Citi also offers its CitiDirect® online banking platform in Nigeria. This is the primary platform used by clients to administer cash management products and access services both locally and globally.</p>
<div class="contacts">
<h5>Contact details:</h5>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Iheyinwa Ugenyi</dt>
<dd class="role">Sales Head Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+234 1 279 8459</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:iheyinwa.ugenyi@citi.com">iheyinwa.ugenyi@citi.com</a></dd>
<dt class="org">Citi</dt>
<dd class="country-name">Nigeria, West &amp; Central Africa</dd>
</dl>
</div>
<img alt="Citi logo" class="logo" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-2012-70x40.png" width="70"/>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Africa]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Doing business in South Africa]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2009 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Famous for its mining and agriculture, the South African economy is underpinned by a strong manufacturing and agricultural base.</p>
<div class="country-facts">
<figure class="map">
<img alt="Map of South Africa" height="154" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2009/03/2009-03-tt-05-cp-south-africa-map-205x154.png" width="205"/>
</figure>
<h4 id="key-facts">Key facts</h4>
<h5 id="geography-and-society">Geography and society</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Population:</dt><dd>48.8 million</dd>
<dt>Population growth rate:</dt><dd>0.8%</dd>
<dt>Official languages:</dt><dd>Afrikaans, English, Ndebele, Northern Sotho, Sotho, Swati, Tsonga, Tswana, Venda, Xhosa, Zulu</dd>
<dt>Capital city (executive):</dt><dd>Pretoria</dd>
<dt>Capital city (judicial):</dt><dd>Bloemfontein</dd>
<dt>Capital city (legislative):</dt><dd>Cape Town</dd>
<dt>Time zone:</dt><dd>CET+1</dd>
<dt>Land boundaries:</dt><dd>Botswana 1,840 km,	Lesotho 909 km, Mozambique 491 km, Namibia 967 km, Swaziland 430 km, Zimbabwe 225 km</dd>
<dt>Coastline:</dt><dd>2,798km</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="economy">Economy</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Currency:</dt><dd>South African rand (ZAR)</dd>
<dt>GDP per capita:</dt><dd>$5,952</dd>
<dt>CPI inflation rate:</dt><dd>11.8%</dd>
<dt>Member of:</dt><dd>UN, IGTA, FATF</dd>
<dt>Fiscal year:</dt><dd>1<sup>st</sup> March – 28<sup>th</sup>/29<sup>th</sup> February</dd>
<dt>Financial capital:</dt><dd>Johannesburg</dd>
<dt>FX regime:</dt><dd>managed float</dd>
<dt>Trade deficit:</dt><dd>$6.7 billion</dd>
<dt>Average days to start a business:</dt><dd>31</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="history-and-politics">History and politics</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Government type:</dt><dd>parliamentary republic</dd>
<dt>Governing party:</dt><dd>African National Congress (ANC)</dd>
<dt>Republic established:</dt><dd>31<sup>st</sup> May 1961</dd>
<dt>President:</dt><dd>Kgalema Motlanthe (interim)</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="country-credit-rating">Country credit rating</h5>
<ul>
<li>BBB+</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="trading-partners">Trading partners</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Top import sources:</dt><dd>Germany, China, Spain, US and Japan</dd>
<dt>Top export destinations:</dt><dd>US, Japan, Germany, UK and China</dd>
</dl>
</div>
<h3 id="the-economic-heart-of-africa">The economic heart of Africa</h3>
<p>Since its re-entry into the global economy, following the demise of apartheid in 1994, South Africa has seen the services sector emerge as the new lynchpin of the most advanced economy in Africa.</p>
<p>Today, the bulk of economic activity still occurs where mining is most prevalent, namely the Gauteng province, home to Johannesburg, the country’s financial capital. Due to its geographical location on the southernmost tip of Africa, South Africa is a logistical haven for reaching the sub-Saharan countries as well as trading across the Indian and South Atlantic oceans.</p>
<p>The country is now in its 15<sup>th</sup> year of democracy, and has undergone substantial economic and social reform, with notable achievements including lower taxes, lower inflation, reduced budget deficits, a relative stronger currency and fewer controls surrounding foreign exchange. South Africa was ranked 45<sup>th</sup> out of 134 economies in the 2008/2009 Global Competitiveness Report published by the World Economic Forum, and has cemented its position as a consistently well-performing emerging market economy.</p>
<figure class="left">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1-gdp-growth-in-south-africa">Chart 1: GDP growth in South Africa (%)</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2009/03/2009-03-tt-05-cp-chart-01-gdp-growth-in-south-africa-pc.png"><img alt="Chart 1: GDP growth in South Africa (%)" height="213" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2009/03/2009-03-tt-05-cp-chart-01-gdp-growth-in-south-africa-pc-t.png" width="300"/></a>
</figure>
<p style="clear:left;">The country’s improving GDP figures are a significant indicator of economic progress. These figures have been boosted by the increasing levels of direct foreign investment into South Africa, which were helped by the establishment of the Investment South Africa organisation in 1997. Investment South Africa was set up by the Department of Trade and Industry in order to promote investment at both a national and a provincial level and many country-wide and regional investment incentives are available.</p>
<p>These incentives include preferential tax rates for SMEs, a series of SME development programmes and foreign investment grants. As there are no restrictions on the extent or type of foreign investment in South Africa, the country has become attractive to businesses looking to reap the benefits of operating in an emerging market, whilst having the comfort and security of a world-class economic environment, such as the Gauteng Special Economic Zone. Gauteng is also reportedly one of the lowest cost locations in the world for establishing and running a business.</p>
<p>South Africa is often referred to as having ‘two economies’ – a dynamic first world economy and a rural and urban economy where socio-economic inequalities from the apartheid regime are still rife. In order to redress these historical inequalities and to help South Africa build an adaptive, sustainable economic environment for all its citizens by 2014, the Government launched its Black Economic Empowerment programme which aims to lift the level of participation of black South Africans in the economy. The country is looking forward to hosting the 2010 FIFA World Cup which will bring with it substantial international media exposure and has boosted the country’s infrastructure investment programmes. It is expected that the 2010 World Cup will create 160,000 jobs, leaving a lasting economic legacy.</p>
<h3 id="legal-and-regulatory-requirements">Legal and regulatory requirements</h3>
<p>South Africa’s colonial past has left its mark on the country’s legal and regulatory requirements for businesses, which closely resemble those seen in Europe today. The South African government aims to encourage foreign investment and South African legislation has been tailored to reflect this open attitude. The legal and regulatory requirements for doing business in South Africa are uniform across the country’s nine provinces:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>South Africa’s banking sector is supervised and regulated by the South African Reserve Bank (SARB), which is also the country’s central bank. The SARB issues licences to banking institutions, and monitors their activities under the Banks Act, 1990 (Act No. 94 of 1990), or the Mutual Banks Act, 1993 (Act No. 124 of 1993) as appropriate.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Central bank reporting regulations require that each cross-border transaction carried out by a bank must be individually reported as far as the balance of payments is concerned, on a daily basis. Monthly reporting on the financial position of the bank is expected, as is periodic reporting of overnight foreign currency positions. Corporates are not subject to central bank reporting requirements.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Financial Services Board (FSB) regulates non-banking financial services firms in South Africa. The FSB is a wholly independent institution that aims to promote and maintain a sound financial investment environment in South Africa.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The agreements that South Africa has in place with international bodies such as the Bank of International Settlements (BIS), the International Organisation of Securities Commissions (IOSCO), and the International Association of Insurance Supervisors (IAIS) mean that financial regulation in South Africa is increasingly moving toward international best practice.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The King Report institutionalised corporate governance in South Africa in 1994. In 2002 the King Committee report was updated (King II) and the Code of Corporate Practices and Conduct came into effect on 1<sup>st</sup> March 2002. The code highlights seven key areas for good governance: discipline, transparency, independence, accountability, responsibility, fairness and social responsibility and is similar to the UK’s principles-based regulatory regime.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>South African companies are currently required to adhere to South African Statements of Generally Accepted Accounting Practice (SA GAAP), which have been fully aligned with International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS). As from 1<sup>st</sup> January 2005, under the Johannesburg Stock Exchange (JSE) listing requirements, listed companies must comply with IFRS.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Under the Companies Act and Close Corporation Act, all businesses must register with the South African Revenue Service, the Unemployment Insurance Fund, the Workmen’s Compensation commissioner and industrial councils (where applicable).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All foreign exchange transactions in South Africa are subject to exchange control regulations, which are governed by the South African Reserve Bank. The exchange controls are designed to limit outflows of money from the country. These restrictions apply to both individuals and businesses but are only imposed on transactions between residents and non-residents. The rules are significant as the level of official reserves of foreign currency is a fundamental factor in the value of the rand, which is a managed floating currency.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All bank transactions (including account maintenance and documentation) are subject to compliance with the above mentioned exchange control regulations.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="taxation-framework">Taxation framework</h4>
<p>Since 2001, South Africa has operated a resident-based tax system, as opposed to a source-based tax system. Under this new regime, residents are (certain exclusions aside) taxed on their worldwide income, irrespective of where it was earned, whereas non-residents are taxed on their income from South African sources only. For the main part, state income is derived from income tax. However, indirect taxes such as VAT make up almost one-third of total government taxes.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>On 1<sup>st</sup> April 2008, the resident corporation tax rate was lowered from 29% to 28%. Non-resident (ie branch) corporate tax is levied at a rate of 33%.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Companies that pay net dividends are liable for Secondary Tax on Companies (STC) taxed at a rate of 10% of net dividends paid. STC is due to be phased out in the second half of 2010 and replaced with a Dividends Tax which will be a tax on the shareholder and collected in the form of a withholding tax.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Value Added Tax (VAT) is levied at a rate of 14% (although some exemptions apply) on the sale of goods and the provision of services.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Securities Transfer Tax is charged at a rate of 0.25% on the transfer or cancellation of equity securities and stamp duty of 0.5% is payable on lease agreements of immovable (real estate) property.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>There is a transfer tax of 8% that applies to the transfer of residential and other immovable (real estate) property, unless the transaction is subject to VAT.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>South African law imposes both transfer pricing and thin capitalisation rules. Under the transfer pricing rules, where goods or services are supplied or acquired under an international agreement between connected persons (ie group companies), the pricing must be conducted at arm’s length. The thin capitalisation rules apply where a non-resident investor provides financial assistance to a resident connected person or entity, in which the investor is entitled to participate in 25% or more of the company’s equity. The rules are designed to limit the amount of interest paid to the lender by the South African company. The thin capitalisation rules do not apply however if the debt-to-equity ratio exceeds 3:1, or if the financial assistance is granted by a parent company to its branch operating as an external company in South Africa.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Withholding taxes are imposed on royalties at a rate of 12%. No withholding tax is currently levied on interest payments made to non-residents.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="treasury-activities">Treasury activities</h3>
<h4 id="local-banking-sector">Local banking sector</h4>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-2-number-of-banks-operating-in-south-africa">Chart 2: Number of banks operating in South Africa</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2009/03/2009-03-tt-05-cp-chart-02-number-of-banks-operating-in-south-africa.png"><img alt="Chart 2: Number of banks operating in South Africa" height="149" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2009/03/2009-03-tt-05-cp-chart-02-number-of-banks-operating-in-south-africa-t.png" width="300"/></a>
</figure>
<p>Overseen by the Reserve Bank, the local banking industry in South Africa is dominated by four large local players: Nedbank, ABSA (a subsidiary of Barclays Bank), Standard Bank and FirstRand. These national players provide both retail and investment banking services as the sector has become highly competitive with the re-entry of many experienced foreign players.</p>
<p>Foreign banks returned to the South African market in the mid 1990s, having left in the late 1980s due to disenchantment with the government’s apartheid policy.</p>
<p>Banks operating in South Africa, when left short of liquidity, need to borrow from the SARB at a fluctuating repo rate, which in turn allows the central bank to monitor liquidity positions.</p>
<p>South Africa operates a single floating exchange rate that is managed by the SARB through intervention in the spot and forward markets, thereby reducing volatility.</p>
<h4 id="liquidity-and-cash-management">Liquidity and cash management</h4>
<p>Integrated and advanced cash management is a well-established concept amongst corporates in South Africa, and as such, there is a wide range of products available. Both single and multi-entity cash concentration structures are permitted and options include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Notional pooling.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Zero balancing.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>One-way target balancing.</p></li>
<li>
<p>Two-way target balancing.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Although multilateral netting is not permitted under South African exchange control rules, single and multi-entity notional pooling is allowed.</p>
<h4 id="bank-accounts">Bank accounts</h4>
<p>Account opening in South Africa is strictly controlled by the Financial Intelligence Centre Act, which applies to both resident and non-resident accounts.</p>
<p>Interest is paid on both resident and non-resident ZAR and foreign currency accounts.</p>
<h4 id="money-market">Money market</h4>
<p>Aside from the liquidity and cash management structures, South Africa has an advanced money market, and the main short-term investment instruments are:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Bankers’ acceptances.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Treasury bills – these are issued by the SARB and normally have a maturity of 91 days, although there are some smaller issues with maturities of 182, 273 or 364 days.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Debentures – again, issued by the SARB, debentures typically have a maturity of 28 or 56 days, though occasionally they are issued with a 91-day maturity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Short-dated government stock.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Negotiable certificates of deposit – issued by major South African banks on a yield basis, with a maximum maturity of five years.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Investor promissory notes – these are generally issued with a minimum maturity of two years.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="payments-clearing-and-settlement">Payments, clearing and settlement</h4>
<p>South Africa is well known for having a sound and sophisticated payments infrastructure. The country’s National Payment System (NPS), which was established in 1994, is the framework that encompasses payments made between banks as well as the steps involved in the payment process from start to finish.</p>
<p>The NPS is entrenched in law and is one of the nation’s pillars of financial stability. The Reserve Bank oversees the NPS and implements risk-reduction measures aimed at minimising systemic risk.</p>
<p>The major payment methods in use in South Africa include: cash, electronic funds transfers, funds transfers via SWIFT, cheques, credit/debit cards, prepaid and contactless cards and mobile e-payments. The main clearing and settlement systems in South Africa are:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Bankserv (Automated Clearing Bureau – ACB)</h5>
<p>Bankserv processes ZAR electronic funds transfers (debits and credits) and cheques, and is mostly used by South African resident legal entities. The infrastructure has existed for approximately 30 years and is designed to provide a cost-effective high volume service to the banking industry. Bankserv offers both real-time and non real-time clearing services with immediate or overnight settlement for electronic payments and collections. Bankserv clears in excess of 4m cheque-based transactions each month.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>SAMOS (South African Multiple Option Settlement)</h5>
<p>Originally developed as an inter-bank real-time electronic settlement system now also used to clear retail and commercial payments as well as bond and equity market obligations. The SAMOS system settles on a pre-funded basis and if a bank has insufficient funds in its settlement account, the system will automatically grant a loan to the bank against acceptable collateral. SAMOS can be used by both resident and non-resident entities.</p>
<p>At the end of 2001, the SARB and the Payments Association of South Africa (PASA) introduced certain clearing and settlement limits that were designed to direct payments through the country’s SAMOS system. The limits are:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Electronic fund transfers (EFT) debits and debit orders may not be issued through Bankserv for more than ZAR 500,000.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>EFT credit payments through Bankserv may not exceed ZAR 5m.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cheques may not be written for a sum larger than ZAR 5m.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Funds transfers greater than ZAR 5m must be initiated via SAMOS.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>The South African rand was included as a Continuous Linked Settlement (CLS) currency in December 2004 and the SARB acts as principal in South Africa’s CLS transactions.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="url-list">
<h4 id="key-websites">Key websites</h4>
<dl class="websites">
<dt>Government website:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.gov.za" target="_blank">www.gov.za</a></dd>
<dt>South African Reserve Bank:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.reservebank.co.za" target="_blank">www.reservebank.co.za</a></dd>
<dt>The Financial Services Board:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.fsb.co.za" target="_blank">www.fsb.co.za</a></dd>
<dt>The Banking Association South Africa:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.banking.org.za" target="_blank">www.banking.org.za</a></dd>
<dt>Department of Trade and Industry:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.thedti.gov.za" target="_blank">www.thedti.gov.za</a></dd>
<dt>National Treasury:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.finance.gov.za" target="_blank">www.finance.gov.za</a></dd>
<dt>South African Revenue Service:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.sars.gov.za" target="_blank">www.sars.gov.za</a></dd>
<dt>Johannesburg Securities Exchange:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.jse.co.za" target="_blank">www.jse.co.za</a></dd>
<dt>SA futures Exchange SAFEX:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.safex.co.za" target="_blank">www.safex.co.za</a></dd>
<dt>Payments Association of South Africa:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.pasa.org.za" target="_blank">www.pasa.org.za</a></dd>
<dt>Association of Corporate Treasures of Southern Africa:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.actsa.org.za" target="_blank">www.actsa.org.za</a></dd>
</dl>
</div>
<div class="profile">
<h3 id="citis-capabilities-in-south-africa">Citi’s capabilities in South Africa</h3>
<p>Citi is one of the largest commercial banks operating in South Africa today. Citi re-established its presence in South Africa in 1995, and the bank has had a strong presence on the African continent for over 50 years, with offices in 16 countries. An additional 23 countries are covered through a non-presence country unit based in Johannesburg. Including partner banks, Citi’s coverage extends to 1,204 branches in South Africa.</p>
<p>Citi’s Corporate Banking Division is the hub for the bank’s strong relationship with top tier South African companies and global corporations with business in South Africa. The bank’s extensive product range, which is tailored to provide integrated banking solutions ranging from Global Transaction Services to complex financing structures, is backed up by customer solution teams, comprising dedicated relationship managers and product specialists. These teams are situated both locally and abroad to provide a diversity of expertise.</p>
<p>Global Transaction Services offers integrated treasury and trade solutions for multinational corporations, financial institutions and the public sector in South Africa. Citi Global Transaction Services is instrumental in the development of clearing, settlement and depository facilities in numerous emerging countries, and is a leading strategic advisor on industry issues such as local securities markets, emerging markets, settlement risk, receivables and payment processes, securities infrastructure and technology integration.</p>
<div class="contacts">
<h5 id="contact-details">Contact details:</h5>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Philip Panaino</dt>
<dd class="title">Director, Global Transaction Services Head South Africa</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+27 11 944 0805</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:philip.panaino@citi.com">philip.panaino@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Maria Mayrhofer</dt>
<dd class="title">Director, Global Transaction Services Sales Head Sub-Saharan Africa</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+27 11 944 0132</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:maria.mayrhofer@citi.com">maria.mayrhofer@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
</div>
<img alt="Citi Logo" class="logo" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-2012-70x40.png" width="70">
</img></div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
</data>
