<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Asia’s accounting scandals spur audit reform]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>A string of high-profile corporate failures and frauds in Asia has called into question the role of the auditors and prompted calls for the profession to be reformed. This falls in line with a global trend of audit reform and a need to adapt to the changing requirements of corporates.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4AF6C885E312C32D88E9A8E18859853B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=20BC92B03E71F29FC0A46B22FD6E57A5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FD8B85C0E8CBFC73AB3F7FB2DF075E5A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AE0A4BEA27619B590F1E9258B28AD48E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6737D987A66453519F2961A4CC570C57"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Justice scales and law books" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2AACAA5F7A699B7D8F5EE472AC53659E" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2AACAA5F7A699B7D8F5EE472AC53659E"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Corporate collapses, frauds and accounting scandals in Asia have blighted the reputation of the audit profession in recent years and have even threatened to undermine investor confidence in their reporting. High-quality audits have been described by the International Federation of Accountants (IFAC) as the “backbone of the global financial system” and there has been a movement across the globe to reform how they are done. This could have ramifications for companies in Asia – and the overseas markets where they are listed – and how they do their corporate reporting.</p>
<p>There is a long list of high-profile cases in Asia that have spurred the need for audit reform. The pattern seems to go like this: a high-profile collapse, revelation of accounting lapses, ensuing litigation and promises of reform.</p>
<p>Jim Peterson, a lawyer and specialist in corporate financial information and author of Count Down: The Past, Present and Uncertain Future of the Big Four Accounting Firms, says that public outrage over the performance of auditors is cyclical. “When things are cruising along nobody cares,” he says. And then something goes wrong. “Then they look back and say ‘where were the auditors?’,” Peterson says. “Then the bureaucrats and politicians stir the pot, then it calms down until there’s another cycle. These cycles tend to run on a seven to ten year cycle.”</p>
<p>There is currently ongoing litigation related to some of the high-profile scandals. In February, for example, a Goldman Sachs banker was on trial in New York related to 1Malaysia Development Berhad (1MDB) – Malaysia’s sovereign wealth fund – and the alleged embezzlement of billions of dollars. The question of ‘where were the auditors?’ has already been asked in a separate US$5.6bn lawsuit the Malaysian government brought against the partners of KPMG Malaysia. In September 2021 this was settled for US$80m.</p>
<p>In China, the public has also been questioning the role of the auditors in the alleged frauds at companies like Kangde Xin Composite Material Group and Kangmei Pharmaceutical. And when the debt-laden property giant Evergrande defaulted on its bonds, questions were asked about accounting irregularities and why auditors gave the company the all-clear when it was so overstretched. There have been other scandals, such as the fraud at Luckin Coffee, which led to it being delisted in the United States. In August 2021, China’s State Council vowed to improve the oversight of accounting firms and published detailed rules on supervision.</p>
<p>A few months earlier, in January 2021, there was a similar move in Singapore to increase the scrutiny of listed companies. The regulatory unit of the Singapore Exchange (SGX) introduced additional requirements for auditors following some accounting scandals, such as the collapse of oil trader Hin Leong Trading and fraud at another oil trader Hontop Energy.</p>
<p>The listing of companies on foreign exchanges has highlighted shortcomings in the audit process. For Chinese companies, the financial statements – or working papers – are deemed sensitive data and cannot be removed from China. This has been the source of a long-running spat between the US and China because US regulators and liquidators cannot inspect the audits of Chinese companies that are listed in the United States. This puts the large audit firms in a difficult position, caught between the interests of the two countries. It also undermines investor confidence in the US-listed Chinese companies.</p>
<p>Pressure has been increasing, and, in December 2021, the SEC finalised rules that would implement the Holding Foreign Companies Accountable Act. This was introduced in 2020 – under the Trump administration – to enable the inspection of US-listed Chinese companies.</p>
<p>The need for audit reform is not unique to Asian companies, and there is a global movement afoot to bring changes to the way corporate reporting is done. The Public Company Accounting Oversight Board (PCAOB), which is the body that could lead audit reform – for the US and potentially set an example for the rest of the world – has been hampered by difficulties of its own. Matt Kelly, Editor and CEO of Radical Compliance, which provides consulting and commentary on corporate compliance, audit governance and risk management, comments that the regulation of the audit industry has been weak for several years.</p>
<p>He describes the PCAOB as “dysfunctional” and says in the US, “we have not really seen reform – the regulator was a mess”. Part of this mess saw the PCAOB Chair William Duhnke removed from his position by the SEC in June 2021. SEC Chair Gary Gensler said at the time said he was looking forward to set the PCAOB on a “path to better protect investors by ensuring that public company audits are informative, accurate, and independent.” He was not forthcoming about the details of the dismissal, but there were news reports of a toxic culture at PCAOB and a story of Duhnke throwing an empty soda can at another board member.</p>
<p>In the US, so far changes have not occurred: “They are not really doing a good job of reform of audits because the regulators have been dysfunctional. The action is definitely coming out of the UK,” says Kelly. “The UK is well ahead of the curve,” he adds.</p>
<p>For those in Asia – and the rest of the world – who have been calling for audit reform, the UK offers a beacon of light as it has gone through an exhaustive consultation process and has offered a number of proposals.</p>


<blockquote><p>To stand up to a big organisation you have to be big yourself or you could be cowed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Kevin Dancey, CEO, International Federation of Accountants</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Following the corporate collapses of Carillion, Patisserie Valerie and Thomas Cook, in the UK people also asked ‘where were the auditors?’ In response, in March 2021, the UK’s Department for Business Energy and Industrial Strategy (BEIS) announced it was launching a consultation to reform the UK’s audit and governance regime.</p>
<p>The BEIS proposals build on recommendations of previous reviews – led by Donald Brydon, John Kingman and the Competition Markets Authority – and include requiring large audit firms to use ‘challenger’ firms to do a substantial part of the audit and putting a cap on the market share of large firms. Also, a new regulator would be introduced with powers to split the audit and non-audit functions of accountancy firms to reduce the risk of conflicts of interest.</p>
<p>On the issue of whether the Big Four accounting firms need to be broken up, Kevin Dancey, CEO of IFAC, says the companies being audited are large – with large extensive operations around the world – and the scale of the audit firm has to match. Also, points out Dancey, “To stand up to a big organisation you have to be big yourself or you could be cowed.” Peterson agrees that the ‘challenger’ audit firms would be unable to take up the degree and quantity of work that would be necessary.</p>
<p>There is an issue with non-audit services and the perception that this could impact the independence of the audit firm. Dancey says that an audit-only firm would not be able to attract the right people to do a high-quality audit. “The audit firm needs to bring in expertise in other areas as well – such as tax – and you can do that within the multidisciplinary firm,” says Dancey.</p>
<p>When asked to comment on the global trend of audit reform, Dancey says, “I think the journey of audit is always how we can do better,” he says, adding that the world is evolving and the profession is always looking to make the process more efficient for all stakeholders. “At IFAC we always look at it through an audit quality lens,” he says, explaining that he takes a step back and questions if any reforms will enhance audit quality or not – a different approach from those who focus on competition. IFAC has outlined the five factors it believes are necessary for a high-quality audit. These are the right process, the right people, the right governance, the right regulation and the right measurement.</p>
<p>On the question of how the audit process could be better, Peterson questions whether the way they are currently done has lost their usefulness to companies. He argues that the idea of a ‘true and fair view’ opinion has lost its value. He says that audit committees and chief financial officers would rather spend their money on a more nuanced and bespoke report that goes into detail on particular countries or departments, for example. “There are regulatory and political constraints on the firms being able to do that,” Peterson says.</p>
<p>Also, he notes in a journal article, that the pass/fail nature of audits is too simplistic and inadequate. This is something that Kelly raises: “Audit inspections are difficult for readers to use. The audit committees do not really know what an audit inspection is telling them.”</p>
<p>If the needs of companies in this respect are already complex, they are set to become even more so. The expectations of what corporations need to report is evolving and Dancey sees a growth in the demand for corporate reporting on environmental, social and governance issues (ESG). He says attention needs to be paid to the sustainability issues – “Sustainability is real and coming to a company near you – avoid this at your peril,” he says. “The treasurers and CFOs of the world cannot treat this in siloes.” They need to have an integrated approach in their company so senior management and boards can make good decisions. Also, they need to have the right reporting in an integrated and responsible way, says Dancey.</p>
<p>This points to a change in skills that will be needed in the future. In the UK’s Brydon report there is the idea of a new professional designation of a ‘corporate auditor’, who could provide multi-disciplinary services across what a corporate requires. This could involve a range of subject matter expertise that will be needed from the profession in areas such as the environment and cyber-security.</p>
<p>In terms of the skillsets needed for this, Dancey comments that accountants are well placed to take this up because of their expertise in quantifying information and corporate reporting. With ESG reporting, for example, Dancey says “Professional accountants have the skills to deal with these issues,” says Dancey.</p>
<p>While accountants may not be well versed in these other areas at the moment, Dancey comments this is why multi-disciplinary firms are important because they can draw on experience of others with different subject matter expertise.</p>
<p>These are just some of the issues that the audit profession is grappling with, both in Asia and other regions in the world. As it addresses the failures of the past, it also needs to look to the future and accommodate the evolving needs of corporates, and also move beyond the cycle of public outrage of people asking where they were.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[A string of high-profile corporate failures and frauds in Asia has called into question the role of the auditors and prompted calls for the profession to be reformed. This falls in line with a global trend of audit reform and a need to adapt to the changing requirements of corporates.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2022-03-04-tta-03-reg__scales-justice-law-books-on-desk-1793492323__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2022-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Reporting]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury’s challenge: environmental performance and financial reporting]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>As investors increasingly clamour to see the relationship between a company’s financial and sustainability performance, so treasury and finance teams will play an increasing role in integrating sustainability into financial reports.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=66FBE57D1A98DB3259E0AA9B3EDACB5A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D56BA8993FE122AE7ED49C560B310444"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=80B85B1995C980F391932DF99E325A85"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F267BDC43B984F09EC15AF7440DDA082"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E01119235CD25026627D85EE643F4D87"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Aerial view of people putting together the world map" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1D9D761EB93538DA4D44E17568300B10" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1D9D761EB93538DA4D44E17568300B10"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Companies are setting increasingly bold environmental goals and ambitious commitments to reduce carbon emissions. Yet these important promises are rarely mirrored in their financial statements, making it difficult for investors and other stakeholders to see the relationship between a company’s financial and sustainability performance. This could change if new sustainable accounting standards come to fruition and regulators act on growing investor pressure to introduce mandatory climate disclosure. Reporting the physical, transition and regulatory risk of climate change would go to the heart of companies’ risk management and governance processes and calls for hands-on treasury and finance expertise.</p>
<p>The IFRS Foundation, the body that oversees the work of the International Accounting Standards Board, IASB, in setting financial reporting requirements for most companies in the world outside the US (where these requirements are set by the Financial Accounting Standards Board) is on track to launch a Sustainability Standards Board, SSB, at the UN’s COP26 climate summit in November. All being well, the new standards will give investors and other stakeholders as clear a view of corporate sustainability as they currently do financial performance in one, integrated report.</p>
<p>Moreover, the different and acronym-heavy measurements and reporting standards surrounding ESG will be replaced with a standard norm. “The idea is that all the different standards will converge into the SSB and take standards forward into the future,” explains Emily Kreps, Global Director of Capital Markets at CDP, a global non-profit that uses investor pressure to cajole companies to disclose around environmental performance.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, Gary Gensler, Chair of the SEC in the US, recently spoke up in favour of the regulator forcing greater clarity and consistency in corporate climate disclosure, flagging new policies towards the end of the year. Earlier in June, the G7 agreed to force companies to report climate issues in line with the global Task Force on Climate-related Financial Disclosure, created in 2015 by the Financial Stability Board to develop broad but consistent climate-related financial risk disclosures for use by companies worldwide.</p>
<h4 id="carbon-intensive-industries">Carbon intensive industries</h4>
<p>The need for financial statements to mirror the reality of climate change is important for all companies but particularly carbon intensive industries, says Barbara Davidson, a Senior Analyst at the Carbon Tracker Initiative, an independent financial think tank which analyses the impact of the climate transition on the capital markets. Her team combed through the sustainability and audit reports, proxy and annual financial statements of companies in the oil and gas, transport and utility sectors to see the extent to which climate-related risks and corporate climate pledges flowed through into financial statements to reflect changes like falls in product demand or commodity prices as the climate emergency grows.</p>
<p>Their findings are worrying. Despite COVID laying bare the impact of falling oil prices on oil companies’ profitability, few oil majors reflected lower oil prices, declining demand in line with IEA scenarios, or regulatory fuel on the fire shortening the lives of assets in their expected future cash flows. “Faced with declining prices as a result of climate change, oil and gas companies will not be able to recover the value of their assets from expected future cash flows,” predicts Davidson. “The costs of running these assets will also go up with efforts to reduce emissions and rising carbon prices.”</p>
<h4 id="asset-value">Asset value</h4>
<p>It’s not just most oil groups inaccurately reflecting the resilience of their assets to climate change in their financial statements. A decline in demand for a myriad of products that emit greenhouse gases could hit all kinds of manufacturing plants making the products. In the transport sector, companies have made bold statements around electrification but the impact on the company of meeting these promises from increased costs, investment and the impact on margins is rarely accounted for.</p>
<p>As for utilities, companies need to accurately account for continued product demand in a low carbon world, and put the cost of changing their offering, the impact of regulation, access to renewable energy and costly new infrastructure into their financial reporting. “Do they have long-term agreements in place to purchase fossil fuels, and if so, how will regulation impact those agreements?” asks Davidson. “When we look at most companies’ financial statements, we don’t know if they have actually considered climate issues when assessing asset impairments.” Elsewhere, she says few companies appeared to consider the costs and impact of their Paris commitments to reduce emissions in their financials.</p>
<h4 id="the-role-of-treasury">The role of treasury</h4>
<p>The task requires all hands to the pump. Finance and treasury teams need to understand how changes in corporate strategy and the impact of regulation will translate into the estimates they use to prepare their financial statements. Moreover, finance teams sitting in the heart of a business are in pole position to source information and act on it. “You can’t have procurement making decisions on energy sourcing and not involve finance teams,” explains Kreps. And because accounting for these issues will impact the operations of many companies, it requires governance and risk management expertise too. Teams made up of people from different business lines rather than keeping the process siloed in sustainability works best.</p>
<p>Treasury also has a central role explaining to investors how they are addressing the issue. Even if integrating the impact of climate change into financial statements is still early stage, treasury and finance need to show investors their sensitivity to the job in hand. Next comes board oversight to ensure the process is mainstreamed into the company, filtering into internal processes. “One of the first questions we always ask is if there is management level oversight, and where the team gathering the data sits,” says Kreps.</p>
<h4 id="auditors">Auditors</h4>
<p>Auditors also play a role, challenging companies on how they are considering these issues and if financial statements are materially updated to reflect climate change. Calls for auditors to do more are growing louder. Many companies file their statements outside the US but list on the US stock exchange in a dual listing that follows two different audit standards. While the risks remain the same, US audit reports often exclude reference to any climate-related considerations. “It means the US market gets less information,” says Davidson. “If US investors are only reading the US filings and US audit reports for these companies, they may receive less information than their overseas counterparts.” A key challenge for auditors is that the timeframes that companies use for calculating expected cashflows do not always cover their timeframe for emissions reductions.</p>
<h4 id="getting-started">Getting started</h4>
<p>A good place to start is disclosing to CDP, says Kreps. The process gives companies an understanding of the types of questions and information they will need to begin to source, builds capacity and educates. “What we provide gives companies a way to prepare for the regulatory environment we anticipate coming.”</p>
<p>Evaluating, understanding and ultimately gathering the metrics companies will need is daunting. “They are not easy metrics to measure,” she says. “It is a significant shift for companies to track, collect and estimate this forward-looking component. It is not like traditional financial disclosure where finance teams can assume how a business line or company will perform in the future – it is much more difficult to do this with environmental metrics.”</p>
<p>But she insists the tools and methodologies are available, like the Science-Based Target Initiatives which have industry specific methodologies to help companies think about calculating their climate impact and modelling. Elsewhere, the PCAF (Partnership for Carbon Accounting Financials) helps financial institutions report their greenhouse gas emissions. “It takes time to adopt these different standards and understand them. The plane is being built as it’s being flown, and this is disconcerting and challenging for treasury teams.”</p>
<p>One potential catalyst for change could come from linking executive pay to meeting climate targets instead of using current metrics linked to profits. This in turn would make climate accounting and reporting processes central. “The more that compensation remains linked to profits which exclude climate targets, the harder it will be to shift practices,” says Davidson, who notes that only “a handful” of companies currently link compensation to meeting emissions reduction targets.</p>
<p>IFRS standards may not be mandatory, and they are also likely to be location and industry specific. “A standard that is relevant to the EU could be different for a resource intensive economy like South Africa so there will need to be nuances,” says Kreps. And although new standards will be unveiled at COP26, the reality will be a long, drawn-out introduction. IFRS accounting standards, and the generally accepted accounting principles, or GAAP, took almost 30 years for consensus. The process will be iterative and evolve over time, with the first mandatory disclosure looking very different from the third iteration. Still, the most important thing is for companies to get started on integrating climate impacts into their financial reporting. “Start now because the reality is the planet doesn’t have the time,” concludes Kreps.</p>



<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Case study</h2>
<p><img alt="Deutsche Post DHL logo" class="org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/deutche-post-dhl-logo-2014-120x23.png?la=en&amp;hash=F8F37586DB82F3DAF8DE30EC402526AE" title="Deutsche Post DHL logo" width="120"/></p>
<p><em>Deutsche Post DHL Group’s Adam Pradela, Executive Vice President Corporate Accounting &amp; Controlling and Klaus Hufschlag, Senior Vice President CREST Finance Business Intelligence &amp; Analytics share the giant logistics group’s progress on climate reporting.</em></p>
<p>We published our first environmental report in 2003. Since then, every year the process has evolved. In 2015 we produced our sustainability and annual report simultaneously for the first time and in March this year we produced our first, integrated annual report containing both financial and non-financial statements. In previous years the reporting process fell to other departments but now it is centralised under Corporate Accounting and Controlling.</p>
<p>The decision to centralise everything under finance has been essential. It has ensured we get the quality of data we need; finance has the skills to gather and process the data and now drives our reporting process. The other key thing we’ve learnt is that companies should treat greenhouse gas emissions like a cost and manage them down like a cost. Once you have the data, you can do this.</p>
<p>Moreover, we don’t only want to report on our carbon emissions, we want to control them and drive them down. With this in mind, we have now introduced incentives from next year so that board members will have a flexible element of their salary tied to ESG targets rather than solely to financial achievements.</p>
<p>Since we published our accelerated roadmap to decarbonisation in March this year, we have seen a significant rise in our share price. Investors appreciate what we are doing. Carbon emissions are a very relevant KPI for our investors, and an area we can show good performance. We have improved our carbon efficiency by 37% since we started our CO2 reduction programme in 2008. Importantly, our stock price went up at the same time as we announced plans to spend €7bn on sustainability by 2030 – the world of investment is going in this direction.</p>
<p>Regulation, increased customer demand as well as investor pressure, is driving our strategy. The new EU taxonomy asks us to show how much of our revenue comes from clean operations and the upcoming Corporate Sustainability Reporting Directive (CSRD) will increase the importance of sustainability reporting. It puts it on the same level as financial reporting and will make it a mandatory part of the annual report. We are quite ahead in these areas. Going forward, we need stability around regulation. We hope the IFRS Foundation will provide this when its new standards are published.</p>
<p>The majority of the €7bn will go into cutting emissions in our aviation arm – we are one of the biggest airlines in the world. We will gradually replace kerosene with sustainable fuel and plan to trial electric aircraft. Also, we started to invest in electric vehicles two years ago. Switching to electric vehicles is a step-by-step process when conventional cars come to end of the line and are replaced, therefore we currently have no needs to write down assets. One challenge is that there are few providers of electric vans – there is a limited capacity of suppliers able to deliver. Another factor is ensuring our suppliers and subcontractors are also interested in delivering sustainability.</p>
<p>We started gathering carbon data early on and have now connected to more than 80 operational systems. Operational systems were never designed for the purpose of external reporting, so we have had to ensure both the data quality and that we have the data in time to feed into our regular reporting. One of the biggest challenges is measuring subcontractor emissions because it involves establishing a data exchange process with our providers. Model-based calculations are not sufficient in the long run. Standardisation has also been a problem since everyone was calculating with different assumptions, but over the years we have achieved a good level of standardisation across our industry.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[As investors increasingly clamour to see the relationship between a company’s financial and sustainability performance, so treasury and finance teams will play an increasing role in integrating sustainability into financial reports.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-09-10-tt-04-fu__aerial-view-people-forming-world-map-249032947__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2021-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Reporting]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Time to act: treasury’s role in integrating financially material ESG data]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>Sustainable reporting has grown over the last decade. Now investors see it as increasingly financially material, and the pressure is on companies to integrate it into their corporate accounting models. It involves the expertise of sustainability teams with the processes and rigour of treasury and finance.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C8AD4610502048704D48DD4FDAD38BCA"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2CE0669537DA66CE718E339CE86F3FCD"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=166F786823C9B63BF3ADA024CBADCCEE"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2989C82683E17437A0A069634E7DD648"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=20D9C5DE09FB6C3EDA19E0632508D788"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Close up of old vintage pocket watch" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B84880355556377D374C7FA08155BBCC" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B84880355556377D374C7FA08155BBCC"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>The pace economies decarbonise is set to pick up in the years ahead. Corporate success will increasingly depend on companies’ ability to articulate to all stakeholders how they are adapting to the new business model coming down the track. It means finance and treasury teams will need to publish corporate accounting models and balance sheets that put financial numbers on their sustainability data and information.</p>
<p>“Companies should prepare for the same legislative and regulatory overhaul in corporate accounting ushered in after the 1930s US stock market crash,” says Leon Saunders Calvert, Head of Research &amp; Portfolio Analytics at London Stock Exchange Group (LSEG). “Back then, reporting via balance sheets and cash flows was challenging. Eighty years on, public companies face another drive in transparency because decarbonising is financially material.”</p>
<p>Of course, sustainable corporate reporting has been growing steadily over the last ten years with some 80% of global companies now reporting on sustainability, according to KPMG. Of this cohort leaders have emerged, already integrating their financial performance with their sustainability performance in a single, annual report. However, it is the pace of this convergence that is about to pick up, as standard setters increasingly eye ESG reporting as financially material, and financial statements no longer giving the full picture. “There are developments towards a more integrated form of reporting,” says Arjan de Draaijer, Global Co-lead, Impact, ESG and Sustainability at KPMG in the Netherlands. “Financial reporting standard setters and sustainability reporting standard setters like GRI (Global Reporting Initiative) and SASB (Sustainability Accounting Standards Board) are increasingly looking at the similarities and connections between financial and sustainable reporting. It all points towards a more integrated perspective on reporting that caters to all stakeholders.”</p>
<p>However, de Draaijer doesn’t believe this means companies will produce one document. “I expect there will be a portfolio of different reports,” he says, predicting a myriad spanning human rights in the supply chain to the financial impact of climate change and, going forward, the impact of biodiversity and inequality on financial statements as well.</p>
<p>According to KPMG, currently only around one quarter of companies at high or medium risk from biodiversity loss currently disclose that risk in their corporate reporting. “This is another element that should be on a treasurer’s mind in the future,” he says. As for the reporting burden, he believes digital publishing and linking reports from corporate websites will make the process easier. “Stakeholders will just be able to search for the information they need.”</p>
<h4 id="outside-in">Outside in</h4>
<p>Another important shift in reporting is also under way. Companies have traditionally approached disclosure and reporting from an inside-out perspective. This typically involves measuring and reporting a firm’s impact on the outside world – like its carbon emissions. Increasingly, companies are using new disclosure requirements (namely the Task Force on Climate-related Financial Disclosures, TCFD) which focus on disclosure through a different, outside in-lens that reports on how climate change will impact the company’s financial performance.</p>
<p>This could entail disclosure on how rising temperatures could impact suppliers in developing nations, or how changing consumer behaviour will impact demand for a core product. “The indicators that are related to this type of reporting are of a different nature,” says de Draaijer. “A carbon footprint is still useful information in terms of detailing the carbon intensity of a product and its vulnerability to a low carbon economy, but this new type of information and data is increasingly appearing,” he says.</p>
<h4 id="investor-pressure">Investor pressure</h4>
<p>Treasury and finance departments need to be able to articulate how sustainability data and numbers are integrated into the company’s business strategy to investors and lender banks. The best way to do this is to make externalities directly financially material and view them as a liability on the balance sheet, urges Saunders Calvert.</p>
<p>Most companies have only just begun. Positively, Saunders Calvert estimates around 41% of the 10,000 companies LSEG covers already report their Scope 1 and Scope 2 carbon emissions associated with energy consumption in their own operations. “There is a demand for this kind of information from investors,” he says. “Investors are telling companies that this is financially material information regarding their cost of capital.”</p>
<p>In contrast however, he says a much smaller proportion of companies have a cost of carbon internally that they manage to; deploy a liability to the balance sheet and seek to offset emissions by, say, paying carbon credits. “Only a small proportion of companies recognise the cost of carbon in the way they manage their financials.”</p>
<p>Nevertheless, he is convinced this is the direction of travel and it matters more that firms have embarked on the journey than their position en route. “If treasury actually have this information on the balance sheet; if they have it as a proxy, or even if they can just show they are on a journey to treating carbon as a cost to the organisation, it will demonstrate to investors they are somewhere on the road to internally quantifying and internalising these externalities,” he says. “Data points around carbon emissions will make their way in time, into actual corporate liabilities. It won’t be a separate statement; it will just sit there as financially material next to other liabilities.”</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Case study</h2>

<p><img alt="Philips logo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/philips-logo-2019.svg?la=en&amp;hash=D05B27C24B090072F3FB0B14665019CF" width="100"/></p>
<p>Dutch health-tech multinational Philips has taken a pioneering lead in sustainability reporting. The company now reports its environmental impact on society at large via a so-called Environmental Profit &amp; Loss (EP&amp;L) account which includes the complete environmental costs associated with its activities and products from cradle to grave. The Philips Environmental Profit &amp; Loss (EP&amp;L) account guides the company’s efforts on all things ecological; it is an economic valuation of the impact that Philips has on the environment, and an environmental footprint of Philips’ complete value chain expressed in monetary terms.</p>
<p>The EP&amp;L account is based on Life-Cycle Assessment (LCA) methodology which are in turn used to steer the company’s EcoDesign efforts and to determine the Green Focal Areas (GFAs) of the Philips product portfolio. The GFAs are product characteristics like energy efficiency, weight and product lifetime that determine the environmental impact of the company’s product portfolio. They form the basis of a steadily growing green solutions portfolio. The EP&amp;L account is a logical next step to extend the scope from individual product value chains to Philips’ complete value chain. It will support the direction of the company’s sustainability strategy by providing insights into the main environmental hotspots from an overall business point of view.</p>
<p>Philips also has a well-established methodology to calculate the number of lives the company positively touches with its products and solutions. It is the firm’s aim to look into valuating these societal benefits in monetary terms as well, including them in future EP&amp;L accounts where possible.</p>
<p>In its 2020 annual report, Philips reported its Green Revenues, generated through products and solutions that offer a significant environmental improvement in one or more Green Focal Areas – Energy efficiency, Packaging, Hazardous substances, Weight, Circularity, and Lifetime reliability that also deliver a contribution to SDG 12. Green Revenues increased to €13.9bn in 2020, or 71% of sales (67.2% in 2019), reaching a record level for Philips and exceeding the 2020 target of 70%.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.philips.com/c-dam/corporate/about-philips/sustainability/downloads/ecovision-methodologies/epl-methodology-2020.pdf" target="_blank">https://www.philips.com/c-dam/corporate/about-philips/sustainability/downloads/ecovision-methodologies/epl-methodology-2020.pdf</a></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h4 id="scope-3">Scope 3</h4>
<p>Disclosing emissions as a liability on the balance sheet becomes even more complicated around Scope 3, a data set ESG reporting leaders are only just starting to get to grips with. Under Scope 3, companies disclose the emissions in their supply chain – the carbon footprint of both the components in their products and of their products once in use.</p>
<p>For example, a coal mining company won’t produce huge emissions in its mining processes, but its product has a profound impact on emissions. In contrast, Tesla’s production processes, says Saunders Calvert, typically score poorly in ESG ratings because manufacturing the electric car is a carbon intensive process. In Scope 3 reporting, this is counterbalanced by a Tesla having minimal downstream emissions. In carbon intensive industries, having a high carbon footprint today isn’t necessarily a bad thing so long as a strategy for decarbonisation is aggressive and credible. Interpreting the data and its financial consequences requires nuance and expertise, he says. “Treasury teams really need to be able to address all sides of the story.”</p>
<p>It will get even more complex with Scope 4 reporting – although this is not a formal category yet. The idea is that when companies report sales of products that have a positive impact on climate or society like, say, insulation, it should carry a benefit on the balance sheet. “Reporting Scope 1 and 2 is mainly about making sure you have the right information from your internal systems around fuel use and energy bills. Scope 3 requires more effort and is quite a struggle,” says de Draaijer.</p>
<h4 id="industry-standards-and-regulation">Industry standards and regulation</h4>
<p>Companies have resources to help them get reporting right. Industry standards like TCFD and SASB articulate what good disclosure looks like and are gaining traction, helping companies disclose and map their data to specific frameworks. But take up is still slow. According to a report from the corporate governance team at FTI Consulting and Sentieo, a financial and corporate research company, fewer than 50 UK public companies currently comprehensively report on climate risks and set targets in line with the TCFD.</p>
<p>Regulation coming down the track will force the process. By 2025, climate risk assessments will be mandatory across the UK, including for listed companies, large private companies, pension schemes, insurance companies and banks. Elsewhere, the EU’s giant taxonomy will land through the course of next year, introducing a classification system of what constitutes sustainable economic activity. Cue the associated EU regulatory drives in support of the taxonomy like growing pressure for mandatory sustainability reporting requirements under the Non-Financial Reporting Directive (NFRD). Under the EU Taxonomy companies will have to articulate what proportion of their revenue is green, says Saunders Calvert. “Revenue is a good proxy for a company’s products or services and is a different set of data points to reporting their carbon emissions,” he says. “Regulation is going to drive clarity around what kind of information is required.”</p>
<h4 id="collaboration">Collaboration</h4>
<p>Of course, gathering data and disclosure won’t only sit with treasury, but much of the responsibility could head treasury’s way. Although many firms have set up reporting systems out of their sustainability departments, as ESG reporting becomes more financially material it is increasingly the focus of CFOs, finance and control departments. “It involves a combination of the subject matter knowledge of the sustainability team with the processes, rigour and risk of treasury and finance,” says de Draaijer, who observes that many of the initial ESG corporate laggards without sustainability departments have fast tracked their sustainable reporting and accounting processes by placing the issue directly with finance teams. “Banks and investors want to know how aligned to the future decarbonised economy a company’s business model is. Are they backing the Netflix of tomorrow – or Blockbuster Video,” concludes Saunders Calvert.</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">The international initiatives pushing convergence of reporting standards</h2>
<p>The European Union is updating the EU Non-financial Reporting Directive.</p>
<p>The World Economic Forum has released its paper on common metrics and consistent reporting for sustainable value creation, defining 21 core metrics.</p>
<p>The five major non-financial reporting organisations (GRI, SASB, IIRC, CDSB and CDP) have published a Statement of Intent, committing to work together towards comprehensive corporate reporting.</p>
<p>The IFRS Foundation’s consultation, still in process, on establishing a global non-financial reporting framework has already received strong support from other organisations, including IOSCO.</p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: KPMG Survey of Sustainability 2020</em></p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Sustainable reporting has grown over the last decade. Now investors see it as increasingly financially material, and the pressure is on companies to integrate it into their corporate accounting models. It involves the expertise of sustainability teams with the processes and rigour of treasury and finance.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/2021-05-06-tt-08-reg__vintage-old-pocket-watch-552011227__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2021-05-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Reporting]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Plastic fantastic: corporate cards]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1C2B7914D47C6409A67989EF765C7686"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B78C6872D925EEF74ADB8751DF4C5DE3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4CEFB50D2BA48270FAD5F8A80CFBFDC7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D7C917225D7D9A4C433229A64F69FD98"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7C952309650C0A40B24AC6047818A6F3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="House of cards" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AF652031F9ECE4E63BF25646A06F6FCA" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AF652031F9ECE4E63BF25646A06F6FCA"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><i>Corporate cards were first introduced in the early 1990s as a means for organisations to manage employee purchases by pre-authorising them for specific vendors and/or product types, restricting purchases based on contract and transaction types, and giving companies the ability to set daily, weekly and monthly limits and controls. Perhaps most importantly for cost-conscious procurement departments, the corporate card solution offered substantially more control than corporate credit cards while lowering transaction costs. Surveys have suggested that transaction costs can be reduced by as much as 90% compared to traditional accounts payable processes.</i></p>
<p>While specific data on corporate card usage in Asia is not readily available, market participants claim that their use is growing, primarily as a way of interacting more efficiently with large quantities of low-spend suppliers for travel, entertainment, supplies and other miscellaneous, relatively small-ticket items. Government and other public entities are also using the cards as a means of managing expenses. Visa estimates the value of potential ‘cardable’ payments in the Asia Pacific region at $12 trillion, with China accounting for $7 trillion of that figure and India a further $1.1 trillion.</p>
<p>According to the company, in the near-term, mature markets such as Australia also represent a significant opportunity for growth, although it also acknowledges that moving payments to cards will require banks and card issuers to develop new, compelling propositions that lead to suppliers preferring card payments over other payment methods.</p>
<h3 id="diverse-backdrop">Diverse backdrop</h3>
<p>Since card providers have to comply with local regulations in each market, corporate card solutions vary from country to country – many countries do not permit cross-border issuance of cards, for instance. So which corporates are actually using cards today – and whereabouts in the Asia Pacific region?</p>
<p>Citi’s initial set of clients in every geography where it launched a business were subsidiaries of global companies headquartered in North America or EMEA, who were looking for cards that could be used by their growing workforce in Asia. However, as the market matured over the last decade, it has seen increased use of card solutions by local companies as well as growing interest from the public sector, explains Deven Somaya, Director, Regional Wholesale Cards Head Asia Pacific at Citi. “In terms of market maturity, Australia is probably the most developed market in the region and both federal and state governments are heavy users of corporate cards. Other mature markets are New Zealand, Singapore and Hong Kong.”</p>
<p>He refers to three key factors that encourage subsidiaries of multinational companies to use corporate cards, the first of which is having visibility into the programme in terms of measurement and control, enabling them to manage their costs and expenses more effectively.</p>
<p>Secondly, increased control of where the company’s money is spent. If someone is using petty cash to make payments, those payments can be made to anyone, whereas the card product digitises the transaction and this process enables systemic controls such as merchant blocks and transaction limits to be put in place. Post factor reporting provides a further layer of visibility and the control aspect of self-auditing.</p>
<p>Thirdly, because the transaction is digitised, it can be passed on by the bank to the client in an electronic format which feeds into various systems and saves a lot of manual entry of data, allowing expense management systems to capture data from the individual and enter an ERP system with additional pieces of information attached.</p>
<p>“Various research reports refer to the reduced costs of processing transactions made with corporate cards,” says Somaya, adding that multinational companies are increasingly globalising their functions, for example managing procurement globally rather than at regional or even national level. “We are seeing a growing number of shared service centres emerging across Asia which are taking a proactive role in managing indirect spend, whether that is on travel or procurement. Local companies are following suit – while the majority of their expenditure is obviously within the region, they are seeing benefits to using the shared services model.”</p>
<p>In the public sector, he describes a ‘bandwagon’ effect where administrations in South-East Asia are constantly looking at what their neighbours are doing in an attempt to adopt best practice. From a public sentiment perspective, providing increased transparency to the tax payer on how their money is spent is appealing to administrations that have made a commitment to reducing corruption.</p>
<h3 id="growth-markets">Growth markets</h3>
<p>According to Somaya, “clients are typically looking for a local solution in each market, but the ability to access consistent reporting and online tools and centralise data remains consistent across all the markets where we provide card services.”</p>
<p>When assessing markets with growth potential, Somaya mentions three countries in particular. “India has experienced considerable growth in corporate card usage, initially for travel but increasingly for procurement also. China is an untapped market in terms of the number of multinational and local companies who could potentially use corporate cards, while Indonesia is another country with a growing number of businesses and rapid economic expansion.”</p>
<p>Beyond those countries, there are areas where Citi is seeing a centralisation of specific industries – for instance, Thailand is a major hub for online travel agencies, which inevitably generates a considerable volume of card payments. “Companies across Asia are committed to improving the efficiency of their payment solutions and high volume; low value transactions are ideally suited to corporate cards,” Somaya concludes.</p>
<p>“In the past, travel management and procurement tended to be managed by different parts of the organisation, but we are seeing increasing consolidation of these functions internally. There is obvious value in using a single provider for all payment services in terms of being able to negotiate more favourable rates.”</p>
<h3 id="a-corporate-perspective">A corporate perspective</h3>
<p>The majority of AirPlus International’s clients are subsidiaries of multinational companies whose head offices are located in Europe or the US, although it is also targeting local customers, particularly in mainland China where it works with global Chinese brands. A number of public sector departments in mainland China also use its services. “In addition to Hong Kong and mainland China, our products are available in Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Philippines, Korea, Japan, Australia, Singapore and India,” says Michiel Verhaagen, Executive Vice President Sales, AirPlus International. “The growth of economies across Asia Pacific means there is considerable scope for future growth in commercial card services,” he believes.</p>
<p>That said, he accepts that many local companies do not fully appreciate the benefits of a commercial cards programme yet. Nevertheless, he is confident that educational initiatives implemented by the various global travel associations is increasing awareness among businesses in the region. “These initiatives have helped to inform these businesses about the benefits of efficient payment and reconciliation process in business travel expenses management and the tools available, including commercial cards. Multinational companies tend to have expense management systems in place, but many local companies have yet to implement similar systems,” he says.</p>
<h3 id="who-is-using-cards">Who is using cards?</h3>
<p>All kinds of companies sign up for corporate card programmes, from big business to small business and across a range of sectors including professional services, mining and resources and manufacturing – in fact, any company that wants to better understand and manage its expenses stands to benefit from having a corporate card programme. That is the view of Geoff Begg, Vice President, Global Corporate Card, American Express Japan and Asia Pacific, who says multinationals are looking for a card programme which enables them to manage expenses locally, regionally and globally.</p>
<p>“There is strong demand in all countries across the region, although India and China in particular are growing rapidly with the formation and growth of new companies. Some of the larger, more established countries are expanding from traditional travel and entertainment-type corporate cards to commercial cards,” notes Begg. He adds that corporate cards are used for all types of travel and entertainment spend from the traditional airline, hotel and restaurant expenses to general retail spend, utilities and even government and insurance spend.</p>


<blockquote>Companies across Asia are committed to improving the efficiency of their payment solutions and high volume; low value transactions are ideally suited to corporate cards.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Deven Somaya, Director, Regional Wholesale Cards Head Asia Pacific, Citi</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>“Companies are moving away from per diem payments to employees to corporate cards for greater visibility and control. There is huge growth potential for corporate cards in Asia Pacific as the migration continues away from costly paper based invoicing to fast, efficient electronic payments on corporate cards.”</p>
<p>Asian companies with heads of finance or procurement who have worked in North America, Europe or Australia seek out corporate cards as they see them as a simple and proven way to improve bottom line results, says Marj Demmer, General Manager of Cards and Payments at ANZ. “Clients are looking for cards that can be used throughout the world with high rates of acceptance and low or no surcharges. International acceptance is important for business travel, but also when procuring from international suppliers. The more the card can be used, the bigger the working capital, visibility and efficiency gains for the client.”</p>
<p>While observing that demand in India is growing rapidly as companies seek greater oversight and control of business expenses, he also acknowledges that card acceptance rates hold back some mature markets such as Japan, where ‘cash is king’. “Leading corporate card providers work with travel management companies to bill travel bookings on ‘virtual cards’, providing enhanced data on staff travel (destinations, travel class, fare type). In mature markets, we are seeing more business-to-business payments shifting from cheque or bank transfers to card.”</p>
<p>In the more developed markets, Demmer expects to see a major shift towards more business-to-business and international payments being made by card. “Treasurers and CFOs will lead this push as they seek to improve the working capital position of their businesses and leverage strategic supplier relationships.”</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Ralph Kaiser, President and CEO UATP says that in China, large international corporations may have some corporate cards but the adoption rate is still low, although use of a corporate card for air travel is increasing. “There is limited usage in emerging markets (which for the purposes of this article include Vietnam, Malaysia, Philippines, Thailand and Indonesia). Corporations contract directly with the vendor for services, or in some instances deal solely with the treasury management centre which must carry the cash float,” says Kaiser.</p>
<p>Clients in developed markets such as Singapore and Hong Kong use international corporate cards that are widely accepted, while in the case of Japan or perhaps Korea, they may be using a domestic product that has limited usage overseas, he adds. “There is an upside in some markets, mainly China and India where domestic corporations are large and successful and are in need of a corporate card solution. In emerging markets, there might be some need but awareness is an issue. Furthermore, the undeveloped infrastructure and high risk of dealing in these markets makes it daunting for networks to issue corporate cards. It has been seen that rates would need to be set at high levels, making international corporate cards uncompetitive compared with direct invoicing or even local bank card solutions.”</p>
<p>According to Kaiser, in China and emerging markets, corporate cards are used almost exclusively with some component of travel. “Infrastructure limitations are part of the issue; the other is the demand to use it for procurement. However, we believe there is large growth potential for corporate cards in major markets like India and China in the short term. The opportunity for growth in emerging markets is also significant, albeit on more of a mid to long range outlook. Growth will be focused on the travel segment – it remains to be seen whether corporate cards can build a product for other segments in Asia, or if purchasing cards may become a factor in the future.”</p>
<h3 id="a-card-for-all-sectors">A card for all sectors</h3>
<p>Kees Kwakernaak, Head of Commercial Cards Asia Pacific, Bank of America Merrill Lynch describes commercial cards as a largely industry-agnostic business. “Simply put, the benefits of travel and entertainment and procurement cards are applicable to all our customers, across all industries. For a number of years we have seen the most robust demand from multinational clients but more recently, local corporates have shown a growing interest in adopting card based solutions. Whilst there are differences across the various markets, the requirement for efficiency, transparency and streamlined processes is universal, which should serve as a sustainable incubator for card adoption in the medium term.”</p>


<blockquote>The growth of economies across Asia Pacific means there is considerable scope for future growth in commercial card services.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Michiel Verhaagen, Executive Vice President Sales, AirPlus International</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Demand drivers are fairly consistent, as clients are unilaterally looking at streamlining their procure-to-pay processes to save on cost and to extend payment terms, he continues. “We see strong uptake in traditional travel and entertainment cards where employees are using their commercial cards to book travel, pay for taxis and general on-the-road expenses. Increasingly, we are also seeing a defined trend whereby clients are using cards in conjunction with central travel accounts. This product is an efficient way for clients to pay for their employees’ travel.”</p>
<p>The potential for ongoing growth in the Asian corporate card market is undeniable, according to Kwakernaak. “Banks in this space have seen a long period of double digit growth in commercial card spend in this region and in our view this will continue for many more years to come. The migration away from alternative payments options (including paper based payments) will continue.”</p>
<p>An obvious growth area for corporate cards is in their use as a payment mechanism for line-of-business or supply chain expenses. The 2014 First Data report ‘Digitalising B2B Payments to Streamline Supply Chains in Asia’ refers to increased use of commercial cards in Singapore for strategic procurement, with increased control and reporting options driving adoption. The firm is seeing increasing demand towards strategic procurement programmes for accounts payable automation and receivable financing for large distribution supply chains. The extent to which clients look for national or regional corporate cards rather than cards that can be used anywhere in the world depends on the business needs for which the programme is rolled out, explains Naveen Gupta, Regional Director Consumer &amp; Commercial Payments, First Data Asia Pacific.</p>


<blockquote>International acceptance is important for business travel, but also when procuring from international suppliers. The more the card can be used, the bigger the working capital, visibility and efficiency gains for the client.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Marj Demmer, General Manager of Cards and Payments, ANZ</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>“For employee travel and entertainment expenses, corporates expect the card could be used anywhere in the world but with suitable controls. However, for large procurement programmes or receivable financing, it is expected that usage of cards has a limited ecosystem to avoid unwanted fraud and keep costs below an acceptable threshold.”</p>
<p>He describes corporate cards as an excellent instrument for short-term financing and payment execution. “We expect demand in established markets such as Australia and New Zealand to continue to increase and we are also seeing increasing demand for corporate card solutions in emerging markets such as India and China. We project growth for these markets to reach up to 30-40% in the next 12 months.”</p>
<p>First Data also believes that the potential ability for commercial cards to transform business-to-business commercial transactions from manual, paper based transactions to more efficient automated processes is an opportunity to boost business productivity, reduce costs and strengthen commercial partnerships across Asia’s supply chain.</p>
<p>Despite all the advantages of automated electronic payments, too few companies are utilising digital payment solutions, Gupta concludes. “The reason for the slow uptake of electronic payments is difficult to pinpoint, although we believe that it is partly attributable to the perceived complexity of migrating so many supplier relationships from paper to electronic systems.” But as more and more leading corporate treasuries embrace corporate cards, hopefully the myths around the complexity of such programmes can be dispelled.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regulation-and-standards/reporting/house-of-cards-is8188076-1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Reporting]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Reporting necessities]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Historically, there has been something of a culture in which ‘treasury does, and then finance reports’. It was something of a macho attitude – a little freewheeling without being irresponsible – of taking, balancing and managing risks that the rest of the organisation barely grasped.</p>
<p>But of course that was in the past, before the succession of corporate and financial industry scandals in the 1990s and early years of the 21<sup>st</sup> century – culminating in the global financial crisis. Today, all corporate and financial dealings are governed by a raft of legal and regulatory provisions, largely led by the US and the EU – and many more are coming down the line.</p>
<p>The universal impetus is towards the prevention of further scandals or disasters by tighter regulation and oversight, in the process protecting consumers and investors. There is political pressure in most countries to try to ensure financial crises are avoided in the future. The Dodd–Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act of 2010 is the exemplar legislation in the move towards reform of the global financial system.</p>
<p>As in so many financial matters, US law and practice tends to become global at least in influence. In Europe, the European Market Infrastructure Regulation (EMIR) is just over a year in force and is similarly aimed at mitigating risk across financial services and markets. The impact of all of this on corporate treasury operations is increasing both in terms of the range of regulations and restrictions of which treasurers must be aware and in the reporting obligations which result.</p>
<h3 id="the-devil-is-in-the-detail">The devil is in the detail</h3>
<p>A corporate treasury operation that masterminded the largest ever deal by a non-US entity in the US private placement market is headed by Dympna Donnelly, Vice President of SAP US-Ireland Financial Services, the arm of the SAP Group treasury responsible for all of the company’s US dollar financing. Last year’s $1.4 billion placement earned that record, with the funds directed principally towards SAP’s acquisition of Ariba. “That was our third successful foray into that private market in recent years, raising a total of $2.65 billion so far,” explains Donnelly.</p>
<p>The SAP Group has over 65,000 employees worldwide but the treasury team consists of just 20 people. “In terms of reporting obligations, our concern is really what is coming directly at us, such as EMIR,” Donnelly says. “Although there are elements of Dodd-Frank that affect us, they are not difficult and are looked after by our treasury colleagues in the US.</p>
<p>“On the other hand, the Foreign Account Tax Compliance Act (FATCA) will have direct implications for us and we are not yet clear about what we will have to do. With FATCA, there will be direct bilateral agreements with the US in all major financial markets, effectively Germany, UK and Ireland for SAP. The national revenue authorities have agreed to co-operate with the IRS – it is in everyone’s interest to avoid any potential mess – but the arrangements will not be identical in all of those agreements.”</p>
<p>That is a constant difficulty with new regulation, Donnelly says. “You know about it well in advance and can see the broad overall plan, but then you do not know enough about the detail of the implementation required. It happened with EMIR, for example, which covers internal foreign exchange (FX), although I don’t think that is related to what it was designed to achieve. Yet the implementation covers internal hedges within our group, which is not in financial services and the movement of funds within the group is entirely for trade-related purposes. That’s the kind of issue that arises when measures are made very broad and designed to catch all activity that might be in breach.”</p>
<p>She adds that trying to design and test reporting systems in advance can be a problem. “You have to wait for the detail of required formats before you can make the system changes and report templates, but the actual implementation time tends to be telescoped. What’s more, the sheer volume of work and time that has to go into extracting the relevant information and adapting the systems in big diverse groups is generally underestimated.”</p>
<h3 id="developing-a-system-response">Developing a system response</h3>
<p>“We look after both the treasury operations and all the relevant reporting,” says Sean Grace, Group Treasurer at Securitas, a world leader in security services and systems. Listed and headquartered in Stockholm, it employs over 300,000 people in 52 countries. The group treasury centre, based in Dublin’s International Financial Services Centre (IFSC), is responsible for all of the funding and treasury activities of Securitas globally.</p>
<p>Grace explains: “Everyone in any role related to finance is highly aware of the growing importance of reporting requirements and in a way it’s quite circular – Boards and top management want to be assured that the organisation is doing everything it should. No one wants to be caught at some stage having to say ‘We didn’t know this was happening.’</p>
<p>“Since Lehmans, the buzzword is ‘derivatives’ and the authorities on both sides of the Atlantic are very wary. But they are then casting their nets very wide indeed, perhaps because they really have not figured out where the real risks are or where the next risk is coming from,” he adds.</p>
<p>That wide-cast net is now bringing in the corporates, says Grace. “Traditionally, we only had to worry about accounting standards and our Boards, now we’re being dragged into the general mess. It’s true that global enterprises are often managing larger sums of money than some banks, but we are doing it to manage and minimise risk, not to make profits per se. Banks have a longstanding – and now growing – set of compliance obligations and have been set up to deal with that. Corporate treasury has not, so now we have to set up special systems.</p>
<p>“In our own case, we rely on smart treasury management and reporting systems, and we think we have good skill sets in both treasury and systems.”</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“We developed very sophisticated internal management reporting systems, precisely because our rapid growth posed massive challenges in retaining oversight and control.”</p>
<p><cite>Michal Kawski, Head of Treasury, Gazprom Marketing &amp; Trading Ltd</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Grace is a firm believer that systems should reflect the organisation’s business rules rather than be driven by the software design. “The ideal system is one you design yourself, choosing what you want to do and what you want to get out at any time. You need to know in advance of every deal what data is required and where it will end up in your reporting at a later stage. Then you are not going to be surprised, and you can pull together whatever report is needed. You certainly want to avoid rigid systems that cannot easily adapt to fit changing circumstances and reporting is definitely in that category these days. Actually, in some ways a positive result from this new regulatory climate is that it forces you to think everything through in a fresh way in the light of both the compliance and the reporting on it.”</p>
<p>The Russian oil and gas giant Gazprom has made a world impact in recent years. Trading in billions, its subsidiary Gazprom Marketing &amp; Trading (GM&amp;T) is a UK registered company with a unique suite of products from gas and electricity marketing, trading and supply, to liquid natural gas (LNG), liquefied petroleum gas (LPG), oil, carbon and FX deals and a retail business, trading as Gazprom Energy. GM&amp;T treasury and commodity broking operations are headquartered in London, with seven other offices globally. Head of Treasury is Michal Kawski, who is happy to acknowledge that today’s reporting obligations are from his organisations’ point of view relatively modest additions. “We are a relatively young organisation but have been growing rapidly in scale and range of business, and have developed the systems to manage all of that. We started in 1999 with two people in a London office, really got going in 2004 and now have over 1,000 staff.”</p>
<p>The Gazprom management systems were developed to report on a daily transactional basis, not strictly treasury. But a key point is that the company has robust centralised information systems for all of its transactions and activities across the full range of accounting and other compliance requirements, internationally, in specific jurisdictions and internally. “We developed very sophisticated internal management reporting systems, precisely because our rapid growth posed massive challenges in retaining oversight and control,” Kawski says. “We placed a strong emphasis on visibility and very strict control of corporate risk management from the beginning. That is now a great strength when new reporting obligations are placed on treasury, as they are also growing in other financial areas.”</p>
<p>Another great need from a treasury perspective, according to Kawski, even apart from EMIR and Dodd-Frank and other such specific requirements, is to monitor the market and be prepared to act and react quickly from a liquidity perspective. “The necessity to keep up with increased reporting actually has a positive impact. The more centralised but also fluid and flexible the systems are the better. Our systems were designed and built on an integrated model, and so the burden on us is significant but probably less than in many organisations with legacy systems.”</p>
<h3 id="the-nuts-and-bolts">The nuts and bolts</h3>
<p>“Has regulation become an increased burden? Absolutely,” says Neil Fleming, Director of Treasury Solutions in Capita Asset Services, one of the largest independent treasury service providers in Europe, administering over £300 billion of client assets. “Bear in mind we have over 250 clients globally, so we have to manage all of their relevant reporting obligations.” Capita has over 100 staff providing a comprehensive suite of treasury solutions such as deposit and FX trading, intragroup loans, cash pools, netting plus cash advisory, counterparty analysis, valuation and accounting services.</p>
<p>“We are very conscious that a number of countries such as Australia, Japan and Switzerland are planning new reporting regulations that will affect our clients. They will each be different and country-specific, however much they have in common. FATCA is coming in, Foreign Bank and Financial Accounts (FBAR) is another US regulation and there is also the whole money market funds (MMFs) valuation issue, which may impact on Europe. Some have been delayed or are still being finalised, like EMIR, and International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) 13 is already with us. The key point is that there is a growing volume and range of regulation in place and on the way, all of it inter-related in many respects and with knock-on effects on what treasury and other financial operations have to do to comply and report.”</p>
<p>Understanding the totality of the risk is at the core, Fleming says, both direct counterparty and any underlying risk. “In the EU everything is heading in broadly the same direction. The MMF valuation issues have not been decided in an EU context yet but the European Commission (EC) proposals are diverging from the Federal Reserve’s. From a reporting point of view, they will all in a sense be pulling from the one general database. So the context from our point of view moves on to the required fields and the construction of the reports. You can only report where you have the information and EMIR requires something in the realm of 80 fields – but your existing treasury system may not have all of them.</p>
<p>“Banks have traditionally built data warehouses to cope with their various reporting requirements, but by and large corporates have not yet gone down that route,” Fleming says, returning to Grace’s point. “We are seeing a lot more smart business intelligence software coming in on top of treasury platforms. Yet a recent survey showed that over half of corporate treasury operations were still using spreadsheets to manage their cash. The smart tools available today are a lot more flexible and user-friendly, and they will be essential not just for external reporting but to keep the Boards satisfied.”</p>
<h3 id="for-the-systems-preservation">For the system’s preservation</h3>
<p>There is a universal urge today towards ensuring financial stability, which is in turn putting increased regulatory and other pressures on ensuring liquidity. In many practical respects, liquidity is more important than capital in ensuring stability. That is the start point for all reporting requirements and in turn for new ways of managing treasury, says Leonard Orlando, Finance and Enterprise Performance Manager at Accenture UK. “Companies need to put in place more sophisticated tools and processes, as well as structured analytics, to accurately predict cash flows in order to understand their liquidity risk more thoroughly. In the future, we will be looking at risk aggregation, effectively putting all of the risk profiles together in a consolidated view.</p>
<p>“The challenging regulatory environment is making the measurement and management of risk more complex. Traditionally, treasury has not been fully integrated with other functions in the business. But now we need to see across treasury, finance and risk management and the correlation of different risks. The question is whether we have the information to aggregate and analyse the full spectrum of risk?”</p>
<p>Although the process and system challenges are complex, there is enormous potential value, Orlando believes, in that aggregated risk picture from the pooled information – not least in preparedness for the future. “I also think that treasury will become increasingly important in corporate strategic decision-making, because it will be the only place with deep insight into the future cash and liquidity position.”</p>
<p>In the ordinary course of daily business treasurers are not really concerned about reporting for external requirements, says John Byrne, Managing Director of treasury management system (TMS) vendor, Salmon Software. “You can simplify treasury to buying and selling money, in more than 1,000 different ways. As a treasurer, I want to know exactly where all my money is right now, as well as currency, jurisdiction, counterparty and all of the other risk and exposure levels across perhaps hundreds of bank accounts in a large multinational. That is the daily task: to see the overall corporate position, clearly and accurately. I will then have the data to furnish accounting with what is needed for regulatory reporting, but it is not my primary concern. I will also be able to show that I am complying with the set corporate policies across all of the areas.”</p>
<p>Treasurers are aware of the regulatory parameters they face and the management systems they use have the rules built in with automatic alerts if any position gets out of line. “On a day-to-day basis, complying with their own corporate policies may well be a stronger imperative. On the simple and often quoted basis that ‘treasurers look forward and accountants look back’, the actual mandatory reporting tasks fall to the accounting function. The onus of compliance, of course, remains with treasury. Once the information is in the systems, reporting is – or should be – relatively straightforward and capable of being automated to a high degree.”</p>
<p>That is the theory, Byrne acknowledges. In practice the rise of new reporting requirements continues to uncover elements that were not provided for in the past, or that are not immediately compatible with existing systems. But he echoes the view that the solutions to these challenges will come in pooled, common data and systems that provide an aggregated view across treasury, accounting and risk management. “Once all of the information is there, you can use it for advanced ‘what if?’ modelling just as readily as a mandatory monthly report.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2013-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Reporting]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
