<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[No to paper, yes to trade]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=BE4CA4A5526E76E5A7BC0B78DA21C0BF]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>Trade growth is all about making strong connections, and yet the paper-trail that follows cross-border commerce stubbornly remains the weakest link. We explore how digitalisation can improve connectivity, paving the way for better business and stronger growth.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4B1AD6FEC2502647041BD3C267F94019"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=581E0D6C951AE5E3F991F3FD79356C85"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CFDF1C3ACD68A790A48DD5112292F1AC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8CB4A8E3F424EFE7F34BB1152FAD88A2"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0550C137AA522A65282E0BEE9CA89DF4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Cobbled path in Italy with sun shining" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BE4CA4A5526E76E5A7BC0B78DA21C0BF" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-05-06-tt-05__t_stretch-appian-way-one-most-important-1607575315__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BE4CA4A5526E76E5A7BC0B78DA21C0BF"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Global trade can be challenging with all the tariff wars, protectionist policies and regulatory uncertainty to navigate. But these are transient worries; for most businesses, there is a greater menace that remains largely unchallenged, accepted almost, and that is the fact that paper still rules supreme.</p>
<p>Of course, it’s no great mystery why trade documentation represents around 20% of the cost of moving goods; it’s grossly inefficient. But as Gert Sylvest, Co-founder, Tradeshift, and GM Tradeshift Frontiers, notes, “although digitalisation within large enterprises is actually at a pretty advanced stage, globally just 8% of trade transactions are digital”. If the means of dramatic improvement is available, why does this state of inefficiency persist?</p>
<p>For many, the missing piece in the puzzle is digitalisation between business partners across the broader supply chain ecosystem. As Sylvest explains, “you can have the greatest level of digitalisation internally, but if the partners you are dealing with – banks, suppliers, buyers, logistics handlers – are not digital, then the whole process reverts to the lowest common denominator.”</p>
<p>With International Chamber of Commerce (ICC) suggesting an annual count of around four billion sheets of paper required to represent current levels of ‘lowest-common-denominator’ activity, it’s no wonder technologists are frustrated. Martin McCann, CEO and Founder of Trade Ledger, even sees current global trade finance practice as “pre-industrial”.</p>
<p>The reason why digitalisation across supply chain ecosystems has yet to take off is clear to Daniel Cotti, MD, Centre of Excellence Banking &amp; Trade at the Marco Polo Network. Where multiple parties involved in international trade are located in different jurisdictions, process harmonisation is often absent.</p>
<h4 id="reinvent-not-fix">Re-invent, not fix</h4>
<p>But setting out to ‘fix’ trade is always going to end in failure, warns McCann. “People have been trying to do this since the 1990s. When you’ve got different laws in different jurisdictions, and different industries with different needs and procedures, where do you even start trying to standardise trade finance documentation?”</p>
<p>Research by BCG last year explored the transit of trade information through paper documents. It found that in typical international trade documentation “a single transaction often requires the interaction of more than 20 entities, and involves between ten and 20 paper documents and 5,000 data field exchanges”. And yet it says only one to two per cent of the available fields are commonly used.</p>
<p>Bodies such as the World Trade Organisation and the World Customs Organisation, charged with driving standardisation initiatives in this space, have “lacked the appetite for transformative change”, says Dai Bedford, EY NextWave Global Trade Leader. Noting a predisposition in some quarters for physical documentation, he says that in some emerging markets, for example, “documentation and administrative processes around customs and port authorities creates jobs”.</p>
<p>It’s a difficult approach to challenge. Nonetheless, change is in the air. With China central to global trade, Bedford says it has invested massively in digitising its whole trade ecosystem. It has been adopting innovations, such as blockchain, to create smart documents, has brought about the legal enablement of digital signatures and is using new technologies to create ‘smart’ ports and shipping.</p>
<p>The knock-on effect in neighbouring trade-focused jurisdictions, especially Singapore, is significant. Challenged by Chinese port efficiency, Singapore has a roadmap that is looking to accelerate development in ASEAN. Singapore Customs has already launched its Networked Trade Platform, described as a ‘one-stop trade and logistics ecosystem’, with reports coming through already of talks to connect this with Hong Kong’s own eTradeConnect blockchain-based platform.</p>
<p>With many stakeholders involved, connecting different ecosystems could allow trade credit services to be consumed at the point of the transaction. “Then we’ll see de-aggregation of the vertically integrated supply chain for trade finance,” states McCann. His ‘ideal’ will necessarily see trade finance providers stop producing and distributing traditional products, and start thinking in terms of new customer propositions and experiences. “The product wrapping and fulfilment factories can just melt into the background; it’s not something customers need to interact with.”</p>
<p>But bringing disparate parties together remains a challenge, comments Marie-Laure Gastellu, Deputy Head of Trade Services, Societe Generale. The possibility of a fully paperless trade value chain within the next five years, to her, seems unrealistic. “There have been commendable initiatives designed to encourage standardisation – the ICC, and the Bankers Association for Finance and Trade, are some notable examples – but we have a long way to go,” she believes.</p>
<p>“Our industry involves many stakeholders who share few common standards, meaning paper is often unavoidable. Between the placing of an order, and that order’s delivery, manufacturers, shipping companies, port authorities and banks must reconcile the information they share in their own standards, sometimes varying from country to country. Despite its limitations, paper continues to help with this.”</p>
<p>The ambition to have paper-free trade can already be met with today’s – and even yesterday’s – technology, says Gastellu, but the problem of ‘admissibility’ refuses to go away. “We could just stop printing the required forms and share them digitally, something for which AI and blockchain are not even necessary, but the lack of shared admissibility that rules within our industry makes this impossible.”</p>
<h4 id="interoperability">Interoperability</h4>
<p>The answer for McCann is not to try to patch-up trade but to focus instead on interoperability. Creating a trusted digital data-sharing environment will, he believes, make individual processes more efficient and inexpensive.</p>
<p>Bedford agrees, adding that collaboration between governments and agencies which are prepared to change the law to move beyond simple digitisation of documentation (using tools such as character recognition software) towards dispensing with documentation altogether, will enable the exchange of data between different trade ecosystems. We are, he notes, “already seeing pockets of progress”.</p>
<p>Indeed, in the UK, digitalisation of trade ecosystems – driven in part by Brexit as the country seeks to open up trade with new partners, including China – has seen improvements in data sharing, with subsequent transparency and trust making efficiency improvements, for example, in shipping insurance. Here, as part of the Insurwave platform, blockchain combined with IoT data gives parties access to real-time information. This allows shippers to track assets and share data with brokers and insurers, enabling dynamic premiums so vessels in transit are never over- or under-insured, with commensurate cost efficiencies. On the finance side, for McCann, although open account and structured trade are seeing some interesting developments, he believes the industry shouldn’t be thinking in terms of an evolution of documentary trade, “rather we should be thinking in terms of revolution”. And this, he says, is all about data accessibility – confirming interoperability as the essential step forward.</p>
<h4 id="network-of-networks">Network of networks</h4>
<p>One solution that can aid progress is the API. At the behest of legislation (largely Europe’s PSD2), banks have been moving towards API-based data-driven infrastructures and the notion of open banking. This is starting to significantly disrupt traditional models of documentary trade, providing alternatives which can begin to de-aggregate the network origination and customer experience at the front-end, from the product and fulfilment elements of the back office.</p>
<p>Visa’s acquisition in January 2020 of Plaid, a technology that allows consumers to share their financial information with apps and services, is a play to begin controlling the evolution of the ecosystems around the customer experience network. It’s an important battle ground and connectivity between FIs and developers is becoming increasingly essential as consumers seek enablement to use fintech applications. Their appetite is irrefutable: according to EY, 75% of the world’s internet-enabled consumers used a fintech application to initiate money movement in 2019, versus 18% in 2015.</p>
<p>Why does this matter? Where consumers go, corporates will follow. Creating a ‘network of networks’ using APIs and augmented by robotic process automation, AI/machine-learning and, for security, blockchain, would allow data to be acquired, analysed and transformed into a common format for all permissioned participants to consume. This network could then be exposed to any new types of workflow that trade participants require, across any digital channel. And then, as Cotti says, “by connecting a critical mass of parties in the trade ecosystem, it makes digitalisation of trade finance a real possibility”.</p>
<h4 id="imagine-the-future">Imagine the future</h4>
<p>Of course, technology is only ever the enabler. “The real disruption is in the demand,” notes McCann. Indeed, within many sectors, as new generations join the workforce, so pressure to replicate their consumer-level experience in their professional lives increases. Millennials, it seems, “just don’t have the same level of tolerance for the inconveniences and challenges in trade services that previous generations do,” he notes.</p>
<p>However, he feels that one of the biggest challenges for a full trade revolution is change management. The tier one banks, which have cornered the MNC market, have seen Basel III capital requirements erode their interest in this space for anything other than key clients. With fintechs typically serving the lower end of the market, the global trade finance gap, which is currently estimated by Asian Development Bank to be around US$1.5trn, is now largely a mid-market issue.</p>
<p>This gap is fast becoming an opportunity for co-operation or disintermediation. On the latter, Big Tech players such as Amazon, Google, Apple, Alibaba and Tencent are moving to control the ‘network of networks’, enabling service origination at scale. “In the next few years we are going to see some very big plays in this area,” predicts McCann. “We’re starting to see disintermediation happen already.”</p>
<p>Indeed, Bedford notes that e-commerce platforms are already providing credit to its small business partners on their platforms “because they have the data” to make correct credit risk assessments. PayPal is offering products like debit cards, cheque deposits and small business loans. In Asia, challenger banks are rapidly gaining ground, with WeBank, MYbank, and Kakao Bank all backed by Big Tech (Tencent, Alibaba, and Kakao respectively). These Big Tech players have the money and, crucially, they have the data.</p>
<p>As for the MNCs, if holding data is vital in this new digital world, at the large corporate end of the spectrum, Bedford says the major banks should still be in a prime position, having a view over entire networks of trade that they are financing. But change is coming here too.</p>
<p>With more stringent Basel IV capital requirements applying from January 2022, bank money could become even more expensive for trade-based products. No wonder then that banks are reportedly looking to sell down trade assets to non-bank investors – institutional investors, fund managers and even wealth managers – to try to plug the financing gap. Banks may retain the corporate data and, critically, trade compliance elements but, he warns, “it’s not going to be easy for them”, as other players really are sensing opportunity.</p>
<p>Driven by millennial demand for a consumer-like experience, fintechs are driving connectivity and data sharing, enabling non-banks to take on trade finance as an asset class through trade platforms. And now it seems more large corporates are looking to self-finance trade, either in-house or through these non-bank investors.</p>
<p>Technology is increasingly making corporate access to their own trade transactional data possible, enabling them to make informed funding decisions on their own trade relationships. What’s more, the emergence of Reg Tech platforms is enabling corporates to manage compliance issues around self-funding (becoming a regulated entity in this respect would be a major concern otherwise).</p>
<p>Banks appear to be under huge pressure from a model that, as Bedford argues, “could completely disintermediate them”. However, whilst many corporates do own all the data they need on their total-cost-of-trade, they can’t necessarily collect it, let alone analyse where the opportunities for self-financing lie. It’s an interesting thought to which McCann adds that MNCs, as currently the least well-served by digital trade services, will be the slowest movers, and thus the last to abandon the old-school documentary trade model.</p>
<h4 id="treasury-challenge">Treasury challenge</h4>
<p>The need now is for forward-looking corporate treasurers who want to be “innovative value-drivers”, says Bedford. “They are going to have to start looking at a more complex view of how they finance,” he says. “It may be that it will be cheaper to issue a corporate bond and have a revolver to finance a supply chain, and make money off that, than it is to deal with a bank.”</p>
<p>Pulling together corporate data from treasury and the rest of the business, and then getting it into a usable state to make such decisions, remains a struggle for the MNC, for now. The notion of a virtual trade function, taking structured and unstructured data into a cloud-based platform, requires investment that as yet might prove elusive for treasury. But as digital solutions are incorporated into the flows of information in open account trade, and the gap in the low to middle markets is increasingly serviced, the idea of digitalisation will begin to feed through to the upper end of the market.</p>
<p>Self-financing will gain ground as more companies seek to better understand the flexibility and security of their supply chains. Access to granular data on fees around finance, insurance, taxation, shipping and so on – and a deeper understanding of production and inventory management – should begin to alert senior management, the board and other stakeholders, to the benefits of greater preparedness and proactivity in meeting the challenges of a rapidly changing business environment.</p>
<h4 id="end-of-the-trail?">End of the trail?</h4>
<p>As large swathes of the lower end of the market start to move towards next-generation solutions, a tipping point will be reached, McCann believes. “All the tools and data are there; what’s been missing so far is the imagination and ambition on the part of the large service providers.”</p>
<p>Quite naturally, caution is encouraged by Gastellu who says reducing the use of paper should not be pursued as an end in itself. “Limiting paper use, and, where necessary, making use of AI and blockchain, is only worth it if it makes trade and supply chain processes more time and cost efficient,” she says.</p>
<p>“Paper should be regarded as what it is: a vessel for information. The ability to decipher and share this information quickly and to a high standard is what differentiates best in class service from time-consuming, inefficient processes. It allows payments to be made quickly and prevents ships being stuck at port.”</p>
<p>Paper still has a future in the trade and trade finance space, and may do so for years to come, despite the promise of APIs, AI and blockchain. “As a very first step, these technologies are used to improve our operational efficiency to the very benefit of our clients, in terms of speed, cost efficiency and security,” says Gastellu. “And they are also the basis for a paper-free trade industry – one day.”</p>
<p>Banks are beginning to respond; it’s that or face disintermediation, warns McCann. But only when true connectivity is established between ecosystems, will corporate treasurers across the spectrum be able to look forward to managing growth, not paper.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Paper-free trade]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=75CACB0F45768F3104878751E7C3FE5D]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=63E5D696976A251EA0F552CEB3029A6C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=224C018E2CE17425F42AF7D378F49BB9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EFD5C856CBB8C6F8D9832F03329D8171"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6039CF073D375F7D1CC34F2371663C57"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=096E277F5ACF963084B2089F13AF1C30"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Stacks and stacks of paper documents" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=75CACB0F45768F3104878751E7C3FE5D" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__stack-paper-files-565403764__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=75CACB0F45768F3104878751E7C3FE5D"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“Despite much talk of AI and blockchain, many people still argue that it is not possible to have paper-free trade documentation. Are they right?”</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Daniel Cotti, MD Centre of Excellence Banking &amp; Trade, Marco Polo Network" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__daniel-cotti__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6728029BA2347FE4E73A6297222C0232" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Daniel Cotti, MD Centre of Excellence Banking &amp; Trade, Marco Polo Network" width="150">
<h3 class="fn">Daniel Cotti</h3>
<h5 class="title">MD Centre of Excellence Banking &amp; Trade</h5>
<h5 class="org">Marco Polo Network</h5>
</img></div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>For hundreds of years, trade finance has been essential for both domestic and cross-border trade flows. Currently, these transactions are responsible for a significant portion of global trade – 80-90% of global trade relies on some type of trade finance. In essence, every time goods or services are exchanged and sold across the border, there is some form of trade finance involved.</p>
<p>One of the critical problems in trade finance is the sheer volume of paper-based documents on which the information flow is based on. Many forms of trade finance such as letters of credit have not gone paperless and still rely on semi-automated and antiquated processes that are based around the physicality of the written word. Besides, these paper-based documents are prone to fraud because of the number of parties involved and the complexity in trade finance transactions.</p>
<p>More recently, service providers, financial institutions and their corporate clients are seeking to streamline processes, reduce transaction time and cost, as well as mitigate fraud risk by replacing the flow of paper with digital data flows and leveraging various technologies. Digitisation is driving down the cost of trade finance transactions and increasing the transparency for all parties involved. This can result in reduced credit risk, enhanced cash flow forecasting, and better allocation of working capital. By providing a global electronic counterpart made up of many interconnecting and intelligent networks, the trade finance market can become digital. By doing so, digital trade finance has the potential to be offered by a larger funding pool and to a much broader market, including SMEs.</p>
<p>However, the shift to digital has been very slow. The reason for the limited adoption is evident: trade finance transactions involve multiple parties, trading parties, financial institutions, credit insurers, shipping companies, customs and other services providers, all located in various jurisdictions and all of whom must adopt digital trade finance solutions.</p>
<p>The good news is that with the introduction of new technology such as blockchain and APIs, we can now more easily link digital processes across the different parties involved in trade. Applying new technologies in trade finance is not new, however, the pace of innovation in this area during the last year is something which has never been seen before.</p>
<p>Technologies such as blockchain have the ability to streamline the trade finance process and increase the speed and adoption of digitising trade finance. With blockchain, trade participants can create a digital ledger of transactions that is distributed amongst a digital network. On the network, each permissioned member can securely amend the digital ledger. The blockchain embodies all the necessary information in one digital document, which is updated and viewable by all participants on the network almost instantly.</p>
<p>Today, blockchain is already being used to simplify trade practices and replace manual and paper-intensive processes in trade finance. One example is Marco Polo, one of the largest trade finance networks with over 30 financial institutions, and tested by over 20 leading corporates including Daimler and MAN. The global network focuses on open account financing offered through a distributed trade finance platform. By connecting a critical mass of numerous parties in the trade ecosystem, it gives the much needed digitisation of trade finance a real possibility. In the coming years, we will see how the journey towards machine-to-machine trade finance is evolving and how many corporates, banks and third-party service providers are catching up and moving to mass adoption in one of the largest global financial markets.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Marie-Laure Gastellu, Deputy Head of Trade Services, Societe Generale" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__marie-laure-gastellu__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=885BEB68FE13E9C51C375266B11FDEEB" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Marie-Laure Gastellu, Deputy Head of Trade Services, Societe Generale" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Marie-Laure Gastellu</h3>
<h5 class="title">Deputy Head of Trade Services</h5>
<h5 class="org">Societe Generale</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Many have blamed paper for the time-consuming and costly nature of trade. With such a bad reputation, it is no surprise that many hope new technologies will liberate us from the constraints of paper. Yet, the prospect of a fully paperless trade value chain within the next five years seems unrealistic.</p>
<p>Though there have been commendable initiatives designed to encourage standardisation – the International Chamber of Commerce and the Bankers Association for Finance and Trade are notable examples – we have a long way to go. Our industry involves many stakeholders who share few common standards, therefore paper is often unavoidable. Between the placing of an order and its delivery, manufacturers, shipping companies, port authorities and banks must reconcile the information they share in their own standards, sometimes varying from country to country. Despite its limitations, paper continues to help enable this.</p>
<p>One must also consider the problem of admissibility. The ambition to have paper-free trade can already be met with today’s – and even yesterday’s – technology. We could just stop printing the required forms and share them digitally, something for which AI and blockchain are not even necessary. But the lack of shared admissibility rules within our industry makes this impossible.</p>
<p>Reducing the use of paper should not be pursued as an end in itself. Limiting paper use, and, where necessary, making use of AI and blockchain, is only worth it if it makes trade and supply chain processes more time and cost efficient. Paper should be regarded as what it is: a vehicle for information. The ability to decipher and share this information quickly and to a high standard is what differentiates best in class service from time-consuming, inefficient processes. It allows payments to be made quickly and prevents ships being stuck at port.</p>
<p>Societe Generale ensures efficiency in this area through membership of joint initiatives like we.trade, the first blockchain-based trade finance platform live in production. We also continue to develop AI-based tools that use optical recognition and machine learning to automate compliance and documents checks. In these technologies, it is not required to make paper disappear. However, where paper is used, it is used more efficiently, and human intervention is devoted to added-value interactions.</p>
<p>Paper will still have a future in the trade industry for years to come, despite much talk of AI and blockchain. As a very first step, these technologies are used to improve our operational efficiency to the benefit of our clients, in terms of speed, cost efficiency and security. And they are also the basis for a paper free trade industry one day.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Gert Sylvest, Co-Founder, Tradeshift and GM Tradeshift Frontiers" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__gert-sylves__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=820B365E06A27D7AC8F128D5CBF29B36" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Gert Sylvest, Co-Founder, Tradeshift and GM Tradeshift Frontiers" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Gert Sylvest</h3>
<h5 class="title">Co-Founder</h5>
<h5 class="org">Tradeshift and GM Tradeshift Frontiers</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The concept of ‘going paperless’ goes back at least 30 years to early iterations of the internet and desktop computing. Given the enormous technological leaps we have made during that time, I find it incredible that we are still having this debate at all.</p>
<p>Technologies like blockchain and artificial intelligence have undoubted potential to revolutionise key aspects of the treasury function, from greater efficiencies, through to enhanced KYC and innovative new financing options. To begin any discussion at this point, however, is to ignore a fundamental step in the journey, without which any benefits of emerging technologies are entirely irrelevant. So let’s walk before we run.</p>
<p>The way businesses trade together has not really evolved much in the past 40 years. Digitisation within large enterprises is actually at a pretty advanced stage, and yet globally just 8% of trade transactions are digital.</p>
<p>The missing piece in the puzzle is digitisation between business partners across the broader supply chain ecosystem. You can have the greatest level of digitisation internally, but if the partners you are dealing with – banks, suppliers, buyers, logistics handlers – are not digital, then the whole process reverts to the lowest common denominator.</p>
<p>Take a step back and compare this to the way you live your life outside of work. How many of us still receive a paper copy of our bank statement every month? How much more convenient is it to download a mobile copy of our boarding pass when we arrive at an airport, as opposed to having to remember to print these documents off at home?</p>
<p>Why do our expectations shift as soon as we go to work?</p>
<p>Firstly, most business software is simply not up to the job. Rather than making it easy for businesses to connect with one another, most business software is designed in islands. True digitisation is just not possible within this framework. The best you can hope for is the equivalent of a telephone that only makes calls to people who use the same telco provider.</p>
<p>Secondly, your business might be committed to digitising its operations and eliminating paper-heavy processes, but if the external partners you deal with are not on board, the system begins to break down. Most supplier onboarding initiatives involve a lengthy to-do list with no real upside for the supplier. That feels like a pretty one-sided deal, and no great motivator.</p>
<p>So what’s the answer? The ubiquity of mobile, internet and social media mean that our personal lives are increasingly governed by a series of digital relationships. If businesses are to get rid of paper then the industry would do well to take inspiration from sites like LinkedIn, which foster a digitally connective ecosystem that makes it very easy to connect and share information.</p>
<p>Consumer technology also teaches us that if you want to influence behaviours, then carrots are far more effective than sticks. If your objective is to eliminate paper-heavy processes, you need to incentivise businesses to make the change as well.</p>
<p>To come back to the original question, technologies like blockchain and AI offer us a glimpse of an exciting future. They also open up the door for a range of innovations that will help suppliers see immediate benefits from going digital, from faster approvals through to enhanced supply chain financing options.</p>
<p>But before we can really say goodbye to the past, we need to get the basics right. The software exists to achieve full digitisation at scale, but the benefits this technology provides have always focused on the buyer. New technology is one thing, but if paperless is ever going to become the norm, then new perspectives and new business models will be required that offer benefits to the whole ecosystem of digitised business relationships.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:200px;">
<img alt="Andrew Wood, Partner, Norton Rose" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-03-04-tt-11-qa__andrew-wood__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FECE5B8F7FF7332CA8A6797D30566ADC" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Andrew Wood, Partner, Norton Rose" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Andrew Wood</h3>
<h5 class="title">Partner</h5>
<h5 class="org">Norton Rose</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Any outsider looking at the paper-intensive world of international trade must struggle to make sense of it. Despite the digital revolution in almost all other walks of life, paper documents continue to be physically signed, couriered across the globe and presented for payment or delivery of goods, much in the same way as they were centuries ago.</p>
<p>Yet these continuing practices belie the huge amounts of time and cost that have already been invested in seeking to update these ancient models for use in a 21st century digital environment.</p>
<p>In truth, paper-free trade must be possible and it must happen. The obvious benefits demand it: reductions in the time and cost of compliance checks and physically preparing and moving paper (not to mention the additional costs and delays that arise when the paper fails to travel quickly enough), the creation of visible and immutable records and the potential for increased protection against fraud and other crime.</p>
<p>The more relevant question is how quickly will it happen? And the answer depends in no small part on how many laws will have to change globally to make it work.</p>
<p>The fact that international trade is not already paperless is largely because, after centuries of successful and consistent practice:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>The customary paper instruments that underpin trade (such as bills of lading, letters of credit and bills of exchange) have established a special legal status which is derived largely from laws requiring physical actions (such as physical (ink) signatures and physical possession of paper); and</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The legal treatment of these instruments is to a significant extent almost universally aligned, resulting in broadly equal treatment (and resulting confidence) across different trading nations.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The problem for paperless trade is that these existing instruments and laws essentially pre-date the electronic world, and the established (paper-driven) rules do not always easily integrate with that world.</p>
<p>The challenge to going paper-free is twofold:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>To ensure the beneficial effects of these paper instruments (such as ease to transfer and pledge) are not lost when presented electronically.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>To create consistency between laws and systems across borders.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>To date, efforts have brought some successes but not universal solutions. For example, various domestic lawmakers and online platforms have sought to afford electronic bills of lading the same legal status as paper bills, such as replicating contractually the requirements for a physical possessory pledge or transfer. Despite such progress, however, many remain legally untested and often successfully operate without paper only within the jurisdiction of the relevant laws or amongst the parties which have signed up to the conditions of the applicable platform(s).</p>
<p>Similarly, legal requirements for instruments like bills of exchange or promissory notes to be “in writing” and “signed” have led a number of legislators to recognise that electronic documents can meet these criteria. But again, for paperless versions to become the norm, the majority of major trading countries will need to share a mutual recognition and acceptance of e-documents and e-signatures (and, looking further ahead, smart contracts and other technological advancements). This will most likely happen eventually, but it is unlikely to be immediate.</p>
<p>Parties will only universally adopt paperless trade once it is tested in courts and has had its intended effect upheld. Until then, parties will live with the practices that have stood the tests of time and legal scrutiny. But as technology continues to advance, the hurdles to paperless trade appear increasingly smaller.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“What are the benefits of taking professional treasury exams?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Connecting digital islands: the future of trade finance?]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2020 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=F5A38A672B49E60A33CACBDED7002BA4]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>With a US$1.5trn trade finance gap globally, there’s a clear need to bring paper-based processes into the 21<sup>st</sup> century. In the past, efforts to digitalise trade finance have often fallen by the wayside – but could more recent technology-powered initiatives really make a difference?</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FE328A0AD40EEA98E011A9AA6FD84C78"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FF32406F66ABBF345D0404918E05D5C4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8C05E6858A09943196CCF7875BFFDC76"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C570B7EF4709B5AABE5FF18556E99C17"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B06CE55C0B15476259A3242FEC441A2C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Digital blockchain created by typography" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F5A38A672B49E60A33CACBDED7002BA4" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2020-01-02-tta-07-tr__blockchain-digital-illuminated-shape-big-data-679065259__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F5A38A672B49E60A33CACBDED7002BA4"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Trade finance plays a vital role in facilitating global trade, both by providing trade partners with the finance needed to support growth, and by helping them mitigate trading risks. But at a global level, the availability of trade finance continues to fall well short of demand. A report published by Asian Development Bank (ADB) in September 2019, Bridging trade finance gaps through technology, estimated the global trade finance gap to be US$1.4trn-US$1.6trn, “or around 8%-10% of global goods trade.”</p>
<p>The report states that Asia Pacific accounts for about 40% of the rejected trade finance applications worldwide. It also finds that banks are more likely to reject the proposals of SMEs due to the higher costs associated with processing those proposals – not least because of the higher costs of obtaining AML and KYC information. In addition, the high costs associated with trade finance instruments like letters of credit (LCs) can put these beyond the reach of smaller businesses.</p>
<p>“Trade finance is very important to achieving sustainable development goals (SDGs), which include things like economic growth and addressing poverty,” comments Steven Beck, Head of Trade Finance at ADB. “Without sufficient financing to support the growth of trade, we’re not going to realise a lot of the goals that we’ve all signed up for.”</p>
<h3 id="going-digital">Going digital</h3>
<p>So what are the obstacles? The ADB report cites three main challenges when it comes to providing trade finance: costly delays and errors in documentary transactions arising as a result of the continued use of paper; the need for financial institutions to conduct significant due diligence “which raises the cost of supplying trade financing”, and banks’ need for knowledge of their clients, resulting in hurdles for SMEs seeking finance.</p>
<p>The first of these three issues is a particular focus for many in the industry. As the ADB report points out, letters of credit can involve over 20 different parties and as many to ten to 20 documents, all of which need to be examined and validated.</p>
<p>“The primary problem with trade finance is that it is paper intensive, creating inefficiencies across the physical and financial supply chain,” comments Hariramchakraborthy Janakiraman, Head of Trade Product, ANZ Institutional. “This results in increased cost, risk and reduces access to financing especially for SMEs.”</p>
<p>It’s clear that digitising these processes could play an important role in addressing the challenges associated with trade finance, and thereby enabling more businesses to access the funding they need. As Janakiraman explains, a significant portion of global trade is now transacted on open account terms. In this context, the digitisation of trade can unlock faster access to financing and reduce operational costs by enabling access to, and streamlining, the information flow between the trade financier and intermediaries such as shipping companies and the customer.</p>
<p>For corporates, Janakiraman says digitalisation “will eventually provide them a single standard to connect digitally with their financiers, shipping companies, suppliers and buyers.” What’s more, he says it will “bring traditional paper-based instruments such as letter of credit and guarantees into the modern world.”</p>
<p>Peter Jameson, head of Asia Pacific Trade and Supply Chain Finance, Global Transaction Services at Bank of America, adds that digitalisation offers multiple benefits in addressing key challenges in this area.</p>
<p>“From a bank perspective, risk reduction is a major benefit,” he says. “Through capabilities such as digital tracking, rule-based solutions (smart contracts/AI), automated regulatory tracking of documents and automated compliance scanning, banks have quicker access to information.” As a result, he says, banks are able to make decisions faster – and most importantly, more accurately – to support their clients’ trade and financing needs.</p>
<p>In addition, Jameson notes that digitalisation brings numerous other benefits for banks and clients, including operational efficiency, enhanced regulatory reporting and expedited transaction processing – thereby helping to bring down overall expenses and improve profit margins.</p>
<h3 id="digital-islands">Digital islands</h3>
<p>When it comes to bridging the gap, efforts to harness technology to streamline trade finance processes date back some time – but historically, such efforts have often fallen short of providing their desired outcome. Last year, for example, it was reported that SWIFT plans to decommission its trade services utility (TSU) in December 2020, calling into question the future of the bank payment obligation (BPO) – an irrevocable undertaking from the buyer’s bank to the seller’s bank to pay under agreed conditions, with data matched electronically via the TSU.</p>
<p>“Digitising trade is not a new phenomenon: members of the trade ecosystem have been trying to convert paper into ones and zeroes for years,” says Ajay Sharma, Regional Head of Global Trade and Receivables Finance, Asia Pacific, HSBC. “The problem is that because much of the work has been done in siloes, we’ve ended up creating digital islands that don’t speak to one another.”</p>
<p>Likewise, the limited scope of individual initiatives may have hindered their effectiveness, as Janakiraman explains: “Prior to the past couple of years, industry participants have been attempting to digitise on their own with a focus on specific documents (eg bill of lading) or processes rather than the end-to-end supply chain. The biggest change over the last few years has been the concerted effort by various involved parties such as banks, corporates, shipping companies, government departments to digitise the entire supply chain.”</p>
<h3 id="strength-in-numbers">Strength in numbers</h3>
<p>This step change includes a growing focus on technologies that could finally help to bring the different parts of the puzzle together. In particular, there continues to be much discussion about the potential of blockchain/distributed ledger technology (DLT) to address challenges in trade finance.</p>
<p>As Sharma points out, “Blockchain can be the superconnector, or a network of networks, that links these digital islands, bringing all parties together. This will greatly reduce trade friction and vastly improve working capital for companies.” He notes that a report co-authored by HSBC and Bain estimates that blockchain could increase global trade volumes by US$1.1trn by 2026, up from the current base of US$16trn.</p>
<p>Janakiraman observes that blockchain “brings a real opportunity to digitise trust in the trade finance industry.” In particular, he says that private blockchain technology offers the unique capability of being able to bring non-trusting parties into a common platform to transact, “while maintaining confidentiality.”</p>
<p>This isn’t just talk – there are already numerous examples of blockchain-based solutions that address the pain points in trade finance. One area of focus is letters of credit: according to Sharma, issuing LCs can take five to ten days using a paper-based process – but with blockchain, an LC can be issued in as little as a few hours. “Put simply, when we remove paper, more trade can be done in the same amount of time,” he says.</p>
<p>Sharma adds that HSBC has already completed 14 blockchain letter of credit transactions, and is working with clients “to either continue or begin their blockchain journeys.” He adds that once clients are familiar with how easy it is to integrate blockchain into their systems, “we’ll be able to move onto full commercialisation.”</p>
<h3 id="ones-to-watch">Ones to watch</h3>
<p>There are plenty of initiatives to watch – and many of these are characterised by high levels of collaboration across different players within the industry. While not an exhaustive list, the following initiatives are making waves in this space:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Marco Polo: facilitating interactions.</strong> Jointly run by TradeIX and R3, the Marco Polo Network aims to “facilitate interactions and create value for all its participants including financial institutions, their corporate clients, and the broader trade ecosystem.” In December, the network successfully completed a blockchain open account trade finance trial which incorporated more than 70 organisations.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>ICC TradeFlow: streamlining paper-based processes.</strong> DBS and Swiss commodities trader Trafigura announced in November that they have plans to launch a blockchain trade platform in Singapore, the ICC TradeFlow platform. The platform is expected to halve document transit time.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Lygon: speeding up bank guarantees.</strong> An Australian platform spearheaded by ANZ, Westpac and the Commonwealth Bank with IBM, Lygon allows for the digitisation of bank guarantees – speeding up the issuance of bank guarantees from up to a month to on or around the same day. The platform has recently concluded a successful pilot and is preparing for commercialisation in mid-2020.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>The Trade Information Network: sharing information securely.</strong> Janakiraman says the Trade Information Network “is a global innovative platform that enables corporates to securely share trade information with banks of their choice and therefore get access to more financing opportunities. The platform aims to be the inclusive industry standard network for multi-bank trade finance and is about to start its pilot, with commercialisation expected in 2020 as well.”</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Networked Trade Platform (NTP) and eTradeConnect: digitising trade data.</strong> Led by the Singapore and Hong Kong regulators respectively, NTP and eTradeConnect aim to “digitise trade data and become one-stop trade information ecosystems,” Janakiraman explains. NTP already has over 2,000 customers after going live in December 2017; eTradeConnect went live in October 2018 and is set for commercial transactions this year.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Voltron: providing an end-to-end solution.</strong> An open platform for documentary trade built on by R3’s Corda blockchain platform, Voltron aims to “improve the trade finance process by simplifying letters of credit, delivering shorter settlement times, instant discrepancy resolution and simplified sanctions screening.” In May 2019, more than 50 banks and corporates took part in a simulation of digital LC transactions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>we.trade: supporting collaboration.</strong> Built by IBM, we.trade supports collaboration between businesses and banks in Europe. In 2018, we.trade announced it was collaborating with eTradeConnect to facilitate cross-border trade and pave the way for a “digitised corridor between Asia and Europe for trade finance business.”</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="blockchain-and-beyond">Blockchain and beyond</h3>
<p>While there are numerous blockchain-based initiatives under way, it’s also worth noting that there’s more to digitalisation than blockchain/DLT. ADB’s Beck says that the bank is currently engaging with a blockchain pilot on Voltron, adding that it’s important to be in tune with blockchain and the possibilities it brings – but he also points out that the hype around this topic has led to some “unrealistic expectations” about the current state of play with this technology and what it can deliver.</p>
<p>In addition, Beck comments that in the last year, the focus on blockchain has been somewhat overtaken by enthusiasm for artificial intelligence (AI). “I think if you ask most people in the market today, they would agree that AI has really taken the number one spot in terms of people’s imagination around what it can deliver to make us more efficient,” he says. “I think certainly in the AML, KYC, CFT space, the ability of AI to pick up patterns on a huge volume of transactions, in a way that human beings just can’t, is very exciting.”</p>
<p>In April 2019, for example, Citi announced it was working with EY and SAS to develop an AI-based risk analytics scoring engine. According to a press release, the platform will provide in-depth analysis of global trade transactions and will harness advanced analytics and natural language processing “to better understand networks of related parties, unstructured data and customer activity over time”.</p>
<h3 id="">Overcoming the barriers to technology</h3>
<p>From blockchain to AI, it’s clear that there are plenty of promising initiatives that could play a role in overcoming the challenges that have long been associated with trade finance. But before the full benefits of digitalisation can be achieved, there are also a number of obstacles that will need to be overcome.</p>
<p>Beck says that the “raison d’etre” of ADB’s trade finance business is to close the trade finance gap – and that the development bank recognises the essential role that technology plays in addressing challenges around AML and CFT. However, he says that three things will be needed before we can achieve these goals through technology:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Regulation.</strong> The first challenge that Beck highlights is the regulatory environment around digital trade. “Some countries, for example, don’t have any legislative grounding for something as basic as digital bills of lading,” he says. “We’re never going to be able to seriously move the needle until we’ve got the proper regulatory frameworks in place that can enable this stuff to take off.” As such, he says it’s important that governments adopt the Model Law on Electronic Transferable Records created in 2017 by the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law (UNCITRAL).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Legal Entity Identifiers.</strong> The second issue that Beck highlights is the role that the Legal Entity Identifier (LEI) could play in addressing challenges around AML and KYC. “In 2010, G20 mandated the Financial Stability Board to create a globally harmonised LEI – an eight-digit number linked to verification of who’s who, who owns whom, and (coming soon) who owns what,” he explains. “I think until we have a harmonised identifier system that’s fully adopted globally, it’s going to be really tough to address a lot of the problems in AML, KYC and CFT.”</p>
<p>In addition, Beck says that the LEI can play an important role in helping financial institutions make the best use of metadata and thereby boost lending to SMEs. “If you’ve got a lot of companies trading on systems and platforms, and able to collect an ocean of information, you need a unique identifier so that you can find the equivalent of a grain of sand – in this case, an SME.”</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Digital standards.</strong> With many proofs of concept and blockchain pilots already under way, Beck argues that these are “totally disjointed – there’s no interoperability between these different platforms.” To bring these together, he says, digital standard protocols are needed that can drive interoperability and interconnectedness. “We’re therefore working with the government of Singapore to start an entity called the Digital Standards Initiative,” he explains. “We expect it to be up and running in 2020, and we’re asking the International Chamber of Commerce to run it because they can bring together all the different components of the trade ecosystem.”</p>
<p>Beck says that this will enable seamless digital trade between these different parties. “In other words, you’ll have the exporter being able to communicate with the shipping company, ports, customers, banks, insurance, warehousing and logistics, as well as with the buyer, so that each of the data elements for each of those component parts are captured. That would drive incredible efficiencies in trade, while lowering barriers for SMEs.”</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Beck hopes that these initiatives will facilitate the use of technology to overcome long-standing challenges in trade finance and thereby address the trade finance gap. However, he also acknowledges that achieving all these goals is a major undertaking. “One of our biggest challenges is to break this down into manageable bite sizes, so we can establish reasonable measurable milestones,” he says.</p>
<p>At the same time, Beck notes that geopolitical factors are driving economies toward decoupling. “We’ve got a lot of forces moving in that direction, both intentionally and unintentionally,” he concludes. “Our Digital Standards Initiative works to keep the world connected into the future. Let’s hope it works. There’s a lot at stake.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[India: one commercial connected nation]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2019 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=86D2DFE238579348974AAE60FCA8BB4D]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article ">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<p><em>When the Indian government took the decision to make digital services available to all citizens, it set about improving online infrastructure and increasing internet connectivity. How has digitally empowering the country affected businesses and, in particular, how should corporate treasurers respond?</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=927E2C3A0F958332DFD214FBEEBC1A45"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B8BD11673702AF9436A252DFBB31BF62"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2A5621952EC7B0A4B70C83812049FFB7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0D547DAAE84DF9181C719DA9BC3A328A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=70D0DF8DA91E4FF49FA765C2B84CC817"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Skyscrapers in the city of Noida, India on a cloudy night" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=86D2DFE238579348974AAE60FCA8BB4D" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2019-11-12-tta-06-tr__skyscrapers-shot-on-cloudy-night-noida-775788769_1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=86D2DFE238579348974AAE60FCA8BB4D"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>India is one of the fastest growing economies in the world, but this phenomenon is not just limited to its GDP figures; it includes the expansion of the overall ‘operating system’ of the country – the infrastructure that keeps it going – covering just about every sector. One of the key elements of this expansion stems from the concerted effort by the government of India to introduce a country-wide programme of digital connectivity.</p>
<p>When it launched its ‘Digital India’ campaign on July 1<sup>st</sup> 2015, The Ministry of Electronics &amp; Information Technology Government of India outlined an extraordinary programme that would ensure all government services would be made available to all citizens electronically.</p>
<p>It covers three key areas: digital infrastructure, services, and empowerment of citizens, especially the unbanked. There is still a way to go on this ambitious journey, with some infrastructure projects having to start with the introduction of dependable electricity in some rural areas.</p>
<p>The government has introduced a number of new measures, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The MGov portal which is a platform to share the inputs and ideas on matters of policy and governance.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A mass roll-out of e-education, e-health and e-shopping projects.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Digital Locker, offering citizens 1GB of free mobile-accessed cloud space to securely store official documents issued by a number of agencies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Jan Dahn scheme of bank account opening has reached over 369 million extra people, the focus on providing accounts on every unbanked adult, with the banks stepping up to provide these basic accounts.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With already high mobile usage and the rise of the smartphone, plus the expansion, through infrastructure development, of internet accessibility, banking the many has laid a solid platform for the uptake of digital services. This has in turn set the tone for a commercial digital revolution to which businesses must respond.</p>
<h4 id="connecting">Connecting</h4>
<p>Alongside some of the cheapest mobile data anywhere – the sheer size of market making India very attractive to some of the world’s major telco players. Driven by rural internet growth and usage, interst use in India recently exceeded half a billion people for the first time. Internet use in India is expected to reach 627 million by the end of this year. This represents almost half of India’s total population.</p>
<p>The speed of progress can be better seen in this table:</p>
<figure>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Internet users in 2015</th>
<th>Internet users in 2018</th>
<th>Internet users by end of 2019</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>260 million</td>
<td>566 million</td>
<td>627 million</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><br/>
</td>
<td>140% jump on 2015</td>
<td>10% jump on 2018</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</figure>
<p>“The internet requirement is directly connected with the digitisation of services,” states Praveen Juyal, Treasury Manager, Amway India Enterprises, a business created to give Indian entrepreneurs the chance to own and operate their own business.</p>
<p>Of course, the more digital services are promoted and adopted, the more internet usage there is. “It’s a win-win situation for both the companies providing digital services and the companies providing internet access,” he believes.</p>
<p>Yet at the same time, we need to understand that digitisation is not an electric switch that government can flick on at any time. To meet the original briefing, there is a pressing need to keep building and sustaining appropriate infrastructure as well.</p>
<p>On August 15<sup>th</sup> 2019, (India’s Independence Day), Prime Minister Modi announced that the government will invest INR100 Lakh Crore (around USD$1.5trn) over the next five years in infrastructure. This investment will be in building roads, railways, airports, ports, hospitals and educational institutions.</p>
<p>Although expressions of concern about the realism of this proposal have been aired (not least from <a href="https://www.griclub.org/news/infrastructure/india-commits-100-lakh-crore-to-infrastructure-in-new-budget_742" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Arvind Subramanian</a>, former Chief Economic Adviser to the government of India) the intention sits well within the scope of Digital India. The last five years have seen massive spending on roads, railways, water, irrigation and urban infrastructure. Connectivity, both physical and digital, has a multiplier effect on the economy.</p>
<h4 id="successes-to-date">Successes to date</h4>
<p>So, is it working? “I believe India is running at a good pace in terms of accepting digital technology,” comments Juyal. Some examples of Digital India highlights for him include are as follows:</p>
<p><strong>Aadhaar</strong>, one of the pillars of ‘Digital India’. Every resident of the country is provided with a unique identity or Aadhaar number. It represents the largest biometrics-based identification system in the world, and is seen as a strategic policy tool for social and financial inclusion. It involves public sector delivery reforms, managing of fiscal budgets, increasing convenience and promoting what the government calls “hassle-free people-centric governance”.</p>
<p>Even given the numbers expected to use it (India has a population of 1.3 billion), Aadhar has been made sufficiently robust to eliminate duplicate or fake identities. The ministry responsible for Digital India says that it could now be deployed as a base or primary identifier solution, facilitating the roll-out of several government-sponsored welfare schemes, “thereby promoting transparency and good governance”.</p>
<p><strong>Bharat Broadband Network Limited (BBNL).</strong> Devised with the National Payments Corporation of India (NPCI), BBNL aims to connect hundreds of thousands of ‘Panchayats’ under the scheme. ‘Panchayat’ is a term used in India for the village council that has been acknowledged by the community as its governing body. Connection to BBNL should ensure better connectivity between local institutions, offices, schools and other government institutions.</p>
<p>One Indian state is using this technology to record the attendance of students and teachers at schools in rural areas, through an app. When a teacher arrives at and leaves the school, they are required to take a ‘selfie’ with their students and upload it to the school administration’s site. “It is a clear move towards the roll-out and acceptance of digitisation,” says Juyal.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Payments Interface (UPI)</strong> is an instant real-time payment system developed by NPCI that allows for multiple bank accounts of participating banks to merge into a single mobile application. It effectively offers users end-to-end fund routing.</p>
<h4 id="buy-in">Buy-in</h4>
<p>It’s apparent that demonetisation in India in November 2016, when Modi announced that the high denominations of INR500 and INR1,000 would become invalid overnight, has played a major role in driving acceptance of its process amongst citizens. According to <a href="https://www.marsh.com/in/insights/research/demonetization-and-digitization-of-the-indian-economy.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Marsh research</a>, it led to the rapid adoption of e-wallets, and credit and debit cards as a means of payment. Such digital payments have, in a large way, replaced cash transactions – at least in urban areas.</p>
<p>But India’s investment in digitisation is having a major positive impact on business that is driving uptake too. At a practical level, the government has already digitised the sharing of cross-border documentation between trade counterparties and customs offices through the Fourth Industrial Revolution project, an online import/export portal that goes some way to easing the previously paper-heavy processes underpinning any trade involving foreign exchange.</p>
<p>At a high level, eCommerce has become India’s fastest growing channel for commercial transactions. The Indian e-commerce market is expected to grow to US$200bn by 2026 (from US$48.5bn in 2018). By 2023, 28% of sales of durables in India will be through online modes, says a survey of over 6,800 shoppers by <a href="https://www.livemint.com/companies/news/digital-influence-to-impact-63-of-consumer-durable-sales-in-india-by-2023-report-1562671243877.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Boston Consulting Group in collaboration with Google India</a>. Electronics is currently the biggest online retail sales category with a share of 48%, followed closely by apparel at 29%.</p>
<p>“If there are more online sales, companies will invest less in their physical shops. All that’s needed is a tie-up with an e-commerce company, and a warehouse from where you can deliver the products to customers,” notes Juyal.</p>
<p>To increase the participation of foreign players in the e-commerce field, the Indian government raised the limit of foreign direct investment (FDI) in the e-commerce marketplace model for up to 100%, at least for B2B models. In the B2C arena, the FDI norms will be subject to riders, such as when a manufacturer is selling country-made goods through online format.</p>
<p>This level of support for e-commerce has made it easier for major foreign brands to reach Indian customers and has seen it emerge as one of the fastest-growing trade channels available for the cross-border trade of goods and services. This is feeding a growing appetite for international brands amongst the swelling ranks of digitally connected aspirational Indian shoppers, a phenomenon also seen amongst China’s burgeoning middle class.</p>
<h4 id="e-government-in-action">e-government in action</h4>
<p>A key initial focus of Digital India has been the optimisation of the country’s administrative processes. The government has established an urban renewal scheme called ‘Smart Cities’, the aim of which is to develop at least 100 cities across the country, making them “citizen-friendly and sustainable”. Part of the programme will move Smart Cities towards a cashless economy where the delivery of electronic services to citizens can be faster and at a lower cost to the providing municipal corporation.</p>
<p>One beneficiary has been Nashik Municipal Corporation (NMC), the governing body of the city of Nashik in the state of Maharashtra. By leveraging the UPI mechanism and the Smart City Payment solution, Nashik Municipal Corporation enables residents to make a variety of seamless ‘municipal’ payments.</p>
<p>Prashant Magar, Head of Department at NMC, told Treasury Today Asia that the digitisation of payments for government service delivery mitigates common issues such as cash payments, lengthy queues at municipal offices, and the need for multiple ID cards. It also goes some way towards the digitisation of payments for, and documentation of, a host of Nashik’s services such as property tax, water tax, and birth and death certificate issuance. NMC was a Highly Commended Winner in the Adam Smith Awards Asia Best Card Solution category in 2018.</p>
<p>An app is also being offered to retailers in the form of a ‘soft’ POS. Registered merchants can now accept cashless payments from citizens via the UPI or NPCI’s BharatQR, a mobile payment app using Visa and Mastercard networks and QR codes deployed at merchant locations in order to pay utility bills.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Most noticeable changes</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><ul>
<li>
<p>To make this a successful launch, the government has disbursed rewards worth around US$23.8m to one million customers for embracing digital payments.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Cash-on-Delivery quickly changed into Card-on-Delivery. Cash transactions resulted in high administration costs for e-commerce companies which reduced their margins; digital payment solutions are evolving fast to address this.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>According to the Reserve Bank of India (RBI), the country’s Central Bank, in June 2018 Indians had 944 million debit cards that could be used for online payment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>E-commerce companies report that 61% of customers use debit cards for payment. This clearly reflects that people are getting comfortable with using debit cards for activities other than withdrawals at ATMs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Mobile e-commerce (m-commerce) is growing rapidly as a secure supplement to the e-commerce industry. Industry leaders believe that m-commerce could contribute up to 70% of their total revenues.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p class="source"><em>Source: <a href="http://export.gov" target="_blank">export.gov</a></em></p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>For Juyal, this all adds up to a change of significant importance. “I believe digitisation is today the hottest topic in India. Everyone – companies, government departments, and individuals – is ready to deep dive into the world of digital life. Companies understand digitisation is the next step to success.”</p>
<h4 id="commercial-success">Commercial success</h4>
<p>Of course, individual success stories abound and Juyal obliges with a tale of digital achievement at Amway India. Having opted for digital solutions in its payment collections method, cash is now only 2% of its total business: it was around 70% just ten years ago. “It was a huge challenge for us to manage cash because it comes with other inherent risks,” he says of the decision to digitise.</p>
<p>Managing physical cash has a cost attached. It requires safes in which to put the cash, it needs banking arrangements so that the cash is picked up every day, and insurance is essential to safeguard that cash. “The whole process has a huge cash outflow,” says Juyal.</p>
<p>In response, Amway introduced a number of digital models to collect payments. “By shifting towards digital modes, we have saved cost and time,” explains Juyal. “At the same time our customers are having the enriched experience of not carrying cash.”</p>
<h4 id="treasury-role">Treasury role</h4>
<p>Today, treasury is no longer just playing a supporting role, Juyal believes. It is now more to the fore. “Treasury can bring changes by implementing new technology, innovations and new ideas which results in savings for management,” he says.</p>
<p>With the RBI introducing new technologies which are capable of changing the payment structure in India, it will also change treasury. By the end of 2019, the 24/7 payment cycle will be functional, says Juyal.</p>
<p>“Amway uses RBI’s National Electronic Funds Transfer (NEFT) and RTGS payment cycles today for making payments, but these cycles only work during the daytime,” he reports. “When the 24/7 payment cycle comes, there will be no time between payment processing and payment settlement for treasuries – and funds can arrive anytime. Managing working capital will not be easy as it is today.”</p>
<p>With increasing numbers of fintechs emerging in the light of Digital India, treasurers need to make sure that they are changing their systems in line with the needs of customers. The pace of change in India is “intense”, with development “almost on a daily basis”, notes Shankar Subramaniam, Head of India Global Transaction Services, Bank of America. “As banks, we have had to invest substantially in technology to keep pace with government plans.”</p>
<p>The Fourth Industrial Revolution trade documentation project, for example, demands upstream capabilities from banks to enable corporate clients to access the data. But corporates too need to ensure their own back office systems and processes are capable of accepting that data. It is, observes Subramaniam, a dynamic environment “in which that capability is still growing across corporates”.</p>
<p>For a small manufacturer supplying to a large corporate, “it can be challenging,” he says. It’s why he feels that part of the role of the banks is to help clients “get up and running, digitally”. But with beneficial solutions such as supply chain finance trickling down from the large corporate buyers to their SME supplier community, he believes there is sufficient motivation to digitise at almost every level.</p>
<p>Indeed, with the government having launched the Trade Receivables Discounting System (TReDS) initiative, the micro, small and medium enterprises (MSME) community now has a bank-agnostic platform enabling the flow of cheaper finance based on financier bids for early settlement of uploaded invoices. “It ensures the supplier gets the best price possible,” explains Subramaniam, noting that RBI is encouraging banks and large corporates “to become more active on TReDS”.</p>
<h4 id="keeping-up">Keeping up</h4>
<p>Depending on the type of customer base, treasury must keep in tune with developments. Treasurers need to ensure customers have access to as many options to make payments as possible. UPI, for example, is now being considered for transfer of invoices as part of the payment message; if it comes online then treasury needs to know.</p>
<p>The core systems are up and running, but even here rapid progress demands that treasurers keep tabs on how Digital India is impacting their business and how best they can respond, says Subramaniam.</p>
<p>“To a certain extent banks are able to support that exploration, but it is incumbent on all treasurers to stay on top of the available offerings,” he notes. “There is a lot that can be gained from Digital India but there is still a lot of work involved in getting to the point where all corporates will feel the benefit.” Of course, nobody said it was going to be easy, but then Digital India really is connecting a nation.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Are you future ready?]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Sep 2018 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>With digitisation and ecommerce having a major impact on companies’ supply chains and relationships – especially in Asia Pacific – businesses are increasingly stepping out of their comfort zones and embracing new business models. Which challenges lie ahead, and what should treasurers be doing to build a roadmap through this changing landscape?</em></p>
<div class="biography right vcard">
<h4 class="fn"><img alt="" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/asia-pacific/ernesto-pittaluga-citi133x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6BF365A5AB0E7686511696357E3EAB71" style="float: left; margin: 0 2em 2em 0;" width="133"/>Ernesto Pittaluga</h4>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi</h5>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" style="margin: 1em 0 0 0;" title="Citi" width="50"/>
</div>
<p style="clear:both;"><a class="button--red-stroke" href="#poll">Take part in the poll</a></p><br/>
<p>Digitisation and ecommerce are having a far-reaching impact on companies’ sales models, supply chains and customer relationships around the world. This is particularly the case in Asia Pacific, which accounts for around half of the total estimated ecommerce value globally. According to the Ecommerce Foundation’s Global Ecommerce Report 2017, China has the world’s largest B2C ecommerce market with over US$681bn in turnover, compared to US$438bn in the US.</p>
<p>Ernesto Pittaluga, Asia Pacific Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi, notes that Asia is home to some of the world’s most important disruptors, such as Alibaba and Tencent. “The proliferation of mobile and social media in the region are also key drivers,” he says. “In China, we now refer to mcommerce more often than ecommerce, because of the significant preponderance of online purchases made using mobile devices. And mcommerce is poised to burst into the mainstream, thanks to a host of technological advances that are making it easier for people to shop on their phones.” At the same time, consumers are increasingly interacting with sellers using a variety of online and offline channels.</p>
<p>Many different factors are contributing to the growth of ecommerce and digitisation within the region. For one thing, the development of new payment infrastructures and the rise of faster payments is key to the appeal of ecommerce. “The emergence of digital wallets which are tied to credit cards in China for example, or the developing QR code solutions in India, will be supporting increasingly frictionless interactions between Buyers and Sellers, in a real-time settlement fashion,” says Pittaluga. “These are major breakthroughs – and we are expecting every market in Asia to be in a similar kind of operational environment by 2020.”</p>
<p>Regulation is another notable catalyst, and many recent developments resonate with high-level regulatory objectives in the region. With some countries having increased numbers of unbanked individuals, and levels of credit card penetration being generally low, the emergence of technology such as digital wallets can play an important role in enabling people to access (and transact in) online channels, thus providing for financial inclusion. Indeed, the move towards a cashless society is a critical regulatory objective, because physical cash creates friction, cost and inefficiencies. In several markets in Asia, for example, consumers already are, or soon will be, able to live much of their lives without the need for physical cash in their wallets – and regulators are actively encouraging this.</p>
<div id="poll">
<h3>Take part in the poll below</h3>
<p>Can’t see the poll? <a href="https://discover.apester.com/media/5b8d095b4246744e9775afeb?src=link" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Access it here</a>.</p>
<p><em>Please note that you are voting anonymously. NO personal data is being collected or supplied.</em></p>
<div class="apester-media" data-media-id="5b8d095b4246744e9775afeb" height="559"> </div>
<script async="" src="https://static.apester.com/js/sdk/latest/apester-sdk.js"></script>
</div>
<h3 id="evolving-business-models">Evolving business models</h3>
<p>Companies across many different industries can expect to face disruption in the coming years. And with growing competitive pressure from innovative new entrants, it is important for more traditional businesses to be able to adapt and prosper in this environment.</p>
<p>Often that will mean stepping outside of established legacy business practices. “Five years ago, a leading European retailer was adamant that they would not pursue online sales as their business was built around a brick-and-mortar retail model,” recalls Pittaluga. “Today, that retailer has completely transformed its business and is now using a variety of online channels in China and other countries in the region.”</p>
<p>Likewise, Pittaluga cites the example of a large and successful processed food company which had previously decided against pursuing ecommerce channels, preferring to rely on its tried and tested relationships with distributors and wholesalers. Today, this business is taking part in an ecommerce payment channels aggregation pilot in China – and remarkably, this change in strategy has come about in the space of only a few months. “A number of our clients which have a traditional business will gradually experience a migration of sales that were traditionally B2B to B2C,” comments Pittaluga. “This is increasingly evident in the branded consumer sector, and others will follow.”</p>
<p>He adds, “What is also interesting is that many of these changes are consumer-driven. It is not a supply-side phenomenon, but rather a journey that to a large extent is being pushed by consumers looking for a frictionless experience – so it’s essential for businesses to understand how their customers are changing and adapt accordingly, as it may not be a question of choice.”</p>
<h3 id="digital-on-the-inside">Digital on the inside</h3>
<p>While the customer-facing digital experience is a major part of this evolution – a trend that Pittaluga refers to as being “digital on the outside” – it is far from the only challenge that companies face. While every company will have its own operational and technical infrastructure, Pittaluga says that one common issue is the question of how companies manage becoming digital on the outside versus being digital on the inside. In other words, it’s one thing to provide online sales for customers via a digital front end – but in order to make the most of technological developments and become future ready, companies also need to pay the same attention to the systems that they use to process and authorise payment instructions, and the extent to which these systems are integrated.</p>
<p>In practice, this may not be straightforward. Very large multinationals that have grown both organically and by acquisition often have many different IT systems that may not be interconnected. When it comes to being future ready and taking advantage of new developments in technology, it is therefore important to integrate the different systems in place to facilitate interconnectedness to the outside. Indeed, IT systems integration is one of the key challenges cited by global treasurers when seeking to capitalise on the potential benefits that emerging technologies could bring to treasury management.</p>
<h3 id="embracing-the-opportunities">Embracing the opportunities</h3>
<p>In the world of treasury, the rise of faster payments is enabling a move from a batch operational environment to a real-time environment. Rather than making payments in batches, companies can make numerous low value payments individually in real-time, in a trend sometimes referred to as the ‘miniaturisation’ of payments. Likewise, treasurers can benefit from having access to fully up-to-date information on a 24/7 real-time basis. While this brings opportunities for companies to speed up the way in which they can collect cash, reconcile payments and sell to clients, it also creates the need for enhanced automation and standardisation of data to support the processing of large volumes of smaller incoming payments.</p>
<p>Alongside these developments, technologies including artificial intelligence (AI), machine learning (ML) and APIs can enable treasurers to operate more efficiently in the changing landscape. Pittaluga observes that a “very important technology shift” is taking place. “For example, In July 2018, Citi Treasury and Trade Solutions announced a strategic fintech partnership to launch Citi® Smart Match, which leverages AI and ML technology, together with the bank’s proprietary assets, to increase the efficiency and automation of the cash application process of matching open invoices to payments received by corporate clients,” he says. “We are also leveraging machine learning to build technology that monitors payments and lets clients know if any payments fall outside their historical norms – and that improves over time as our clients’ businesses evolve.”</p>
<h3 id="what-are-treasurers-doing">What are treasurers doing?</h3>
<p>In order to succeed in this environment, a proactive approach is needed. Understanding all the nuances of the changing landscape and formulating a digital roadmap can be daunting, but this is an area banks may be able to help with.</p>
<p>“We like to be very structured in supporting clients through this process,” says Pittaluga. “We’re having co-creation sessions with our clients to explore how they can give their customers a better buying experience. Faster payments, a digital front end and less friction in the payments process are all tangible benefits that improve customer experience.”</p>
<p>When it comes to building a structured digital roadmap, the following six building blocks can be used as a starting point:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Policy and governance.</h5>
<p>Developments like faster payments and the miniaturisation of payments call for different/additional controls, both for banks and for corporates. Creating a digital scorecard, ensuring policies include emerging technologies provisions, setting clear guidelines around third party vendors and working on a Cybersecurity Playbook could also be key elements of this pillar.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Liquidity and working capital management.</h5>
<p>This area is being bolstered by data and game-changing technology such as AI. Using data analytics in forecasting – and investing in AI and APIs for automatic investment decisions and to enable business growth initiatives – are also areas to explore and include in the digital roadmap.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Accounts receivable and accounts payable.</h5>
<p>Likewise, treasurers can benefit from new technology in this area, including faster payments as well as the use of data analytics/ AI to enhance receivables reconciliation procedures and explore automation opportunities, among other opportunities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Risk management, accounting and reporting.</h5>
<p>The use of predictive analytics for FX and other risk factors analysis, as well as to better project how the business will evolve, could present considerable opportunities in the future. Companies should also look at leveraging existing technological developments to prevent/minimise fraud.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Systems, technology and information services.</h5>
<p>Companies should aim to evaluate new connectivity options, understand the impact of a real-time operational environment, and embrace the opportunities that distributed ledger technology could bring for supply chains, among other things.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Culture.</h5>
<p>Building a culture which values innovation is also important when it comes to embracing new developments and technologies.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="recruitment-and-skills"> </h3>
<h3 id="recruitment-and-skills">Recruitment and skills</h3>
<p>As topics like data analytics, blockchain and AI become increasingly mainstream, it’s essential for companies to have employees who possess the relevant skillsets. Likewise, when recruiting, it is important to be aware of how expectations are evolving. “One client told us that they have realised that younger generations that have grown up in the digital space are themselves already digital on the inside,” says Pittaluga. “So hiring young talent nowadays to support very basic administrative functions may prove to be an increasing challenge.”</p>
<h3 id="looking-forward">Looking forward</h3>
<p>The pace of change is showing no signs of slowing – so which developments should treasurers be monitoring? For one thing, there is a growing emphasis on the concept of ecosystems, which is defining corporate strategy for many of the most important emerging players in ecommerce, technology and other industries. “The ecosystem concept is going to be very relevant in this area, with more players, greater specialisation and a lot of technology-driven changes,” says Pittaluga. “We also expect that some of the more important disruptors will get a larger share of the economic value in the future.”</p>
<p>Where Citi is concerned, Pittaluga says the bank will continue to focus on helping clients navigate these challenges and capitalise on the associated opportunities. “In summary, what we expect to see in the next two years is significant technology-driven progress towards automation, greater efficiency and better client experience,” he concludes. “Enablers to this growth will include technologies such as robotics, AI and machine learning – but they will also include continuing evolution in the region’s payment infrastructure and the rise of real-time settlement. This is a unique and interesting business environment, with significant changes that offer great opportunities.”</p>
<div class="boxed">
<h3>Have your say</h3>
<p>Share your views on the digital future of treasury by taking part in our exclusive poll.</p>
<p><a class="button--red-stroke" href="#poll">Take part now</a></p>
</div>
<!-- How big a focus is developing an eCommerce strategy for your company?
Major focus
Moderate focus
Slight focus
Not a focus
Not sure

How deeply involved is treasury within this strategy?
Deeply involved
Somewhat involved
Minimally involved
Not involved at all
Not sure

How big will the impact of eCommerce be on the role of treasury within your organisation?
Major impact
Moderate impact
Slight impact
No impact
Not sure --></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Digital Asia: innovation, disruption and frictionless trade across the sectors]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Feb 2018 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=E5704C6E93C83DCB8178472B01F91E67]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3C3EC3A2ADBCD3D236681DA7956C2E45"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2577D0F6AF44EA782F49768B7CA8C038"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C1C9F73239B24B24BBBCBC2154CB0776"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C5647183F71BA31A2250192D9DBA755C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DFF78111A01EDCD91CA7F418C27D9D7E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Young businessman silhouette standing in front of city" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E5704C6E93C83DCB8178472B01F91E67" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/back-view-young-businessman-silhouette-standing-ss692070439-edit1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=E5704C6E93C83DCB8178472B01F91E67"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" title="Citi" width="50"/>
<div id="top">
<p><em>The momentum driving the digital agenda across Asia has, as its source, the increasing power of the consumer.</em></p>
</div>
<div class="boxed right" id="insight-nav">
<h4>In this article</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="#omni-channel-and-digitisation">Omni-channel and digitisation: shaping consumer and healthcare strategies in Asia</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="#energy-power-chemicals">Energy, power and chemicals: opportunities and challenges in 2018</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="#the-industrials-evolution">The industrials evolution: harnessing the power of disruption</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="#technology-media-and-telecoms">Technology, media and telecoms: true globalisation is here</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<br/>
<div>
<img alt="" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/asia-pacific/ernesto-pittaluga-citi133x200.jpg?h=200&amp;w=133&amp;la=en&amp;hash=FA9D263ABB6FB18AB39F45DBCE757D7A" style="float: left; margin: 0px 2em 2em 0px; height: 200px; width: 133px;"/>
<h4 class="fn">Ernesto Pittaluga</h4>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi<br/>
<br/>
</h5>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" title="Citi" width="50"/></div>
<p> </p>
<p>As Asian demographics change and consumer wealth rises, the interest in ‘frictionless’ relationships with vendors gains ground. Failing to meet consumer wants and needs can and will lead to loss of business on a grand scale.</p>
<p>Innovation and the adoption of disruptive technologies has become a key marker of the commercial will to thrive, not just to survive. With pressure mounting on the supply-side to deliver, the impact is being felt across multiple sectors. This is enabling some clear winners to emerge in ‘Digital Asia’.</p>
<p>Major online retailers understand that a strong and sustainable digital relationship with consumers is critical. They know that granting consumers easy access to goods and services is essential; from channels to payments, to transportation and logistics, all must flow in the most frictionless manner possible. Online retailers understand that there is fierce competition and that standing still is not an option.</p>
<h3 id="strategic-shift">Strategic shift</h3>
<p>With digitisation deeply impacting the corporate space, we see global consumer brands switching marketing strategies. Where they were building relationships with their retailers, supporting brand recognition with consumer advertising, they are now showing a far greater understanding and use of digital platforms that are capable of reaching and allowing interaction with consumers directly. This is informing product and service offerings, with knock-on effects across many different sectors, from media and telecoms, to utilities to manufacturing. It seems that many corporates are having to relearn how to run their business.</p>
<p>This dynamic can potentially generate challenges for treasurers. The flow of payments and collections across new platforms may be less than optimal in terms of the value and availability of data harvested. However, the move towards immediate payments, request-to-pay and real-time 24/7 clearing technologies provides new opportunities, for example, the reduction of friction facilitating significant working capital improvements.</p>
<p>We, at Citi, are well positioned to support our clients as they digitise. Our Treasury and Trade Solutions business is organised around truly ‘global, simple and digital’ lines, enabling access to a broader solution set, deeper analytics and wider connectivity. In China, for example, we were the first foreign bank to connect to the People’s Bank’s IBPS, in support of a client’s B2C relationships, providing 24/7 immediate payment updates that allowed quicker release of inventory to the buyer.</p>
<h3 id="gathering-pace">Gathering pace</h3>
<p>The drive towards digital enablement and eCommerce will continue apace. All businesses must be prepared to innovate and to transform. However, this is a fast-changing environment that requires an agile way of uncovering and responding to trends.</p>
<p>Although this is largely a consumer-driven transformation, the dynamics in many different industries will change. In fact, it is difficult to think of an industry that will not be impacted. Of course, the banking industry is revolutionising its own approach and Citi is at the forefront of that change.</p>
<p>In this article, we look at sector specifics, revealing the key trends and innovative digital responses that are enabling treasurers to move with confidence towards frictionless digital trade.</p>
<div style="text-align:center;margin-bottom:2em;">
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="#top">Jump to top</a></div>
<!-- Rohit Jamwal -->
<figure class="portrait left" id="omni-channel-and-digitisation"><img alt="Hand touching global connection icon" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/hands-touching-global-connection-icon-customer-767487700-edit-967x450.jpg?h=450&amp;w=967&amp;la=en&amp;hash=6CA80E1DBE716DDBB9D4D14353BD5822" style="height: 450px; width: 967px;"/><br/>
<br/>
</figure>
<h2>Omni-channel and digitisation: shaping consumer and healthcare strategies in Asia</h2>
<p> </p>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float: left; margin: 0 2em 2em 0;"><img alt="Rohit Jamwal" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/rohit-jamwal-pic133x200.jpg?h=200&amp;w=133&amp;la=en&amp;hash=CC0CE082B008B6792DB9FBF09025412C" style="height: 200px; width: 133px;"/>
</figure>
<h4>Rohit Jamwal</h4>
<h5>Asia Pacific Consumer and Healthcare, Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi<br/>
<br/>
</h5>
<p>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" title="Citi" width="50"/></p>
<div class="introduction">
<p>The consumer and healthcare companies in Asia are at an inflection point of growth. By 2025 the world will look different due to a continued shift from West to East. Asia will be driving the growth due to urbanisation and burgeoning middle class. This potentially will disrupt the West-centric model that many companies have followed in the past. A challenge will be to drive innovation in a global marketplace that’s heavily weighted to Asia Pacific. Rohit Jamwal, Asia Pacific Consumer and Healthcare Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions at Citi, explores the options and opportunities.</p>
</div>
<p>Across Asia Pacific there has been a continued shift toward online retailers as consumers increasingly skip traditional brick-and-mortar stores and the growth of mobile commerce and contextual commerce becomes ubiquitous. At the same time, mass production and messaging has less appeal today than ever, says Jamwal, so companies are focusing on the localisation of products and crafting personalised advertising strategies to appeal to an increasingly sophisticated consumer base.</p>
<h3 id="opportunities-and-challenges">Opportunities and challenges</h3>
<p>With sales growth on everyone’s agenda, the race for “the next one billion consumers” is all about opening up new markets, demographically and geographically. Reaching these markets is necessarily pushing digital strategy to the fore. Improving data accessibility is creating opportunities for companies to exploit direct-to-consumer models, allowing the introduction of new channels whilst maintaining traditional customer touchpoints. New banking technology (eg APIs) is facilitating bundling of products and a readiness for product extension (eg consumer finance) to accelerate point of sale conversion.</p>
<p>Rapid expansion of eCommerce brings a fulfilment challenge, while traditional multi-layer distribution models may no longer be efficient, especially in terms of inventory management, logistics (notably so for perishables) and data fidelity. To thrive, companies need to re-assess distribution and procurement value chain. Social networks may disrupt online businesses in some categories since on-demand retail is feeding instant gratification for consumers.</p>
<p>The liberalisation of government policies is also helping to grow consumption of consumer and healthcare products by the burgeoning middle class across Asia. For example, on December 1st 2017, China implemented new tariff rates on a selection of 187 consumer goods, reducing import duties from 17.3% to 7.7%. The goods covered in the import-duty reduction including food, healthcare products, medicine, clothing and other daily-use products.</p>
<h3 id="digital-channels-are-the-new-normal">Digital channels are the new normal</h3>
<p>Digitisation holds many answers and is seen as a disruptive force for many reasons. It removes many entry-barriers for challengers, but also provides speed-to-market for all participants, ultimately creating a “battle for the customer”, notes Jamwal. In the consumer ecosystem, for example, the corporate adoption of the Internet of Things (IoT) can help drive internal efficiencies by fortifying supply chain management. Companies are also using store beacons – which communicate with a shopper’s smartphone in the hopes of improving the in-store shopping experience – store beacons are immersing retailers with data that they never previously had access to.</p>
<p>But the most obvious use is in how the company interacts with its customers. For example, consumer-focused companies are beginning to use chatbots as service and marketing channels, while artificial intelligence, augmented reality and virtual reality are driving customer experience and expectations. This is something to which all serious contenders must respond.</p>
<p>Technology advancements are also priming major changes in the life sciences sector, offering greater access to information and a rapidly improving ability to respond to it, notes Jamwal. Biosimilars, genomics, point-of-care diagnostics, electronic medical records and wearable health care devices, for example, are reshaping the way in which the sector interacts with the market.</p>
<p>The non-traditional players seeking to monetise Big Data are enabling digitisation of healthcare administration ecosystems. As government healthcare spending reduces, and consumer ‘out-of-pocket’ costs for popular treatments increase, the sector can only keep up by investing in new technologies, creating new, more efficient models.</p>
<p>At the same time, notes Jamwal, the shift towards holistic patient management and the customer experience has seen companies revisit their marketing models, heralding the arrival in Asian healthcare of packaged financing and subscription modelling.</p>
<h3 id="treasury-facilitator">Treasury facilitator</h3>
<p>As new models such as these surface, treasurers are emerging as the go-to advisors on key matters such as implementing new payment methods, credit management and working capital management where extended cash conversion cycles and stretched supply chains threaten continuity.</p>
<p>Due to digitisation and innovation, the positive effects are reaching the corporate back offices and shared service centres, notes Jamwal. But market fragmentation in payment methods means treasury’s selection of the right banking partner becomes integral to achieving end-to-end efficiency and delivering enhanced customer experiences.</p>
<h3 id="a-banking-match">A banking match</h3>
<p>For consumer players offering the omni-channel experience, and for healthcare firms seeking cost and technology synergies from account structures such as on-behalf-of, arguably it is their banking partner that holds the key to success.</p>
<p>With Citi hosting “the largest ecosystem of consumer and healthcare sector corporate clients, individual consumers and B2B suppliers”, and providing access to an expansive network of networks, on-ground support to business, Jamwal believes clients have a major opportunity to “plug into Citi’s infrastructure and drive business growth”. What’s more, with “best-in-class in technology and regulatory compliance” on tap, that growth is both scalable and sustainable across the region and the world.</p>
<div style="text-align:center;margin-bottom:2em;">
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="#top">Jump to top</a>
</div>
<!-- Tim Waggett -->
<figure class="portrait left" id="energy-power-chemicals"><br/>
<img alt="Crude Oil Surface" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/crude-oil-surface-background-textured-382067620-edit-967x450.jpg?h=450&amp;w=967&amp;la=en&amp;hash=A4798636F2B7A9DCC1DE3DC7702AADCB" style="height: 450px; width: 967px;"/></figure>
<h2>Energy, power and chemicals: opportunities and challenges in 2018</h2>
<p> </p>
<figure class="portrait right" style="float: left; margin: 1em 2em 2em 0;">
<img alt="Tim Waggett" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tim-waggett133x200.jpg?h=200&amp;w=133&amp;la=en&amp;hash=F2131470F217ECFD6B55D70FD4FDB3C0" style="height: 200px; width: 133px;"/></figure>
<h4 class="fn">Tim Waggett</h4>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Energy, Power and Chemicals Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi<br/>
<br/>
</h5>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" title="Citi" width="50"/>
<div class="introduction"><br/>As 2018 dawns, a number of themes will continue to provide opportunities and challenges to companies across the Energy, Power, Chemicals (EPC) sector. These include the recovery in the price of crude oil, a greater focus on driving financial returns, nascent investment in upstream and alternative assets, M&amp;A within the Chemical subsector and the impact of China’s hugely significant Belt and Road Initiative (BRI). Tim Waggett, Asia Pacific EPC Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions at Citi, explores the key themes.
</div>
<p>Following the precipitous fall in the price of crude in 2014/5, OPEC and non-OPEC countries have extended their production quotas to mid-2018, providing producers with much needed relief, as prices will likely remain range-bound. Despite disruption from US shale producers contributing to oversupply, many shale producers are now focused on debt reduction to strengthen balance sheets after years of profligate borrowing. This will likely help to underpin more robust and higher prices.</p>
<p>Some industry estimates suggest ~US$1trn of capex investment has been removed since 2014/5 which has had a profound effect across the industry, none more so than Oilfield Service (OFS) companies as major participants in the energy supply chain. In an effort to drive down costs, OFS have made significant headcount cuts and been involved in M&amp;A transactions.</p>
<p>For an industry that had become used to high prices, the impact of significantly reduced revenues has “unquestionably” forced energy companies to rethink their strategy and focus on returns, for which the industry has a mixed track record, says Waggett.</p>
<h3 id="time-to-move">Time to move</h3>
<p>With environmental and political pressure to deliver on climate emission reductions, clean energy, the potential disruption within the automotive sector, renewables and the rise of Liquified Natural Gas (LNG), energy companies continue to strive for improved financial returns at a time when ‘peak oil’ is the cause of some concern for the industry, given the duration required for new projects to generate acceptable ROI.</p>
<p>That said, Chinese and other State-Owned Enterprises have combined with the supermajors to participate in the bidding rounds organised by the Brazilian and Mexican governments for offshore exploration blocks. Citi’s global network has supported a number of successful JVs and will continue to do so as explorations progress.</p>
<p>Further significant activity has stemmed from China’s Belt and Road Initiative. As a key part of the country’s expansion of its commercial influence across the region and into Europe, ~25% of investment is attributed to power and energy companies, according to Citi research. Chinese SOEs are at the vanguard of this initiative, with Western expertise increasingly assessing the business opportunities.</p>
<p>And further restructuring is evident in the chemicals sector, as companies seek to scale up as firms aim to take advantage of anticipated significant population and economic growth, notes Waggett. The US$156bn Dow Chemical and DuPont merger has created the world’s largest chemical company but other M&amp;A transactions have enabled Asian firms to go global. North American and EMEA headquartered companies are also participating in the industry consolidation.</p>
<h3 id="everyday-efficiencies">Everyday efficiencies</h3>
<p>From an operational perspective, EPC clients are adopting commercial cards as a more efficient payments mechanism, notes Waggett. By supplementing low-value, high-volume traditional T&amp;E cards with a variety of higher-value procurement card formats (including virtual cards), treasuries have been channelling spend through a single provider, both regionally and globally.</p>
<p>Using aggregated card data and Big Data analytics, efficiencies can be derived across the organisation, driving working capital benefits, he explains.</p>
<p>This renewed focus on working capital has encouraged many to investigate supply chain finance (SCF) to drive further efficiencies. “This is where digitisation and Citi’s use of Big Data analytics has significantly moved the needle in terms of being able to dissect client flows and change the angle of engagement with clients,” says Waggett.</p>
<p>As an example, Citi’s partnership with Visa and Mastercard provides insights on how many clients’ suppliers are card-enabled as a merchant. This information is analysed to better understand client flows and metrics around these, potentially revealing more efficient payments structures which may be replicated in other treasury centres.</p>
<h3 id="trading-paper">Trading paper</h3>
<p>And as the sector is predicated on trade flows, the need to digitise and automate has taken on a new urgency. Removing paper to enhance workflow is a key area of focus, says Waggett.</p>
<p>Where manual intervention has been eliminated, the focus of productivity can shift to advanced technologies such as machine-learning and AI. These, says Waggett, offer “further practical improvements to workflow and operational efficiency”. Some EPC players are, he notes, already engaging with these cutting-edge ideas.</p>
<h3 id="disruption">Disruption</h3>
<p>The rise of mobile payments, and the move to faster payments in various jurisdictions, is also assessed by forward-thinking companies with downstream businesses. Such disruptive digital solutions are creating new efficiencies and ultimately enhancing working capital, notes Waggett.</p>
<p>“But there is also recognition by treasurers that more disruption is coming,” he adds. “The sooner they get on board, the better equipped they will become as meaningful contributors in the discussion.”</p>
<p>The understanding of what disruptive technology means for the business, and where the opportunities exist, should be the focus of the debate for all now, he believes. “This is where trusted advisors such as Citi can bring a globalised and cross-sectoral view to the discussion.”</p>
<div style="text-align:center;margin-bottom:2em;">
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="#top">Jump to top</a>
</div>
<!-- Vincent Couche -->
<figure class="portrait left" id="the-industrials-evolution"><br/>
<img alt="silhouette engineer contruction workers" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/silhouette-engineer-standing-orders-construction-crews-426500653-edit-967x450.jpg?h=450&amp;w=967&amp;la=en&amp;hash=367F3E63C902548F84D4E29E1344B251" style="height: 450px; width: 967px;"/><br/>
</figure>
<h2>The industrials evolution: harnessing the power of disruption</h2>
<figure class="portrait right" style="float: left; margin: 2em 2em 2em 0;"><br/>
<img alt="Couche Vincent" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/couche-vincent---grey133x200.jpg?h=200&amp;w=133&amp;la=en&amp;hash=4EF01C8CDBA3049F7CBDD2445886CBE9" style="height: 200px; width: 133px;"/></figure>
 
<h4 class="fn">Vincent Couche</h4>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Industrials Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi<br/>
<br/>
</h5>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" title="Citi" width="50"/>
<p> </p>
<div class="introduction">
<p>At first glance, industrials might seem a stable sector. However, in reality, it is in the midst of a fundamental transformation, impacting businesses across all sub-sectors. Vincent Couche, Asia Pacific Industrials Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions at Citi, highlights the latest trends.</p>
</div>
<p>The industrials sector is currently undergoing a period of transformation. This is driven by significant M&amp;A activity across the various subsectors – including aviation, automotive, heavy machinery, shipping, power and construction – as companies seek to expand into new geographies and take advantage of technological innovation.</p>
<p>This activity is hugely exciting for a sector that creates the backbone of the global economy, says Couche. “Technology is creating the opportunity for many of these companies to redefine themselves and differentiate their products as they pivot towards future growth,” he comments.</p>
<h3 id="evolving-sales-opportunities">Evolving sales opportunities</h3>
<p>At the heart of this transformation is the proliferation of eCommerce and the technological disruption brought by the Internet of Things, cloud-based solutions, additive printing, robotics and artificial intelligence across Asia Pacific. These disruptive forces have already had a significant impact on the automobile and logistics industries. For some time, companies in both industries have recognised the opportunities that arise from embedding technological innovations in their products and their manufacturing techniques and from selling directly to consumers. “Other industries are not quite as advanced,” says Couche. “But all companies recognise that digitalisation is an enabler for growth.”</p>
<p>Simply creating a digitisation strategy does not guarantee success, however. Couche explains that for industrials companies to be successful they must offer a first-class user experience to customers. “Key to this is the payment experience,” he says. “If paying for the goods and services is inefficient, then consumers will simply take their business elsewhere.”</p>
<p>Because of this, treasury teams have become a crucial part of the eCommerce strategy, working to understand the payment trends that exist in the markets that the business is selling in. This is especially pertinent in Asia, where alternative payment methods such as Alipay and WeChat Pay dominate in key markets such as China. “We work with clients to ensure they can receive payments through these different methods in the most efficient manner,” says Couche.</p>
<p>Paradoxically, the increase in volume of low-value digital payments can create reconciliation issues for treasury teams in industrials companies. If managed incorrectly, this may increase costs and complexity internally.</p>
<p>Citi has developed a host of tools to help treasury teams solve this issue. For example, the growth of eCommerce is leading to a surge in popularity of Citi’s sophisticated Virtual Account and PayerID solution set. “These allow our clients to easily identify who has paid and what they have paid for,” says Couche.</p>
<h3 id="working-capital-focus">Working capital focus</h3>
<p>Disruption is also occurring on the supplier side. Couche explains that a combination of the increasing cost of labour in traditional manufacturing hubs such as China, tied with the adoption of digital solutions in manufacturing processes and into end-products, is allowing industrials companies to re-evaluate their supply chains. As a result, many are working with a greater number and a different set of suppliers to get new technology and to reduce both costs and counterparty risks.</p>
<p>Treasury is very much at the forefront of these projects, notes Couche, who is also seeing a growing alignment between treasury and procurement. “These two departments, which have traditionally worked in relative isolation, are working in tandem so that new suppliers can quickly be onboarded,” he says. “Treasury is also driving a greater working capital focus throughout the organisation, and that is leading companies to think more strategically about the payment terms they offer.” Couche notes that treasurers are also thinking about how supply chain finance (SCF) solutions might enable them to achieve their working capital objectives.</p>
<p>The widening of the supply chain and the increase in the number of crucial suppliers is seeing corporates think beyond traditional SCF solutions, many of which only cater for the strategic portion of the supplier base. “We have seen a growing adoption of purchase cards and virtual card solutions for single and recurring low-value payments,” says Couche.</p>
<p>Citi has also seen an increased interest in dynamic discounting solutions, whereby a supplier can request an early payment in return for a buyer discount. These solutions have the dual benefit of supporting suppliers across the supply chain while also offering the buyer returns on spare capital that are more attractive than most short-term investment solutions. “Citi has recently partnered with fintech firm C2FO to offer these solutions to our clients,” Couche says.</p>
<h3 id="incoming-opportunities">Incoming opportunities</h3>
<p>The most exciting thing for Couche is that there is so much more technological disruption to come. He cites the growth of connected technology and the rise of 3D printing as just two forces that may redefine how companies in the industrials sector operate. “Technology is providing businesses with the opportunity to refine themselves and achieve further growth,” he says. “We advise that treasury stays close to the business to understand the direction that it is heading and to be the catalyst for change where possible.”</p>
<p>When these industry-specific changes are considered alongside the emergence of faster payments and hyper-connectivity – where data flows in real time – with banks through APIs, the future will look very different, says Couche. “In my view, it is the perfect time to be a treasurer in the industrials sector,” he comments. “These changes will create ample opportunity for treasury teams to build on their strategic mandate and find new and exciting ways to add value to their organisations.”</p>
<div style="text-align:center;margin-bottom:2em;">
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="#top">Jump to top</a>
</div>
<!-- Aman Singh Chadha -->
<figure class="portrait left" id="technology-media-and-telecoms">
<img alt="satellite dish above city" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/satellite-dish-above-city-129648791-967x450.jpg?h=450&amp;w=967&amp;la=en&amp;hash=5612AD53AB20066B48BC0900E625556E" style="height: 450px; width: 967px;"/><br/>
</figure>
<h2>Technology, media and telecoms: true globalisation is here</h2>
<figure class="portrait right"><img alt="Aman Chadha Singh" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/aman-chadha-singh-133x200.jpg?h=200&amp;w=133&amp;la=en&amp;hash=2C22C1279E6D682829D29F5F5B081011" style="float: left; margin: 2em 2em 2em 0px; height: 200px; width: 133px;"/>
</figure>
<h4 class="fn">Aman Singh Chadha</h4>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Technology, Media and Telecoms Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi<br/>
<br/>
</h5>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo org" height="29" src="/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.png" title="Citi" width="50"/>
<br/>
<br/>
To be successful in Asia Pacific’s highly competitive technology, media and telecoms sectors, the local needs of customers must be met. Aman Singh Chadha, Asia Pacific Technology, Media and Telecoms Sector Sales Head, Treasury and Trade Solutions at Citi examines the options available for clients operating in the sector.
<p>Companies in the Technology, Media and Telecoms sector (TMT) are known to be trailblazers. Recent history is filled with examples of companies from this sector running on the cutting-edge of innovation, developing products and services that change the shape of the lives that we live today at an astonishingly fast pace.</p>
<p>This is especially true over the past decade, where the rise of the internet and the increasing accessibility of data has created a wealth of opportunity for businesses to innovate. As a result, established businesses have rapidly evolved their offerings, with a host of innovative ‘internet-first’ companies emerging in this period. It is no exaggeration to state that combined, technology, media and telecom companies have been facilitators of much of the global growth story in recent years.</p>
<p>Success in the internet age for TMT companies is not a given, however, notes Chadha. Indeed, to be successful in Asia Pacific, these companies must diversify their business models and build nuanced sales strategies to appeal to consumers in markets as varied and diverse as India and Singapore. At the same time, they must ensure they maintain a global outlook in order to ensure operational and financial efficiency and the cohesion and direction of their offering.</p>
<h3 id="local-offerings-for-local-people">Local offerings for local people</h3>
<p>Companies that want to be successful in the TMT sector must offer a smooth checkout process to make accessing their products and services as simple as possible, says Chadha. This means giving consumers access to their preferred payment method.</p>
<p>This can be a challenge for businesses in Asia Pacific, given the explosion in payment options that has occurred over recent years. Today, businesses must not only accept cash or card payments, says Chadha, they must also accept payments from a variety of mobile wallet-based payment solutions if they are to appeal to the rapidly expanding tech-aware consumer-base they desire.</p>
<p>The number of individuals using these solutions is staggering, and highlights why businesses are having to enable collections through them. For example, in China, the country’s most popular messaging platform, which also doubles as a mobile wallet, has over a billion active users and processes billions of dollars’ worth of transactions a year.</p>
<p>“Given the sheer size of the consumer base that can be reached by opening up these collection channels, TMT companies are very interested in understanding the payment trends in the markets they operate in,” says Chadha. “They then look to work with a bank such as Citi that has a deep presence in these markets to open these payment channels in the most efficient way possible.”</p>
<p>To facilitate these local sales strategies, TMT businesses are evolving the structure of the organisation to not only appear local, but to become local, says Chadha. For example, previously many of the big internet companies had Irish or Dutch entities that were responsible for much of the invoicing and collections activity. “We are now seeing these companies shift this onshore into the markets that they are doing business in,” he says. “The shift to local buy/sell models is not just because of local tax or regulatory concerns. It also helps these companies to grow sales faster, by being closer to the actual consumer and opening up additional avenues to sell and collect.”</p>
<h3 id="pushing-the-boundaries">Pushing the boundaries</h3>
<p>By becoming local, businesses in the TMT sector are better placed to innovate for growth. This accounts for the products and services they offer as much as the way they operate.</p>
<p>“Companies in this sector are not interested in the status quo,” states Chadha. “They want to push the boundaries of what is possible and shape the future by working with the regulators to develop new structures and ways of doing things that are more efficient and facilitate what they are trying to achieve strategically.” Citi is playing a crucial role in helping its TMT clients achieve this by helping them formulate the ideas, discussing them with the regulators and, ultimately, bringing these ideas to fruition.</p>
<h3 id="treasury-at-the-forefront">Treasury at the forefront</h3>
<p>No matter whether the business is expanding its geographical footprint, shifting its operating model or opening up new revenue streams, one thing is for sure: the treasury department will be busy. It is necessary, therefore, to ensure that treasury is operating efficiently so time can be spent thinking strategically rather than managing manual processes.</p>
<p>This is where TMT companies see real value in their relationship with a knowledgeable banking partner in the region that can help them to quickly roll out new services and solutions to enable the company to meet its objectives.</p>
<p>A bank with a wide footprint across the region can also help TMT companies plug into the various in-country networks and offer payment aggregation services that allow them to use local payment service providers in an efficient manner. This helps TMT companies drive standardisation at a central level, without forsaking the company’s ability to offer a bespoke experience to its customers in the different markets across the region.</p>
<div style="text-align:center;">
<a class="button--red-stroke" href="#top">Jump to top</a></div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Accelerating supplier payments]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2017 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><div class="people right company">
<div class="vcard">
<h4 class="fn">Rajah Chaudhry</h4>
<h5 class="title">Founder &amp; CEO</h5>
<img alt="Paycelerate" height="20" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logos/paycelerate-logo-2017-100x20.png?la=en&amp;hash=D2670F070C2FACCDC266D3A745664FA7" width="110"/> 	</div>
</div>
<h5>Tell us a bit about yourself and your background.</h5>
<p>My background is in investment banking. I spent ten years working in this space in both Hong Kong and Australia, mainly with Deutsche Bank. Seven years ago, I left banking and founded ChinaScope, a financial data and analytics provider. This was my first foray into the world of fintech, before fintech was even included in the financial lexicon.</p>
<h5>Do ex-bankers make good fintech entrepreneurs?</h5>
<p>I think the answer is very much dependent on the individual. In my case, as an investment banker, I was trained to be a perfectionist. At the bank, we would never do anything without it being triple checked and you would never put anything out to a client without it being as good as perfect.</p>
<p>I quickly learnt that you cannot be a perfectionist working in fintech. The innovative nature of the sector means that you are always pushing the boundaries of what is possible, at speed and whilst working with imperfect information. The result is that some mistakes will be made, and failures will happen. Becoming comfortable with this fact and trying not to be a perfectionist was probably one of the biggest challenges I faced when switching from banking.</p>
<h5>Where did the idea for Paycelerate come from?</h5>
<p>The idea for Paycelerate was born out of the frustration I experienced when launching ChinaScope. As I am sure other small business owners will attest, when you start out there are very few financing options available.</p>
<p>Even once the business starts making progress and attracts institutional or venture capital, the banks are still not going to offer finance, unless you can provide proof of profitability – which is unlikely to happen in the early stages.</p>
<h5>How vibrant is the fintech community in Hong Kong?</h5>
<p>The scene is vibrant. There is a lot of hype and everyone is talking about fintech – you could probably go to a fintech event every night of the week. This community is playing a positive role in building an understanding of what fintech companies are trying to achieve.</p>
<p>My only concern is that despite all the talk, there are very few companies out there with an actual product. To some degree, this is just the nature of Hong Kong. I hope to see more people translating their ideas into products in the coming years so the momentum that currently exists around fintech in Hong Kong can continue to grow.</p>
<h5>What about across the rest of Asia?</h5>
<p>I think what is happening in China speaks volumes. It is a completely different ballgame there when you compare the market to Hong Kong, or any other country for that matter. One issue is that the market in China is so saturated that there will be a lot of companies that just cannot survive. When you couple that with the growing dominance of the big tech firms, it is going to get increasingly hard for smaller players to penetrate the market.</p>
<p>China does have an advantage, though, because of its massive consumer market. This is what the majority of fintech companies in China are catering for.</p>
<h5>What can regulators do to help fintech thrive?</h5>
<p>Regulators across Asia are reacting differently. In China, for example, one of the reasons why the fintech community is so vibrant is because the regulators are quite hands-off. That is, until companies start having a noticeable impact on the economy – we have seen a prime example of this around cryptocurrencies recently.</p>
<p>In Singapore, which is like Hong Kong in the sense that it has a relatively small consumer market, the regulators are being very proactive and supporting fintech. Lots of companies are receiving funding and numerous products are hitting the market.</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="diagram-01">Diagram 1: Accelerating supplier payments</h5>
</figcaption>
 <img alt="Diagram 1: Accelerating supplier payments" height="75" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-11and12-tta-10-ff__diagram-01__accelerating-supplier-payments__300x75.png?la=en&amp;hash=EC447598A0B1B499327B3CF8A6594A0E" width="300"/></figure>
<p>In contrast, the regulators in Hong Kong are taking a more free-market based approach. There is nothing inherently wrong with this, but the fintech space would certainly be boosted with a little bit more support to ensure more companies can receive funding.</p>
<p>Broadly speaking, I think the regulators in Asia are doing a good job by facilitating innovation without creating risks to the economy. Ultimately it is a balancing act. Only time will tell what is the best approach.</p>
<h3 id="unlocking-value-in-the-supply-chain">Unlocking value in the supply chain</h3>
<p>Around the world, SMEs are struggling for cash. This is largely due to their inability to access readily available and reasonably priced funding from traditional lending sources. “In Asia Pacific, this problem is especially acute with somewhere between 50% and 70% of SMEs claiming to be unfunded or underfunded,” says Rajah Chaudhry, Founder &amp; CEO at Paycelerate.</p>
<p>On the other side of the equation, large corporates are increasingly stockpiling cash and searching for ways to use it. “This is proving to be a challenge as there are few options available to invest short-term cash,” explains Chaudhry. “The options decrease even further if the corporate is seeking a healthy yield from these investments.”</p>
<p>Paycelerate looks to solve both issues by offering a dynamic invoice discounting solution. “Invoice discounting – where suppliers offer discounts for accelerated payment of invoices – has existed for some time in Asia,” says Chaudhry. “Yet despite the benefits it can offer buyers and suppliers, invoice discounting has not gained the kind of traction it should have. This is largely down to the absence of a system to manage the process, making invoice discounting a highly manual, convoluted process that is impossible to roll out on any large scale.”</p>
<p>In contrast, Paycelerate’s solution is flexible in the sense that suppliers can select when they want to accelerate a payment. “This is a much more efficient process and gives SMEs the ability to more strategically manage their working capital on a week-by-week basis,” Chaudhry says.</p>
<h3 id="supply-chain-finance-plus">Supply chain finance +</h3>
<p>To do this, the solution links up with the corporate buyer’s ERP system either through an API or similar data transfer option. Once an invoice has been received and approved by the corporate buyer, invoice data will be sent to the Paycelerate platform and the supplier will be alerted that there is an opportunity to receive accelerated payment, subject to a discount being offered on the invoice. The supplier can then select what payment(s) they want to accelerate and receive payment almost instantly.</p>
<p>Also, unlike more traditional forms of supply chain finance, Paycelerate’s solution negates the need for suppliers to go through lengthy and complex KYC checks when onboarding. “As a result, suppliers can be on-boarded and begin using the solution in a matter of minutes using our online portal,” Chaudhry says.</p>
<h3 id="realising-the-benefits">Realising the benefits</h3>
<p>So what are the benefits of using the solution? Chaudhry explains that suppliers ultimately get the chance to access a much cheaper form of funding than they would from a bank. “If a supplier offers the buyer a discount of 0.5% on a HK$100,000 invoice to receive payment 30 days early, that equates to an annual 6% cost of financing for the supplier,” he explains. For the buyer, the discount means that they improve their yield to 6% on an annual basis as well – a better return than most, if not all, other risk-free short-term investment options.</p>
<p>Despite the clear benefits the solution can offer, Chaudhry admits that it is not always an easy sell. “Corporates generally understand how the solution works and the benefits it offers,” he says. “The issue is that it requires a small change to an existing process. From my experience, many corporates can suffer from organisational inertia, which makes getting them to make these changes a challenge at times.”</p>
<p>Corporates may also need to make some changes in how they work with their suppliers to attain full value from the solution. “Although the solution works with all forms of invoicing, it works best when the buyer and supplier are using electronic invoicing,” notes Chaudhry. “This is because the quicker the invoice can be received and processed, the quicker the supplier can access the financing.”</p>
<h3 id="future-ambitions">Future ambitions</h3>
<p>After building solid foundations in Hong Kong’s corporate community, the next step for Chaudhry is to launch in Singapore. “This is the short-term ambition,” he says. “Medium term we are looking to launch in Australia and Taiwan as both these markets have expressed an interest in this type of solution.”</p>
<h3 id="company-timeline">Company timeline</h3>
<ol id="timeline">
<li>
<data value="2016-06">June 2016</data>
<p>Paycelerate founded in Hong Kong</p>
</li>
<li>
<data value="2016-10">October 2016</data>
<p>Platform developed</p>
</li>
<li>
<data value="2017-01">January 2017</data>
<p>Testing completed</p>
</li>
<li>
<data value="2017-03">March 2017</data>
<p>Launch with Hong Kong clients</p>
</li>
<li>
<data value="2017-08">August 2017</data>
<p>Soft launch in Singapore</p>
</li>
<li>
<data value="2018-03">March 2018</data>
<p>Planned launch in Australia</p>
</li>
</ol></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Trading paper for precision: seizing the digital advantage in the trade space]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Sep 2017 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>The trade and supply chain space is ripe for disruption in so many ways. But how can this be achieved and to what effect? ANZ’s trade experts, Michael Lim and Hari Janakiraman, consider digitisation in this key function and explore the future prospects.</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard">
<img alt="Portrait of Michael Lim, Head of Trade &amp; Supply Chain, ANZ" class="photo" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-09and10-tta-04-st-michael-lim-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=88406D19BB204AEFBB9BC4DC8F61D714" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Michael Lim</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Trade &amp; Supply Chain</h5>
<img alt="ANZ logo" class="logo org" height="30" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/anz-logo-2015-93x30.png?la=en&amp;hash=C7EA0E5DF84BA01415D50BAC7E3E5652" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="ANZ" width="93"/>
</div>
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;clear:both;">
<img alt="Portrait of Hari Janakiraman, Head – Trade &amp; Supply Chain Products, ANZ" class="photo" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-09and10-tta-04-st-hari-janakiraman-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=EBF1BF603BD9F1E4E8642CBB8666ED6C" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Hari Janakiraman</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head – Trade &amp; Supply Chain Products</h5>
<img alt="ANZ logo" class="logo org" height="30" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/anz-logo-2015-93x30.png?la=en&amp;hash=C7EA0E5DF84BA01415D50BAC7E3E5652" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="ANZ" width="93"/>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Some aspects of life just seem to be fixed. A casual look at the trade and supply chain space would reveal a set of underlying processes that haven’t greatly altered over hundreds of years. Paper is still king and the humble fax is still much in evidence as a means of sharing documentation.</p>
<p>“Trade is probably about 20 years behind from a technology perspective,” notes Michael Lim, Head of Trade &amp; Supply Chain at ANZ. The chief reasons for this lag, he believes, are more commercial than technology-driven. Progress in most international transactions is largely suffering at the hands of an over-populated chain of participants.</p>
<p>The will of so many actors to move forward is yet to create a kind of tipping point but it really ought to. “Given that we still see so much paper in the sector, the opportunity to apply new technologies, generate efficiencies and improve the customer experience is huge,” Lim states.</p>
<h3 id="gathering-pace">Gathering pace</h3>
<p>To be fair, this opportunity has not gone unnoticed and the feeling is that a competitive momentum is building. With an increasing number of fintechs showing interest in this space, there is acknowledgement by leading banks and financial institutions (FIs) of the need to adapt to the digital agenda to remain relevant, says Hari Janakiraman, Head – Trade &amp; Supply Chain Products at ANZ. “We are seeing more banks investing in technology companies to ensure they are in the driver’s seat.”</p>
<p>Indeed, many banks, including ANZ, have a stated objective to promote the digitisation of trade. This is generating much more support within these organisations to come up with relevant initiatives.</p>
<p>In addition to the impetus given to the trade space by the competitive agenda, there has been increasing attention from governmental and regulatory bodies, notes Janakiraman. There has been active interest, support and leadership from stakeholders such as the Monetary Authority of Singapore and the Hong Kong Monetary Authority. This has seen the establishment of a number of working groups and initiatives willing to provide seed-funding as a means of stimulating involvement in the drive to digitise.</p>
<p>With regulators and major industry participants all pushing in the same direction, it would certainly seem that a collective momentum to digitise the trade space is driving progress. “We are now seeing change in a more productive way,” comments Lim. “Progress is much more organised and a lot of the banks have come to the conclusion that the best way to deliver on the benefits of digitisation is to cooperate because the real value is, ultimately, in getting the broadest network of participants.”</p>
<h3 id="points-of-progress">Points of progress</h3>
<p>In practical terms, the focus on technology has given rise to a number of broad approaches. Highlighting three in particular, Lim acknowledges that the removal of paper will be a key target when it comes to optimising trade processes.</p>
<p>The conversation around distributed ledger, and in particular blockchain, looks increasingly promising in this respect, he notes. This is exemplified by ANZ’s recent blockchain trial that digitised the bank guarantee process for commercial property leasing. The trial, in collaboration with Westpac, IBM and Scentre Group, has proved such a success that it is now being moved through to the pilot stage. However, while distributed ledger technology is going to play a greater part over the next few years, even as industrialised flows of data in this space ramp up, Lim feels paper “will be around for quite a while yet”.</p>
<p>The rise of the third-party platform, although not new per se, is another key development, especially in the supply chain financing specialism. The reason is simple: corporates that are multi-banking across multiple jurisdictions are not interested in managing commensurate numbers of banking platforms if they can avoid it. The role of these platforms in consolidating trade processes is, Lim feels, indisputable.</p>
<p>Perhaps one of the more scientific recent developments in the trade space is the application of machine learning. With computing power and data storage having reached a critical mass and affordability, machine learning – where computers understand and process without being explicitly programmed – is a distinct possibility in ever more applications. Its adoption, notes Lim, will help trade practitioners on all sides of a deal to be a lot more efficient in capturing, using and automating their existing manual processes and data flows.</p>
<p>But it will be the willingness of the various stakeholders to cooperate and keep aside their competitive differences that will truly be ground-breaking, says Janakiraman. The creation of a more open environment has been noted in the last few months as a number of banks have announced partnerships and collaborative networks.</p>
<p>But it is the rate of development here that is most interesting. It looks like technology is both enabling and compelling the banks into collaboration. This is perhaps on the understanding that if partnerships are not agreed between certain players, then certain other players who are cooperating will seize the initiative and win the business. As Lim comments, “If the industry is to evolve, it cannot be done alone”.</p>
<h3 id="joined-up-thinking">Joined-up thinking</h3>
<p>Bringing organisations and technologies together to achieve a cohesive end-to-end game-changer for clients will not work without a digital strategy. ANZ’s internal discussions led it to conclude some time ago that customers want self-service, ease of access, a transparent and reliable service, fast execution and surety of funding. Its approach to the digitisation of trade reflects these multiple needs.</p>
<p>The efficiencies and the cost savings for the bank will naturally be derived from transformative technologies such as distributed ledger and machine learning. Individually, these can offer a more instantaneous way of doing business over “shuffling bits of paper from office to office”, notes Lim. The provision, for example, of deeper insight for customers through data analysis, is thus a strong motivational force to bring them to market.</p>
<p>It is true that these technologies are subject to ongoing development, but even in the interim they can be used to automate selected labour-intensive processes. On the paper reduction side alone, there’s a potential 30% to 50% turnaround time saving for customers.</p>
<p>However, says Lim, as the digital future of these tools becomes reality, and their respective benefits are brought together – just as banks must work together – then the real transformation of trade will take place.</p>
<p>One area where the power of combination is yet to be fully revealed is in the Internet of Things (IoT), says Janakiraman. “We are looking at how we can embed RFID/chip technology into various parts of the supply chain to ensure the entire process becomes visible to the bank,” he explains.</p>
<p>This would not only eliminate the need to receive paper-based information but, in creating full process visibility for the financier, risk management enhancements are achieved. This has an important customer benefit.</p>
<p>The term ‘RegTech’ has entered the common lexicon in recent months. Trade has a lot of opportunity to exploit robotic process automation (RPA) as a means of harvesting and analysing regulatory data in real time, says Janakiraman. Better understanding of risk equates not only to faster, better and more cost-effective compliance but also, as a result of such efficiencies, the opportunity to make improved funding offers for clients.</p>
<h3 id="visible-benefits">Visible benefits</h3>
<p>Indeed, the overarching benefit of digitisation can be seen in the drive towards greater depth of trade financing across the board. IoT, RegTech and RPA and all the other new technologies can combine to give unprecedented visibility with a positive effect on risk-based funding decisions.</p>
<p>But deeper visibility and process improvements also mean funding solutions that were previously only made available for higher value transactions (because of their administrative cost), suddenly have commercial viability lower down the value scale.</p>
<p>The availability and tracking of multiple sources of trade data in almost real-time also provides improved opportunities to support sustainable finance programmes, where provenance of raw materials, for example, is vital.</p>
<p>This, notes Lim, demonstrates the capacity of big data analytics in tracking every redistribution point, or node, in a supply chain. “Once you have that level of data and visibility, it makes it a lot easier for a business to quickly identify where inefficiencies and potential losses are taking place.”</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>The efficiencies and the cost savings for the bank will naturally be derived from transformative technologies such as distributed ledger and machine learning. Individually, these can offer a more instantaneous way of doing business over “shuffling bits of paper from office to office”.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Michael Lim, Head of Trade &amp; Supply Chain, ANZ</p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Many large and sophisticated corporates have been able to accumulate detailed trade data from counterparties and from banks and can use this to provide visibility and analytics across, for example, their accounts payable and receivable. They might then use this insight to match and optimise their use of trade finance facilities.</p>
<p>This has not commonly been available for smaller to mid-tier corporates and those from emerging countries, especially those with multiple banking relationships, says Janakiraman. As trade data becomes more accessible through the advent of new technologies, the benefits enjoyed by the larger corporates will become available to a far wider cross-section of the trade community. “This will give them a level of visibility they have never had before, helping to level the playing field.”</p>
<h3 id="all-pull-together-as-a-team">All pull together as a team</h3>
<p>In helping corporates make informed decisions on funding and even purchasing, disruptive technologies, and the will of banks to cooperate and create a functioning ecosystem for all trade partners, are essential. But the regulators too must all pull together to create the desired global trade proposition.</p>
<p>“There is a lot of work that needs to be done to update regulatory and legal frameworks to support the aims of trade,” suggests Janakiraman. “There are still debates around whether a digitised bill of lading has the same weight as its paper counterpart. There are still debates between certain countries as to what is acceptable as a digital document. These debates need to move on.”</p>
<p>The ICC is reviewing standards of trade document creation, drilling down for example into what constitutes a digital invoice. This level of granularity is complemented by its push to organise working groups looking at broad policy recommendations for governments and regulatory bodies. With the likes of ANZ fully on board, it is reviewing how digitisation may be best facilitated. It is also considering how its own ICC business rules need to be revamped to encompass the future exchange of digital trade documentation.</p>
<p>The banking community has a reflective task too, says Janakiraman. Where banks agree to form trade networks, certain anti-competitive issues may arise. All such agreements must be conducted with the utmost transparency, he insists. “It needs to be clear to all stakeholders that this is not about forming a cartel but servicing the client and benefiting the community.”</p>
<h3 id="a-waiting-game">A waiting game</h3>
<p>The technologies referred to earlier are in development in the treasury context; they are practicable solutions in the making. “From ANZ’s perspective, we are operating on the expectation that truly commercialised and industrialised digital trade flows will be a reality, potentially within three to five years, closer to three,” says Lim.</p>
<p>It is well understood that paper will not be removed from the equation completely, and certainly not within that timeframe. However, Lim believes that there will be a more rapid transition to digital flow in the trade corridors and sectors where proactive government and regulatory bodies are working with the industry and financial sector to drive that change.</p>
<p>Here he pays particular attention to the flows in and out of the markets of Singapore and Hong Kong, where the regulatory authorities are indeed proactively supporting the digital agenda. Lim also suggests that advancement will be more notable where there are large concentrations of industry players that are prepared to use their scale to both drive progress and materially benefit from the efficiencies of digitisation.</p>
<h3 id="anz-in-the-real-world">ANZ in the real world</h3>
<p>Wherever progress is seen, it will be at the invitation of the end-users and not the banks, says Janakiraman. The broad ANZ policy on technology is, he explains, about enhancing the customer experience through self-service, connectivity and speed based around its channels’ data-processing efficiency.</p>
<p>It is the ANZ approach that if there is an issue to be resolved, then it will work with a group of customers to find the best solution. Under this model, there is no developing a product in isolation and then hoping to find a real-world problem for it to fit.</p>
<p>This understanding sits at the heart of the ANZ approach to the world of trade digitisation. “We invested our time and resources to develop the Distributed Ledger Technology Guarantees Proof of Concept because it solves a genuine customer and industry problem,” explains Lim. “Our aim is to make sure we are focusing on enhancing the customer experience and everything we do is designed to deliver for our customers.”</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Invoice financing reimagined]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2017 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=FA30C8084CCF52C1899412E64873C70D]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A99A0603E7D0FCC30E4DCA447972DE85"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9010C7F0EAD38815878B3090310C6E5D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6213B2CF582D15BD171803C055011B35"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BB2AB8F4CF1BF8451D8FFFC5A4A53C6B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AC56FB85C1CB39990ED179793165F951"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Kush Patel, CEO and Co-Founder, Tallysticks" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FA30C8084CCF52C1899412E64873C70D" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__kush-patel__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FA30C8084CCF52C1899412E64873C70D"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>In the first of our new series profiling some of the world’s most exciting fintech companies we speak to Kush Patel, CEO and Co-Founder at Tallysticks to hear how the company is looking to transform the trade finance space with blockchain and smart contacts.</em></p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><div class="vcard">
<h3 class="fn">Kush Patel</h3>
<h5 class="title">CEO and Co-Founder</h5>
<p><img alt="Tallysticks" class="logo org" height="19" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/tallysticks-logo-2017-115x19.png?la=en&amp;hash=5EFAB4902B4852868BDCC2C6E2F31743" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Tallysticks" width="115"/></p>
</div></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><h4>Tell us a bit about yourself and your background. How did you get into fintech?</h4>
<p>I began my career in finance and I got into a fintech because of Tallysticks. Specifically, after a successful career on Wall Street as an emerging markets strategist, and as a diplomat with the US Government, I decided to venture out on my own. I have start-up experience in a range of industries, including: investments, pharmaceuticals and, now, financial technology. According to a few, I’m an outside-the-box thinker with a talent for crafting efficient business strategies.</p>
<h4>Where did the idea for your company come from?</h4>
<p>The idea started with simply matching a payment to an invoice. In other words, it was to be an invoicing solution on the blockchain. Then a major European bank asked if we ever thought about integrating an invoice financing solution with our invoicing platform. We designed and presented the process flow a week later. With positive interest from the bank, we built a light solution. Meanwhile, we were asked to enter a hackathon which was sponsored by Barclays. Between winning the hackathon with our invoice financing app and getting there through our own merit, we ended up in the finals of the Barclays Techstars Accelerator programme. That, of course, sent us on our way.</p>
<h4>What makes fintech such an exciting space and what do you find most interesting about it?</h4>
<p>Banking is an industry in transformation, a change that was brought about with the 2008/2009 financial crisis. Having previously worked with financial markets, I’ve learned that any time there is turmoil, there is an opportunity. As a result, I wouldn’t want to be anywhere other than in the front-seat of a fintech company during this period of revolution.</p>
<p>Banks, of course, are friends to the fintech community, but they remain too slow to adapt to the rapidly innovating financial technology landscape. As a result, fintech companies are being forced (in part by investor demands) to go it on their own and build robust proprietary platforms. Eventually, the circumstance will be such that banks will find it cheaper to outsource various services to the fintech companies than continue to operate them in-house.</p>
<p>Think of how Amazon disrupted retailers. Post the dot.com crash, bricks and mortar retailers built online stores, thinking that they timed their strategy correctly. In truth, they didn’t understand how to leverage their online presence to reduce the existing cost overheads or simultaneously offer better service with things like home delivery.</p>
<p>Today, with Amazon eating into retailer profits, retailers are looking to leverage Amazon’s site and infrastructure to service customers. Similarly, various payment, lending, and even account management platforms are beginning to create global frameworks, or marketplaces in the case of lenders.</p>
<p>So eventually, much like with retailers, it will be cheaper for banks to plug into those platforms than to continue offering those services with legacy in-house systems. Put differently, banks will channel their customers directly to outsourced platforms through white-labelled interfaces and in some cases even provide the supporting compliance buffer as well as balance sheet.</p>
<h4>What are the challenges for fintech currently?</h4>
<p>Banks remain too slow to adopt innovative fintech solutions or work with fintech companies. In part, this is because banks are saddled with legacy systems and are afraid of disrupting peers or cannibalising their own profits.</p>
<p>As a result, fintech companies are starting to ignore the banks and sell their solutions directly to corporates: we included. Eventually, banks will take notice. Whether banks respond in time for fintech companies to agree to work with banks will be a question best answered by time, however.</p>
<h3 id="a-dynamic-offering">A dynamic offering</h3>
<p>Tallysticks is an invoicing software solution that leverages the functionality of blockchain to share a common record of immutable invoice-related data for all parties to transparently edit and update. The shared information thread, together with software automation can help to streamline the purchase order-to-invoice-to-payment workflow processes.</p>
<p>Due to its invoice-related focus and nature of the underlying technology, Tallysticks sees itself as an ideal solution for multi-party interactive workflows such as post-trade settlement of OTC commodity trades and more relevant, dynamic discounting of invoices.</p>
<h3 id="plugging-the-funding-gap">Plugging the funding gap</h3>
<p>The main challenge that the solution aims to solve is the US$2trn SME funding gap that largely results from a working capital shortfall. “SMEs account for over 60% of all employment and nearly 60% of GDP output,” highlights Patel. “Yet SMEs receive less than 30% of all lending.”</p>
<p>In Patel’s view, this funding gap exists because of the mismatch in payment cycles between large corporates and SMEs. “Large corporates pay bills on 90-day payment cycles and SMEs are often required to pay bills on 30-day payment cycles, sometimes even less,” he explains. “As a result, SMEs supplying to corporates are net 60 days short in terms of cash flows.”</p>
<h4 id="diagram-01">Diagram 1: How it works</h4>
<p><a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__diagram-01__how-it-works__696x882.png?la=en&amp;hash=DED31A2803B72CD06D8CE1EC5794E520" target="_blank"><img alt="Diagram 1: How it works" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2017-01-02-tt-09-ff__diagram-01__how-it-works__696x882.png?la=en&amp;hash=DED31A2803B72CD06D8CE1EC5794E520" width="500"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: Tallysticks</em></p>
<p>The banks have looked to address this need through invoice financing solutions. Typically banks offer financing directly to the supplier in the expectation that the buyer will pay the invoice. “This requires three parties to engage in the transaction – the lender, the borrower (the supplier) and the debtor (the buyer),” says Patel. “With three different parties involved – one of which has no vested interest in the arrangement between the other two, traditional invoice financing is clumsy. To manage the risk of this three-party transaction, banks impose harsh measures on borrowers which SMEs don’t like and so, they turn down the capital they desperately need.”</p>
<p>It is ensuring that SMEs are able to access this capital that the Tallystick’s solution looks to solve. “In contrast to traditional bank invoice financing, Tallysticks offers financing to suppliers via the buyer through an invoice portal,” outlines Patel. “This is called dynamic discounting and is much more efficient than supplier finance because the borrower and the debtor are the same party.”</p>
<h3 id="blockchain-a-game-changer">Blockchain: a game changer</h3>
<p>Patel notes that dynamic discounting is offered by a few other software platforms. What he believes makes the Tallysticks solution stand out, however, is that it is underpinned by blockchain technology. This enables businesses to potentially borrow through a marketplace at more affordable rates with a high degree of automation.</p>
<p>“More specifically, since reducing cost is the goal of any marketplace, the aim of our marketplace is to reduce the cost of capital,” he adds. “With our marketplace SMEs are able to access capital at lower rates with flexible financing terms whilst companies using dynamic discounting can expect to earn a healthy risk-free rate of return.”</p>
<p>Tallysticks are already in discussions with several corporates about deploying the solution and the invoice financing solution will be ready in Q317 with financing initially offered through a special purpose vehicle. The corporate treasury dynamic discounting solution should also be ready around the same time with the invoice financing marketplace operational in 2018.</p>
<p>“As long as we deliver our vision, help corporates achieve a better return on equity, offer a more stable supply chain, a streamlined payables process, a simplified supplier management process and more efficient invoice capture, I believe corporate treasurers and corporate finance departments should be quite interested and pleased with our solution,” concludes Patel.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><h3 id="company-timeline">Company timeline</h3>
<ol id="timeline">
<li>
<p><strong>July 2015</strong><p> <br/>
<p>The idea to connect invoicing to blockchain is born.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>September 2015</strong><p> <br/>
<p>System design and development ramps up.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>October 2015</strong><p> <br/>
<p>Tallysticks announced at Rise New York. POC completed and Techstars application submitted.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>November 2015</strong><p> <br/>
<p>A major continental bank contacts Tallysticks to build a blockchain-based supply chain finance solution. Tallysticks later integrates the solution to a mobile payments API to win the Barclays hackathon.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>December 2015</strong><p> <br/>
<p>Filed four patented processes, including automated custodial transfer and automated transaction settlement. Tallysticks selected into the Barclays Accelerator powered by Techstars from a pool of nearly 700.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>January 2016</strong><p> <br/>
<p>The company completes its first round of funding with investors valuing the company at more than £1m.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>April 2016</strong><p> <br/>
<p>Tallysticks gets voted to be a top 100 European Fintech start-up.</p>
</p></p></li>
<li>
<p><strong>September 2016</strong><p> <br/>
<p>The company gets chosen to participate as one of only six start-ups in the EY Start-up Challenge in October 2016.</p>
</p></p></li>
</ol>
<p class="source"><em>Source: <a href="http://tallysticks.io" target="_blank">tallysticks.io</a></em></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Digital flows]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jul 2016 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=262AE17BF34C4B5A45E818EF13C48ECD]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F2DABC7B2DA359EF05E7C24DC7C909A3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=25C854D9E74C368F494E33DAC1CAA3C8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A0895553CB1AFAE37F2308869C8D8022"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=396BBC233B48EDAC2D5BC166784D1E91"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=83ECB3AD88296101AD3C97BBF268BE78"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Electronic circuit" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=262AE17BF34C4B5A45E818EF13C48ECD" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/electronic-circuit-grunge-background-223552864-edit-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=262AE17BF34C4B5A45E818EF13C48ECD"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>The digitisation of trade has been a long time coming. It would seem however, that real momentum is beginning to build and that trade is truly beginning to enter the digital era. But what does a digital trading ecosystem mean for corporates and what may a fully digital trading ecosystem look like? Treasury Today explores.</em></p>
<p>Over the past century, technological advancements around trade have dramatically reshaped the way global business is conducted. Be it the developments made in transportation, that now see planes, trains, ships and automobiles weave a complex web of trade routes across our planet, keeping the global economy, and indeed our everyday lives, ticking over. Or the ever expanding digital ecosystem, where data flows invisibly and instantly around the world.</p>
<p>The result of these changes is a world that demands instant gratification. No longer do businesses and consumers want to wait more than a few days for goods – even if these are being shipped from the other side of the world.</p>
<p>At a consumer level, arguably this has been achieved. Businesses have been able to develop complex supply chains and distribution networks that enable instant gratification for their customers – Amazon, for instance, are now offering one-hour delivery on some goods in certain locations.</p>
<p>But at a commercial level, this isn’t often the case, and goods can only move as quickly as the paper documentation that supports them – just as was the case a century ago. This causes delays, risk and ultimately cost to businesses on both sides of the trade. But paper’s tenacious grip over the trade ecosystem may be beginning to abate and corporates may soon, if not already, be able to digitise at least some of their trade activity.</p>
<h3 id="the-last-bastion-of-digitisation">The last bastion of digitisation</h3>
<p>It would be natural however for some treasurers to be sceptical of that comment, and not without good reason. After all, the promise of digitising trade documentation, and the trade ecosystem more broadly, has existed for some time. Indeed, it was Professor Paul Todd at Southampton University, who, in 1997, wrote that “it is possible, on the basis of existing technology and under the existing legal framework, to replace bills of lading by electronic documents, which can in principle afford to the parties security at least as great as existing paper documents.”</p>
<p>And nearly two decades on, whilst there has been some progress, it still remains a key topic for the industry. “I describe trade finance as the last bastion of paper and manual process in financial services,” says Ian Kerr, CEO at Bolero, a company that has been pushing for the digitisation of trade for nearly two decades. “If you look at other areas such as cash management, payments, investments and so forth, these have all moved onto digital channels.”</p>
<p>For Kerr, trade is an area gripped by inertia. “The processes in trade finance have been around for many centuries,” he says. “Bills of lading for instance were first launched in the 13<sup>th</sup> century and how these are used hasn’t changed much since then.”</p>
<p>Vivek Ramachandran, Global Head of Product and Proposition Management at HSBC, is another who agrees that trade has been slow to digitise when compared to other areas. And he offers two key reasons for this. “A trade transaction has many stakeholders involved in the process, and is typically cross-border,” he explains. “Even the most basic transaction will feature an importer, an exporter, a logistics company, customs, clearing houses and often multiple financial services companies. As a result, it is an incredibly complex ecosystem and one where it is difficult to drive change. Even if 99% of the process is digital, it all falls down as long as one party requires paper to be introduced into the transaction.”</p>
<p>Moreover, Ramachandran also believes that the lack of coordinated regulatory pressure on a global scale has further limited digitisation in the trade world. “A lot of digitisation in cash management has been driven by regulatory considerations – think SEPA,” he explains. “But, in the trade space there hasn’t been this coordinated regulatory response on a global or regional level.” This leaves both institutions and corporates with a lot of questions over how a fully digital trading ecosystem can be created and what standards this should adhere to.</p>
<h3 id="incremental-steps">Incremental steps</h3>
<p>Trade is therefore digitising incrementally with small but meaningful enhancements being made to solutions by all parties in the ecosystem. And these in turn can have a big impact on how corporates can look to automate and streamline their trade processes, and ultimately be the building blocks that lead to a fully digital ecosystem.</p>
<p>Bolero has recognised this incremental change in the market. “It is a conservative industry and this has to be recognised,” explains Kerr. “What we are seeing however is the adoption of digitised trade solutions by some very high profile corporate names and consequently their financial partners and trading partners. There is a momentum shift in the market and these companies want to become fully digital in the next five years.”</p>
<p>And banks are recognising this as well, with many investing heavily in their own solutions to ensure that where possible trade and the management of trade documents can be done digitally. Bank of America Merrill Lynch (BoAML) for instance, earlier this year, announced an enhancement to their CashPro® Trade solution which enables electronic document identification and retrieval allowing the entire transaction history and associated documents to be viewed through a single window.</p>
<p>As Percy Batliwalla, Head of Global Trade and Supply Chain Finance at BoAML, explains: “Enhancements such as this ensure our clients have full visibility over the transaction and know what needs to be approved and by when. Whilst this may seem fairly basic and fundamental it hasn’t existed before in such a way that can really add benefit by streamlining the often tedious, manual process of document identification.</p>
<p>“In trade, corporates have relatively simple requirements: they want enhanced working capital, operating efficiency and cost reduction. And incremental improvements such as this that we and others have done can therefore add a lot of value to what our clients are doing today.”</p>
<h3 id="the-bank-payment-obligation">The bank payment obligation</h3>
<p>In fact, data matching sits at the heart of digitising trade and ultimately it will be this that enables corporates to achieve straight through processing. The question that remains is how exactly this will be achieved.</p>
<p>To date, the solution that has widely been seen as having the most potential is the bank payment obligation (BPO). Billed as the first end-to-end automated trade solution, the BPO is an irrevocable conditional obligation from one bank to pay another bank, subject to the presentation of compliant data in the SWIFT Trade Service Utility (TSU) – which matches data items such invoices and orders – and is based on ISO 20022 standards.</p>
<p>Despite the solution’s attributes, take up has been slow to say the least. Numerous explanations have been given for this, but one key reason it seems is the poor education and positioning of the product by the banks. “The positioning of the solution is very important,” explains Nadine Louis, Market Manager, Corporate and Supply Chain Markets at SWIFT. “Some simply see this as just a digital alternative for documentary trade. But it has more potential than that and can actually assist corporates with their open account transactions by enabling them to receive much faster financing than would typically be available.”</p>
<p>And SWIFT are seeing the solution grow in popularity, especially given its ratification by the ICC and also the BPO+ transaction that took place last year which utilised electronic documentation – provided by essDOCS – straight through, end-to-end for the first time in BPO transaction. This removed the need for data from documents to be manually entered into the SWIFT TSU, thus mitigating risk and eliminating inefficiency from the process.</p>
<p>Also rapidly gaining credence in the SWIFT portfolio is the relatively new MT798 trade envelope. “In fact MT798 is used by corporates to communicate with their banks instructions related to import LCs, standby LCs, guarantees, or export LCs, in a similar structure as used between banks with the MT7xx family messages,” says Louis. “That’s why MT798 is seen as an extension of those flows in the corporate-to-bank space.”</p>
<h3 id="growing-the-digital-ecosystem">Growing the digital ecosystem</h3>
<p>With developments like these, it would be fair to say that trade is truly beginning to be brought into the 21<sup>st</sup> century and that there will continue to be a concerted effort by industry moving forward. But as we have already explored, financial services alone cannot drive the digitisation of trade. There are numerous other parties that also need to be brought on board.</p>
<p>Regulators therefore will play a big role in driving the acceptance of digital trade globally. That being said, despite the talk, there remains no concerted effort to bring the world’s regulators together to agree on a single set of principles and standards that will define how a digital trading ecosystem will work.</p>
<p>A disparate landscape will continue to exist adding complication for corporates and those delivering digital solutions. And whilst it may still remain difficult to trade digitally in emerging markets, there are countries, such as Australia, Canada and Singapore, with its ‘smart nation’ concept that are looking to push ahead.</p>
<p>The increasing regulatory burden on financial services more broadly may however accelerate the digital agenda. “Reacting to regulation is a challenge and you can sometimes feel that you are always behind the curve,” says BoAML’s Batliwalla. “But they are a reality of doing business and it is more prudent to focus on the opportunities these create. Digitisation can help financial services meet the standards of the regulators around areas such as know your customer (KYC), anti-money laundering (AML) as well as more broadly reduce systemic risk.”</p>
<p>Away from regulators, corporates themselves have a vital role to play in driving the digitisation of trade. “A lot of what we are doing is still around education,” explains Bolero’s Kerr. “It is about growing an ecosystem and once one corporate adopts a digital solution and the benefits around increasing efficiency, removing cost and risk are made obvious to those companies in its ecosystem, they may then adopt and it will continue to spread.”</p>
<h3 id="a-brave-new-word">A brave new word</h3>
<p>As we have explored, there are many things that corporates can use today that can help them digitise their flows. But, the promise of digitisation doesn’t stop at just making what we do today more efficient and effective. It actually provides the chance to go back to the drawing board and start thinking about not just how to make what is done today more efficient, but also how it can be done differently.</p>
<p>Distributed ledger, the internet of things (IoT) and big data are all areas that banks and other players are currently experimenting with. Distributed ledger, out of all of these, perhaps provides the most potential, in respect of creating a platform that can piece together all the disparate parts that make a trade transaction happen and in turn create a visible and secure chain of events that can go a long way to removing risk from the process. The recent Qingdao scandal for instance – where warehouse receipts were used to borrow loans from banks against a single deposit of metal – probably wouldn’t have occurred should the distributed ledger have held all the documentation and transaction flows.</p>
<p>Yet to corporates, the distributed ledger still largely remains a theory, rather than a reality. And despite banks working on solutions there is still little information around what these entail and how they plan to be commercialised.</p>
<p>The IoT is another, perhaps even more ambitious, area that the industry is beginning to explore. And it may be that in the future every item contains a chip with its own IP address that allows all parties involved in the transaction to track the movement of goods and thus automate the financial flow – perhaps utilising the distributed ledger – alongside this. “This will provide full visibility over the flow of goods and finance in a transaction,” says Kerr. “The risk can be reduced and so can pricing as a result.”</p>
<p>HSBC’s Ramachandran concurs. “There is an untapped opportunity to merge physical and financial supply chains and provide financing earlier into the system,” he says. “At present, traditional supply chain finance is dominated by post shipment financing. But, with this extra visibility there is a real chance to bring pre-shipment financing into the equation.”</p>
<p>Despite the promise of these areas, there are few that are brave enough to say exactly how this will all develop. And BoAML’s Batliwalla issues caution: “Whilst it is important to focus on these cutting edge technologies, we must not lose sight of the fact that there are corporates today with real challenges that banks can help to solve,” he says. “As an industry we must have two parallel areas of focus: namely how we can add value today, as well as how we can transform the industry in the future.”</p>
<h3 id="the-third-dimension">The third dimension</h3>
<p>And looking to the future there may be technology that will more broadly transform the world of trade and how it is conducted. As previously mentioned, no longer is trade defined by the physical movement of goods and services, it is also defined by the flow of data around the world. And according to a recent report by McKinsey, the value of data flows added $2.8trn to the global economy in 2014, slightly more than the $2.7trn traded in goods.</p>
<p>Few would argue that this trend will not continue, and it may even grow at a greater speed as the development of 3D printing accelerates making it a real possibility for companies to completely re-define their supply chains and how these operate. And for some market leading companies this is already happening. The Mckinsey report highlights that General Motors is using 3D printing to make fuel nozzles for jet engines and expects the aviation unit to be manufacturing 100,000 parts using the technology by 2020.</p>
<p>“This has the potential to fundamentally change what our clients do,” says HSBC’s Ramachandran. “It will be these trends that shape the digitisation of trade and trade finance in the future, rather than the streamlining of traditional trade flows. And it poses many new questions to corporate treasurers with regard to how they manage the financial flows that accompany this movement of data and the technology that will facilitate this.”</p>
<h3 id="moving-ahead">Moving ahead</h3>
<p>Given all these developments, it would be fair to argue that after much delay, the digitisation of trade is truly upon us and that it will be the next five years that will shape how this space will play out.</p>
<p>Of course, there remain numerous hurdles that must be overcome, especially in regard to entire trade ecosystem coming together to decide on an agreed set of standards that will define how the digital era of trade will operate. But it is certainly an exciting time, and one that will pose numerous new opportunities, as well as challenges to treasurers, who must not only stay abreast of what they can do to help streamline their trade flows today, but also be prepared for the potential changes in global trade that may take place in the years to come.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[A long time coming]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Nov 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=75320BAA8506EF82C52645BC684945B4]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=57BE7344BA0EF6A6D5D98EC25009ED8F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EC02EFAFA624901B7226390A6A13FCA4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AD832750BE579A793C5FD42B55B48B1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=0622B1F5F737C6E8C95B94F35405FAD9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EBB4579DE0097B437548CB18792091BC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Vintage pocket watch" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=75320BAA8506EF82C52645BC684945B4" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/stockphotovintagepocketwatchandhourglassorsandtimersymbolsoftimewithcopyspace791115461920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=75320BAA8506EF82C52645BC684945B4"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>Adopting e-invoicing could bring great benefits not only to treasuries in terms of improved working capital metrics but in greater efficiencies right across the corporate organisation too. Onboarding suppliers is no walk in the park, however. To make it work, all internal stakeholders – and the procurement team especially – need to be onside.</em></p>
<p>Already, some industry commentators are billing 2016 as a watershed year for e-invoicing in Europe. Perhaps we shouldn’t be too surprised. Last year was also predicted to be the year that sending electronic invoices became mainstream; as was 2014 and, well, nearly every year all the way back to 1997 when the EU and the OECD launched the very first initiatives aimed at eliminating barriers for e-invoicing.</p>
<p>History therefore tells us that it might be sensible, this time around, to avoid bold, hyperbolic predictions about 2016 being ‘a seminal year’ for e-invoicing. But even if universal acceptance remains some way off, there are a number of compelling reasons why e-invoicing should see increased uptake in the year ahead – providing, it should be added, that corporate buyers can finally overcome that thorny issue of supplier onboarding.</p>
<p>Unbelievably, this is the issue that, despite years of attention, corporates continue to cite as their greatest impediment to rolling out e-invoicing. A study conducted earlier in 2015 by Tradeshift is but the latest addition to a growing list of evidence supporting this point. The research found that while 76% of businesses had e-invoicing or were making plans to implement it, only 19% said that more than half of their suppliers were using it.</p>
<p>It stands to reason that if corporates cannot encourage a greater percentage of their supplier base to use e-invoicing, the paper invoice will continue to prevail. Going on estimates from e-billing and payments specialists Billentis, an organisation could save 1-2% of its turnover by replacing paper invoices with electronic invoices and optimising the related processes: the missed cost and efficiency savings that failure would represent for corporates could be very significant indeed. The good news, at least, is that there are no shortage of ideas – from both treasurers and solutions providers – on what can be done to make greater supplier uptake a reality.</p>
<h3 id="because-its-the-law">Because it’s the law</h3>
<p>We will talk more about those in a moment. Before we do, let’s turn our attention to the principal macro-level driver now for e-invoicing uptake across Europe: legislation. These regulatory drivers for e-invoicing broadly fall into two categories: direct and indirect.</p>
<p>Firstly, e-invoicing has been directly addressed both by national regulators (Norway, Denmark, Sweden and Portugal, for instance) and, more recently, at the supranational level by the European Commission (EC). The EC Directive, which was approved by the European Council in 2014, follows the example set by the aforementioned national regulators, by requiring public authorities in Europe to support e-invoices sent to them, on the condition that they comply with common standards also set out in the legislation.</p>
<p>“Many countries now mandate electronic invoicing,” says Markus Ament, Chief Product Officer at cloud-based supply chain finance and e-invoicing providers Taulia. “Global companies come to us and tell us that they now have to comply with e-invoicing legislation in various countries. So compliance is a very big driver at the moment.”</p>
<p>Legislation mandating e-invoicing in public procurement has been complemented by the work being done by the OpenPEPPOL Association, an international non-profit body whose purpose is to solve interoperability issues for public procurement. As Richard Manson, Director and co-founder of e-invoicing providers CloudTrade explains, e-procurement processes have traditionally tended to be based on a three corner model in which buyers and their suppliers needed to enter into a relationship with the same solution provider.</p>
<p>“That made interoperability a challenge,” Manson says. Under the four corner model established by OpenPEPPOL, suppliers have a relationship with access points, the aim of which is to establish something much like a telephone network, where the existence of different phone networks does not prevent telephone calls being made between networks. “That is what PEPPOL is really all about; it is allowing suppliers to send to buyers that are on the PEPPOL network, irrespective of what service provider they are with. And it is allowing buyers to receive invoices from buyers on the PEPPOL network, irrespective of what service provider they are with.”</p>
<p>PEPPOL has already been successfully applied to public procurement with a number of Scandinavian countries, and it now looks as though other countries – including the UK – will soon follow suit. When the Department of Health (DoH) announced its eProcurement strategy in May 2014, for example, a recommendation was made for the adoption of PEPPOL specifications throughout the healthcare sector for e-ordering, e-invoicing and advanced shipping notes. Alongside legislation to make e-invoicing mandatory for public procurement, this development might just propel the use of electronic invoices to the same levels we see in Scandinavia. “By mandating this in the public sector and getting suppliers to send and receive electronic documents, they will by implication create an infrastructure that can be used in the private sector as well,” Manson says. “That is the strategy, and in my view, it is a sensible strategy.”</p>
<p>In the indirect category, attention is being given by a growing number of regulatory bodies to the issue of small companies whose clients fail to pay on time (a practice which has been on the receiving end of much censure in the mainstream press of late).</p>
<p>Already there are a number of schemes in place in different countries. We have the Prompt Payment Code in the UK, the EU Late Payment Directive and the SupplierPay initiative in the US, all aimed at creating a culture of reasonable – and responsible – payment terms amongst corporates. And there could be further measures moving forward; as it stands, participation in the UK’s Prompt Payment Code is voluntary, but the idea of making it compulsory for all companies has been recently mooted by ministers.</p>
<p>Naturally, using e-invoices sent instantly via the internet, and often with payment options embedded in the file, would be very likely to help suppliers to retrieve money more quickly from their buyers. And that is even before taking into account the additional services that some Fintech vendors (Taulia among them) are now offering as part of their e-invoicing solutions to clients.</p>
<h3 id="persuading-suppliers">Persuading suppliers</h3>
<p>The key ideas taken up by some of the new providers that have entered into the e-invoicing space in recent years is relatively simple, yet it has the potential to help both corporates meet their obligations vis-à-vis on time payments and, smaller suppliers in terms of alleviating pressure on their working capital metrics. They could also, by virtue of that, play a critical role in tempting those still reticent suppliers to start invoicing electronically.</p>
<p>One explanation frequently used to explain why onboarding has in the past been difficult is that some SME suppliers simply do not enjoy any significant benefit from e-invoicing, at least in the way it has traditionally been practised. It often comes down to the frequency by which an SME sends invoices to a corporate customer. When invoices are being sent at a very low frequency – say one or two each month – very little efficiency is to be gained by moving from manual to electronic. So when the first e-invoicing platforms began to appear in the late 1990s with business models predicated on charging suppliers for a service that was of ultimately little value, interest was, understandably, muted at some companies.</p>
<p>Even when explicit charges are not a factor, many providers still require invoices to be produced and sent as an XML or EDI file that, for some suppliers, would entail costly and difficult changes to billing applications and infrastructure that their budget and invoice volumes simply cannot justify.</p>
<p>New vendors that have emerged in recent years, such as CloudTrade, for example, have experienced some success (in 2014 they were reported to have doubled in size for the second consecutive year), simply by offering such suppliers a “cheap and undemanding” alternative. CloudTrade requires PDF invoices to be sent via a technology even the smallest and least sophisticated business should have access to: email. When a PDF is created by an application – for example, finance or accounting package – in almost all instances it will be a text PDF with the invoice data embedded within the layers of the PDF. The data is mapped by CloudTrade and delivered to the buyer in the format that is required by their system. “If you remove those barriers then you will see higher adoption, because ultimately you want to make it as simple and as non-disruptive as possible for suppliers to join the party,” says Manson.</p>
<p>If making e-invoicing easier and less expensive solves part of the problem, offering suppliers stronger incentives for sending e-invoices is perhaps the next step. If the e-invoicing service is provided free of charge and, critically, is offered as a means by which suppliers can gain better access to financing, then the reasons for suppliers not choosing to move away from paper are suddenly all but non-existent. After all, supply chain finance (SCF) and e-invoicing would seem to be mutually reinforcing.</p>
<p>“Quite frankly, many new clients today come to e-invoicing through SCF solutions,” says Taulia’s Ament. “They look at the market for SCF solutions and see that their approval cycles are not ready yet. So why not do electronic invoicing at the same time? That way they can get the approval cycles down and have a successful SCF programme.”</p>
<p>So now, even suppliers for whom e-invoicing does not offer, in itself, greater cost savings or efficiencies, by serving as the foundation for a supplier financing or dynamic discounting programme it can still be an enabler to greater cost savings and efficiencies. If SCF continues to gain momentum globally – it is now growing at 30% annually according to a 2015 report by BCR Publishing – then we may just see greater uptake of e-invoicing too, especially now there are free-at-the-point-of-use solutions available on the market for suppliers. But, as we will see, treasurers have an important role to play in ensuring suppliers are aware of such solutions and understand the benefits. This is where cross-functional collaboration becomes important.</p>
<h3 id="working-with-procurement">Working with procurement</h3>
<p>Often the decision to roll out an e-invoicing programme comes from the area of the business that most obviously stands to benefit from it: the treasury function. But the success of the supplier onboarding process will, to an extent, be determined by the level of support it receives from other business units (procurement in particular). Treasurers that are not able to get other relevant departments involved at an early stage are likely to struggle.</p>
<p>In a webinar hosted in early 2015 by Shared Services Link and the Tungsten Corporation, Mark Boswell, a Procurement Business Process Manager at confectionary giants Mondelez International explained why this is the case, and what steps treasurers can take to bring other departments like procurement onside.</p>
<p>“Why should you involve procurement?” asks Boswell. The answer, of course, is that they are the department which can be of most assistance when it comes to supplier onboarding. “In most organisations, procurement is the commercial link to the supplier base. So they are the ones that can nominate and convince vendors to sign up.”</p>
<p>That buyers will be automatically receptive is not guaranteed though. “Don’t bother me with invoice issues,” buyers are often heard to say, “just pay my vendors on time.” Even those who were prepared to listen would still lament the long list of other priorities in their in-trays that must take precedence. What Boswell soon began to appreciate was that for the procurement departments to be recruited as an ally in the roll-out of e-invoicing, programmes need to be articulated to them in a language they understand.</p>
<p>“You need to listen to procurement’s needs,” Boswell says. “They need to know where they can be expected to be involved. I’ve often gone to our buyers across the community and asked, what do you want and what are your issues?”</p>
<p>What procurement needs, above all, is a compelling reason to be involved. There are no shortage of these, says Boswell. For instance, e-invoicing can cut days or even weeks off the time that it takes to deliver an invoice cross-border to a remote location, eliminating the need for procurement to scan paper invoices and attend to the instant errors that might crop up. Even more beneficial to procurement, perhaps, is that their suppliers are given instant feedback on the status of any invoices that they send. “We tell them not only if we have received it,” says Boswell, “but if there are errors we articulate back to them through the portal what those errors are. Then we guide them to take proactive action if those errors are to do with the presentation of their invoice, for example.”</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom quote-block" style="">
<blockquote>Paper-free supplier-invoicing may not be universal yet, but it will be one day.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Ensuring that these advantages are understood within the procurement department’s senior leadership team is a first step but is not usually sufficient in itself. In order for procurement to become an effective partner in supplier onboarding, the message needs to cascade down until it is embedded in the company’s various sourcing teams. “I think one of the key things is that we have sourcing teams that are e-invoicing champions and who are able to drive that change and be the catalyst of change throughout the procurement organisation,” Boswell says.</p>
<p>Also found to be beneficial was segregating the different sourcing areas, including ‘direct’ suppliers where they source packaging, raw materials, commodities, and those which fall under the indirect category such as marketing, manufacturing, and IT. Doing this allowed the company to get targets defined that were specific to those teams. “We get the buy-in at the top, we set targets aligned through the organisation. Ultimately that makes the implementation a lot easier with the teams at the bottom of the pyramid,” adds Boswell.</p>
<h3 id="bold-predictions">Bold predictions</h3>
<p>What we have, then, are a host of factors that would suggest that e-invoicing should see greater take-up in the year ahead, even amongst suppliers who would in the past have proved difficult to onboard. Governments in Europe and beyond are taking a much more active role in encouraging firms to explore electronic alternatives to the paper invoice, in some instances going so far as to legislate to this effect. And all of this is happening right at the time when (thanks to both the launch of new solutions and the lessons treasurers are increasingly learning around the importance of cross-functional collaboration) supplier onboarding does not present quite the same obstacle it did once in the not too distant past.</p>
<p>Taking all of this into account, do those bold predictions referred to at the beginning of this article make any more sense than in previous years? Will 2016 be the seminal year in which businesses completely dispose of all paper-based invoices for good? Most probably not. But, realistically it should, like the past several years, be one in which the electronic invoice continues to win over more of those previously hard-to-onboard suppliers that have so long been a blight on corporates looking to optimise their invoice-to-pay (I2P) processes. Paper-free supplier-invoicing may not be universal yet, but it will be one day.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: E-invoicing]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: May 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“Given the drive towards green business practice, is e-invoicing a technology that corporates in Asia should be embracing? If so, what recommendations can be made about successfully adopting e-invoicing solutions? Also, are there any specific developments in this space for treasurers to be aware of?”</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="James M. O’Neill, Senior Analyst, Banking Group, Celent" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2015-05and06-tta-03-qa-james-oneill-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=209238246716CFD72977A0B4E9B35965" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">James M. O’Neill</h3>
<h5 class="title">Senior Analyst, Banking Group</h5>
<h5 class="org">Celent</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>While e-invoicing has been introduced in Asia with varying degrees of success over the past ten years or so, with the resumption of normal trade activities since the global banking crisis in 2008 and the near-completion of the ASEAN Economic Community (EC) programme during this coming year, now is as good a time as ever for corporates to examine opportunities for greater adoption of e-invoicing technologies.</p>
<p>As a group, the ten countries that make up the ASEAN EC enjoy an aggregate market size (in GDP terms) that exceeds three of the four BRIC countries, and while progress to date has been focused on the creation of a free trading zone within the ASEAN EC region, several bilateral trading agreements have been reached or are in process of negotiation within the greater region. Today, the European Union (EU) is the ASEAN EC’s third-largest trading partner after China and Japan, and several individual member states have already negotiated bilateral trade negotiations with the EU. It is simply a matter of time before the ASEAN EC builds on these bilateral agreements to conclude block agreements with the EU and other important trading partners.</p>
<p>In this context, e-invoicing becomes an important strategic tool for Asian corporates that wish to take advantage of the new opportunities afforded by these free trade agreements. The UN Economic Commission for Europe has noted that e-invoicing in Asia is at a “nascent” stage, pointing to factors including the lack of a regulatory framework, a lack of industry standards, concerns regarding tax implications, and an overall lack of coordination amongst participants in the regional supply chain.</p>
<p>This is a regrettable situation for Asian corporates as trading partners in remote locations within Europe and North America are further along the way in terms of trade automation. In fact, some larger companies require their trading partners to send and receive critical information including invoices electronically. For the Asian corporates themselves, e-invoicing provides an opportunity to create efficiencies and reduce trading costs at several steps of the trading process. By linking billing systems directly to their accounting systems, corporates can reduce invoice preparation time, better ensure invoicing accuracy, and dramatically reduce the time of invoice delivery while also greatly improving delivery accuracy.</p>
<p>The leading corporates employ e-invoicing solutions that have real-time integration with their accounting systems, allowing invoicing to take place as soon as the goods or services have been delivered rather than having to wait for accounting personnel to manually push invoices to their trading partners. Ultimately, e-invoicing is part of a wider electronic ecosystem whereby both suppliers and customers are linked as well as the various banks involved in the clearing and settlement of funds relating to these trading relationships.</p>
<p>For Asian corporates who wish to benefit from the general uptake in regional trading that is expected to take place as the ASEAN EC vision becomes a reality, the time for upgrading to modern billing and collections processes is now.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="John Pierce-Jones, Head of E-Invoicing, Technology, Fundtech" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2015-05and06-tta-03-qa-john-pierce-jones-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=8FE9800C80E38730851CAF70BDBE9F07" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">John Pierce-Jones</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of E-Invoicing, Technology</h5>
<h5 class="org">Fundtech</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>Electronic invoicing is growing in Asia, setting a trend that will continue into the future. Corporates in Asia can look to electronic invoices not only for greener business practices, but also as an opportunity to eliminate the cost and inefficiencies of paper-based invoices, ultimately leading to more efficient processes within the treasury for more efficient payments. Each year, corporations worldwide send and receive millions of invoices and bills. Manual processing of these invoices is not only slow and error-prone, but also costly. Furthermore, inconsistencies in invoice formats from country to country can cause inconvenience for cross-border and global corporations. Customer demand for electronic invoicing is also on the rise, with many looking for digital versions of their invoice data for direct input into their accounting systems.</p>
<p>E-invoicing and e-billing systems centralise all of the components of this process to facilitate communication, dispute management, auditing, and reporting all in a single system. This eliminates the manual labour and costs associated with printing, mailing, archiving, and reconciling paper invoices. Potential for benefits in Asia is expected to manifest similarly to Europe where, according to a 2014 Billentis report of the public sector, savings could be €40bn. However, today less than 10% of invoices in Europe are electronic, signaling immense opportunity.</p>
<p>For corporates that speed up the billing process for receivables by sending their invoices electronically rather than on paper and then manage them online, instant delivery together with query management tools can lead to faster settlement and reduced Days Sales Outstanding (DSO).</p>
<p>Furthermore, standardised billing across all regions ensures the customers of corporates benefit from the same invoicing format and same level of service in every country; something of particular value for corporations that do cross border and international business. The opportunity to post invoice data on a central hub and make this information available to all customers online empowers them to monitor, track, search, and query their invoice and payments status.</p>
<p>On the Accounts Payables (AP) side, corporates can accept supplier invoices in any format straight into their e-invoicing hub which reduces manual input, eliminates errors and helps to drive down costs. There is also the option for AP departments to make an instant switch from paper to electronic by utilising a ‘Paper-to-Data’ service. Whether a company processes invoices by mail, email, EDI or other electronic channel, the data is captured, validated to agreed business rules, approved by nominated users and finally uploaded to an ERP or accounting system. Getting the invoice approved more quickly maximises the opportunities for taking advantage of Dynamic Discounting or Early Payment Discount schemes.</p>
<p>Treasurers may then also consider implementing more automated workflows and online payment options to streamline processes further. The added ease of billing or invoicing can contribute significantly to relationship satisfaction between the corporate and its customers and trading partners. While environmental issues remain important drivers, the move away from paper is being further accelerated by legislative and regulatory changes with 13 countries in Asia either having already mandated or intending to mandate electronic invoicing following government initiatives.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="Amit Sharma, Managing Director, Head of eCommerce and Channels Asia Pacific, Global Transaction Services, Bank of America Merrill Lynch" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2015-05and06-tta-03-qa-amit-sharma-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=2D8B6F1E961A0ED7B9594410F1B977C2" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Amit Sharma</h3>
<h5 class="title">Managing Director, Head of eCommerce and Channels Asia Pacific, Global Transaction Services</h5>
<h5 class="org">Bank of America Merrill Lynch</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>As is the case with numerous digital initiatives in the Asia Pacific (APAC) treasury management space, e-invoicing is a work in progress amongst the region’s corporates. It is however an industry migration that we have great confidence in and we believe adoption will grow. Aside from clear efficiency and risk management advantages, we see the added benefits of e-invoicing as consistent with the greener business practices embraced by forward-thinking corporations regionally.</p>
<p>However, for e-invoicing to transition from niche usage to mainstream treasury practice, several moving parts need to converge. Sending invoices electronically to the customer is one piece of the puzzle. Ensuring confidentiality and security is another pivotal consideration, and brings various parties into the wider picture. Hence, at the transaction level, the invoice issuer, receiver, processor, auditors (internal/external) and internal IT teams must play a role for e-invoicing to gain traction in APAC.</p>
<p>At the most immediate level, challenges exist on the audit front. In our conversations with clients, it is clear that internal corporate audit teams must be geared to accept electronic invoices and that this part of the process is a challenge that still needs to be broadly resolved. Furthermore, there is the mind-set battle across the treasury function whereby shifting attitudes from ‘pushing paper’ to ‘clicking data’ requires a wider acceptance from various internal and external parties. Also, concerns such as fraud, duplicates and authenticity remain open issues within many discussions around e-invoicing.</p>
<p>So what are the short-term solutions? In our view, the success of e-invoicing will rely heavily on the adoption of digital signatures. There are several factors underscoring the importance of digital signatures in the broader e-invoicing picture. Firstly, the relationship between invoicing and tax implications must be considered. This is especially true given that there are restrictions in Asia governing digital delivery of invoices in several markets. For example, China and India either have specific guardrails around e-invoicing, or in the case of the latter, do not permit the practice at present. As a result, many corporations have taken to sending a PDF copy of the e-invoice to their customers to perform digital scanning and improve the AP process via the PDF invoices. In parallel, they also send the physical copy of the invoice. With practices such as the aforementioned processes common in the market, we take the view that a legal framework governing digital signatures would have the potential to better protect participants and drive e-invoicing adoption.</p>
<p>The good news is that progress is clearly being made on the digital signature component. In Thailand and the Philippines, electronic invoice presentment and Payment (EIPP) is quite popular and the local banks are hosting the EIPP platform, and mainly providing distributor/dealer financing. However, this is still not addressing the end-to-end requirement of eliminating the need of sending paper invoices in these markets, unless there is a legal framework, to say the invoices hosted out of the EIPP platform can be downloaded by the customer as the true cope of the invoice. Moreover, if governments can start to adopt business to government (B2G) invoicing this is still not addressing the end-to-end requirement of eliminating the need of sending paper invoices in these markets and requires a more defined legal framework.</p>
<p>Once the digital standard of the invoice is agreed, ERP vendors will then embrace the platform and provide standard integration. This is the trend in EMEA where governments are adopting e-invoicing as standard which has ultimately led to the market quickly embracing it. From a long-term perspective, we take the view that to have an agreeable industry standard for transmitting the invoices in a digital format support is needed by suppliers, buyers, banks, technology providers will help increase the take up of e-invoicing. In APAC, there is still plenty of work and consideration at the government level to be done, but the right moves are clearly taking place. One thing is crystal clear though, only partnership across business functions will ensure the success of the APAC e-invoicing drive.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“What value do banks’ Know Your Customer (KYC) processes really add for corporates? And how will utilities help to improve the KYC process for treasurers? Also, I have heard talk of a growing trend around Know Your Customer’s Customer – what impact will this have for corporates operating in Asia?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[The shipping forecast]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Mar 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=420&usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&hash=C4532B25FEA515B1ED00BAC45CEA9775]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=30D87A64FE3B2C90E7835C7D265E7B98"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=40FCCC2B795CEF8868DAF8CBFF82DE4B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D2EF3DF8A3803765305743E4FB1DAD63"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=37132609F0F241136BD12F08796A2633"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6ACE94ED670A7E38357BB8B85209AA2E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Tugs pushing a ship" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C4532B25FEA515B1ED00BAC45CEA9775" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/tugs-pushing-a-ship-ss-65749798.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C4532B25FEA515B1ED00BAC45CEA9775"/></picture> </div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>Paper documentation has been the mainstay in the trade space for a very long time. But in recent years the conversion to a digital format of some elements has taken place. Is paper really on its way out?</em></p>
<p>Overseas trade has for many hundreds of years relied upon a full set of documentation to ensure the dispatch, shipping, offloading and receipt of goods by the paying customer. Such a requirement is unlikely to change dramatically, however, the form of that documentation certainly will. Currently the trade world is shifting from paper to electronic and in doing so is ushering in an era of vastly improved administrative efficiency, security and accessibility. The problem is that it is taking the industry a long time to let go of paper.</p>
<h3 id="why-not-drop-the-paper">Why not drop the paper?</h3>
<p>In theory, the preparation, dispatch and receipt of electronic documents facilitates cost savings and process efficiencies whilst reducing the potential for fraud. Back in 1997, Professor Paul Todd from the Law School at Southampton University wrote a paper in which he asserted that “it is much easier to dematerialise non-negotiable shipping documents, such as waybills, than it is to dematerialise the negotiable bill of lading, since it is necessary to send only information by a computerised system, rather than proof of title.” Professor Todd concluded in his paper that “it is possible, on the basis of existing technology and under the existing legal framework, to replace bills of lading by electronic documents, which can in principle afford to the parties security at least as great as existing paper documents.” He did however accept that changes may be required in some states to the rules on personal data protection, admissibility of computer-generated documents in court, and the transmission of encrypted data across national boundaries.</p>
<p>That was almost two decades ago. Today, the issues with digitisation of trade documentation are not just legal. There is also a persistent perception that electronic documents are somehow less secure than paper and that they are open to abuse by hackers and other cyber-criminals. Of course, there is an element of vulnerability with all electronic systems but those who hang onto this argument might like to consider the following. In 2014, an investigation was launched at Qingdao port in China around a private metals trading firm suspected of duplicating paper warehouse certificates in order to use a metal cargo multiple times to fraudulently raise financing. And a statement issued in December 2014 by the International Federation of Freight Forwarders Associations (FIATA) warned its members to be on the lookout for forged ‘master bills of lading’. A number of these paper documents had recently been presented to a consignee’s bank for payment, the documents “indistinguishable from the paper originals.” Paper has very little in the way of security.</p>
<h3 id="where-are-we-now">Where are we now?</h3>
<p>With this in mind, it is worth looking at the general state of play in the world of trade documentation. A trade conference in Singapore in August last year saw representatives of US food processing company, Cargill, and Australian mining company, BHP Billiton, take to the stage to discuss the use of electronic presentation (ePresentation) and electronic bills of lading in the export space. Back in December 2012, BHP Billiton was part of the first-ever fully electronic presentation of LC documents in mainland China, with partner the Sichuan Emei Ferroalloy steel mill and its receiving bank, China CITIC Bank (ANZ was BHP’s advising bank). Today, both BHP and Cargill are fully committed to ePresentation and Singapore session moderator, Ian Kerr, CEO of multi-bank trade solutions platform, Bolero, says the joint presentation “was really a call to action of the industry for the adoption of new technologies.” The general agreement on stage was “it is time the industry moved to electronic systems.” A few weeks later, at a trade conference in Beijing, speakers from China Minmetals, the Agricultural Bank of China, National Australia Bank and Bank of America Merrill Lynch’s global trade office for Asia Pacific gave a similarly enthusiastic pitch for the adoption of ePresentation by importers and banks. If major industrial players want it and banks want it, what is the hold up?</p>
<p>Kerr admits that it will require “alignment of all involved parties” before real growth is seen, not just in Asia but right across the globe. Until then, he says, the whole suite of ePresentation in trade can only be as fast as its slowest constituent. Unfortunately, it is often the demand by local customs and excise officials to see a paper document that prevents progress. Notwithstanding certain entrenched local practices, inroads into digitisation have been made in some countries, for example, there has been progress with certificates of origin used in agri-business, veterinary or export health certificates used when shipping livestock, and the Shipper’s Export Declaration for export control of items over a certain value (the latter is now known as an Electronic Export Information Filing). “It’s about gaining momentum,” he states.</p>
<p>As progress is made there has been more activity in terms of thoughtful solutions offered by the key players, particularly infrastructure providers such as SWIFT, Bolero and Essdocs.</p>
<h3 id="main-offerings">Main offerings</h3>
<p>Essdocs dates back to 1986 in its first incarnation as the Seadocs (Seaborne Trade Documentation System) project and was the first significant attempt to use electronic documentation for goods carried by sea. It never got beyond the trial stage and in any case, according to legal expert, Professor Todd, no provision was made for the transfer of contractual rights and liabilities to holders of the bill, apart from the original shipper. This made it “fatally flawed” contractually. Fast forward several years and with the problems ironed out, Essdocs claims to be the largest electronic bill of lading network globally (it says it is being used by more than 2,100 companies across 65 countries: the latest Asian banking signatory announced late last year was Agricultural Bank of China).</p>
<p>Rapidly gaining credence is the relatively new MT798, SWIFT’s trade envelope aimed at de-risking open account trading. It is basically a means of carrying the range of MT7xx trade messages used to initiate import letters of credit (LCs), standby LCs and guarantees, or to receive export LCs. The MT798 transfers large documents from corporates to banks via FileAct, with FIN messages allowing corporates to communicate with the banks on both sides of a trade. SWIFT reported in June last year that 11 corporates and 27 banks had adopted MT798 messaging.</p>
<p>As a key infrastructure provider, SWIFT is in a natural position to engage with the trade sector and also offers the Bank Payment Obligation (BPO). This “irrevocable payment undertaking” delivered by banks was first used back in 2012 by BP Chemicals’ Global Credit Manager, David Vermylen and his trade partners at Oman-based PET manufacturer, Octal, and Standard Chartered. It has since gained a degree of traction in the Asian commodities trade sector. In October 2014, UniCredit Bank and its correspondent bank, Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi, processed the first BPO deal ever between Germany and Japan, taking the total number of banks processing BPOs to 14. The UniCredit deal covered a transaction between German industrial mixer firm, RVT, and Mitsui Plant Systems (MPS) in Japan.</p>
<p>It is worth noting that the BPO struggled to get any traction until its rules of engagement, held in the SWIFT domain, gained unanimous approval in April 2013 from the International Chamber of Commerce (ICC) Banking Commission. André Casterman, Head of Corporate and Supply Chain Markets at SWIFT told Treasury Today at the time that the rules underpinning BPO “should be independent from our technology and legally binding so that counterparties can resolve potential disputes, should those arise.”</p>
<p>Another interesting provider of e-commerce solutions for the international trade finance community is eLCY. This is an independent vendor offering an auction site for the confirmation of LCs and direct corporate risk, and a multi-bank portal that enables the secure transmission of approved trade-related instructions and messages. Similarly, Global Trade Corporation (GTC) is a software firm providing multi-bank trade finance solutions for core elements such as LCs, guarantees and documentary credits and collections.</p>
<h3 id="the-possibility-of-full-stp">The possibility of full STP</h3>
<p>“In a perfect ePresentation scenario, the exporter would ship the goods and apply for an electronic bill of lading to be issued by the carrier, with which the exporter would transmit the necessary documents electronically to the presenting bank,” suggests Gabriel Sham, Director GTS Product Head Trade Services Asia at RBS. “The presenting bank would check the documents against the relevant LC and forward the documents electronically to the issuing bank, which would in turn check the documents to ensure compliance with the terms and conditions of the LC before making the payment. The issuing bank would then forward the documents electronically to the importer, who would use the documents for obtaining clearance of the goods.” Throughout the transaction, he adds, the various parties would log into the same platform for access to the documents and for forwarding the documents to the next party.</p>
<p>For the buyer or importer, digitisation offers the opportunity to negotiate extended payment terms using dynamic discounting, says Sham. “This is because the buyers, usually multinational companies with better credit ratings than their suppliers, can use ePresentation or BPOs to leverage their lower cost of capital and provide financing to the suppliers.” In return, they may ask for better payment terms or a reduction in the cost of goods.</p>
<p>For the seller or exporter, a BPO lessens the non-payment risk “because the seller or exporter takes on the risk of a bank instead of the buyer.” With the BPO, the risk of discrepancy dispute and the costs associated with it are removed as data is matched automatically without manual checking of documents.</p>
<p>“Whether ePresentation or BPO, the immediate benefit is a reduction in turnaround time, which, depending on the payment terms, might mean that the buyer or importer is required to pay sooner,” notes Sham. “However, the buyer or importer can also benefit by the timely clearance of cargo without the need for an LOI (Letter of Indemnity).” LOIs are intended to allow delivery without a bill of lading. They tend to be seen as problematic by trade insurance bodies such as the International Group of P&amp;I Clubs, largely because there have been a number of fraudulent uses of these paper documents over the years.</p>
<p>Despite the obvious advantages, the reality of today’s trade documentation is that paperless solutions are not deployed everywhere. Dermot Canavan, Head of EMEA Trade Products for RBS, feels that treasurers have many things to juggle right now and that the relatively low level of uptake of these solutions is more a matter of focus than a reflection of the products’ fitness for purpose. “There are only so many hours in a day, and they have to look at where they are going to get the biggest bang for their buck,” he suggests. But he adds that there is also “a degree of inertia” to contend with and a reluctance to invest in new systems. “Banks are looking to make ePresentation or the BPO more accessible at a low cost of investment,” says Sham. “However, while we can educate customers on the benefits and when to use them, the onus remains with corporates to decide when to adopt.”</p>
<p>With credit risk being now of paramount importance to just about every party, improving trade confidence is a persuasive argument for treasury action, especially where using the BPO, for example, can increase end-to-end security and potentially open new markets, notes Canavan.<br/></p><h3 id="digital-law">Digital law</h3>
<p>If the law cannot always be relied upon to secure the transfer of goods when using a digital replacement for a bill of lading, it seems provident that the document itself should offer its own means for the transfer of contractual rights and liabilities. Sham notes that the providers of the Bolero and Essdocs platforms have set up internationally recognised legal frameworks based on a common user agreement to enable such a transfer. SWIFT messages issued in line with the appropriate central bank guidance also have a legally binding effect on the sender.</p>
<p>“Every party on Bolero signs up to our framework but there is no point in having a trade mechanism unless there is a legal framework to support it,” says Kerr. Back in 1996, when Bolero was a fledgling company, it commissioned a “significant number of leading law firms” to carry out what it says was “one of the most comprehensive studies into the use of electronic documents in global trade across multiple jurisdictions”. The study covered the major legal systems in common use. This included English Common Law, US Common Law, German/Dutch Law and Napoleonic Law as well as Mixed Jurisprudence systems (as found in Japan, for example), and also those of Emerging Jurisdictions such as in China.</p>
<p>It used the results of its tests of legal feasibility to form the basis for the Bolero Rulebook and governance of the title registry. This legally underpins its entire technical operation and is binding on those parties who have agreed to be bound to it. The rulebook is administered by Bolero members but crucially is fully compliant with ICC’s eUCP (Uniform Customs and Practice for Documentary Credits).</p>
<h3 id="gaining-traction">Gaining traction</h3>
<p>The level of appetite among Asian corporates to adopt full ePresentation generally depends on whether the corporate is an exporter or an importer, and on the volume of transactions, notes Sham. There is a cost involved in terms of supporting software and architecture and the cost/benefit decision lies in the hands of the individual company. However, he adds, digitisation is gaining momentum in the region. “We are seeing the concept of digitisation gaining traction with large companies in the mining and commodities sectors,” says Sham. “With more focus on operational and working capital efficiency, the interest in electronic trade documentation is gaining momentum and we could soon see more documentary flow of this kind between Western and Asian businesses.”</p>
<p>Spurred on by the success of China CITIC Bank and BHP Billiton (as mentioned above), in June 2013, Bank of China (BoC) and Agricultural Bank of China (ABC) executed their first fully electronic, end-to-end LC transactions, followed soon after by Industrial and Commercial Bank of China (ICBC). Since June 2013, the Bolero platform has been used in China for a number of commodity transactions, including a major iron ore deal for the Shagang Group and a $21m deal for Yanggu Xiangguang Copper Co. Ltd, the largest ePresentation deal to date by one of China’s Big Four. In January 2015, Switzerland-based ferroalloy distributor, RFA International, announced that it was moving from paper documents to ePresentation, via Bolero, to serve deals between its production units and clients at steel mills and larger foundries in 60 countries across Asia, Europe, the Americas and Africa.</p>
<p>ePresentation is the foundation that allows these deals to take place. As such deals increase in number, Bolero’s CEO, Kerr, whilst not predicting a paperless world anytime soon, does envisage a “tipping point” which will be driven by the corporates and banks “buying into the benefits.”</p>
<p>With some documentary forms clearly in advanced stages of digitisation and others needing to catch up, full STP in the trade space is not yet a reality. As Professor Todd stated in his work almost 20 years ago, it has been possible to partially dematerialise and to keep paper documentation for some purposes for some time. But, he added, doing half the job seems pointless once the reality is grasped that there is nothing that paper can do that computerised documentation cannot. “If you are going to dematerialise, dematerialise totally.” That argument, it seems, has still not gone away.</p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: E-invoicing evolution]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Jan 2015 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“I’ve recently heard talk about e-invoicing being integrated into supply chain finance platforms. Is this really happening? Also, what other developments in the e-invoicing space should treasurers be aware of?”</em></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="Matthew Stammers, European Marketing Director, Taulia" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2015-01-tt-01-qa-matthew-stammers-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=B2A0BF862166F1D98FD632CDE458B373" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Matthew Stammers</h3>
<h5 class="title">European Marketing Director</h5>
<h5 class="org">Taulia</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>There is a revolution starting to happen in supply chain finance (SCF). What was previously an elitist programme between businesses, global banks and the very largest suppliers, is shortly to become a democratised process between a business and all of their suppliers because of what e-invoicing brings to the party.</p>
<p>Initially, SCF was a bank-led initiative that was developed in order to help large multinational corporations improve their working capital KPIs. For these large companies, it worked well within this narrow remit. However, the solution has always promised so much more, and in this format the benefits were limited, in so far as that it would only work for a company’s top 25 to 100 suppliers. This was primarily due to the regulatory constraints on the banks – as the providers of the SCF programme – surrounding KYC, anti-money laundering and also in more recent times Basel III. The on-boarding process with suppliers was therefore very arduous, and the costs outweighed the benefits when companies were looking to on-board all but the very largest suppliers onto their SCF programme.</p>
<p>The new generation of SaaS based e-invoicing platforms, however, are game changers as they approach the subject from a very different perspective. These providers approach SCF and e-invoicing from a supplier-adoption approach, where the most important aspect is getting as many suppliers on the platform as possible. This is vital because without a critical mass of suppliers using an e-invoicing platform to send, receive, and process invoices, a business doesn’t have a viable project. The ‘DNA’ of these SaaS-based vendors is therefore driven by this supplier adoption approach.</p>
<p>Traditionally the benefits of using an e-invoicing solution include increased automation, accuracy and efficiency. It is a useful tool to improve a business’s accounts payable processes. However, it is not a game changer in this guise. Where e-invoicing starts to get really exciting is when it’s used to enable and underpin a dynamic and electronic trading relationship between a business and its suppliers. The core feature of e-invoicing is that it connects a business with the majority or all of its suppliers. This network can then be used to offer early payments to these suppliers.</p>
<p>How so? This can either be through utilising excess liquidity or, if the working capital position is sensitive, through the injection of third-party financing – what was previously known as Supply Chain Finance. And because the goal of an e-invoicing network is to connect a business with all of its suppliers, financing opportunities are now available to the whole supply chain, not just the top 25-100 largest suppliers.</p>
<p>The primary benefit, therefore, from such a solution is that it resets the relationship between a company and its suppliers, allowing corporates to strategically approach the management of their supply chain. For example, a company can utilise the strength of its credit rating to offer third-party affordable financing to all its suppliers, thereby strengthening the health of a supply chain. Or the treasury function can utilise excess liquidity to fund early payment in exchange for a discount, reducing a company’s Cost of Goods Sold (COGS). From a treasury perspective, this offers an opportunity to step beyond its usual remit and be involved more deeply in the strategic goals of the organisation. Of course, using a SaaS service offers corporates other operational benefits through using the cloud, including: full visibility, real-time information, quick on-boarding and set-up, enhanced security, cost savings on resources and continually updated software.</p>
<p>The SCF and e-invoicing space is one that is constantly evolving and the current incarnation of SaaS providers have removed all of the barriers that have historically prevented widespread adoption. There are other exciting developments in this space that providers like ourselves are beginning to realise surrounding the use of big data. There are now years of supplier trading history on a provider’s servers and by using analytical tools built into the platforms this can be analysed, looking at areas such as risk and credit worthiness. This creates a powerful analytics suite that can allow corporates to model scenarios based on what suppliers have been doing and are likely to do.</p>
<p>All in all, the benefits of e-invoicing and SCF are becoming increasingly strategic and vital to corporates – creating a very attractive solution.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<div class="copy__body"><!-- BOXED -->
<div class="vcard" style="min-height:150px;">
<img alt="Venkatesh Somanathan, Asia Pacific Head of Trade Finance Product Management, Global Transaction Banking, Deutsche Bank" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/trade-digitisation/2015-01-tt-01-qa-venkatesh-somanathan-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=9C3145B9497C346D9B0A2FF2FD3DE716" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Venkatesh Somanathan</h3>
<h5 class="title">Asia Pacific Head of Trade Finance Product Management, Global Transaction Banking</h5>
<h5 class="org">Deutsche Bank</h5>
</div>
<!-- BOXED --></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>The trends that we are currently seeing around invoicing, and e-invoicing in particular, are dovetailed into a wider trend surrounding what corporates expect from their banking partners. Corporates now look to banks to offer more than their ‘traditional’ payments and financing functions and expect them to address some of the challenges that they face in other areas. It is here that an opportunity lies for banks to reinforce and ‘retool’ in order to meet the developing needs of corporates.</p>
<p>It is as a result of these new requirements that developments such as integrating e-invoicing solutions into supply chain finance (SFC) platforms take place. This integration is part of a greater effort to ensure that corporates can have an automated end-to-end solution across their supply chain. At the heart of this is the auto-matching capability that automatically reconciles a corporate’s purchase order with a supplier’s shipment documents. Once this reconciliation has taken place, a payment file will then be generated on the electronic platform used for supplier financing.</p>
<p>E-invoicing can also be introduced into this process so that when a purchase is made, all parties can reconcile the various documents and generate an invoice to the buyer, which can then be matched against the order and shipment details. Once this automated process is completed, corporates can quickly and seamlessly conduct the next phase of payment and financing.</p>
<p>This solution can offer corporates numerous benefits, primarily due to its integrated nature, which means that treasurers will not have to duplicate work and enter the same information multiple times on various platforms, thus offering greater efficiency and also reducing errors. Another benefit is the increased visibility and control over the transaction across its life span that a treasurer can have. Finally, with a greater number of companies using shared service centres (SSCs), electronic solutions are becoming increasingly vital as they allow for cost savings through reduced investment in resources, infrastructure, software and technology.</p>
<p>Currently, we have a number of clients using this solution. These are the most advanced multinationals with very large supplier bases. Yet, I believe it is possible that one day this solution could be adopted by smaller corporates. There are, however, a number of challenges that must be solved before this can become a reality. The first challenge is that any corporate wishing to utilise this type of solution must have the technical capabilities, as must the suppliers in their supply chain. Secondly, there are still some markets – such as China and India — where local regulations limit the use of such solutions, although there are steps being taken to change this. Finally, current e-invoicing and supply chain finance solutions are primarily bundled in with a bank’s propriety platform. However, corporates have multiple banking partners. Therefore, there needs to be a bank agnostic platform. It is my belief that going forward, BPO transactions will help to facilitate and develop the external requirements for e-invoicing, creating a universal bank agnostic platform.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">TT comment</h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">E-invoicing in 2015</h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>According to e-invoicing expert Bruno Koch of Billentis, 2015 may well be a seminal year in the development of e-invoicing, with many countries around the world making the practice mandatory.</p>
<p>In January 2015, a further group of taxpayers in Ecuador will be required to support e-invoicing joining companies from the financial service industry, exporters and telecoms industry who adopted the technology last year.</p>
<p>There will be further developments in Central and Eastern Europe too. In Germany, the Ministry of Finance has released new legislation that is relevant for e-invoice processing and storage. From 2015, e-invoicing and VAT e-administration will become mandatory in the Ukraine. Elsewhere, in Slovenia, all domestic suppliers to the public sector will be required to send only electronic invoices to public administrations from January 2015.</p>
<p>In Southern Europe, changes are also afoot as e-invoicing will become compulsory in some large market segments in Spain. The change comes after many years of debate and the mandate covers invoices issued by certain suppliers of goods and services to the Spanish public administration. This will be live early 2015.</p>
<p>With such developments on the horizon, it is likely that e-invoicing will become an increasingly important agenda item for corporates, creating many opportunities for efficiencies. Treasury Today will keep readers informed about vital developments in this space.</p></div>
</div>
<div class="v-spacing--bottom highlight-block">
<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question</h2>
<div class="copy__body"><p><em>“What is the state of play with the Payment Services Directive 2? What will the major changes be? And what do I, as the treasurer of a European company, need to think about in relation to the PSD2?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
	<node>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Digitisation]]></category>
		<title><![CDATA[Pushing the boundaries of e-trading]]></title>
		<publish_date><![CDATA[ Published: Oct 2011 ]]></publish_date>
		<hero_image><![CDATA[]]></hero_image>
		<complete_body><![CDATA[<div class="gs-grid__col gs-grid__col-1-10 gs-grid__col--expand" style="">
<div class="hero hero--article spaceing">
<div class="hero__heroarticle__img-wrap">
</div>
</div><div class="v-spacing--bottom">
<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<div class="copy__body"><p>As the use of e-trading platforms continues to grow, a new e-solution has just been launched by Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets. More than just a trading venue, Arena offers the bank’s clients access to a full range of tools, economic research and analysis designed to help them formulate and execute their hedging strategies.</p>
<h3 id="the-rise-of-online-trading">The rise of online trading</h3>
<p>For the past few years, significant volatility in the <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> market has made currency management a higher priority than before for many multinational corporations. With companies looking more closely at how they mitigate <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> risk, the use of e-trading platforms has mushroomed. Corporations have gradually expanded the way in which they use this technology: whereas eight years ago companies used to talk about using e-channels for their smaller transactions only, today larger transactions are also being executed via e-platforms. Indeed, research published in 2011 by GreySpark Partners and Best Execution indicated that over 60% of <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> deals are now conducted online – and predicted that this figure will reach 90% by 2014.</p>
<p>E-trading platforms offer a number of benefits over the conventional voice-based model, including faster execution speeds, lower transaction costs for <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> providers and greater competition in the market as traders compete to offer the best prices. In addition, <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> platforms are providing the industry with greater transparency of the flows going through the market. This increased visibility has given <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> providers a better insight into how the market operates – which can lead to more effective risk management and ultimately to better prices for clients.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the anticipated impact of recent regulatory initiatives has the potential to make electronic trading even more attractive to clients. “We are looking very closely at the regulatory developments and are very aware that they are likely to shape the services we offer; particularly in the clearing space”, says Rob Garwood, Head of <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> Sales at Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets. “As regulatory changes become more transparent, they will be an important consideration as we continue to develop our service offering to all our client segments.”</p>
<p>Against this backdrop, the latest e-solution to come to market is Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets’ Arena. Launched in September 2011, Arena is an e-trading platform with a holistic attitude: in addition to <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> and money market deal execution, the platform provides access to a wealth of Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets information, including proprietary economic research, market commentary, interactive charting and risk analytic toolkits. Reputable market data and live news are also being provided from well known third-party sources.</p>
<h3 id="development-process">Development process</h3>
<p>“Arena is aimed at our commercial, mid-market and major corporate clients as well as hedge funds, banks, central banks, asset managers, wealth managers, insurance companies and private equity fund managers,” says Garwood. Arena has been developed with a close eye on the needs of these diverse user groups. A crucial element of Arena’s development was a year- long consultation process, which included a series of workshops in which representatives from different client sectors discussed their requirements with the bank’s IT development, sales and marketing teams.</p>
<p>“I think those sessions were particularly useful because they became quite open forum discussions,” says Garwood. “Although many of our customers came in with preconceived ideas about what they needed, they left the discussions with a better idea of what they actually needed, because they were able to hear views from other companies in the same peer group. In essence, Arena is a product built by the customers for the customers.”</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="arena-development-process">Arena development process</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2011/10/2011-10-tt-11-pp-diagram-01-arena-development-process.png"><img alt="Arena development process – Treasury Today" height="217" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2011/10/2011-10-tt-11-pp-diagram-01-arena-development-process-t.png" width="300"/></a>
</figure>
<h3 id="features-and-functionalities">Features and functionalities</h3>
<p>In catering for diverse client sectors, it is important to offer functionalities that will suit each of these sectors. The consultative workshops helped to identify the different needs and priorities of the different client segments. While all clients using the e-portal require access to prices and research, the ways in which these are used can vary considerably. Whereas a hedge fund might be primarily looking for fast prices, the corporate treasurer may prioritise economic research and risk analytics. Accordingly, Lloyds has focused on developing a solution which offers a wide range of tools, functionalities and information sources. The bank’s clients have the opportunity to customise their view of Arena on an individual basis by deciding what tools, modules and information they wish to access and how these will appear on their screen.</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="arena-functionalities">Arena functionalities</h5>
</figcaption>
<a class="enlargeable" href="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2011/10/2011-10-tt-11-pp-diagram-02-arena-functionalities-screenshot.png"><img alt="Arena functionalities diagram – Treasury Today" height="176" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2011/10/2011-10-tt-11-pp-diagram-02-arena-functionalities-screenshot-t.png" width="300"/></a>
</figure>
<p>Some interesting tools and functionalities provided by Arena include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5><abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> trading</h5>
<p>Arena allows users to trade in more than 50 currencies, from majors to a broad range of emerging markets. Spot, forwards, swaps and time options are available. Features include the automatic calculation of broken date <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> trades and customisable dealing limits for users.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Money markets</h5>
<p>Money market deposits can be placed in 19 currencies, with a range of tenors from one day to a year, and various settlement options are available.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Trade blotter</h5>
<p>This tool allows clients to view the status of all trades conducted with Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets – including voice trades as well as trades executed through Arena. <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr>, interest rate, inflation and commodity trades can be viewed individually or on a consolidated basis and can be exported to Excel.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Technical analysis</h5>
<p>Clients have access to a userfriendly system which draws upon real-time and historical data of up to ten years with direct access to the bank’s London-based technical analysis team.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Price alerts</h5>
<p>Users can set up price alerts which appear as a pop-up. A significant number of currency pairs can be selected.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Risk analytics</h5>
<p>These toolkits enable clients to tailor technical market analysis for foreign exchange and interest rates, covering for example volatility, spread, correlation and historical analysis.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Economic research and insight</h5>
<p>Users of Arena can access reports, video briefings and updates provided by the respected Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets’ economics team, led by Trevor Williams, Chief Economist. This includes daily economic updates, monthly exchange rate and interest rate forecasts with detailed analysis of UK and global economic issues. Live news is also available from a well known third party.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="case-study">
<h2 id="case-study">Case study</h2>
<h3 id="arena">Arena</h3>
<div class="people vcard">
<figure class="portrait left"><img alt="Portrait of Rob Garwood" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2011/10/2011-10-tt-11-pp-rob-garwood-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h4 class="fn">Rob Garwood</h4>
<h5 class="role">Head of <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> Sales</h5>
<img alt="Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets" class="logo" height="25" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/lloyds-bank-corporate-markets-logo-2012-120x25.png" width="120"/>
</div>
<h5 id="what-were-lloyds-bank-corporate-markets-goals-in-developing-arena">What were Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets’ goals in developing Arena?</h5>
<p>Lloyds has provided foreign exchange e-commerce facilities for its corporate clients for many years now. We realised though that as our business grew our clients needed a more sophisticated platform that would cover a broader range of product areas. In that sense one of our aims was to bring as many client services into one venue as possible. Today, Arena is not just an <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> execution platform but a tool for money markets, research, strategy and risk analytics and we are working hard to add further services by year end.</p>
<h5 id="what-are-the-advantages-of-coming-to-the-market-relatively-late">What are the advantages of coming to the market relatively late?</h5>
<p>I think an advantage of developing a sophisticated platform now is that user requirements are much better defined today than they were five or six years ago. We have been able to bring an industry leading product to market in an incredibly short period of time. Our clients are more knowledgeable about what their real needs are and our system developers have been able to match those needs in an efficient and focused manner.</p>
<h5 id="which-features-of-arena-are-of-the-greatest-interest-for-corporate-treasurers">Which features of Arena are of the greatest interest for corporate treasurers?</h5>
<p>Client needs do vary from one corporate to another. For instance, many of the major corporates we spoke to valued our economic research and our execution platform in equal measure. For mid-market and commercial clients execution mattered but was not as important as the risk management information and suite of risk analytic tools available through Arena today. The beauty of Arena is that the client is able to prioritise those interests so that their desktop view displays just the content they want to see.</p>
<p>Clients can also access Arena’s very user-friendly charting system for analysis of real-time and historical rates, or specific currency pairs, and of course there’s direct access to the expertise of the technical analysis team based in London. The corporates that we speak to are largely sterling-based and so will have a primary interest in our cable and euro/sterling views. Additionally, clients are not just looking at the currency markets today but also other asset classes such as gilts and equities, for example. So our technical analysis is useful as it covers all these product areas.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, our clients’ business, and therefore their exposures to emerging markets, have been increasing dramatically. We are therefore heavily focused on developing appropriate research, strategic idea generation, risk management information and pricing in this area. At the end of the day our aim is to match these services to the needs of our clients.</p>
<h5 id="given-the-time-constraints-experienced-by-corporate-treasurers-is-well-filtered-information-a-particular-priority-for-them">Given the time constraints experienced by corporate treasurers, is well-filtered information a particular priority for them?</h5>
<p>Yes, absolutely. The filtering process is key and this is an area that we have worked hard on. The idea is that clients will be able to filter specific information, whether it’s at a specific currency or geographic-macroeconomic level, or by specific industry sector or asset class. We’ve arranged this so that at level one you are looking at pricing and general economic research; at level two you might be looking at another part of the site which would help the client generate ideas – for example, the risk analytics toolkits and customised economic research. Clients can use these resources to generate ideas about how to manage their own <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> exposures more effectively. So the funnelling effect takes the client from the broad information set, narrowing down to the specifics that they wish to discuss – and they can communicate with us either using our chat facility or over the phone.</p>
</div>
<h3 id="future-developments">Future developments</h3>
<p>Arena has been developed using a modular framework which is intended to make future development of the platform as straightforward as possible. “We’ve designed the platform to be modular so that in the future Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets can develop specific areas of Arena that are of particular interest to our clients,” comments Garwood. “Some areas need much more continuous investment than others – for instance pricing. Delivering a price sounds simple, but there are always demands on latency and on making the delivery of the price pre-trade, at-trade and post-trade as efficient as possible. The modular aspect allows us to look at price specifically so that we can be as efficient as possible when we transact with our clients.”</p>
<p>The recent release of Arena is just the first step in what promises to be an ambitious and versatile product. During the course of 2012, the transaction banking elements of the platform will be enhanced. Besides <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> trading functionalities there are plans to offer Scottish Widows investment products on the platform and cash flow analysis and liquidity management features will be developed further. Additional asset classes including vanilla interest rate derivatives are also due to be included at a later date.</p>
<p>“In addition to <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> trading, as the platform is developed further we aim to offer the full range of liquidity management products to our clients.” concludes Garwood. “Not many banks do this, which is surprising. Our aim has always been to bring client products and services into one venue.”</p>
<div class="profile">
<h3 id="are-you-seeing-the-views-that-matter">Are you seeing the views that matter?</h3>
<p>More than an <abbr title="Foreign Exchange">FX</abbr> and money market deposits trading platform, Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets new e-solution Arena offers insight, analysis, reporting and trading – all in one single, customisable view.</p>
<p>There’s a wealth of research from our respected team of economists, so whether you need a better view of macroeconomic developments or a specific currency or sector, you’ll find the information you need. Live, streaming news feeds from well known third-party sources also brings you up-to-date market data.</p>
<p>With the capability to customise the Arena interface, you’ll only get the data you want and when you want it, so you’ll always get the best view of the markets you’re interested in. That doesn’t just apply to the market data and insight, but the display of the trading modules and other applications Arena offers, such as customisable rate alerts, a dynamic trade blotter, risk analytics and charting tools. Visit <a href="http://www.lbcmarena.com" target="_blank">www.lbcmarena.com</a> for more details.</p>
<p class="cf"> </p>
<img alt="Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets logo" class="logo" height="25" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/lloyds-bank-corporate-markets-logo-2012-120x25.png" width="120"/>
</div>
<div class="disclaimer">
<h5 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h5>
<p>The information in this article (“Information”) does not constitute or form part of any offer to sell or an invitation to subscribe for, hold or purchase any securities or any other investment. The Information shall not form the basis of or be relied on in connection with any contract or commitment whatsoever. The Information is not intended to form, and should not form, the basis of any investment decision, and is not and should not be treated as investment research, a research recommendation or advice. Readers should conduct their own independent enquiries and obtain their own professional legal, regulatory, tax or accounting advice as appropriate. Any transaction which a reader of the Information may subsequently enter into may only be on the basis of such enquiries and advice, and that reader’s own knowledge and experience.</p>
<p>While reasonable care has been exercised in preparing the Information, no representation or warranty, express or implied, is made as to the accuracy, reliability or completeness of the facts and figures contained therein by Lloyds TSB Bank plc, Lloyds TSB Scotland plc, Bank of Scotland plc, their group companies or any of their directors, officers, employees, associates and agents (altogether, “Lloyds Bank Persons”). The Information has not been independently verified by any Lloyds Bank Person and is subject to change at any time. To the fullest extent permitted by applicable law, regulation and rules of regulatory bodies, Lloyds TSB Persons accept no responsibility for and shall have no liability for any loss in relation to the Information, however arising.</p>
<p>Lloyds Bank Arena is a registered trademark of Lloyds TSB Bank plc. Lloyds Bank Corporate Markets, Lloyds TSB Corporate Markets and Lloyds TSB are trading names of Lloyds TSB Bank plc, Lloyds TSB Scotland plc and Bank of Scotland plc. Lloyds TSB Bank plc. Registered Office: 25 Gresham Street, London EC2V 7HN. Registered in England and Wales no. 2065. Lloyds TSB Scotland plc. Registered Office: Henry Duncan House, 120 George Street, Edinburgh EH2 4LH. Registered in Scotland no. 95237. Bank of Scotland plc. Registered Office: The Mound, Edinburgh EH1 1YZ. Registered in Scotland no. SC32700. Authorised and regulated by the Financial Services Authority under registration numbers 119278, 191240 and 169628 respectively.</p>
</div></div>
</div>

</div>]]></complete_body>
	</node>
</data>
