<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Supply chains in crisis: treasury’s response]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>The semiconductor and auto industries encapsulate the challenges companies face in their supply chains. The ability of companies to access vital components that go into making their products was tested during Covid and has now grown even more complicated because of Russia’s invasion of Ukraine. Expect buyers to do more to support their suppliers, more nearshoring and the emergence of corporate winners and losers.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=944A8EA81380B23036597AEC91F4D0A5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=ABABD9100B81EC93D02410BEA00050AC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A60984D36F563EC4DA38D88D8380003B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5848654C5ABF399EF22FDA9A4D0233ED"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=969FCC2153EC6A5B067DD4671136DC6F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Cargo ship leaving dock at sunrise " class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B751B8EA04E27A7073A391EE4F059E74" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B751B8EA04E27A7073A391EE4F059E74"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Last year around half of the global supply of neon, the colourless, odourless gas that goes into manufacturing semiconductors, came from Ukraine. A by-product of the steel industry, two companies, Ingas and Cryoin, based in war-ravaged Mariupol and Odessa respectively, supplied semiconductor manufacturers around the world until the Russian invasion disrupted their role in the industry’s complex supply chain.</p>
<p>The car industry, which like semiconductors depends on a globalised supply chain where outsourced manufacturing capabilities feed key factories, is also struggling because of the war. Around 17 specialist factories in Ukraine manufacture wiring harnesses used to group and guide the 1km long snake of cables inside a vehicle that form a key part of a car’s electrical system. Now disrupted production from Ukraine has impacted European car companies including VW and Porsche’s ability to source the vital component. Elsewhere, the food industry is going to have to find alternatives to the tonnes of corn, wheat and oils it sources from Ukraine’s breadbasket, and global agriculture will have to turn elsewhere for its fertilisers.</p>
<p>Today’s supply chain issues don’t come out of the blue. <a href="/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/chip-maker-infineon-talks-treasury-strategy-ttia">Semiconductor manufacturers</a> begun diversifying their sources of neon after Russia annexed Crimea in 2014, and one of the biggest corporate lessons from the pandemic when borders suddenly shut was around diversifying suppliers, building stock buffers and preparation. However, war in Ukraine has accelerated supply chain risks beyond procurement and logistics divisions, leaving treasury teams playing a pivotal role shoring up supply chain finance programmes by ensuring privileged buyer status, and building capacity as nearshoring and onshoring trends gather steam. “For most companies, the direct impact of the war on their business is limited,” says Emmanuel Bulle, Head of EMEA Research at Fitch which estimates only ten to 15 of the 200-odd EMEA corporate issuers it rates have over 25% direct exposure to Russia via sales and EBITDA. “Companies’ main exposure is indirectly via their supply chains.”</p>
<h4 id="visibility">Visibility</h4>
<p>Supply chain transparency that extends down the chain to reveal companies’ Tier Two and Tier Three suppliers has become key to shoring up production and safeguarding against a hit on revenues. For instance, Ukraine-based suppliers to European auto manufacturers may still be able to service their main clients but their own smaller suppliers may no longer be in business. Visibility is essential to ensure OEMs can accurately assess their requirement for buffers and leeway and understand if supply chain issues will just manifest as a slowdown in production – or require more drastic action like moving production. Visibility of suppliers’ payment terms allows treasury teams to see the time lapse between ordering, receiving and payment of those components and gives a window into the financial strength and liquidity of suppliers.</p>
<p>Visibility also plays into another emerging theme: buyer support. With operational payables and receivables data on-hand, companies can delve deeper into their supply chains and wider ecosystems to firm up and stabilise the weakest points with financial support, aware that suppliers favour buyers who are able to provide better terms. Buyers can change payment terms, particularly prepayment, or pay suppliers early. Elsewhere, visibility allows treasury to see if invoices have been approved, and act quickly to pay suppliers rather than let approved invoices sit unpaid in their treasury system.</p>
<p>In another trend, some treasury teams are using surplus liquidity to provide early payments in support of stressed supply chains, notes Alexander Mutter, Managing Director, Head of Enterprises EMEA at Taulia, where research finds supplier demand for early payment has trebled in recent years as suppliers request support accessing liquidity. “Early payments are a way companies can focus their liquidity. Automated processes mean all approved invoices get paid by the buyer earlier and straight through. Or companies can choose to have invoices funded by selecting individual invoices on a fully digitised and integrated working capital platform which can be funded by banks, or the buyers, to bridge the gap in the chain,” he says. Having to temporarily adjust payment terms with suppliers was among the top three most effective supply chain finance optimisation strategies, according to a recent quarterly Economist Impact Report.</p>
<p>It is an analysis endorsed by Fitch, where Bulle also notes that large buyers have grown increasingly wary of the risk of smaller, unrated suppliers short on working capital and unable to refinance, impacting their supply chain. Buyers now see that it can be in their interest to come to the rescue with better payment terms and financial support off the back of their high credit rating, he says. “Large companies’ ability and need to support their suppliers is increasingly apparent in our analysis and reviews. We have seen a few large corporates rolling out more supply chain finance programmes in a reflection of the need to support suppliers. If a supplier comes under financial stress, buyers are offering better financing terms.”</p>
<h4 id="technological-solution">Technological solution</h4>
<p>Technology is key to visibility and treasury’s ability to support suppliers. It involves centralising accounts payable and receivable (AP and AR) to eliminate duplication across separate locations. Centralisation also improves the business’s negotiating position across branches and reduces errors and the risk of missed payments. Effective supply chain management requires overarching dashboards and sweeping business network solutions, adds Mutter. He advises storing information on data and flows alongside raw material pricing and currency and interest rate costs, enabling treasury to manage cash flows and risk together. “Treasury can link their entire network or ecosystem via one platform,” he says. “Many treasurers or solution providers only think on a contractual basis or counterparty basis, but treasury should adopt a network approach, mindful of relevant entities on their purchase and sales side and build connectivity to operate as needed.”</p>
<p>Elsewhere, treasury teams are using electronic invoicing to facilitate faster finance requests. This solution reduces the time to generate bills, deliver statements and invoices, and resolves any disputes, thereby improving efficiency. International logistics group DHL recently used the e-invoicing services of Tradeshift, a cloudbased digital B2B network and supply-chain management platform to onboard 50% of its vendors within eight months, enabling them to process 21,000 e-invoices per month, up from 12,000-15,000.</p>


<blockquote><p>Early payments are a way companies can focus their liquidity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Alexander Mutter, Managing Director, Head of Enterprises EMEA, Taulia</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h4 id="nearshoring">Nearshoring</h4>
<p>In another trend, the argument for nearshoring is becoming more compelling for treasury. Many industries already reap the benefits of Tier One suppliers, building factories next door to their biggest OEM customer, explains Dominic Tribe, Director, at supply chain consultancy Vendigital. “In the car industry, manufactures build, say, seats on the same day which then go on a conveyer belt into the manufacturing facility,” he describes. A jump in the cost of freight plus tariffs and duty, means that manufacturing in China is not necessarily a cheaper option, particularly for companies paying to ship bulky components. Although sourcing certain parts of a supply chain from Asia will remain cheaper – even with rising container shipment costs and tariffs – treasury and procurement teams are increasingly looking at their supply chains on a case-by-case basis, exploring the financial impact of onshoring or nearshoring, says Tribe.</p>
<p>Still, onshoring holds a range of treasury challenges. The costs like labour and overheads may increase if the company moves production to a different country. It will mean treasury teams will need to decide whether they pay their suppliers more going forward, pass the costs onto their customers or if it’s preferable to swallow it in their margin.</p>
<p>Nor will it ever be possible to re-shore all production because some components like semiconductors are only manufactured in specific countries – the UK doesn’t have any semiconductor manufacturing capability. Other manufacturing processes rely on a highly skilled labour force that is more difficult to relocate than capital equipment. Wiring harnesses are a good example, says Tribe. “They are complex to manufacture, requiring skilled manual labour and when being fitted to vehicles, the weight and size makes them difficult to install and are one of the first components to go into a car once the chassis is built. The process can’t be automated and involves skilled labour.”</p>
<p>Experts also note that the capital cost of moving production can run into millions, risks duplication and involves unravelling complex ownership rights over assets. Moving production assets requires an asset register to provide clarity on whether the supplier or end customer owns the manufacturing equipment. For example, in the auto sector bespoke tools and processes used by suppliers in the manufacturing process are typically owned by the car companies. “If companies decide to move their supply chains, treasury will need a clear distinction between who owns what asset,” says Tribe.</p>
<h4 id="winners-and-losers">Winners and losers</h4>
<p>It is becoming apparent that the evolving supply chain crisis and fundamental challenge to globalisation wrought by Covid and exacerbated for some corporates by war in Ukraine will create winners and losers. For instance, shortages in high-grade nickel sourced from Ukraine and used in electric vehicle batteries is likely to disrupt and lengthen auto groups’ road maps to electrification, providing an opportunity for new groups to move into the market. “EV start-up companies like Volta and Arrival could steal market share in the short-run,” predicts Tribe. He also believes electric car manufacturers’ ability to access semiconductors (each vehicle requires around 3,500 semiconductors and missing just one can thwart the whole assembly) will also create winners and losers. “Semiconductors are not like a screw you can replace,” he says. “They are made to specific auto standards and can have controlling safety features – in most cases you can’t just swap A with B.”</p>
<p>Such is the level of crisis in the supply chain it goes well beyond prices and volatility. Some experts predict it will ultimately force companies to decide whether they can continue to secure the physical goods that go into their manufacturing process or not. “Those prepared best, will cope better,” says Taulia’s Mutter. “The longer the war in Ukraine goes on the harder the physical supply chain will be hit.” Positively, companies are stronger now thanks to cash buffers, balance sheet strength and lessons learnt from the pandemic. The enduring pressure to integrate ESG across supply chains in response to <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_22_1145" target="_blank">forthcoming legislation</a>, also means that treasury teams are better prepared for the future than they were a few short years ago.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[The semiconductor and auto industries encapsulate the challenges companies face in their supply chains. The ability of companies to access vital components that go into making their products was tested during Covid and has now grown even more complicated because of Russia’s invasion of Ukraine. Expect buyers to do more to support their suppliers, more nearshoring and the emergence of corporate winners and losers.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2022-05-06-tt-01-ia__logistics-transportation-container-cargo-ship-plane-722035285__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2022-05-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Chip maker Infineon talks treasury strategy]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>The semiconductor industry is more dependent than most on free trade and open markets. Alexander Foltin, Treasurer at European chip maker Infineon, talks about his treasury priorities and how the industry thrives on a mix of cooperation and competition.</em></p> <picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=DFA2F2C75A6B369B8533AA111D029095"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EC27AC13D9D1420016898C20C33A0C9E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CB71DA103CE80027C588C21699DCDDA7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=33EF755EDA81F630C329224E397FAFAD"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3A2366A1BAC4B0B8B7DE4A645FD37DC4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Computer Hardware Data Chip" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9FD635CAE5C0D11FBB2DAED89551B82A" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9FD635CAE5C0D11FBB2DAED89551B82A"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>Semiconductors, the brains of all modern electronics from cars and phones to new technology like the IofT and strategic 5G networks, have rarely seen such demand. Yet surging demand, accelerated by the pandemic’s impact on digitisation trends, comes against the backdrop of the industry’s vulnerability to geopolitical risk, also on the rise. US/China tension has led to the US restricting Chinese companies’ ability to access foreign-built chips – when the US cracked down on Huawei in 2019, share prices in all the big chipmakers plunged. Elsewhere, the push to re-shore manufacturing in the US and Europe shows how geopolitics can muddy complex supply chains based around outsourced manufacturing capabilities to key factories or foundries in Taiwan and South Korea. When it comes to trade skirmishes, the industry that makes the tiny components essential to our digital lives and modern economies holds all the ingredients of a key battleground.</p>
<p>“Protectionism is the very opposite of what we at Infineon advocate,” says Alexander Foltin, Group Treasurer and Head of Investor Relations of German chip manufacturer Infineon, where navigating tight supply from contract manufacturers like Taiwan’s TSMC under its outsourced model alongside its own in-house manufacturing increasingly influences treasury strategy. “We favour a globalised industry with open markets, a level playing field of fair and free global trade.”</p>
<p>Semiconductors are particularly vulnerable to protectionism, explains Foltin, who oversees a highly centralised treasury, created from scratch when Infineon was carved out of Siemens 21 years ago. A complex manufacturing chain of specialist clusters (plus chips’ high value to weight ratio) mean chips are flown around the world with processes and value added on route before they wind up in an end device.</p>
<p>European manufacturers’ strength lies in areas like power semiconductors, security and sensor technology but also in manufacturing high-end wafer equipment, while in Asia and the US key competences are in leading-edge processors, memory components and electronic design tools. Today’s market thrives under co-opetition, the mix of cooperation and competition whereby companies share a common technology pool of opensource chip architecture, and standard and software agreements are interoperable for common benefit.</p>
<h4 id="liquidity">Liquidity</h4>
<p>Keeping up with the competition and ensuring his treasury always has enough on hand to finance growth has put liquidity centre stage. “We have to be able to find the financial means of supporting our growth track,” says Foltin. “We would never bring cash down to bare operating levels. We want to have the financial freedom, especially through cycles and down phases, to proactively invest.” A reassuring nod to his belief that a certain portion of today’s tight supply is cyclical. The industry only tipped from a scarcity of demand to today’s scarcity of supply in less than 12 months, he says. “It was only a year ago that several semiconductor markets took a nose-dive.”</p>
<p>Infineon is increasingly discussing ways to make supply more resilient by sharing risks with its customers in the automotive and other industries. In part, this mirrors a trend already visible amongst Infineon’s own contract manufacturers, the first to ask for down payments from customers like Infineon. “There is an interest from foundries to share risk with their customers.”</p>
<p>Now Infineon is asking customers to commit ahead rather than rely on just-in-time delivery strategies based on their own fluctuations in demand. “We have capacity reservation agreements that we offer our customers,” he says, explaining that treasury is an integral part of these negotiations, brokering the deals, checking on the risk and most of all safeguarding the liquidity position. “If customers want to ensure against the risk of a lack of capacity, they can make capacity reservations and thus share the economic risks.”</p>
<p>Conversations with customers “aren’t easy,” but he says concerns around certainty of supply makes them constructive. “Delivery capability certainly has a value,” he explains. “If you are selling a US$40-50,000 car, to have a €4-5 component missing is frustrating. The most expensive chip is the one that halts your production.” The long lead times in chip production also means companies can’t make up the shortfall quickly. Production normally takes 12-14 weeks, but that becomes six-12 months if the firm needs to procure new machinery, assuming there is cleanroom space available. “Building new facilities is a multi-year endeavour,” he says. “In this sense, there is a certain understanding that burden sharing needs to be done.”</p>


<blockquote>Although trade finance is low risk and short-term, profits are low making scale important – difficult against the backdrop of dimmed growth.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Gianluca Romeo, Director, Banks, EMEA, Fitch Ratings</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<h4 id="credit-rating">Credit rating</h4>
<p>Against the backdrop of tight supply and uncertain geopolitics, his other treasury failsafe is easy access to the financial markets and a strong investment grade credit rating. Arranging the financing for the company’s 2019 €9bn purchase of US rival Cypress Semiconductor proved its worth.</p>
<p>Financing came via a final mix of one third equity and two thirds debt spanning two straight capital raises, a hybrid bond placement, a jumbo euro bond and one US private placement in a strategy carefully choreographed to keep the rating agency (S&amp;P Global) happy, despite the unprecedented size of the deal – half of Infineon’s market cap. “We spent a lot of time with the rating agency upfront, presenting financing scenarios to ensure our target equity debt mix would safeguard the company as investment grade.”</p>
<p>Although the rating slipped from BBB flat to BBB – when the deal closed, it was still investment grade. Since then, S&amp;P has bestowed a positive outlook on the company, indicating a road to a potential return to BBB flat. This has ensured the door was always left open to the right kind of investors at the right price, he says. “If you are sub investment grade you run the risk of markets being closed or unavailable. We have funded ourselves up to 2033.” It also meant the company could access the ECB’s bond buying programme, set up to support investment grade companies with stable funding through the pandemic.</p>
<p>The process also marked another coming of age in today’s volatile and challenging semiconductor market. Prior to the Cypress deal, Infineon didn’t have an established set of core banks providing an RCF. In a quid pro quo, the group of banks advising on the deal committed funding lines in return for the M&amp;A advisory mandate. “They had to chip in and put their money where their mouth was, guaranteeing to underwrite the initial transaction,” he said.</p>
<p>Since then, the company has syndicated out to 20 national and global institutions, initially providing committed financing across a short-term bridge facility as well as term loans out to 2024. Take-out transactions were all allocated competitively. “Normally you have initial underwriters who take the largest piece of cake, then financing is pre-allocated according to ticket sizes in the syndication,” he explains. “Following the syndication, we had all our banks on an equal footing so that whenever a refinancing came up, they could compete equally.” Although the process is more laborious for banks and treasury, it assures Infineon gets “the best service” from “highly motivated banks,” giving them a chance to “prove their worth.”</p>
<p>It’s just the kind of competitive, level playing field that plays to banks’ individual strengths that he wants in the global chip market. And one of the reasons he questions if investing billions in more manufacturing capabilities in Europe to reduce dependency on highly skilled Asian contract manufacturers would ultimately benefit. The EU has earmarked a portion of its €750bn COVID-19 recovery fund to strengthen Europe’s semiconductor design and manufacturing capabilities. Elsewhere Bosch recently received €140m in European subsidies for its new €1bn semiconductor factory. In the US, leading the re-shoring drive, plans to beef up the domestic industry have been enshrined into a new bill “Creating Helpful Incentives to Produce Semiconductors for America Act,” or CHIPS outlining plans to create a US$10bn federal grant, investment tax credits and a variety of research and development funds. Yet Foltin isn’t convinced that getting into a spending race is viable, questioning if the EU can match government incentives elsewhere. “We welcome support for a road map for the European industry, but we need sensible, intermediate steps on route to getting there.” In the meantime, it makes the arguments for free trade even more compelling.</p>
<h4 id="flip-side">Flip side</h4>
<p>Semiconductors is one industry particularly vulnerable to souring US/China relations. But the flip side of a tougher US stance on China is better US/EU trade terms, an entente recently evident at the G7 gathering in Cornwall. For example, the US and EU have just announced a five-year truce on aircraft subsidies to Airbus and Boeing which has led to billions of tariffs on their respective exports over the last 17 years. The reason, says Robert Silverman, a partner at New York law firm GDLSK which specialises in international trade and customs, reflects the new administration’s effort to work more closely with its key trading partners. It also reflects a united response to the emergence of China’s Commercial Aircraft Corp (Comac), a competitor to the two plane makers.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, he notes a pause in the threat from European countries to impose digital taxes on US tech giants and less talk of reciprocal US threats of duties on European products. “The current administration wants to be on better trade terms with the EU,” he says, adding that duties on steel products into the US from the EU imposed under Section 232 are also likely to be softened.</p>
<p>In contrast, Chinese companies importing into the US remain out in the cold, particularly vulnerable to anti-dumping duties. He estimates around two thirds of all products from China into the US are subject to 301 tariffs which are either 7.5% or 25% (depending on the commodity) and will stay in place for a while yet. “Democrats and Republicans have divergent views on many issues, but everyone wants to be tough on China,” he says. All the while China is forming its own alliances through the BRI and, more recently, via the 2020 extended Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership, widened to include an additional ten countries but not the US or EU. “This is a sign that points to the potential increase in tensions between the US and China,” warns Gianluca Romeo, Director, Banks, EMEA at Fitch Ratings.</p>
<p>In a ripple effect, Silverman says he notices more companies shifting their supply chain from China to reduce the assessment of duties. “We are seeing some movement to some of the European countries where it is less expensive to manufacture products like Poland or Turkey. But it has to be done the right way to make sure you are not still subject to additional China duties,” he says. “The pandemic hasn’t dimmed the number of US custom audits and penalty cases, and potentially high duty rate items are at the top of the list.”</p>
<p>In another trend, companies are looking more closely at their tariff classifications under harmonised tariff schedules. “Tariff provision ‘A’ might be subject to additional duties, or dumping duties, and tariff provision ‘B’ may not,” he explains. “Companies are taking time to ensure that a product is being classified in the right way.” US Customs is also on the lookout for items where duties have been avoided because of misclassification. He also notes about the possibility of valuation reductions. Most duties in the US are set at a percentage of dutiable value resulting in companies increasingly trying to lower their dutiable value. “If an importer buys from a trading company who then buys from a factory, the factory price is usually lower than the trading company price. In the US, if the transactions are set up the right way, dutiable value can be based on the factory price not the trading company price,” he says, explaining that furniture imports from China are a good example of this process in action. Duty-free up until 2018, they are now subject to a 25% rate. “Furniture importers didn’t care what the customs value was because there was no duty. Now they want to lower the dutiable value – 25% of a smaller number is less duty.”</p>
<h4 id="mind-the-gap">Mind the gap</h4>
<p>Protectionism and its impact on global trade is also one of the culprits behind crimped availability of trade finance. In 2020 a raft of important trade finance banks including ING and Natixis exited or reduced their trade finance offering. And although other players are filling the gap created by their exit, Fitch’s Romeo says demand still exceeds supply. “The free space resulting from banks exiting the market isn’t being absorbed. The consequence is reduced access to trade finance especially for SMEs; large corporates remain a target for trade finance banks.” Although trade finance is low risk and short-term, profits are low making scale important – difficult against the backdrop of dimmed growth, he says. “Protectionism is a major risk for banks with trade finance programmes. It is a main driver for banks deciding to expand their business – or disengage.”</p>
<h4 id="labour">Labour</h4>
<p>Of course, protectionism isn’t just a consequence of souring US China relations. Witness how labour unions recently complained that Mexico breached USMCA (the free trade agreement between Canada, Mexico and the US that replaced NAFTA) over labour rights in its manufacturing processes. Protectionism also includes sanctions. Russia and Iran, which together account for a large slice of the global population, are both excluded from free trade agreements. Elsewhere, protectionism is a consequence of nationalism. Brexit jettisoned bilateral agreements and has led to new duties and costly customs paperwork for fraught UK companies exporting to Northern Ireland – within their own country. <a href="https://treasurytoday.com/treasury-practice/strategic-treasury/brexit-pandemic-recovery-and-the-importance-of-cash-ttia">The global and freewheeling semiconductor</a> industry is both particularly vulnerable to protectionism, and because of its strategic importance, in danger of feeling its wrath. Any change to the backdrop of free trade and open boarders that have allowed the industry to flourish would be detrimental. “When you reduce protectionism you have GDP gains, less corruption and improved competition,” concludes Romeo.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[The semiconductor industry is more dependent than most on free trade and open markets. Alexander Foltin, Treasurer at European chip maker Infineon, talks about his treasury priorities and how the industry thrives on a mix of cooperation and competition.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-07-08-tt-ia__silicon-wafer-hardware-data-processing-background-1928734808__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2021-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Supply chain risk in China]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=4CAB72403569BA625A505D6C63E74D04"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F8BE8C56F291623B661F4FCCDA38CA25"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=328DA1E20775710D5018B9F27DF1FE0D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=86546786452130BB8C1C308DC03E2AA4"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=D7EB222FE1C94D19D619B230F3BA6315"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Shipping containers at Hong Kong port" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFC7B4676E747219B6C72C5B58445B00" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFC7B4676E747219B6C72C5B58445B00"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<p><em>“To what extent is COVID-19 and the strained US-China relationship is causing companies to rethink their supply chains.”</em></p>



<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Portrait of Ker Gibbs, President, The American Chamber of Commerce in Shanghai" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__kers-amcham__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FE75BF4BBAF7DA18A07A4504714B13F3" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Ker Gibbs</h3>
<h5 class="title">President</h5>
<h5 class="org">The American Chamber of Commerce in Shanghai</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Some companies are thinking about moving their supply chains out of China, but it is not dramatic. According to our recent survey, only a small number (15%) of US businesses are considering moving some of their production outside of China. Everyone is paying attention to geopolitics, but any shift in supply chains should be seen in the context of rising labour costs and the fact that China is no longer a low-cost producer, rather than rising US China tensions.</p>
<p>For those companies that are moving their supply chain, the top destinations are SE Asia, India and Mexico – the US is way down the list.</p>
<p>However, the issue that jumped out when we asked companies to name their biggest challenge is US China tensions. This tension is particularly hurting companies’ ability to hire and retain staff at their Chinese operations. This is disturbing given that they regularly cite not having the right people to run their businesses on the ground in China as a key challenge.</p>
<p>US companies are more optimistic about doing business in China with a Biden presidency. Under Biden they believe there will be more consistency on policy, and hope that a new administration will be less combative. But people are not naive about the reality of the US China relationship and understand that the underlying issues have not gone away.</p>
<p>There will be a certain amount of decoupling in key areas like the semiconductor sector and dual use military technology as a direct result of policy. It will be increasingly difficult to navigate export controls in key areas wherever technology is concerned. But I believe these areas will remain isolated.</p>
<p>Our members have located in China to serve the Chinese market. They are in China, for China, in a clear distinction from the old model where companies made things in China for export to the world. Today’s supply chains are more complex, and many companies do their final assembly in China using inputs sourced from elsewhere.</p>
<p>We believe our members will continue to invest in their Chinese supply chains. China is the only major market fully open for business – COVID has been controlled and business is quite good. US businesses located in China are feeling more optimistic and are increasing their capacity to take advantage of the consumer market.</p>
<p>One new issue on the agenda is the dual circulation economy. Beijing’s new economic strategy lays out the idea that the country will continue to expand domestic production for exports while also shifting the economy towards a greater relative emphasis on production for domestic consumption. Our members are concerned how Chinese polices could shape the idea of dual circulation, and the role of foreign investment in dual circulation.</p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Portrait of Jack O'Sullivan, Founder, Modmo.io" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__jack-modmo__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6395EE8DD120E4D50C59601C001B6F45" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Jack O'Sullivan</h3>
<h5 class="title">Founder</h5>
<h5 class="org">Modmo.io</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>I tried to develop my company from Ireland, but found it was challenging managing the supply chain and production from home. I travelled to Shenzhen in China to meet some factories and suppliers, hoping to make real progress. However, as a small company at the time, we weren’t able to get the meetings with the big factories.</p>
<p>I ended up going to Vietnam to see a motorbike factory. I was so impressed I skipped my flight home and have stayed ever since. It has been three years now. I am currently engrossed in product development and manufacturing in an industrial hub outside Ho Chi Min. I’ve built a fairly big team and we are doing well from Europe’s E-bike boom. Vietnam is less developed, so we are not competing as much to get into the factories. We also got in early. If you are a new company entering Vietnam today, you could struggle to get into the high-tech, high quality factories with a small brand.</p>
<p>Most of our sales are into Germany, Switzerland, the Netherlands and Austria. We employ 16 people in Vietnam today and have produced 1,000 frames so far; we began shipping in December 2020 and aim to produce 1,000 bikes a month from next year.</p>
<p>Around 60% of our parts are sourced from Vietnam, the rest comes from China and Taiwan. We aim to increase this to 100% in the first half of 2021. The majority of the inputs from Vietnam come from within 50km of our factory, and not having to go to China saves us huge amounts of time. The bike’s final assembly and manual processes all take place in a factory in Ho Chi Min that we rent with other manufacturers. We are looking to open our own factory in Q1 next year.</p>
<p>The growth in E-bikes has led to key suppliers of bike parts like rims, saddles and breaks in China and Taiwan stopping taking orders for 2021. Some factories are even saying if you place your order now, you won’t receive it until September 2022. It’s lucky we are in Vietnam. There isn’t as much of a bike industry in Vietnam and so local factories haven’t had the same problems. People are also working hard to convert old factories used in the auto sector to produce bike parts.</p>
<p>Tariffs are another reason for choosing to manufacture in Vietnam. With the European Free Trade Association (EFTA) trade agreement, 99% of tariffs will go to zero over the next six years. That is attractive because there are high tariffs for E-bikes into Europe made in China.</p>
<p>In some ways it’s easier to build a supply chain in China because you can find suppliers through Alibaba – it is a huge marketplace and there is nothing like this in Vietnam. Big companies in Vietnam don’t even have websites. It means finding suppliers involves building your network and attending industry trade shows. Finding high quality factories up to IOS standards is also difficult; finding factories that can produce large quantities of a product is another challenge. Nor do many factories in Vietnam have that much money to invest in their equipment.</p>
<p>Laws are also unclear in Vietnam which makes things challenging. But there is a large and available workforce. Labour costs are also lower than in China, though higher than in Cambodia.</p>
<p>More companies are arriving in Vietnam. The main frame factory we use is doing around four times more business now compared to just six months ago. And Vietnam hasn’t locked down with COVID, so factories have been running the entire time. This has bought a lot of business from China – along with EFTA. The more companies that come here, the easier it will be to do business.</p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Portrait of Anne Petterd, Partner, Baker &amp; McKenzie" class="photo" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__anne-petterd__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=689E8BB5462924314AAC865AF0EE4F7A" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Anne Petterd</h3>
<h5 class="title">Partner</h5>
<h5 class="org">Baker &amp; McKenzie</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>We have not seen many businesses move their supply chains out of China, but we are seeing businesses increasingly react and ‘sit up’ regarding trade tensions. Assessing the impact of higher tariffs due to trade tensions on inputs to production then becomes a catalyst to review supply chain disruption risks more holistically for the business.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, the increased focus on supply chain disruption means that we are seeing more companies making supply chain disruption a board level issue. Other key trends are increased use of data and digital transformation to really understand the risk areas for supply chains and transform supply chains.</p>
<p>It is important to remember supply chain risk doesn’t just include higher tariffs resulting from trade tensions or the impact of the pandemic on procurement. For example, depending on what companies make, the complexity of their supply chains and where they manufacture, their supply chains could have modern slavery risks or face increased regulation around sustainability. The supply chain issues of focus also vary between industries. A particular point of focus for consumer goods businesses in recent times has been both investors and informed consumers demanding to know more about the entire supply chain used to produce a product.</p>
<p>The viability of moving supply chains needs to be assessed, especially if a business has its own manufacturing operations. If a business uses an outsourced manufacturing model, this might give the business more flexibility, but even this can be challenging because there may be significant practical and cost limitations in finding alternate manufacturers.</p>
<p>Many businesses remain heavily dependent on China as a key part of their supply chain. The size and scale of manufacturing in China and related established transportation routes can make finding alternative locations and transportation routes challenging. For businesses seeking to relocate part of their supply chain, often what they do in the current place of manufacturer, they can’t entirely do in another jurisdiction. For example, another jurisdiction might lack the necessary skilled labour or critical inputs.</p>
<p>Achieving the objectives for a supply chain move need to be carefully thought-through. A business might want to move manufacturing or assembly to a new location so as to qualify the goods as ‘made in’ the new jurisdiction under relevant rules of origin. If the inputs to a product are not wholly sourced from a single jurisdiction, the business might need to navigate more complex rules of origin that look at the level of sourcing and effort that can be attributed to that jurisdiction.</p>
<p>Looking longer-term, a critical catalyst to businesses in deciding to move or change their supply chains will be factors like the business’ ability and readiness to utilise robotics and undergo digital transformation as labour comes out of supply chains and more robotics and digitisation goes in. Connected with this, many governments are focused on how they can attract more advanced manufacturing to assist to build up critical mass for new industries.</p>
<p>The past few years have made for a wild ride in trade and supply chains. The many sources of supply chain disruption have introduced a level of uncertainty that businesses have to manage. Supply chain management in the past was often siloed to a particular area within a business. Now it is a whole of business as well as a critical business issue. Recognising this, more businesses are setting up their own supply chain task forces with responsibilities to look at supply chain management risks and strategies across the business.</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<p><em>“With bitcoin reaching increased heights, what should treasurers be aware of and doing?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[“To what extent is COVID-19 and the strained US-China relationship is causing companies to rethink their supply chains.”]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2021-01-02-tt-08-qa__panorama-shipping-containers-port-hong-kong-1391979872__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2021-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Companies stuck between risks and opportunities of new BRI infrastructure]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>New ports, roads and rail networks are springing up across Asia as China’s giant BRI infrastructure build comes on stream. The potential for foreign companies to invest off the back is huge, but it also comes with complex issues attached. None more so than navigating the growing East West digital divide.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5A06FF9D592BE5D7D7944E87CE338C2C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C38F395C09EEC6945B07364021F437E8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=65DD4D54B732D0598B09FACB962D2E6E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7C3CE2566F3F86D1924AE8D98510B625"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A236B7399B5705759F373E9C3E99D641"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Modern city viaduct junction by fisheye lense" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=51D0269F502D7E49EE4A19F8AC5C4470" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=51D0269F502D7E49EE4A19F8AC5C4470"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>Opportunities for foreign companies to get involved in helping construct Sri-Lankan capital Colombo’s Port City have been relatively thin on the ground. Chinese state-owned companies have dominated the ambitious construction led by China Communications Construction Company, CCCC, since a line of dredgers began reclaiming land from the Indian Ocean in 2014.</p>
<p>But as the skyline of Colombo’s own Dubai, complete with a marina and glittering financial and entertainment districts, begins to change, the hope is foreign investors from property developers to hotel chains, logistics companies and service providers will start to arrive. “Colombo’s Port City offers a competitive alternative to Singapore for regional banks and insurance companies and a place for back office services. The working population will need restaurants, bars and gyms,” enthuses Chris Devonshire-Ellis, founding partner at Dezan Shira &amp; Associates Asia, who advises multinationals on BRI investment opportunities.</p>
<p>As thousands of Chinese-built and funded BRI projects in more than 100 countries stretching along the old silk route begin to come to fruition, enthusiasts say the real BRI opportunity for multinational companies shut out during the construction phase has finally arrived in the project’s next evolution. The BRI requires an estimated US$26trn, but China will only fund around US$1.3trn. Witness how China is only financing a third of Port City’s US$24bn price tag, making foreign investment both crucial and leaving a huge opportunity to leverage off brand new infrastructure.</p>
<p>Yet many multinational companies view BRI investment through a cautious lens. It is saddled with a bad reputation linked to some countries amassing debts they can’t repay, corruption scandals and mistrust around local employment opportunities and over reliance on Chinese expertise and supply chains within projects. Elsewhere, the climate emergency is growing, but much of the BRI’s energy infrastructure is polluting and tied to fossil fuels. Between 2000 and 2019, Beijing’s two leading policy banks (China Development Bank and Export-Import Bank of China) provided US$183bn in energy finance to BRI countries, which went mostly to oil, coal and hydropower. This compares with the banks’ US$4.8bn funding for solar and wind projects, according to data from Boston University’s Global Development Policy Center.</p>
<p>Perhaps the biggest roadblock to corporate opportunities comes via souring China US relations. A digital overlay that includes 5G connectivity and AI technologies lies at the heart of the BRI and is key to transforming the new infrastructure into integrated ports, rail networks or smart cities. Yet US sanctions make working with much of China’s tech sector increasingly difficult for many companies, leaving unknowns around how they will navigate the digital integration behind their investment. It makes a challenging backdrop for multinationals wanting to take advantage of Asia’s explosive consumption markets.</p>
<h4 id="the-upside">The upside</h4>
<p>To be sure, multinationals are starting to invest off the back of BRI infrastructure. Korean, Japanese, Singaporean, French and Canadian companies are amongst a cohort of investors offering new consumer-facing businesses in Cambodia (a big recipient of BRI lending) to capture the upside of new infrastructure, says Henry Tillman, CEO and Founder of China Investment Research, part of consultancy Grisons Peak. Elsewhere, he notices that western companies are moving their manufacturing arms out of China to countries like Cambodia, Laos, Vietnam and Thailand, benefiting from Chinese-built transport corridors across the region and alongside which real estate developers are beginning to snap up swathes of land.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, investment flows into Pakistan off the back of new infrastructure includes companies from the US, Saudi Arabia, Netherlands, Turkey and the UAE. “The world remains transfixed on Chinese debt in the BRI and is not focused on the equity investment going in,” says Tillman.</p>
<p>AECOM’s Scott Dunn, Vice President, Strategy &amp; Growth South East Asia, observes similar changes. The US engineering group, which designs new BRI infrastructure as well as supervising the construction process and ensuring completed assets function as designed, is one western company involved in BRI construction. “In some cases, multinational companies are starting to come in and in certain areas where the infrastructure is finished, we are seeing an increase in trade because of better facilities. Pakistan has benefited from a new port and roads. It’s a big improvement compared to what it was before he says.</p>
<p>The ripple effect for businesses and investors of good infrastructure is best encapsulated in the transformation of Greece’s Piraeus port, believes Mukhtar Hussain, Head of BRI and Business Corridors, Asia Pacific at HSBC. Ever since China Ocean Shipping Company, COSCO, overhauled the creaking infrastructure, the port has turned “from problem child to success story.”</p>
<p>More lies ahead. In the BRI’s next phase, China will actively court foreign companies. It is already evident in Chinese companies working with global names on the ground in BRI countries like Germany’s Siemens, GE and Honeywell. Going forward, Chinese companies seeking to invest in the region will increasingly partner with multinationals who already have a footprint, predicts HSBC’s Hussain. “A Chinese company doing something new in a market where a multinational already has a long-term association will be keen to align and create a win-win. We expect more international cooperation to manifest in actual examples as China seeks to be more inclusive.”</p>
<p>BRI projects only count for a small amount of AECOM’s US$20bn annual revenue, but the firm is involved in a growing number of projects. AECOM’s work is divided equally between strategic partnerships with a cohort of Chinese developers or contractors and working directly with local government-owned groups building out their transport system. “We are one of the larger global companies doing this kind of work,” he reflects.</p>
<p>And experts expect the pipeline will continue to flow as ASEAN countries’ demand for BRI infrastructure continues unabated. HSBC estimates around US$70-80bn of Chinese infrastructure investment to ASEAN countries is currently in the pipeline. The dialogue is also beginning to shift from the infrastructure story to how BRI can be a force for global good, notes Hussian. This could be around building social infrastructure like hospitals, housing and schools, he suggests. “The BRI could drive much more investment into these critical sectors. This is what governments need and we see BRI evolving accordingly.” he says.</p>
<h4 id="the-problem">The problems</h4>
<p>But despite the investment potential, foreign corporates remain wary. They cite familiar worries around unstable currencies in some emerging economies and challenges around transferring money. Political instability is another concern. Malaysia’s high speed and urban rail programme, part of which was tied to BRI, turned messy following a change of government when the new regime renegotiated the price and changed the routing. “If you look at all the countries the BRI touches, many are politically unstable. It means things can change quickly which is a risk because infrastructure investment is long-term and doesn’t happen within one political cycle,” says AECOM’s Dunn. “Ultimately success will depend on how the currency risk is protected and how transparent the financial and legal systems of BRI countries become, especially in Southeast Asia.”</p>
<p>But other, bigger challenges lie beneath, none more so than finding the right partner on the ground. Andre Wheeler, Director of Wheeler Management Consulting based in Perth, Australia, advises all clients seeking to partner with a local entity off the back of BRI infrastructure to carefully unravel who they are investing alongside. It involves a deep dive of the corporate structure, operating and litigation history and key management and decision makers, as well as ascertaining ownership of the infrastructure assets.</p>
<p>Wheeler, who estimates that only 6% of the current investment in BRI projects is by non-Chinese entities, advises all his clients to peel back the layers. Investors might find they are partnering with Chinese state-owned companies and not a local entity at all, he warns. “There are a number of instances where a local corporation has been set up, in a sense a “front” company, but regulatory and management control comes from China. Landbridge in Australia is such an example.”</p>
<p>Partnering with private Chinese companies is just as much of a risk. New powers have recently given the Chinese state more control over private enterprise within China, he says. “The CCP has increased its control in private enterprise, particularly through the broadly defined “national security interest” test. Investors should ensure they are investing or partnering with a company that falls outside Chinese law – and is not an SOE.”</p>
<p>More straightforward investment comes via construction of apartment blocks or warehouses in 100% ownership models, he suggests. He also flags how some BRI countries also offer investment opportunities without the complexities of Chinese partnership like Sri Lanka, and increasingly Vietnam, which straddles the BRI as well as Japanese, Indian and African trading corridors. “Vietnam has opened up its foreign investment laws and is also wary of China. It is becoming a little like Switzerland and investors like this,” he says.</p>
<p>In Columbo, companies seeking to invest will typically partner with a local entity, familiar with local regulations and able to do the groundwork, says Devonshire-Ellis, who reassures investment doesn’t involve partnering with a Chinese company. “There is no need to be involved with the Chinese whatsoever. Companies invest alongside local entities.”</p>
<p>Elsewhere, Wheeler says the Philippines offers less complex investment opportunities, and believes that more big-ticket infrastructure investment in the region will start to appear without Chinese involvement. Most recently he is advising on investment opportunities linked to a new feasibility study around a land bridge in Thailand between two seaports on the Andaman sea and the Gulf of Thailand to bypass the Strait of Malacca. In another example, initiative like Japan’s Indo-Pacific Fund, a collaborative effort with America and Australia to develop and offer complementary infrastructure within the Indo-Pacific region, also suggests a shift away from China.</p>
<h4 id="digital-divide">Digital divide</h4>
<p>But the biggest potential risk and roadblock for multinational companies seeking to invest off the back of BRI infrastructure comes courtesy of the growing digital divide between China and the West. A digital overlay that spans 5G connectivity and AI technologies lies at the heart of the BRI and is key to transforming Chinese-built infrastructure into integrated ports, rail networks and smart city packages, complete with facial recognition systems and big data analysis to automate services such as traffic management, sewage systems and public safety. According to research by RWR Advisory, a Washington-based consultancy, Chinese companies have done 116 deals to install smart city and so-called safe city packages around the world since 2013, with 70 taking place in BRI countries.</p>
<p>For example, logistics, supply chain and freight forwarding groups setting up shop in Colombo’s Port City will likely have to integrate Chinese technology protocols and standards. “Port City investors may be engaging with a sovereign Sri Lankan company, but the infrastructure and digital connectivity will be provided by China,” says Wheeler. This leaves investors in danger of signing up to agreements with Chinese tech companies, blacklisted by the US. “Potential investors are wary of US sanctions, and not having enough knowledge around who they are contracting with,” he says. The US has sanctions against 24 entities, including the CCCC and its five subsidiaries, all companies involved in an estimated 900 projects across BRI countries.</p>
<p>It leaves western companies needing to judge which part of BRI they can focus on, and what part of the opportunity to tap on a case by case basis. It also plays into how treasury teams navigate the growing narrative around the emergence of two separate supply chains – one for the Chinese market and Asian bloc, and one for the rest of the world. Chinese manufacturing entities are increasingly seeking lower cost production outside China, and Asian countries are increasingly relying on consumption markets within Asia – particularly China, explains Hussain. “Trade and investment in Asia is becoming increasingly Asia-centric and intra-Asian trade flows are increasingly more significant than investment flows from Europe and the US.”</p>
<p>Witness how Chinese companies are preparing to invest off BRI infrastructure in contrast to foreign groups’ caution. There has been a jump in Chinese companies raising money for BRI investment via IPOs, notes Anastasia Gordeeva, BRI Manager at law firm Charltons Law in Hong. “An increasing number of Chinese companies are listing BRI-related projects on the Hong Kong stock exchange via IPOs. It is enabling them to tap overseas investment, as well as a Chinese investor base via Hong Kong’s Stock Connect with Shanghai and Shenzhen stock exchanges,” she says.</p>
<p>Of course, the pandemic has pressed pause on many multinationals’ ability to leverage BRI infrastructure anyway. “We still supply some advisory services to people who are interested in BRI projects, but travel has been non-existent with COVID and we are doing it all on the phone,” says Wheeler. HSBC’s Hussain agrees the scale and speed of BRI projects has diminished on the back of worsening geopolitics and the consequences of COVID. Meanwhile, some companies held back from making big decisions before the US election in the hope of more certainty and predictability around US tariffs.</p>
<p>But the momentum, scale and long-term timeline driving BRI suggests it will only be a short break. Multinationals will increasingly want to take advantage of China’s more pragmatic view on international involvement and constrained ability to be the sole financier of all things BRI. “There may have been a slowing of BRI investment right now, but it’s here to stay. China judges the short term by decades, and this is an opportunity for a company with a long-term view,” says Hussain. Just exactly how companies navigate the opportunity remains to be seen.</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[New ports, roads and rail networks are springing up across Asia as China’s giant BRI infrastructure build comes on stream. The potential for foreign companies to invest off the back is huge, but it also comes with complex issues attached. None more so than navigating the growing East West digital divide.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2020-11-12-tta-ia__modern-city-viaduct-junction-by-fisheye-184820606__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2020-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Shifting sands]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=822337486856AB3413203F3C669BB293"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=72362EFD80939BC2BE27385207E4624F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BADA4BD11862BA9CEBDE2009C56F5C6F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=988E16D35B91EB248991D7078CEA0EF1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C2A786328A9DF80F3CC40D1188C05622"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="US and China flags on concrete, breaking into each other" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C780EB8FE3B70A970C3D881E64D32FB7" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C780EB8FE3B70A970C3D881E64D32FB7"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Following the introduction of trade tariffs in 2018, continuing trade tensions between the US and China have major implications for global trade. What do treasurers need to be aware of in this challenging new environment?</em></p>
<p>The significance of trade across Asia Pacific cannot be overstated. As Steven Beck, Head of Trade and Supply Chain Finance at Asian Development Bank (ADB) explains, “We’ve seen trade lift millions out of poverty over the past few decades. People forget the critical role trade played, and continues to play, in Asia’s transformation.”</p>
<p>But the last couple of years have brought considerable uncertainty about trading relationships, not least due to escalating trade tensions between the US and China. In 2018, the US imposed hefty trade tariffs on goods from China, with trade worth over US$250bn already affected – and further tariffs have been threatened. China has already retaliated with tariffs to US$110bn of US goods ranging from soya beans to bourbon. While talks between the two nations are ongoing, the situation is far from resolved – and despite the tariffs introduced last year, the trade deficit grew to record levels in 2018.</p>
<p>“Trade tensions over the past 18-24 months have had an impact on client activity,” observes Ajay Sharma, Regional Head of Global Trade and Receivables Finance, Asia Pacific at HSBC. “Many initially thought it was a storm in a teacup, but they now realise it’s something far more structural. Hong Kong and Singapore, the bellwethers of Asian trade, have reported a fall in trade figures, which in turn has impacted trade finance markets.”</p>
<h4 id="shifting-supply-chains">Shifting supply chains</h4>
<p>One major consideration is the impact of protectionist measures on supply chains. “Given the interconnectivity of global supply chains, assessing the impact of protectionism is even more complicated than in the past,” comments Sonam Donkar, Group CFO – Commercial Organisation at Vedanta Group. “This puts at risk the real economic gains that have come through closer trade and investment links evolved over decades of partnering.”</p>
<p>Agatha Lee, Head of Global Trade and Loan Products, Asia Pacific at J.P. Morgan, notes that Asian exports are vulnerable to the US-China trade dispute on two fronts: changes to global supply chains and slowing Chinese domestic demand. “The shift in supply chains – away from China – inevitably comes with costs, especially around logistics and expected risks involved with new suppliers,” she says. Lee adds that slowing domestic consumption in China will impact regional neighbours, which have seen direct exports to China rise exponentially in recent years.</p>
<p>Looking further ahead, the implications could be even more significant. “According to views by J.P. Morgan’s research team, the US-China tensions have the potential to trigger the existing manufacturing supply chains to permanently shift out of China,” says Lee, noting that ASEAN countries, which have fairly low-cost wage structures and large, relatively young working populations, stand to benefit the most.</p>
<p>Countries that are heavily dependent on shipments to China may see a negative impact, however. “In Asia, we view Taiwan to be most vulnerable, given both China and US are Taiwan’s top trading partners, and the Taiwanese economy is heavily reliant on global trade,” says Lee. “While South Korea and Japan are also big exporters to China, we view them to be fairly immune.”</p>
<h4 id="planning-for-multiple-eventualities">Planning for multiple eventualities</h4>
<p>Corporates in the region are watching the situation closely. Donkar says organisations are far more exposed to protectionist measures than in the past and are consequently monitoring the impact of these measures closely. She adds that with G20 countries doubling trade restrictions in recent months, “it has become imperative for organisations to have dedicated think tanks to assess the impact of potential scenarios impacting short-term and long-term profitability.” When it comes to engaging with the situation and insulating themselves against a potentially adverse trade environment, Donkar says organisations are focusing on being alert and using advocacy forums to share opinions.</p>
<p>“I am seeing lots of clients focus more time on planning for multiple eventualities so they can position themselves to make changes, should the landscape change,” says Peter Jameson, head of Asia Pacific Trade and Supply Chain Finance, Global Transaction Services at Bank of America Merrill Lynch (BofAML). “For example, we are seeing clients ask more questions around how we could support them in new markets (eg Bangladesh, Vietnam). So they are clearly considering alternative options in terms of where they might source or manufacture for their supply chains.”</p>
<p>Jameson says that this is a logical approach, as the cost implications of shifting supply chains – for example, on-boarding new suppliers or building new production facilities – are significant, and “not something they would seek to do until the long-term outcome of the geopolitical situation is clear.”</p>
<p>This clarity may not be forthcoming, however. Jameson notes that “the only certainty is uncertainty”: with the geopolitical landscape continuing to shift, it is likely that other trade relationships globally will likewise shift in line with domestic/foreign policy agendas. Consequently, “as no set of outcomes can really be predicted we are seeing clients planning for the broadest possible range of eventualities.”</p>
<p>Companies are therefore adopting a wait and see approach. For example, Jameson says that where the US/China discussions are concerned, “rather than react to the latest sound-bite or policy announcement, many clients choose not to react quickly but to wait to see how things play out.” He adds that companies are striking a balance between the fear of not being prepared, and the fear of moving quickly and investing significantly in new infrastructure that might end up not being needed.</p>
<p>HSBC’s Sharma likewise emphasises the impact of uncertainty on clients in the current market. “They like to have stability when they make long-term decisions, so the main impact we’re seeing is a state of inertia among clients – they’re waiting to see how the trade truce pans out,” he says.</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: US China trade defecit keeps growing</h4>
<p>Chinese trade surplus with the US 2004-2018 (in US$bn)</p>
<p><img alt="Chart 1: US China trade defecit keeps growing" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__us-china-trade-defecit-keeps-growing__967x565.png?la=en&amp;hash=340E09F8D34FC14E5A836E7FC5EC08E5"/></p>
<p class="source">Source: Chinese Customs Administration, National Bureau of Statistics of China</p>
<h4 id="intra-regional-growth">Intra-regional growth</h4>
<p>But despite the uncertainty, the current market also has plenty of opportunities. Beck notes that against the headwinds, “we continue to see resilience and growth in developing Asia – truly the engine for global economic growth and trade growth.”</p>
<p>For one thing, he notes that China’s shift to a consumer-led economy is presenting more opportunities for growth and connectivity. “Intra-regional supply chains are strengthening,” he says. “We live in an inter-connected world, where contagion and ‘knock-on’ is real; but the notion of an intra-Asian buffer, with increasingly inter-dependent economies less reliant on the West, is trending. The global financial crisis accelerated this trend, and it continues unabated.”</p>
<p>Free trade deals also have a significant role to play in supporting trade within the region. The Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP) suffered a setback when the US withdrew from the partnership in early 2017. But the remaining 11 countries went ahead with the agreement, and in March 2018 the TPP’s successor, the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership (CPTPP), was signed. The deal is already in force for seven of the participating markets.</p>
<p>“Even without the US, the CPTPP will be among the largest multilateral trade deals enacted, covering 11 economies which constitute 14% of the world GDP,” says J.P. Morgan’s Lee. “Beyond lowering trade barriers and boosting trade flows amongst the countries, the agreement also includes greater protection of intellectual property rights and provisions to increase minimum labour standards for workers in participating countries.” Consequently, she says the deal is broadly “trade positive” – albeit on a smaller scale than the previous TPP agreement.</p>
<p>Beyond the CPTPP, other trade deals are also playing a role in helping trade to become freer across the region. HSBC’s Sharma notes that last year the EU signed agreements with both Japan and Singapore, adding that “the EU-Japan deal is the world’s largest bilateral trade agreement.” Other recent developments include deals signed by Australia with Indonesia and Hong Kong. “It’s encouraging to see all these positive trade developments coming out of Asia which will reduce the friction in trade,” Sharma says.</p>
<h4 id="infrastructure">Infrastructure</h4>
<p>Meanwhile, China’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) continues apace. The initiative, which is expected to cost a total of more than US$1trn, is intended to improve trade routes between China and over 70 countries across Asia, Europe, the Middle East and North Africa. Its wide scope includes road, rail and maritime infrastructure, as well as power projects and manufacturing plants. Lee says that in principle, the initiative “should be a positive sum game for all players along the New Silk Road Economic Belt, which will connect China with Europe through Central and Western Asia, as well as the 21st Century Maritime Silk Road which connects China with Southeast Asian countries, Africa and Europe.”</p>
<p>“Infrastructure investments underway, whether they’re called One Belt or by another name, promise to create stronger links to underpin the trend toward greater intra-regional trade and cooperation,” says Beck. “Asian Development Bank (ADB) is playing an important role in some of these projects, closing the infrastructure financing gap, bringing expertise, project management as well as environmental and social safeguards to many of these projects.”</p>
<p>BofAML’s Jameson points out that while BRI is designed to promote and facilitate trade – as well as being an important foreign policy tool – it is not a new concept. “It has been referred to as the ‘new Silk Road’, which reminds us that trading and creating connectivity between markets is centuries old,” he comments. “It is also a two-way benefit – not just facilitating goods manufactured in China to reach new markets overseas, but with the increasing middle class in China, it aims to facilitate the flow of imports of consumer goods in the other direction, opening up this important new export market to overseas countries.”</p>
<p>Consequently, Jameson says that while the initiative won’t really resolve the issues around protectionism, “it will help China (in particular) diversify its trading hinterland by providing greater connectivity for trade and FDI. This will help diversify its trading partners, in the event any particular relationship becomes increasingly protectionist.”</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the initiative is not without controversy. Lee notes that while the initiative was intended to boost productivity and infrastructure among BRI host countries, “concerns have grown about both corporate and political governance. The initiative is hampered by concerns about debt sustainability of host countries and producing low economic returns to China, even as it pays political dividends.”</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Five challenges – and how to manage them</h2>
<!-- BOXED -->
<p>Peter Jameson, head of Asia Pacific Trade and Supply Chain Finance, Global Transaction Services at Bank of America Merrill Lynch, recommends that treasurers in the region should take note of the following challenges, and prepare accordingly:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Uncertainty.</strong> Plan and prepare – the landscape is changing fast, so be flexible and ready to adapt.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Managing risk.</strong> Explore options for new sourcing/procurement in other markets, or new client bases in new markets. As well as developing the physical flows, consider how to ensure your bank can support the financial flows.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Continued regulation.</strong> Be aware of regulatory developments and challenges, from regulatory convergence in developed markets to local regulatory complexity in developing markets. This is not new, but the situation continues to evolve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Rising interest rates.</strong> At least in USD, this is driving up attention on yield. As rates rise, pressure for efficiency and sourcing liquidity from inside the company’s supply chain will be key.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Environment, social and governance.</strong> This is rising up the agenda for corporates and treasurers, while investors are increasingly focused on this topic. Moreover, with diversification into new emerging markets, the importance of understanding your supply chain, the ethics of your suppliers, and the reputational risk of getting it wrong, ESG is an increasingly important component of doing business.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h4 id="boosting-trade">Boosting trade</h4>
<p>Beyond these developments, there are several key themes that may help to boost trade in the current climate. For one thing, Jameson says that digitisation is playing a role in driving globalisation, by providing faster access to new markets and clients. “It also drives down the costs of supply chains, including entry into new markets, hence helping companies diversify more easily, should they need to,” he adds.</p>
<p>“We also see the rise of e-commerce in Asia as a driver of shipments in the region as more consumers take to shopping online,” says J.P. Morgan’s Lee, adding that Asia Pacific today accounts for about 50% of global ecommerce activity, “which is expected to be worth US$2trn in three years”. She adds that cross-border purchases are estimated to dominate one in five transactions done via e-commerce worldwide by 2022, compared with one in seven today. “With more Asia-based merchants joining the online marketplace, this could mean a huge boon to intra-Asia trade,” she says.</p>
<p>Risk mitigation is another key area when it comes to supporting trade. “From a banking point of view, we see companies leaning towards capabilities that help them manage risk in their supplier chains,” says Jameson. He adds that these include traditional trade capabilities, as well as supply chain finance as a tool for providing liquidity to important supply chains and support smaller customers.</p>
<p>Also important is focusing on opportunities in new markets. Jameson says that while protectionist agendas are a western phenomenon, paradoxically economic growth potential lies in emerging economies. “Therefore, it’s natural we should see a shift away from protectionist markets (which offer slower economic growth) into new markets that are perceived to be more open, and with more potential.”</p>
<p>In order to maximise opportunities in the current market, Jameson says there are several steps that treasurers should be taking. He underlines the importance of knowing where the company’s cash is and what the supply chain looks like. Treasurers should also know how they would move their assets, including capital, supply chains and customers, in light of uncertainty – “and be prepared to do so”. Finally, he comments that none of these actions should be at the expense of efficiency, “as that drives margin – and hence the ability to compete.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Following the introduction of trade tariffs in 2018, continuing trade tensions between the US and China have major implications for global trade. What do treasurers need to be aware of in this challenging new environment?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2019-05-06-tta-02-ia__flags-united-states-china-ss760710751__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2019-05-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Making the most of intraregional trade]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B6199300B2DD5DC3DACDDE34A15D4690"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AFBE05F0151C380675B253BA57B99E35"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=34B8B93DA73B827BE75BBFDF7EE33174"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=60848C3787D487F4FB0AD9F49795CCCD"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=30E2CD119DD4F7BF93D486FCE9FB7F71"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Cargo ship packed with containers" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9C258A952EA0A6D54E11AE8D44605689" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9C258A952EA0A6D54E11AE8D44605689"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>A number of initiatives are set to support the growth of intraregional trade over the coming years. Where are the opportunities, and how can treasurers support their organisations in reaping the rewards in this evolving landscape?</em></p>
<p>Where trade is concerned, the last 12 months have brought their fair share of challenges. Eleven Asia Pacific countries signed the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership (CPTPP) in May, paving the way for better trading conditions across the region. However, other factors have also been at play – not least of all the brewing global trade war sparked by trade tariffs imposed by the US on Chinese exports.</p>
<p>So far, the impact of these measures has been limited: despite the scale of the tariffs announced earlier this year Chinese exports rose by almost 15% year-on-year in September, resulting in a record trade surplus with the US. However, the recent depreciation of the renminbi may have played a part in this increase, and it is also likely that many companies have chosen to expedite orders before tariffs kick in. Meanwhile, further tariffs on US$200bn of Chinese exports were announced at the end of September – meaning that around half of all Chinese exports to the US will be covered by tariffs.</p>
<p>While the longer-term impact of the trade war could be considerable, Asia’s external trading relationships are only part of the picture. Intraregional trade accounts for 50% of total trade in East Asia and the Pacific, according to research published by the World Bank. And while intraregional trade only accounts for 5% of South Asia’s total at present, the World Bank report noted that there is plenty of room for improvement: “Gravity models show that total goods trade within South Asia could be worth US$67bn rather than the actual trade of only US$23bn.” The report notes that trade amongst South Asia countries is continuing to grow, with much scope for future improvement – India and Pakistan, for example, “have merely scratched the surface of their bilateral trade potential”.</p>
<h3 id="driving-growth">Driving growth</h3>
<p>Looking at the region as a whole, a number of factors are expected to drive intraregional trade in the coming years. “Asia is the engine of global trade growth,” says Ajay Sharma, Regional Head of Global Trade and Receivables Finance, Asia Pacific at HSBC, noting that the value of intra-Asian trade is already equal to that of Asia’s trade with Europe and North America combined. He adds that intra-Asian trade growth will be driven by the region’s continuing urbanisation and its burgeoning middle class. “It’s projected that by 2030 44% of the population in Asia will live in cities, and that they will contribute to over 85% of the region’s GDP,” Sharma says. “Also by 2030, Asia will be home to 1.2 billion middle-class households and account for two-thirds of the world’s middle-class population.”</p>
<p>Other notable drivers of growth include China’s Belt and Road Initiative: as well as improving physical infrastructure in more than 60 countries, the projects included within the initiative could bring a range of other benefits across the region. “These infrastructure projects – and the trade they enable – will provide a commercial boost to contractors and supply chains, and create wealth in communities along the routes,” comments Sharma.</p>


<blockquote>Consumption economies in Asia tend to be heterogeneous and diversified. Apart from different rules, legal constructs and regulations, each differs in its consumption preferences, language and market practices.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Rakshith Kundha, head of Trade and Supply Chain Solutions, South East Asia and India, Global Transaction Services, Bank of America Merrill Lynch</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Another notable development is the Regional Comprehensive Economic 
Partnership (RCEP), a free trade agreement between the ten ASEAN 
countries (Brunei, Cambodia, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, Myanmar, the 
Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam) together with six partners
 (Australia, China, India, Japan, South Korea and New Zealand). The 
agreement, which could incorporate 3.4 billion people and 30% of global 
trade, is intended to lower trade barriers and improve market access for
 goods and services for Asian businesses.</p>
<p>In addition to the RCEP, Sharma notes that Asia as a whole “will 
benefit from the region’s collective efforts to further liberalise 
trade, which also include the economic integration of ASEAN and the 
pending ratification of the CPTPP”.</p>
<p>Likewise, Vivek Gupta, Head of Trade and Supply Chain for Greater 
China and North Asia at ANZ notes that a number of regulator-sponsored 
trade-related initiatives are progressing well, including the Hong Kong 
Monetary Authority (HKMA) sponsored Trade Finance Blockchain Project set
 to go live in the fourth quarter of 2018, the Singapore National Trade 
Platform (NTP) and the Global Trade and Connectivity Network (GTCN) 
project which is jointly sponsored by the HKMA and the Monetary 
Authority of Singapore (MAS).</p>
<h3 id="rising-stars">Rising stars</h3>
<p>Alongside these initiatives, there may be space for some of the less 
prominent players in the region to make headway in intra-regional trade.
 “In the last couple of years, we’ve seen the gradual movement away from
 ‘Made in China’,” comments Aziz Parvez, head of Trade and Supply Chain 
Finance, Asia Pacific, Global Transaction Services at Bank of America 
Merrill Lynch. “Benefiting from lower labour costs, land and resources, 
businesses – particularly consumption-driven industries – are relocating
 their manufacturing centres into ASEAN and South Asia.”</p>
<p>Parvez notes that manufacturing is increasingly tilting towards 
countries such as Vietnam, Indonesia, India, Sri Lanka and Bangladesh. 
“Evolving patterns of consumption in Asia are also altering existing 
supply chain designs,” he observes. “We are seeing the emergence of 
Asian economies being major consumers of industrial and commercial 
goods. The above developments, combined with changes that may occur if 
the trade dispute extends, would require businesses to closely partner 
with their banks as they look to rework their supply chains.”</p>
<p>That’s not to say that the big players will be falling by the 
wayside. Agatha Lee, Head of Global Trade and Loan Products for Asia 
Pacific at J.P. Morgan predicts that traditionally strong contributors –
 namely China, Korea and Japan – will maintain their stronghold on 
intra-Asia trade. “Not only have Japanese, Korean and Chinese corporates
 evolved into MNCs, expanding their manufacturing outside home markets 
starting with APAC countries, there has also been increasing demand for 
‘made-in’ Japan, Korea and China goods across the region,” she explains.
 “But the rising stars are the fast-growing ASEAN economies – the likes 
of Vietnam, Cambodia, Philippines and Indonesia – which have seen a 
significant uptick in the production and exports of consumer items 
including clothing, electronics, perishables and general goods to the 
region.”</p>
<h3 id="challenges-and-headwinds">Challenges and headwinds</h3>
<p>Alongside these opportunities, there are also a number of challenges 
for companies operating in this environment. “Consumption economies in 
Asia tend to be heterogeneous and diversified,” comments Rakshith 
Kundha, head of Trade and Supply Chain Solutions, South East Asia and 
India, Global Transaction Services at Bank of America Merrill Lynch. 
“Apart from different rules, legal constructs and regulations, each 
differs in its consumption preferences, language and market practices.” 
He notes that companies need to navigate different financial markets 
with varied rates of financing, as well as dealing with a larger number 
of currencies – and, consequently, increasingly complex foreign exchange
 risk management.</p>
<p>Trade costs can also be an obstacle for trade within the region. “The
 UN reports that average intra-Asian trade costs, excluding tariffs, can
 range from 51% to 130% of the value of the goods, depending on the 
source and destination,” notes Sharma, adding that intra-EU represents 
‘best practice’ as trade costs are 42%.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, ANZ’s Gupta cites several headwinds affecting trade 
finance in the region. These include the possibility of US and China 
tariffs reducing demand down the line as costs to the ultimate consumer 
increase, as well as the depreciation of emerging market currencies and 
the possibility of rising domestic interest rates as emerging market 
central banks increase their interest rates.</p>
<p>This could lead to higher working capital costs for companies and 
their supply chains, alongside potential long-term structural impact of 
tariffs on supply chains. Gupta also cites the prospect of “rapid 
regulatory changes in Asian countries impacting access to trade 
finance”, and the resulting importance of remaining close to key trade 
banking relationships.</p>
<p>But alongside these challenges, trade barriers arising from 
protectionism can sometimes have a different effect. J.P. Morgan’s Lee 
observes that protectionist measures “sometimes have the potential to 
bring trading partners closer, and in turn drive more intra-regional 
activity”. She notes that an agribusiness conglomerate significantly 
boosted shipments from Australia to China earlier this year after 
Beijing imposed tariffs on US agricultural products, adding: “We expect 
similar such activities, which would bolster regional trade.”</p>
<p>Lee notes that other factors can act as a barrier to intra-Asia 
trade. She notes that World Bank figures show that South Asia’s rate of 
intra-regional trade remains among the lowest in the world. She also 
notes that a lack of funding options can inhibit trade in developing 
markets. “In markets like Cambodia, Myanmar and Laos, local financing 
can be challenging given their less developed financial infrastructure,”
 she comments.</p>
<h3 id="how-can-treasurers-help">How can treasurers help?</h3>
<p>As treasurers take on an increasingly strategic role within their 
organisations, there is much that they can do to support their 
companies’ trading activities in this environment. First and foremost, 
it is important to understand that strategies that may be effective in 
other regions are not always suitable in Asia.</p>
<p>“Given the different regulatory and legal constructs in various Asian
 markets, treasurers would need to plan carefully for future growth,” 
comments Bank of America Merrill Lynch’s Kundha. “A model geared towards
 centralisation of cash flow, procurement and sales may bring tremendous
 efficiencies in open markets, but may not always work across 
heterogeneous markets.”</p>
<p>In addition, there are a number of other ways in which treasurers can support their organisations in this climate:</p>
<ul><li>
<h5>Understand procurement patterns.</h5>
<p>Kundha advises that treasurers should consider current 
procurement and sales patterns, taking into account factors such as the 
locations of shared service centres and pool headers, the technology 
solutions deployed and the entities through which sales are routed.</p>
</li><li>
<h5>Contingency planning.</h5>
<p>Lee points out that contingency planning is key in this 
environment: “Treasurers will be relied upon to take a holistic view and
 ensure the business is well-prepared regardless of scenarios and 
outcomes,” she says, adding that strategies around FX hedging, cash flow
 forecasting, risk mitigation and ensuring sufficient credit and funding
 “will be critical”.</p>
</li><li>
<h5>Staying close to regulators.</h5>
<p>Lee also notes the importance of staying close to regulators. 
“Maintaining frequent and open dialogues with regulators will be key to 
ensuring clear understanding of government’s objectives around trade 
policy changes that impact corporates, and for both sides to work 
towards a mutual solution,” she says.</p>
</li><li>
<h5>Leverage supply chain finance.</h5>
<p>Kundha points out that supply chain finance “can be an important 
tool to ensure funding across a physical supply chain that is spread 
over several geographies”. And Gupta notes that some fintechs are now 
offering niche supply chain finance (SCF) solutions, which have the 
potential to accelerate supplier onboarding and the fuller utilisation 
of SCF programmes.</p>
</li><li>
<h5>Engage with the industry.</h5>
<p>Lee observes that engaging with industry organisations, forums 
and conferences can help treasurers keep abreast of best practices and 
gain insights from their peers.</p>
</li><li>
<h5>Work with the right banks.</h5>
<p>Also important is choosing banking partners which have detailed 
knowledge of the relevant local markets, from business culture to the 
regulatory climate, and taking advantage of their support.</p><p><br/><br/></p>
</li></ul>
<h3 id="looking-to-the-future">Looking to the future</h3>
<p>Predicting the future is never straightforward, but it seems likely 
that initiatives currently under way could play an important role in 
reshaping Asia’s trade patterns in the future. “We see increasing 
engagement among the Asian governments to intensify the economic 
integration; the proposed free trade agreement between ASEAN member 
states, or Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP), is a good
 example,” comments Lee. “This should help boost to intra-Asia trade 
volumes going forward.”</p>
<p>Parvez, likewise, predicts that intra-Asia trade is set to grow, 
supported by initiatives such as the CPTPP. “Supply chains will continue
 to shift, given lower cost manufacturing locations and new centres of 
consumption,” he says. “Apart from large corporates, both Asian and 
global, who will look to manufacture and sell within Asia, we are also 
likely to see a lot of activity in the MME space.”</p>
<p>In the meantime, Parvez notes that there is already a high volume of 
manufactured goods coming from the Chinese MME segment to different 
Asian markets. “While they clearly have the advantage of scale, we may 
in future see some of them also shifting manufacturing bases, a trend 
already playing out in the large corporate space,” he concludes.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[A number of initiatives are set to support the growth of intraregional trade over the coming years. Where are the opportunities, and how can treasurers support their organisations in reaping the rewards in this evolving landscape?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-11and12-tta-02-tr__aerial-view-container-cargo-ship-import-ss784765822__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2018-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Will the ‘People’s Currency’ become the world’s currency?]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FA411D006EF4BC400451F2A1EFC9F08C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7BBE2BAD9258B2E30F0C2BBD532E50A9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=54A8883CCDA9464824E8018C54B1E69D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8EB8D59F908F99D329DA89273FDA416A"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=45C39D2BAC99B3E108809900557D35D3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Chinese Yuan Isolated Close up" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6E7349C0417E69E3D9A05EC39B8D1F5C" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6E7349C0417E69E3D9A05EC39B8D1F5C"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>China is determined to internationalise the renminbi – a course of action which could challenge the US dollar’s long-held dominance as the world’s reserve currency. What progress has China made? Will it achieve its ambitions? And what do treasurers need to know about using the currency? Treasury Today Asia investigates.</em></p>
<p>The geopolitical landscape is changing. China, the once reluctant global superpower, is awakening. The country’s leader, Xi Jinping, has said that China is ready to “take centre stage in the world” – and driving this transformation is China’s economic power. Indeed, Xi asserted in a speech late last year that it was time for China to promote its economic model, defined as socialism with Chinese characteristics, around the world.</p>
<p>China’s emergence as a leader on the international stage comes at a time when the world is looking for leadership as the United States looks inwards and Europe deals with its own turmoil. And as the epitome of the potential of the developing world, China is well placed to establish a new world order. Xi has expressed this, saying that China can provide a “new choice” for the developing world.</p>
<p>By promoting its economic model to the world, China is also promoting its currency. And from a symbolic point of view, displacing the US dollar as the world’s most dominant reserve currency will be a strong indication that China has taken centre stage.</p>
<h3 id="long-term-project">Long-term project</h3>
<p>The desire to push China outward and internationalise the renminbi is not new. In fact, Chinese leadership has been taking steps to achieve this for just under a decade, as the country’s economy expanded and became more integrated with the rest of the world.</p>
<p>Many date this project back to 2009 when the HKMA and PBOC struck an agreement to settle trade in renminbi between Hong Kong and five cities in the mainland. In 2010, this agreement evolved and cross-border settlement extended to cover 20 provinces and cities. That year also saw the first renminbi-denominated corporate bond issued in Hong Kong by Hopewell Highway Infrastructure.</p>
<p>Since then, China has taken many other steps to internationalise the currency. These include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Letting foreign companies use currency to settle foreign direct investments (FDI) in China.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Directly trading the currency with other countries.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Creating offshore RMB hubs in cities around the world.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Allowing freer convertibility of the currency in several Free Trade Zones.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Launching the China International Payment System (CIPS).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Permitting certain foreign banks to trade in the mainland bond market.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>These actions have proved successful in promoting the use of the currency around the world. SWIFT data showed the renminbi became the world’s fifth global payment currency in 2015. China’s efforts also saw the IMF include the renminbi in the basket of currencies that make up the Special Drawing Right (SDR) in 2016. This was the first time a currency had been added to the basket for a decade and marked a significant step for the internationalisation of the renminbi, making it a reserve currency alongside the US dollar, euro, yen and British pound.</p>
<p>Commenting on the decision, Christine Lagarde, Managing Director of the IMF, said: “The Executive Board’s decision to include the RMB in the SDR basket is an important milestone in the integration of the Chinese economy into the global financial system. It is also a recognition of the progress that the Chinese authorities have made in the past years in reforming China’s monetary and financial systems. The continuation and deepening of these efforts will bring about a more robust international monetary and financial system, which in turn will support the growth and stability of China and the global economy.”</p>
<h3 id="symbolic-gesture">Symbolic gesture</h3>
<p>Despite the excitement around the inclusion of renminbi in the SDR, it was arguably a symbolic development. Professor Kathy Walsh, an expert in renminbi internationalisation from the University of Technology Sydney says: “SDR inclusion for China was about status. Many central banks already held the currency in reserve. Australia, for example, had 5% of its reserves in renminbi. So, from a practical perspective, the inclusion made little difference.”</p>


<blockquote>Being a leading reserve currency provides certain benefits. Most notably the concept of ‘exorbitant privilege</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Kathy Walsh, expert in renminbi internationalisation, University of Technology Sydney</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>In fact, Walsh believes that status and prestige are key drivers behind China’s desire to internationalise its currency and eventually challenge the US dollar’s dominance. “Being a leading reserve currency provides certain benefits,” says Walsh. “Most notably the concept of ‘exorbitant privilege’. In times of financial turmoil, there is always a flight back to the US dollar, even when the US caused the turmoil. China believes that it should have a similar status as the world’s largest trading nation – and soon to be its biggest economy.”</p>
<h3 id="currency-impasse">Currency impasse</h3>
<p>Talk of renminbi internationalisation suddenly subsided not long after SDR inclusion. Walsh says multiple factors led to this but highlights the competing economic and political objectives of Chinese policymakers as being the key reason. “I talked to several people at the time and not everyone agreed that internationalising the currency should be a priority,” she says. “Some feared China was at risk of losing control of its economy and the stock market crash and economic headwinds it faced emphasised this fear.”</p>
<p>With the Chinese regulators unsure whether to internationalise the currency further, some corporations lost interest in adopting it. “Our research at the time found that many international companies were open to using the currency,” says Walsh. “This was because the cost of hedging renminbi offshore was less than the cost of hedging USD onshore. But there needed to be more incentive than this, and it didn’t come. Because of this, the US dollar continues to dominate.”</p>
<h3 id="difficult-times">Difficult times</h3>
<p>Had China missed its moment to internationalise its currency? It seemed that way in 2017 when the project was dealt a further blow after China reintroduced controls over its financial system, including regulatory measures to stem the money moving overseas. These moves had a negative impact on global renminbi usage. SWIFT data from December 2017 showed the currency only accounted for a 1.61% share of global cross-border and domestic payment activity that year. This is down from the 2.31% share the currency accounted for in 2015.</p>
<p>The controls mentioned above also knocked the confidence of the corporate community, which began to doubt whether China was serious about internationalising its economy and currency. They also required corporates to undo lots of hard work, as the treasury team at Solvay explained to Treasury Today Asia earlier this year. The treasury had been taking advantage of regulatory relaxation and the promotion of the currency, putting in place cross-border cash pools and conducting cross-border settlement in renminbi for some years. Then, almost overnight, the company had to readjust its processes and revert to using US dollar, as China introduced stringent capital controls. This showed that renminbi internationalisation isn’t a one-way street.</p>
<h3 id="turning-the-page">Turning the page</h3>
<p>After a tumultuous few years, there are signs that the project to internationalise the currency is back on track. SWIFT data from May 2018 shows the renminbi has regained its position as the fifth most active currency for global payments with a share of 1.88%. Meanwhile, data from the Chinese Securities Regulatory Commission indicates that the renminbi is currently the third most used currency for trade finance.</p>
<p>Corporate interest in using the currency is also increasing. Both Citi and Standard Chartered say they are speaking more to clients about renminbi strategies. “Conditions in recent years haven’t been conducive to renminbi internationalisation,” says Sandip Patil, Managing Director and Region Head, Global Liquidity and Investments, Asia Pacific, Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions at Citi. “However, the environment has changed since the turn of the year and there is much more interest from corporates around the currency and how it might suit their treasury operations.”</p>
<p>There are multiple forces driving this in Patil’s opinion, including developments around CIPS, the opening of the capital markets and the continued progress of the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) – all of which show that China is serious about internationalising. But the most important driver is the shifting geopolitical landscape. “There is clear tension between the US and China, which is creating instability in the markets,” says Patil. “Corporates are exploring how to navigate through this instability, and many, especially those with a material interest in China, are looking to diversify and use the renminbi for some trade transactions with China.”</p>


<blockquote>Flows between China and the rest of Asia are largely denominated in US dollar. But as the renminbi has internationalised, more Asian companies are adopting it for their dealings with China.
<p><cite> </cite></p></blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Sandip Patil, Managing Director and Region Head, Global Liquidity and Investments, Asia Pacific, Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions, Citi</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Frankie Au, Head of RMB Products, Transaction Banking at Standard Chartered, supports this view. He says the headwinds preventing corporates from adopting the renminbi have disappeared, especially regarding the two-way flow of the currency. “China has also relaxed hedging rules, allowing corporates to hedge renminbi exposures offshore, which provides much more flexibility for corporates operating a renminbi portfolio,” he adds.</p>
<p>Because of these measures, Au says that there is growing curiosity from corporates about how to use the currency and what benefits it can offer. “Some companies are being forced to consider the currency because they are receiving requests from their counterparties to be paid in renminbi,” he comments. “However, many more are thinking strategically and looking at how the currency can enable them to achieve better pricing, win more business and reduce the cost of doing business with Chinese counterparties.”</p>
<p>Citi’s Patil agrees, noting that interest in the currency is especially high amongst Asian companies. “Flows between China and the rest of Asia are largely denominated in US dollar,” he says. “But as the renminbi has internationalised, more Asian companies are adopting it for their dealings with China. By doing so they are achieving greater efficiency and pricing advantages over using the US dollar. As a result, I expect to see a lot more intra-Asia trade settled in renminbi over the coming years.”</p>
<h3 id="strategic-adoption">Strategic adoption</h3>
<p>For all the pricing and efficiency benefits companies can achieve using renminbi for trade with China, Patil warns that adoption cannot happen overnight. Both Au and Patil recommend that corporations carefully consider their renminbi strategy to ensure it is executed effectively.</p>
<p>Indeed, there are multiple commercial and operational factors to consider. For instance, on a commercial level, it is likely companies will need to adjust their organisational and procurement policies to accommodate the new currency. Corporates should also renegotiate payment terms with suppliers to reflect the change.</p>
<p>From a treasury perspective, Citi’s Patil explains that treasurers must ensure the company has settlement accounts and intercompany agreements in place to support the currency. He adds that treasury teams will also need to investigate their cash management infrastructures. Doing so will ensure they optimise how they use the currency.</p>
<p>Treasury must also play a key role in working through and solving the unique issues encountered when using the renminbi, as highlighted by HSBC’s 2017 Renminbi Internationalisation Survey. Corporates noted a number of issues that can arise when using renminbi for cross-border business, including a lack of solutions for surplus cash onshore, unclear and shifting regulations and onerous documentary requirements.</p>
<p>To work through these considerations and challenges, many corporates are focusing on small-scale experiments with the currency. Citi’s Patil says most of the bank’s clients are adopting renminbi in a handful of legal entities. “This sandbox-style approach gives the business the opportunity to work through all the nuances associated with using the currency without the risk of full-scale adoption,” he explains. “Most importantly, it gets people comfortable with the currency, which is crucial for long-term usage to occur.”</p>
<h3 id="renminbis-belt-and-road-boost">Renminbi’s Belt and Road boost</h3>
<p>A crucial driver for greater renminbi internationalisation will be China’s ambitious BRI. The project, which will boost the flows of trade, capital and services between China and the rest of the world, will not only increase trade with Belt and Road countries but also promote the use of renminbi as a trade currency.</p>
<p>“Promoting the international use of the Chinese currency is one of the stated objectives of Belt and Road,” says Vina Cheung, Global Head of RMB Internationalisation at HSBC. “Because of this, we expect the currency to be used increasingly for trade and investment flows along the Belt and Road. We also expect to see a sizeable renminbi offshore-debt market emerge to fund the infrastructure development.”</p>
<p>Standard Chartered’s Au adds that it makes sense for the renminbi to be used for subsequent transactions if these infrastructure projects are funded in the currency. “This will avoid a currency mismatch, removing the currency risk and reducing the cost of the project overall,” he says.</p>
<p>The corporate world agrees. HSBC’s renminbi survey shows over 70% believe that BRI will have either a significantly positive or a positive impact on renminbi usage in the future. In another survey conducted by China Construction Bank, 72% of all respondents said the Belt and Road initiative is having the biggest impact on RMB internationalisation.</p>
<p>To support this, the Chinese government is determined to improve the currency’s infrastructure, as Yin Yong, Deputy Governor at the People’s Bank of China (PBOC), explained in a speech last year: “The PBOC will continue to improve the renminbi cross-border payment framework and make the renminbi play an important role in pricing, settlement, investment, financing and trade. The currency’s internationalisation will be a medium- to long-term process backed by China’s strong economy.”</p>
<p>For more on China’s BRI and what it means for your business, read our deep dive into the topic in the <a href="/2018/07/belt-and-road-opportunity-or-threat-ttia">July/August edition of Treasury Today Asia</a>.</p>
<h3 id="will-china-become-the-worlds-leading-currency">Will China become the world’s leading currency?</h3>
<p>Overall, the signs for the renminbi are positive. HSBC’s 2017 Renminbi Internationalisation Survey shows that more businesses not currently using renminbi for cross-border transactions are planning to do so in the future. This then begs the question: will China achieve its ambitions and become a truly international currency? And will this be at the expense of the US dollar?</p>
<p>“The renminbi will become a global currency,” predicts Walsh. “It won’t displace the dollar, however. In fact, I believe there is room for two strong reserve currencies. The big question is how long this will take. I used to think it will happen in ten years but now I think it will be closer to 20.”</p>
<p>Standard Chartered’s Au shares a similar view. “The renminbi is on the rise,” he says. “It will take time for it to reach its potential but it is heading in the right direction and I believe will sit alongside the US dollar as one of the world’s major reserve currencies.”</p>
<p>Citi’s Patil expects that geopolitics will play a big role in the renminbi’s future. “China will become an increasingly dominant player on the global stage, especially as the US takes a more protectionist stance and the renminbi will follow,” he says. Patil does, however, note that this will depend on continuing deregulation and increasing liquidity in the offshore renminbi market.</p>
<p>HSBC’s Cheung believes renminbi internationalisation is inevitable. “Renminbi usage shall reach the stage of balancing China’s influence as a leading trading nation and the growth engine for the world,” she says.</p>
<p>It may be easy to dismiss the renminbi’s potential to challenge and displace the dollar. But it has only been 100 years since the US dollar displaced the British pound – so who’s to say another change isn’t on the horizon?</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[China is determined to internationalise the renminbi – a course of action which could challenge the US dollar’s long-held dominance as the world’s reserve currency. What progress has China made? Will it achieve its ambitions? And what do treasurers need to know about using the currency? Treasury Today Asia investigates.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2018-09and10-tta-06-cnf__chinese-yuan-isolated-ss1142191967__300x200.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2018-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Building bridges]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F56C35ABBEC4C1C60362910B5F135034"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CD369B6401E804DF7F89A9AC21102649"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F2F8003874C668FAB6EB352911161FBD"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C0FA114FDD049E47CABE57C156644EC9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=8DF7F51AC8719E87990257C5493B0DBF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Rainbow Lights on Akashi Ohashi Pearl" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5ADE2DB4A7EED133EEDE58F7F9ABA589" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5ADE2DB4A7EED133EEDE58F7F9ABA589"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>While protectionist sentiment continues to shape the economic policies of some western markets, initiatives currently gaining momentum in Asia could lead to the development of new trade corridors and opportunities, both within the region and with trading partners further afield.</em></p>
<p> In President Trump’s inaugural speech, he declared, “From this day forward, a new vision will govern our land. From this day forward, it’s going to be – only – America First. America First.”</p>
<p>The phrase ‘America First’ has a long history: Woodrow Wilson used the same words during the 1916 presidential election, while the America First Committee was set up in the 1940s to oppose US involvement in World War II. More recently, evidence of the protectionist sentiment evoked by this phrase has not been hard to find. In January 2017, Trump withdrew from the Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP), a free trade agreement which was also to include Australia, Brunei, Canada, Chile, Japan, Malaysia, Mexico, New Zealand, Peru, Singapore and Vietnam. Likewise, Trump’s administration is currently renegotiating the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), a pact being drawn up by the US, Canada and Mexico.</p>
<p>These developments have considerable implications for world trade. Natalie Blyth, Global Head of Trade and Receivables Finance at HSBC, says that trade “is more contentious now than it has been for decades”, noting that from the US’ decision to pull out of the TPP to negotiations over Britain’s future relationship with the EU, “trade is at the heart of public discourse and it’s proving divisive”. Meanwhile, the pattern of trade growth has shifted over the last few years. “Before the global economic crisis trade consistently grew faster than GDP. Since 2009, we have seen a dislocation of trade, as values collapse compared to volumes, and trade growing below the rate of GDP,” notes Blyth.</p>
<p>Indeed, since 2009 the US has passed 1,297 economic or trade measures deemed ‘harmful’ to global trade, according to research published by Gowling WLG – compared to 206 measures deemed to be liberalising. The survey also noted that 5,657 measures have been introduced by the EU which can be seen as actively restrictive for trade. Overall, the report noted that the number of trade measures considered to be harmful rose by over 6,000 between 2009 and 2015, whereas the number of trade measures considered liberalising rose by over 2,500.</p>

<h3 id="the-rise-of-protectionism">The rise of protectionism</h3>
<p>The roots of the current wave of protectionist sentiment can be traced back a number of years, as Damian Glendinning, Treasurer at Lenovo, explains. “The past 60 years have seen a significant increase in global trade, as emerging countries, especially in Asia, have undergone rapid economic development,” says Glendinning. “In many cases, this consisted in providing cheap labour for products assembled in the emerging market, and then exported to developed countries for consumption. Inevitably, this has led to job losses and an element of ‘hollowing out’ in the developed markets.”</p>
<p>Glendinning notes that until now, this process has brought relatively little friction: “The mature market economies have focused on higher value-added manufacturing and services, while global supply chains have become the norm in many industries.”</p>
<p>More recently, however, Glendinning explains that political events in several mature economies have started to call this process into question, with populist movements either being elected, or becoming a major political force. “The main promise is usually to take back control, and it often involves promoting the home economy by introducing protectionist barriers,” he says. “The promise is usually to bring back jobs which have been ‘stolen’ by the emerging market countries, who are accused of not ‘playing fair’ by maintaining barriers to entry to their own domestic markets.”</p>
<p>Glendinning says it should come as no surprise that this has happened: “It would have been truly exceptional if such a major shift in manufacturing presence and wealth distribution had happened without any tension or resistance at all.” But the key question is how far this trend will go, and whether protectionists will be successful in reversing the movement of economic activity towards emerging markets.</p>
<p>“In the long run, I suspect most people will agree that protectionism is unlikely to work,” comments Glendinning. “It tends to lock in uncompetitive structures and practices, and puts a stop to further innovation and development, meaning the protectionist countries simply fall further behind. Today, several emerging market economies – China and India in particular – have reached the point where the size of their domestic economies and financial reserves mean that countries initiating a trade war with them are likely to lose more than they will gain.”</p>
<p>That doesn’t mean that there will not be efforts to bring in protectionism by some countries, notes Glendinning – “particularly those where fractious domestic politics can result in impulsive actions”. He also says that retaliation against protectionist moves by some countries could lead to potential trade wars, which could be ‘very disruptive’ to today’s highly integrated global economy. “At the moment, it is difficult to assess the likelihood that this will happen – most people in global businesses hope it does not,” he observes. “It is very difficult to stop progress – but progress rarely happens in a smooth, straight line.”</p>

<h3 id="impact-on-asia">Impact on Asia</h3>
<p>As Blyth points out, trade is essential for prosperity, stability and security. “According to the OECD, manufacturing workers in countries that are relatively open to trade earn between three and nine times more than their peers in closed economies,” she comments. And Asia has seen the benefits of greater collaboration: “Half a century ago Southeast Asia was tearing itself apart, but this year the ASEAN bloc celebrates its 50th anniversary. Through cooperation and commerce, the member states have collectively built the world’s seventh-biggest economy.”</p>
<p>“It would be hard for me to think of any region that’s benefited more from free trade than Asia,” comments Atul Jain, Head of Trade Finance – Asia Pacific at Deutsche Bank. “The reality is that most nations in the region – with perhaps the exception of India – have really defined their strategies as export-led over the last few decades.” Jain points out that almost 40% of global trade cuts through the region, with intra-Asia trade constituting about a third of that volume.</p>
<p>Jain says that rhetoric around protectionism “certainly has people worried”, noting that it is becoming very much a western world phenomenon – “which is interesting, because over the last few years, these are the markets that have been promoting an open trade environment and really championing the WTO”.</p>
<h3 id="resurgence-of-the-tpp">Resurgence of the TPP</h3>
<p>Protectionist sentiment has certainly made its mark in the last year – and the withdrawal of the US from the TPP was particularly significant. But while the success of the TPP will obviously be tempered by the withdrawal of the US, it may not all be bad news. “There was a concern that this would have a significant impact on overall trade business – that the agreement would be dead, and every country would have to go through bilateral agreements with the others,” explains Aziz Parvez, Managing Director, Head of Asia Pacific Trade &amp; Supply Chain Finance at Bank of America Merrill Lynch. “But that doesn’t seem to be the case. All of the other countries have come together, under the new name of the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Pacific Partnership (CPTPP).”</p>
<p>Parvez says that while the value of the agreement would have been even greater if the US had been included, it is still meaningful. “The markets we’re talking about include 500m people, with a combined GDP of US$10trn,” he notes. “The agreement could potentially allow companies to move goods, services and investment between member markets seamlessly. As well as benefiting large companies, this may also benefit smaller companies which may have found it harder to navigate all the different trade rules in the past.”</p>
<p>Likewise, the agreement may open up new markets for some countries. “For example, Singapore could gain access to markets like Canada and Mexico, when Singapore hasn’t had any such trade agreement before,” comments Parvez.</p>
<h3 id="one-belt-one-road">One Belt, One Road</h3>
<p>Alongside the nationalistic sentiment arising in some western markets, a number of developments in Asia are adding some different dynamics to the evolving trade landscape. Jain says that with China taking a stronger role, the balance of power in the region is shifting – and that this is giving rise to the idea of an Indo-Pacific trading bloc, including the United States, India, Japan and Australia. He points out that this would allow the relevant countries to establish a counterweight to China’s growing strategic relevance.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, China’s ambitious ‘One Belt, One Road’ initiative – also known as the Belt and Road initiative – is also attracting considerable attention. One Belt, One Road is a development strategy which aims to create new economic corridors spanning more than 60 countries across Asia, Europe, the Middle East and Africa, and covering 60% of the world’s population. The ‘belt’ is a reference to the Silk Road Economic Belt, a land-based network connecting China to Europe. The ‘road’ refers to a modern maritime Silk Road connecting China to east Africa and the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>First announced by President Xi in September 2013, the initiative could see China injecting as much as US$150bn per year into a wide range of infrastructure projects connecting China to other countries. Specific projects include the 850km long Bangkok to Nong Khai railway in Thailand, the East Coast Rail Line in Malaysia and Gwadar port in Pakistan.</p>


<blockquote>Both the TPP and One Belt, One Road could seriously help drive trade across the globe, opening up a lot of opportunities in the countries that are participating.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Aziz Parvez, Managing Director, Head of Asia Pacific Trade &amp; Supply Chain Finance, Bank of America Merrill Lynch</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<span class="scWebEditInput" contenteditable="false" id="fld_A702964D1B89483C9F0620FEE886BFF6_D74F396D5C5E4916BD0ABFD58B6B1967_en_1_1263b552eb70432da45674fd8143c516_19076_edit" sc-part-of="field">
</span><span class="scWebEditInput" contenteditable="false" id="fld_A702964D1B89483C9F0620FEE886BFF6_D74F396D5C5E4916BD0ABFD58B6B1967_en_1_1263b552eb70432da45674fd8143c516_19076_edit" sc-part-of="field"></span>
<p>“This plays to the interests of a lot of parties, and not China
alone,” says Jain. “If you look at China building roads into Kazakhstan,
the benefit for China is clear – they increase their influence into
Kazakhstan, they improve their access and ability to source oil and
other commodities. But at the same time, the infrastructure that gets
left behind from that is obviously a massive benefit to the local
economy and the movement of goods.”</p>
<span class="scWebEditInput" contenteditable="false" id="fld_A702964D1B89483C9F0620FEE886BFF6_D74F396D5C5E4916BD0ABFD58B6B1967_en_1_1263b552eb70432da45674fd8143c516_19076_edit" sc-part-of="field"></span><span class="scWebEditInput" contenteditable="false" id="fld_A702964D1B89483C9F0620FEE886BFF6_D74F396D5C5E4916BD0ABFD58B6B1967_en_1_1263b552eb70432da45674fd8143c516_19076_edit" sc-part-of="field">
</span>
<p>Jain adds that another aspect of this initiative is that many of the
capital goods being used to build the new infrastructure are coming from
developed markets such as Germany, which are consequently benefiting
from job creation. “What’s very clear is that China, the markets
impacted and the developed markets supplying equipment into these
corridors, all win,” he comments. “And that’s fairly rare.”</p>
<p>It’s also important to note that this initiative is not happening in
isolation. Parvez says that in combination, developments like One Belt,
One Road and the CPTPP bode well for the future of global trade. “For
me, both of these initiatives are a reason for optimism,” he says. “I
believe they will help drive trade growth across the globe, opening up a
lot of opportunities for the participating countries.” Parvez notes
that the initiative is already proving relevant to the commodity space –
particularly non-agricultural commodities, where these are being used
to build infrastructure.</p>
<h3 id="what-are-businesses-doing">What are businesses doing?</h3>
<p>Jain points out that the last few years have seen a number of
pressures affecting trade, from the bursting of the commodities bubble
to the stresses arising from AML and KYC requirements. These factors
have led to a subdued environment for most economies in terms of their
capex investment – and as a result, there is little evidence of
companies taking a knee-jerk reaction to current developments.</p>
<p>“There’s definitely a wait and watch approach, but also a very
constructive, positive attitude, and a willingness to get into the
spaces where they see the opportunity today,” Jain explains. “So rather
than viewing these developments as something to be cautious of, I see
many clients looking at One Belt, One Road and thinking about how they
can capture part of that value chain and participate in those
corridors.” He adds that many clients are asking about these
opportunities, “even in the less obvious sectors that don’t immediately
make you think of infrastructure”.</p>
<p>Jain says that one of the messages the bank is giving clients is to
start looking at ASEAN as a destination for goods and services, rather
than just a source. “Over the last few years, there’s been a big focus
on how to take advantage of the young population, urbanisation and low
labour costs in order to get more production out of ASEAN,” he explains.
“But with rising consumerism and the growing middle class, the question
is how companies can start to play on that.”</p>
<p>That said, Jain points out that intra-ASEAN trade is still
challenging: many clients have to deal with over 30 documents in order
to trade within the ASEAN corridor. As a result, other developments may
be needed in order to facilitate trade, from the removal of tariff
barriers to the free flow of labour.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Jain says another message for corporates is to centralise
their treasuries. “It’s difficult to predict when significant currency
volatility is going to take place, and it’s difficult to predict how and
when capital controls will materialise. So having the flexibility to
really think through that and be dynamic about how they manage treasury
is critically important for our clients.”</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>While the world trade arena is fraught with challenges, there are
plenty of positive developments which may bring opportunities for
companies in the coming years. “For me, there are considerable grounds
for optimism,” concludes Parvez. “Both the TPP and One Belt, One Road
could seriously help drive trade across the globe, opening up a lot of
opportunities in the countries that are participating. This could lead
to new trade flows, auguring well for the world economy in general.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[While protectionist sentiment continues to shape the economic policies of some western markets, initiatives currently gaining momentum in Asia could lead to the development of new trade corridors and opportunities, both within the region and with trading partners further afield.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/rainbow-lights-on-akashi-ohashi-pearl-ss253911046-1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2018-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Crossing borders: transacting in Asia’s new reality]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Geopolitical issues have dominated the headlines in recent months, but Asia Pacific has proved resilient to these shocks. Corporations doing cross-border business in the region now need to focus on their short-term tactics and long-term strategies to fit Asia Pacific’s new reality. In this article, Mark Evans, Managing Director, Transaction Banking at ANZ explains how corporates can navigate shifting demand patterns and how China’s policy goals and economic profile are shaping the region.</em></p>



<img alt="Mark Evans" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/technology/emerging-technology/markevans_photosept09-150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=57F1ABFDB9FD5B02779FA0697F482A34" style="margin:0 2em 2em 0;float:left;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Mark Evans</h3>
<h5 class="title">Managing Director, Transaction Banking</h5>
<p><img alt="ANZ" height="30" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/anz-logo-2015-93x30.png?h=30&amp;w=93&amp;la=en&amp;hash=821DDF7A288FB6448A229723FE07E0E6" style="margin-top: 1.5em; height: 30px; width: 93px;" width="93"/></p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>The geopolitical shocks of last year – namely Brexit and the election of Donald Trump – dominated global headlines, with businesses understandably concerned about how the new reality of resurgent economic nationalism might affect cross-border trade and capital flows. Despite the heightened volatility and uncertainty, we do not think these events should be a cause for overreaction. Rather, companies should focus on obtaining a more nuanced understanding of Asia Pacific’s own new reality, characterised by evolving demand patterns and the changing role of China.</p>
<p>The corporate community tends to agree. They tell us that long-term shifts in demand are more significant than short-term volatility, despite the practical challenges the latter may present in the short term. We also find that businesses seeking to make the most of opportunities in this new reality are realigning their thinking to match China’s policy goals and changing economic profile.</p>
<h3 id="shifting-demand-patterns">Shifting demand patterns</h3>
<p>Much attention has been paid to the potential impact on this part of the world of Donald Trump’s trade policies, but we believe that Asia is well placed to withstand the resurgent politics of anti-globalisation. Others agree: the Asian Development Bank recently forecast that Asia-Pacific economies (excluding Japan) would account for 60% of worldwide economic growth this year between them, even with a moderate slowdown expected in China. The prosperity of businesses relies on the extent they can tap into this economic dynamism.</p>
<p>Australia, for instance, is already seeing the impact of shifting demand patterns from Asian economies in this new reality. While resources exports have been subject to some volatility in recent years – and there is little doubt the China-led supercycle is over – other sources of demand from increasingly wealthy Asian populations is catching up, supported in recent months by a softer AUD.</p>


<blockquote>Businesses hoping to tap into these shifting sources of demand need a more nuanced understanding of China’s long-term development and the rationale behind its policies and decision-making.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Growth in services exports, in particular tourism, education and financial services, is rapidly compensating for weaker shipments of resources. Recent data shows the value of tourism-related services alone has almost caught up with iron ore. The constraints here are almost exclusively on the supply side, in the form of the number of flights it is possible to run from key markets, China especially. The positive knock-on effects from expanding supply by adding more flights, such as more hotels, tourism jobs and service infrastructure, are considerable and nowhere near reaching their potential.</p>
<p>And, of course, foreign brands still enjoy some crucial advantages within China, especially when it comes to tapping China’s growing middle class’ demand for quality, trustworthy products. Consumer trust in suppliers is in short supply in China, particularly in the food supply chain, leading to the ever-increasing popularity of daigou sales, where orders are placed online in China for sales agents to pick up produce in physical stores overseas with receipts often required as proof of purchase in the specified location. Reinforcing the message of trust with discerning Chinese consumers is therefore becoming increasingly important.</p>
<h3 id="understanding-a-changing-china">Understanding a changing China</h3>
<p>This means, of course, that businesses hoping to tap into these shifting sources of demand need a more nuanced understanding of China’s long-term development and the rationale behind its policies and decision-making. To say the least, this is not necessarily easy for those outside the country or those doing business across its borders, but it is increasingly important to consider in both long-term strategic planning and short-term tactics.</p>
<p>Taking account of China’s “multiple personalities” is a useful way of understanding the tension between broad policy aims and the sometimes-opaque evolution of rules and regulations for companies transacting with the country.</p>


<blockquote>China embodies the contradictions between a laissez-faire economy and a centrally planned one.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Look at the country’s Five-Year Plans (FYP). They contain detailed blueprints of economic development with measurable targets that cascade from the national to the provincial to the local level—for instance in the 13th FYP to roll out 30,000km of new high-speed rail covering 80% of major cities by 2020. They also reveal the commitment to develop strategic new industries, with the goal of making them account for 15% of GDP. So, while on one level they confirm that China’s demand for resources is far from over, on another they highlight those strategic sectors that are likely to take over from the old, investment-based economy, and which might well become as important to businesses in the future.</p>
<p>At the same time the FYPs also reveals the tensions between long-term strategy and short-term policy. Take the government’s hope for more international business to be conducted in renminbi – reiterated in its commitment in the 13th FYP to continue with the internationalisation of the currency. This necessitates exposing China’s financial system more fully to global market forces, something that is sometimes hard to square with the government’s overriding commitment to promoting stability.</p>
<h3 id="awkward-positions">Awkward positions</h3>
<p>Shifts between the two priorities can put foreign companies doing business in China in an awkward position. After taking several steps to liberalise the flow of capital across its borders in recent years, and to allow the market to play a greater role in the fixing of the value of the renminbi, volatility in the value of the currency (down 6.6% against the USD through 2016) and the level of its foreign exchange reserves (which fell by nearly US$320bn in the same period) made Beijing think more carefully about this process.</p>
<h4 id="chart-01">RMB’s share as an international payments currency</h4>
<p>Customer initiated and institutional payments. Messages exchanged on SWIFT. Based on value.</p>
<p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2017-07and08-tta-06-st__chart-01-rmbs-share-as-an-international-payments-currency-970x713.png?la=en&amp;hash=F6ADB3A7B99B9B649A3284C4EC55887B" target="_blank"><img alt="RMB’s share as an international payments currency" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2017-07and08-tta-06-st__chart-01-rmbs-share-as-an-international-payments-currency-970x713.png?la=en&amp;hash=F6ADB3A7B99B9B649A3284C4EC55887B" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: SWIFTWatch</em></p>
<p>Last November, the authorities took steps to impose certain exchange controls (via its “window guidance”), some of which hit foreign companies’ abilities to remit dividend payments. It looks like these controls have recently been relaxed – but pinning down what is and is not allowed is far from straightforward.</p>
<p>Perhaps unsurprisingly, such measures mean international usage of the RMB has diminished in recent months. But such short-term fluctuations do not change the long-term calculus, or negate the goals set out in the 13th FYP. On the capital account, the plan makes clear that the bid to make the RMB an international investment currency will continue. On the current account, pressure to transact more in renminbi across borders will grow, as Chinese exporters and importers seek to reduce the risks of dealing with a third currency – typically USD – in their international contracts.</p>
<p>Ultimately the greater use of the RMB across borders will work to the advantage of businesses transacting with the country, too, since they will be able to deal more often with direct currency cross rates (and pricing) without worrying about the RMB’s value to third-party currencies. In the end, of course, full internationalisation will require allowing the renminbi’s value to float, something that seems unlikely in the short term but necessary in the long term – and so important to plan for.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Geopolitical issues have dominated the headlines in recent months, but Asia Pacific has proved resilient to these shocks. Corporations doing cross-border business in the region now need to focus on their short-term tactics and long-term strategies to fit Asia Pacific’s new reality. In this article, Mark Evans, Managing Director, Transaction Banking at ANZ explains how corporates can navigate shifting demand patterns and how China’s policy goals and economic profile are shaping the region.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2017-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Crossing borders: navigating the new reality of international business]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>The seemingly inexorable march of globalisation has redefined how businesses operate, enabling them to reach more customers, improve efficiency and ultimately become more profitable. However, in an increasingly complex world, the benefits that have been delivered by globalisation can no longer be taken for granted.</em></p>



<img alt="Mark Evans, Managing Director, Transaction Banking, Institutional, ANZ" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/technology/emerging-technology/markevans_photosept09-150x200.jpg?w=150&amp;la=en&amp;hash=E13215BF65D8B93719F26B88A4D3838A" style="margin: 0px 2em 2em 0px; float: left; width: 150px;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Mark Evans</h3>
<h5 class="title">Managing Director, Transaction Banking, Institutional</h5>
<p><img alt="ANZ" class="logo org" height="24" src="/i/logo/anz-logo-2015-75x24.png" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="ANZ" width="75"/></p>
<p>Mark Evans is Managing Director, Transaction Banking, Institutional at ANZ. Mark is responsible for end-to-end transaction banking services – including payments, cash management, trade finance and supply chain finance solutions – across ANZ’s home markets of Australia and New Zealand and the bank’s footprint globally.</p>


<img alt="Mike Lim, Head of Trade and Supply Chain, ANZ" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/technology/emerging-technology/mike-lim-150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=924A5D07F376305EDB037427C41DABA7" style="margin:0 2em 2em 0;float:left;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Michael Lim</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Trade and Supply Chain</h5>
<p><img alt="ANZ" class="logo org" height="24" src="/i/logo/anz-logo-2015-75x24.png" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="ANZ" width="75"/></p>
<p>Based in Sydney, Mike Lim is responsible for ANZ’s Trade &amp; Supply Chain business which supports our customers in 34 countries. Mike has over 25 years of banking experience in Client Coverage, Risk and Product with the past 15 years focused on trade, commodities and structured finance.</p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>In his book, The World Is Flat: A Brief History of the Twenty-First Century, American author Thomas Friedman details the development of globalisation, beginning in 1492 when Christopher Columbus set sail, opening up trade between the new and old worlds. This period was known as Globalisation 1.0. Globalisation 2.0 followed between 1800 and 2000, as businesses, empowered by technological developments and progress in transport and logistics, began to expand across borders.</p>
<p>In the current era, which Friedman defines as Globalisation 3.0, individuals and businesses from every corner of the world are interconnected and empowered, shrinking the world and creating a truly global marketplace and economy. However, recent events, including the UK’s decision to leave the European Union and Donald Trump’s protectionist rhetoric, have thrown much of what was taken for granted about globalisation into doubt. For businesses operating in Asia Pacific (APAC), this raises some interesting questions about the future of the international business landscape – and whether businesses will be able to continue operating across borders with relative ease.</p>
<h3 id="in-perspective-globalisation-and-international-business">In perspective: globalisation and international business</h3>
<p>The hope is that, despite the events of 2016 and the recent backlash against globalisation, governments will continue to allow global trade to flourish. “Globalisation and the rise of global free trade has had an incredibly positive impact on the global economy,” says Mark Evans, Managing Director, Transaction Banking at ANZ. “Open markets are proven to bring economic growth, innovation, productivity and prosperity.”</p>
<p>The globalised world has also afforded businesses all manner of opportunities to grow by expanding into new markets and creating new revenue streams. Indeed, the latest statistics from the S&amp;P 500 highlight that 44.3% of their profits are made outside of their home market of the US. This trend is further emphasised by large international brands, with stores and products which are ubiquitous around the world.</p>
<p>Globalisation and free trade have enabled businesses not only to increase revenues by tapping into new markets, but also to operate more efficiently, says Michael Lim, Head of Trade and Supply Chain at ANZ. “The opening up of emerging market economies has enabled businesses to think more strategically about their supply chain and pick and choose where they are producing,” he says. “The rationale behind each decision will vary from company to company, but essentially the aim is either to drive cost savings by producing in countries with low labour costs, or to gain a competitive advantage by producing close to the resource base, thereby creating speed and agility in the supply chain.”</p>
<p>Asia Pacific has played a central role as corporate supply chains have evolved, and China has been a particular beneficiary. In the 1990s, China produced less than 3% of global manufacturing output by value. Today, thanks to various economic and trade policy reforms, the country produces nearly 25% of global goods and is the world’s largest exporter.</p>
<p>In more recent years, other countries in Asia, most notably from the ASEAN region, have looked to leverage this trend and take on segments of the supply chain. With over 80% of companies based in emerging markets planning to relocate parts of their supply chains to other emerging markets, it is a strategy that many businesses hope they are able to continue to follow.</p>
<h3 id="challenges-facing-international-business-models">Challenges facing international business models</h3>
<p>This cannot be taken for granted, though, as these operating models are under increasing pressure as globalisation comes under attack. “Socially, there has been a clear backlash around the world against globalisation,” says Evans. “In the western world, people are angry that jobs are being lost as work is outsourced into low-cost markets. This has resulted in political disenfranchisement, with a shift towards political leaders that employ protectionist policies.”</p>
<p>This is most evident in the United States where Donald Trump’s decision to pull the US out of the Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP) – a trade agreement that encompassed 40% of global GDP – and his desire to impose high tariffs to punish foreign governments which adopt unfair trading practices and force US firms to import less, seemingly contradict the globalist policies of most American multinationals.</p>


<blockquote>In particular, ANZ suggests businesses should take a good look at their supply chains, especially if these include countries which are currently embroiled in trade disputes or are leaning towards protectionism. Again, the advice is not to panic but to make sure that a degree of flexibility is built into the supply chain, providing the option of switching suppliers should the need arise.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>While the shift in US policy is causing concern, the US is not the only country to be preaching protectionism. The UK’s decision to leave the European Union is another example, and other countries in Europe are also increasingly looking inwards. This poses a considerable risk to international business, and Evans notes that he has already seen the confidence of many businesses knocked as a result.</p>
<p>It is not just political forces that are putting pressure on the structure of international business. Uncertainty around regulation remains a key impediment, especially in some of APAC’s more restricted markets. To highlight this, Evans discusses some of the recent challenges ANZ’s clients are facing in China. “Doing business in China is much more complex than before and we need to be in a position to help our clients navigate the complexity of Asia’s diverse markets.”</p>
<p>Businesses are also being affected by extra-territorial regulation. “Regulations are tightening, especially around areas such as anti-money laundering and modern slavery,” Evans explains. “This is, of course, a positive move, but what makes it difficult for businesses is that local governments are interpreting these rules differently. Corporates need to be much more careful when using low-cost labour in emerging markets to make sure that they are not breaching any local laws regarding modern slavery, for example.”</p>
<h3 id="the-importance-of-options">The importance of options</h3>
<p>As a result of these pressures, it is not surprising that some firms have begun to ask whether the costs of manufacturing outside of their home markets may outweigh the benefits. These are certainly questions that multinational corporations and their treasury teams, which have increasingly become pivotal in the strategic direction of the company, should be considering.</p>
<p>“We have had numerous clients come to us and ask questions about the various political, economic and social trends in the markets they are operating in,” says Lim. “This is a positive sign because it shows that our clients are thinking proactively about what all these developments mean and trying to understand the risks and opportunities that these create for the business. But our overriding advice is always not to panic: these trends are very unlikely to cause business to grind to a halt.”</p>
<p>That said, some alterations may be needed. As a result of these conversations, ANZ is already seeing many treasury teams make some changes, with some increasing their hedging in light of increased market volatility. “This is helping smooth out that volatility for the business over the short term and this will be a key role for treasurers in the comings months and years,” says Evans.</p>
<p>But any true risk management strategy cannot rely on short-term hedging strategies alone and the business must adapt and evolve in accordance with the changing business environment. “Every good business strategy considers the risks to that strategy and should always have options to move in another direction should need be,” says Evans. “Treasurers should certainly be looking at putting in place a Plan B should these anti-globalisation trends continue. This isn’t alarmist, simply good practice.”</p>
<p>In particular, ANZ suggests businesses should take a good look at their supply chains, especially if these include countries which are currently embroiled in trade disputes or are leaning towards protectionism. Again, the advice is not to panic but to make sure that a degree of flexibility is built into the supply chain, providing the option of switching suppliers should the need arise.</p>
<p>“Supply chains are complex constructs and take a long time to establish and cultivate,” says Lim. “As a result, these cannot be changed overnight, but we do believe that treasurers and procurement teams need to be working together to consider alternative options with the objective of making sure that the business can continue to operate smoothly, no matter what political or regulatory changes occur.”</p>
<p>Ultimately, for treasurers, it is about staying ahead of the game – and with forward planning, this shouldn’t be a problem. “Regulations and legislation don’t typically change overnight,” says Lim. “There is always time to react, but sometimes this does require businesses to be uncharacteristically nimble. We therefore encourage our clients to keep abreast of the winds of political change and ensure they have an action plan for the alternate scenario.”</p>
<h3 id="digital-trade-flows">Digital trade flows</h3>
<p>While treasurers manage the risks of doing business across multiple international markets, there are also opportunities that must be considered, particularly in the digital space. E-commerce, for instance, has proliferated in recent years and now accounts for an estimated 12% of all trade. For businesses, the ability to reach a broader audience without the need for a bricks and mortar store is clearly attractive.</p>
<p>If sales are to go truly digital, so must the underlying processes that support these. “We have been talking about international trade going digital for decades and in recent years this has begun to gain some real momentum,” notes Lim. “But as e-commerce takes hold, corporates are beginning to see the full benefits of removing paper and creating efficiencies, both from a cost and control perspective and in terms of removing friction from the process.”</p>
<p>It is not easy though, and corporates can often find themselves caught having to manage local laws that can sometimes prohibit the digitisation of business. “We hope that this will not always be the case,” says Lim. “Countries such as Singapore are leading the way in promoting digital trade flows. I think these efforts will converge and we will see other countries following suit because the benefits for all parties are clear.”</p>
<h3 id="payments-innovation">Payments innovation</h3>
<p>If the product and document flow is to be seamless, the payment flow needs to be similarly smooth. Unfortunately, at present, the underlying payments infrastructure often causes problems for organisations operating and selling internationally. Payments, especially cross-border, are cited as being slow, expensive, opaque and problematic from an operational and compliance perspective.</p>
<p>Despite this, Evans is keen to highlight that a lot of work is being done at present to improve the payments infrastructure. “SWIFT’s global payment innovation (gpi) initiative is just one exciting development and we are very interested to see how it works now it is live,” he says. “It has the potential to solve many of the cross-border payments challenges that companies face by providing full visibility over transactions, delivering certainty and eventually also providing rich remittance information.”</p>
<p>Evans also notes that blockchain will have a role to play in the payments space and in the digitisation of trade documents. “It is clear that distributed ledger technology will provide our clients enormous benefits at some stage in the future,” he says. “We have already been involved in a number of groundbreaking pilots, including testing the technology in cross-border payments, and we will keep working on this area. It is important though that expectations are managed. Treasurers need to understand that it is not going to fix all the challenges in international business overnight, but slowly benefits begin to be realised.”</p>
<p>All this innovation, no matter what form, typically brings a standardised set of benefits. As Evans explains: “For all parties involved in international trade, these digital solutions help provide transparency, certainty and efficiency, creating a better trading environment for all.”</p>
<p>To take advantage of all this technological change, treasurers once again need to be prepared. Lim advises that treasurers should ensure that their processes are efficient and standardised. “If they are not, it will be very difficult to move quickly and take advantage of these new technologies once they become available,” he says.</p>
<h3 id="finger-on-the-pulse">Finger on the pulse</h3>
<p>Despite the events of 2016 and a perceived pushback against globalisation, business remains increasingly international, from the existence of complex supply chains to the opportunities brought by e-commerce. But in this period of heightened volatility, it is prudent to question current business models and their long-term viability.</p>
<p>Managing this dichotomy between the forces of globalisation and localisation will pose an interesting challenge to corporates and their treasury teams in the years ahead. In order to prepare for what is to come, both Evans and Lim reaffirm that it is important to have options in place and to plan for any different scenarios that could impact the business. “This is crucial to help corporate treasury teams, as well as procurement teams, manage risks proactively and position themselves to take advantage of any opportunities as they arise,” concludes Evans.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[The seemingly inexorable march of globalisation has redefined how businesses operate, enabling them to reach more customers, improve efficiency and ultimately become more profitable. However, in an increasingly complex world, the benefits that have been delivered by globalisation can no longer be taken for granted.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2017-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Trade winds]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=45697C7EDF70DA6037F6B347EE8EC320"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5789283460AFCEBE51D6D1EB28CCE71E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=5717A67FD02E4A2EBCF60AC2DF2E8425"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=43A0977C7FDA633DA0D3395E61C9CF29"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=693A2717102A660F6289728D001EDF3E"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Old windmill at dawn in Australia" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7D6331D0CA7F9695DF602C02AE294D42" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7D6331D0CA7F9695DF602C02AE294D42"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>In recent years, trade growth has failed to outpace the rate of global economic growth, for the first time since 1985. The impact of this has been felt in Asia especially, as the world’s most vibrant trading region, impacting both its economies and companies alike. In this article, we look at what corporate treasurers can do to navigate the business through these difficult times, and also how new technology is transforming trade finance.</em></p>
<p>The MSC Oliver – the world’s largest containership – is a feat of human engineering. At just under a quarter mile in length and with a payload of 19,224 twenty-foot equivalent units (the standard size of a shipping container) – 39,000 cars in real terms – the liner bookmarks another chapter in the race to build bigger and better vessels. It was built partly to meet the expected increase in global trade volumes, or at least that was the expectation when the ship was ordered a few years previous in 2013.</p>
<p>At that point the Baltic Dry Index (an indicator of the cost of moving major raw materials by sea, and an index intrinsically linked to world trade volumes and the health of the global economy) had been steadily climbing, reaching its highest level since 2010. But since then, the index has fallen to its lowest level since the 2007-08 crisis (<a href="#chart-1">see Chart 1 below</a>). The result: bigger vessels, but less cargo to ship.</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Baltic Dry Index 388.00 0 (0%)</h4>
<p><a href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2016-05-06-tt-07-tr-chart-01-baltic-dry-index-967x359.png?la=en&amp;hash=72D2805343BD403943FEF95A2D10941F" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: Baltic Dry Index 388.00 0 (0%)" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2016-05-06-tt-07-tr-chart-01-baltic-dry-index-967x359.png?la=en&amp;hash=72D2805343BD403943FEF95A2D10941F" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: <a href="http://investing.com">Investing.com</a></em></p>]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[In recent years, trade growth has failed to outpace the rate of global economic growth, for the first time since 1985. The impact of this has been felt in Asia especially, as the world’s most vibrant trading region, impacting both its economies and companies alike. In this article, we look at what corporate treasurers can do to navigate the business through these difficult times, and also how new technology is transforming trade finance.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/20160506tta07tranolddisusedwindmillatdawnneargemtreenorthernterritoryaustraliass3151312071920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-04-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[India: the new factory of the world]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>Much has been made of China and its position as the world’s largest manufacturing and trading nation. Yet, as wages in China rise corporates are increasingly looking beyond the country to other markets. India is looking to take advantage of this opportunity and mobilise its enormous workforce. In this article we explore the steps India is taking to make it a business friendly location and what corporates need to know when trading with and in the country.</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CEBE5EA7201A40E383BC9090E8AF2ACF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F05C4427CBD778870429F9F4581A559D"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9653F30DA95AF1E87551D3B6093FC129"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=200666E88DD748D73ABF059CC26BA801"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=C72882DE20B7130A5B766E8D2910F63C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Traditional Indian slipper shoes" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BFBFA6C01CE2654D39FBEFF7ECF51FD6" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BFBFA6C01CE2654D39FBEFF7ECF51FD6"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>In August this year, Taiwanese electronics manufacturing giant Foxconn announced that it had signed a $5bn deal to establish both R&amp;D and manufacturing facilities in western India before 2020. The deal is the largest foreign investment to date in the country’s technology manufacturing sector and will see the company build up to 12 new factories and hire as many as one million workers. Although Foxconn, like many other foreign names such as Panasonic and Lenovo, has had manufacturing operations in the country for a number of years, the announcement highlights India’s increasing pull as a manufacturing hub for foreign multinationals.</p>
<p>This is a dramatic shift from two decades ago when India was regarded as a closed and unfriendly business destination. As a result, India largely missed out as foreign multinationals expanded their operations into Asia and established low-cost manufacturing centres across the region. Regulatory change, investment and a new national focus on growth and progress however, has seen the tide begin to turn. India is now set to be at the centre of another seismic shift in global trade and supply chains as it aims to become the new factory of the world.</p>
<h3 id="building-new-corridors">Building new corridors</h3>
<p>In the last 20 years there has been a dramatic swing in global trade corridors. Where once trade was conducted primarily between developed Western nations: today, emerging markets (EMs), and more specifically Asia, are now at the heart of global trade flows. EMs for example, now account for nearly half of world exports – up from one-fifth in 1990. And according to the IMF, one-third of the $15trn of global trade is now conducted between emerging and developing economies, known commonly as South-South trade.</p>
<p>The changes in global trade flows cannot be attributed to one key factor; instead they are the result of a variety of shifts and events in the wider world over the past few decades. For starters, geopolitical developments – such as the breakup of the Soviet Union and the liberalisation of emerging economies – have played a significant role. Improvements and a reduction in the price of communication technology, thanks to the rise of the internet, have also played an important role in making the world smaller and more interconnected. Meanwhile, the creation of trade bodies such as the WTO in 1995 has looked to regulate global trade and allow it to flow freer and fairer.</p>
<p>Using these developments as a springboard, EMs have blossomed as their governments have liberalised trade, recognising the economic benefits afforded to them by adopting an export-led economy. Regional and bi-lateral trade agreements, which have proliferated in recent years, have been used to further widen these new trade corridors.</p>


<blockquote>India is now set to be at the centre of another seismic shift in global trade and supply chains as it aims to become the new factory of the world.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>With it now easier to do business in many EMs around the world, corporates have taken the opportunity to transform their supply chains and trade policies, adopting a model known as the vertical supply chain. In a vertical chain, the basic functions in the production cycle are outsourced to countries with low labour costs and the higher skilled functions are kept in traditionally more high-skilled countries – Apple’s goods, for instance, are designed in California and assembled in China.</p>
<p>The growth of vertical supply chains has transformed China and has seen the country being nicknamed ‘the factory of the world’, sitting at the heart of many global supply chains. China has been able to take the lead in this regard because its vast population has allowed for huge volumes of output and also for labour costs to be kept low. But recent signs suggest China may be intentionally loosening its grip as the world’s manufacturing hub as it shifts towards a more consumption-based economy, looks to expand its service sector, and its middle class grows. These developments are seeing workers in China demanding higher wages and thus the cost of business is increasing.</p>
<h3 id="make-in-india">Make in India</h3>
<p>It is against this backdrop where India’s opportunity lies. The country already boasts a sizeable economy worth over $2trn and posted a 7.4% growth rate in 2014 making it the fastest growing major economy along with China. Unsurprisingly, GDP per capita is also on the rise, increasing to $1,610 in 2014 from $1,560 the previous year. Continuing at this growth rate, the economy should move from the ‘lower middle income’ category to the ‘upper middle income’ level in the space of ten years.</p>
<p>“To help achieve this there is now a big push in the country to transform India into a manufacturing hub,” says Anjali Mohanty, Head of Global Transaction Banking – India at Deutsche Bank. As well as helping boost the economy the move will also benefit the Indian population. As Mohanty explains: “India has a population over 1.3 billion and with more than ten million people moving into employment each year, the country has a vast workforce. Manufacturing is the only sector that can produce jobs to this scale.” As <a href="#chart-1">Chart 1</a> depicts only 9.4% of India’s 487 million strong workforce is employed in the manufacturing sector.</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Industrial revolution</h4>
<a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__chart-01__industrial-revolution__585x985.png?la=en&amp;hash=2DFD37F6ED5B1D7A20D163102D3FADD6" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: Industrial revolution" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__chart-01__industrial-revolution__585x985.png?la=en&amp;hash=2DFD37F6ED5B1D7A20D163102D3FADD6" width="400"/></a>
<p class="source"><em>Source: Bloomberg Business Week</em></p>
<p>There is good reason for this: when compared to other economies, India’s trajectory is quite unique. It progressed from an agricultural economy straight into a services-based economy, essentially skipping the manufacturing phase which most go through. As a result, India exports around 3% of the world’s services but only 1.7% of merchandise. “To transform the Indian economy into one based on manufacturing therefore is not an easy task and one that hasn’t been attempted by any country before,” adds Mohanty.</p>
<p>To help achieve this, the Modi government have implemented a number of initiatives that build on the work done by previous administrations. The most notable of these is ‘Make in India’ – a national program that is designed to facilitate investment, foster innovation, enhance the skills of the workforce and ultimately build a best-in-class manufacturing infrastructure.</p>
<p>“This is just one of many initiatives that the Modi government has implemented or is looking to implement,” says Mohanty. For instance, the government is beginning to invest heavily in, and seek outside investment in infrastructure – something that can be argued as being underdeveloped. “The cost of doing business in India due to the leakage that occurs because of the poor infrastructure is one of the biggest drains on a company’s profitability.”</p>
<p>Overall the main objective of these initiatives is to make India an easier and thus more attractive place to do business. Although there has been some progress made already, India is regarded by the World Bank as being the 142<sup>nd</sup> most difficult country to do business (out of 189), Mohanty therefore advises caution: “These changes won’t occur overnight,” she says. “India is an extremely large and complex market and it will therefore take time before we begin to see results.”</p>
<h3 id="diversifying-trade-flows">Diversifying trade flows</h3>
<p>Once change does occur and India begins to play an even more important role in global trade, its key trading partners are likely to be based in the East. The China/India corridor is one that looks set to gain particular significance. “China has already replaced the US as India’s primary trading partner,” says Sonal Priyanka, Managing Director, Regional Head of Trade, South East Asia, India and the Middle East at Societe Generale. “This corridor will continue to grow as India develops into a manufacturing hub and potentially becomes the world’s largest as the country purchases intermediate goods from China, converts these into finished goods before exporting them to the rest of the world.”</p>
<p>The Modi administration has also began investing in India’s regional neighbours to facilitate greater trade flows. “ASEAN for example, will be a key trading partner for India moving forward. In recent years we have already seen India invest in the region to drive further trade,” says Vijay Vashist, Global Head of Trade &amp; Supply Chain Finance and Trade Asset Management at DBS. “As part of this focus, the Modi government has recently given the green light to support a new tri-lateral highway, a road which links Thailand to India.”</p>
<p>Away from Asia, Africa and the Middle East will also play a big role in Indian cross-border trade moving forward. “We are already seeing a lot of development and growth in these trade corridors,” says Societe Generale’s Priyanka. In 2014 India’s trade with Africa was worth $74bn, up 80% since 2008 while it is expected that by 2030 Indian trade flows with the Middle East and Africa will reach up to $2.7trn, up from just under $200bn in 2013 – making it the region’s top trading partner.</p>
<p>In terms of what India will be trading, the country wants to be at the heart of, it seems, all sectors. On the ‘Make in India’ website, there are 25 different sectors ranging from automobiles to wellness. Of course, it would be a tough ask for India to be at the centre of trade flows for all of these sectors, but there are some that the country already has an advantage in and that provide a big opportunity to corporates.</p>
<p>“Tourism is an industry that employs 40 million people and it is predicted to grow at rates of 8% in coming years,” says DBS’ Vashist. “However the tourism infrastructure is underdeveloped, so this presents a good opportunity for airlines and hotel companies to expand in the country.” Aside from this, Vashist highlights industries such as textiles, automobiles and software where India has been strong in exports and opportunities are expected to grow.</p>
<h3 id="a-paper-based-ecosystem">A paper-based ecosystem</h3>
<p>As Indian corporates begin to increase the amount they trade cross-border with counterparts and as India becomes an increasingly important location for multinational supply chains, trade financing products will be needed. Today, 85% of global trade occurs on Open Account – otherwise known as non-documentary trade. Yet, in India, Open Account is not the dominant tool and Letters of Credit (LCs) are still used heavily by corporates for both imports and exports – according to SWIFT data, India is in the top five countries globally in this regard.</p>
<p>Of course, in today’s increasingly digital world, corporates globally are striving to move away from paper-based products. As a result, some of the banks operating in India have stepped in to move the documentary burden away from corporates. This is a service that Deutsche Bank for example, has begun to offer its clients by managing the paper documents and offering a view of these through a single online portal. “This helps mitigate risk, increases security and also makes reconciliation easier and quicker,” says Mohanty.</p>
<p>The Indian government has also recognised the challenges that such a high usage of paper creates for corporates in India of all sizes. One of the biggest is that because of the inefficiency associated with paper and also the red tape that exists, many Indian companies – especially small and medium enterprises – are paid late. To counteract this, the government introduced the Factoring Regulation Bill in 2012 that provided a statutory framework for factoring and has addressed the issue of late payment.</p>
<p>Despite these developments and attempts by some corporates to digitise their operations in India, it is no easy task to remove paper from the process. “These digital solutions need to work in the regulatory framework of India which currently is very paper intensive,” says Societe Generale’s Priyanka.</p>


<blockquote>With it now easier to do business in many EMs around the world, corporates have taken the opportunity to transform their supply chains and trade policies, adopting a model known as the vertical supply chain.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>The growing Indian trade flows with Africa also mean that paper-based solutions set to remain a key part of corporate operations. “When an Indian company begins selling into Africa or an African company begins selling into India, they will use LCs to mitigate the risk associated with the transaction because of the nature of the market and the unfamiliarity between the counterparties,” says Priyanka. “For some corporates however, this may not be enough so we offer a service called LC confirmation. In these instances, Societe Generale, as confirming bank, takes on the risk of the LC issuing bank of the African importer and this is proving to be a very popular solution for these flows due to the risk rating differential between the two regions.”</p>


<blockquote>Another product which is gaining particular traction in India is supply chain finance (SCF) and this looks set to become particularly important as India becomes a key part of global supply chains.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Another product which is gaining particular traction in India is supply chain finance (SCF) and this looks set to become particularly important as India becomes a key part of global supply chains. “A lot of companies in India are in the growth phase and need investment. As a result, there can be some pressure applied to the supply chain,” says Deutsche’s Mohanty. “This is magnified when we consider the infrastructure challenges, inefficiencies around paper-based trade on one hand and Indian banks getting more risk averse, which together creates a big working capital dilemma for many of the smaller suppliers and buyers.”</p>
<p>To resolve this challenge, SCF solutions can be utilised to provide medium to long-term support for the supply chain. “There is an added benefit for these companies because it will often reduce their cost of borrowing as well,” adds Mohanty.</p>
<h3 id="an-indian-summer">An Indian summer</h3>
<p>The new factory of the world is still a work in progress and of course, everything is not in India’s control. In 2015 for example, exports slumped as global demand remained sluggish and without this demand some corporates may be reluctant to tinker with their supply chains or invest significant capex building new factories in India. There also remains a lot of work to be done around the regulatory environment and in reducing the red tape, although the steps that have already been taken are a good indication that the country is moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>Yet overall, the outlook is bright. “If we look back to 1990, the Indian economy was very much closed off, tariffs were high and there were lots of restrictions on imports and foreign investment,” says DBS’s Vashist. “There has been plenty of progress since then through liberalisation and reform. This has directly impacted Indian trade flows, especially in the last few years. For instance, the percentage of trade to GDP has picked up from 15% in 1990 to 35% in 2005 and climbed to 54.2% in 2013. This is a fairly substantial amount.”</p>
<p>India however, is not going to become the world’s prominent manufacturing centre overnight. Whilst trade volumes are increasing, it will take time to reach the levels of China, but it certainly seems to have the potential to become a global manufacturing powerhouse in the coming years.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Much has been made of China and its position as the world’s largest manufacturing and trading nation. Yet, as wages in China rise corporates are increasingly looking beyond the country to other markets. India is looking to take advantage of this opportunity and mobilise its enormous workforce. In this article we explore the steps India is taking to make it a business friendly location and what corporates need to know when trading with and in the country.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-11and12-tta-08-tr__indian-traditional-slipper-shoes-ss98721512__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Redback rising: RMB trade invoicing gaining traction]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>According to the latest SWIFT tracker, renminbi (RMB) has advanced to the fifth most widely used currency for global payments. With the value of cross-border deals settled in the redback more than doubling in 2014, it is not surprising that more multinational companies are choosing to invoice in RMB as they look to improve profit margins.</em></p>



<img alt="Ann Lin Khoo, Regional Product Manager, Liquidity Management Services, Asia Pacific, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/citi-rmb-ann-lin-khoo-150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=479EAADB777C25F6C9ACACF0A89038E6" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Ann Lin Khoo</h3>
<h5 class="title">Regional Product Manager, Liquidity Management Services, Asia Pacific, Treasury and Trade Solutions</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi logo" class="logo org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Citi" width="50"/></p>


<img alt="Tracy Ge, China Sales Head Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/citi-rmb-tracy-ge-150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=7C37D98507A829EEADB973BF24EB7991" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Tracy Ge</h3>
<h5 class="title">China Sales Head Treasury and Trade Solutions</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi logo" class="logo org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" title="Citi" width="50"/></p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Opportunities for RMB cross-border trade settlement have developed rapidly since the first liberalisation moves in 2009. Today, there is a growing trend towards the use of RMB for transactions. Indeed, the latest SWIFT RMB Tracker data shows the Chinese currency has moved up from its position as the 20<sup>th</sup> global payment currency to fifth in the last two years.</p>
<p>Multinational companies (MNCs) are taking advantage of a number of benefits – whether to reduce foreign exchange (FX) risk and administrative costs, gain from potential RMB appreciation, or to expand and strengthen relationships in their supply chain ecosystem. In fact, there is growing evidence that companies can improve their negotiating position with Chinese customers and suppliers when the Chinese currency is used for trade invoicing purposes.</p>
<p>While there are strong incentives for companies outside of China to transact in RMB, not all companies are prepared to jump on the bandwagon at this point. What are the considerations that treasurers need to evaluate before making the switch to RMB as an invoicing currency?</p>
<h3 id="key-benefits">Key benefits</h3>
<p>For companies buying from China and selling overseas, especially MNCs executing inter-company transactions with their Chinese entities, settling such deals in RMB reduces exposure to FX risks. It also enables centralisation of FX management at the regional, group or in-house bank level, which allows for economies of scale and improved pricing negotiation. For example, entities are able to receive proceeds settled in RMB earlier (versus foreign currency receipts in China), facilitating improved cash flow forecasting and negotiation for better pricing terms. Other benefits include potential discounting from third-party suppliers and access to a larger supplier base.</p>
<p>For companies sourcing from overseas and selling to buyers in China, there are benefits to be gained with a simpler documentation process by using RMB (versus foreign currency payments) enabling a more efficient collection cycle and access to a larger customer base. For MNCs with significant intercompany flows with China, there are benefits in centralising the FX risks with an overseas function such as a treasury centre or in-house-bank versus using the local Chinese entity which may not have the know-how or primary responsibility to effectively manage FX positions.</p>
<h3 id="likely-first-movers">Likely first-movers</h3>
<p>With the benefits in mind, the types of companies most incentivised to adopt RMB at present are those with manufacturing and sales in the China market. These companies are typically in the fast-moving consumer goods, healthcare or industrials sectors. Naturally, it makes sense for these companies to offset their operational expenses in the same currency that is generated from their revenue. In addition, due to the benefits from FX hedging, companies with significant intercompany flows with China have also been the first to review and make the switch to RMB.</p>
<p>On the other hand, invoicing in USD is still the more convenient choice for US-headquartered companies since they can eliminate FX risk by trading in their home currency. Other Western MNCs may find managing USD FX risk to be less challenging than managing RMB risk. Similarly, transaction flows from businesses, such as electronics or oil commodities, where China is part of the supply chain and not the only supplier or buyer, will continue to be denominated in USD.</p>
<p>Weak currencies have served to bolster RMB appeal too. Recent depreciation of the euro, for example, has notably influenced the dynamic of European companies’ adoption of RMB. Indeed, volatilities in the European currencies and other weak global currencies have prompted some companies to gradually increase their use of RMB in a bid to diversify and mitigate FX exposures.</p>
<h3 id="considerations-before-making-the-switch">Considerations before making the switch</h3>
<p>Changing an invoicing currency is never easy as this involves a comprehensive review across all relevant business units and systems. A company needs to ensure there is sufficient implementation resources assigned to execute the change and the perceived benefits, as have been highlighted above, are sufficient to warrant the costs likely to incur.</p>
<p>The change to RMB trade invoicing needs to be a long-term strategy as it cannot be easily reversed given the rules and regulations in China and the potentially high switch-back costs. The following considerations should be evaluated:</p>
<h4 id="introduction-of-a-new-currency-code-cnh">1. Introduction of a new currency code – CNH</h4>
<p>With the existence of two currency codes for RMB, namely onshore CNY and offshore CNH, companies will need to ensure that their treasury and dealing systems allow for trading in CNH as a new currency. In addition, any incremental risks, tenor availability and instruments available in accessing the CNH market needs to be considered in foreign exchange policies. It is the case too that the trade settlement currency for RMB remains as CNY and therefore may create currency/system conflicts which need to be reviewed.</p>
<h4 id="changes-to-trade-documentation">2. Changes to trade documentation</h4>
<p>While the RMB internationalisation initiative has simplified processing, there are still cross-border controls in place and nuances which companies must understand for effective implementation. Supporting documentation will need to be amended accordingly to ensure proper validation can be conducted by the relevant authorities in China. The list includes the intercompany trade agreement, purchase order, place of acceptance authority document and the invoice (the<em>fapiao</em>which is an official invoice registered at the local tax bureau and is used as a form of proof of purchase).</p>
<h4 id="understanding-the-nuances-of-rmb-settlement">3. Understanding the nuances of RMB settlement</h4>
<p>We have seen significant progress over the past few years, however compared to USD, RMB settlement is still very much in its infancy and there are several considerations that a corporate should be aware of in ensuring that their payment obligations continue to be fulfilled on a timely basis.</p>



<h3>Additional information required for RMB payments with China</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>CNAPS bank code.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Detailed transaction details for reporting (RCPMIS/BOP).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Accurate beneficiary name (in English).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Other considerations</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Different clearing and settlement systems can result in varying payment cut-off times and holiday handling schedules.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Beneficiaries can access the funds once they are received by the bank in China.</p>
</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<h4 id="benefiting-from-the-different-programmes-in-china">4. Benefiting from the different programmes in China</h4>
<p>Moving on from simplifying processes for current account activities, the country has seen the introduction of payment programmes stemming from the Shanghai Free Trade Zone (SFTZ) and nationwide initiatives allowing payments to be performed on a net basis or on-behalf-of. These programmes allow companies to conduct payments with China on a more streamlined basis, as they do in other more developed countries.</p>
<h3 id="the-rmb-journey-continues">The RMB journey continues</h3>
<p>Without doubt, RMB internationalisation will accelerate. Over time, this will introduce incremental changes and flexibility offered by way of pilot programmes such as other Free Trade Zones, as well as improvements to cross-border controls and processes.</p>
<p>There will be potential tipping points for increased RMB invoicing going forward, and Citi continues to lead the way in helping clients to evaluate the opportunities created from ongoing regulatory reforms. At the right time, and specific to a company’s needs, RMB invoicing can certainly open new doors for companies – whether by negotiating cost savings or pursuing attractive new trading relationships with buyers or suppliers only willing to trade in RMB.</p>
<p>The key for treasurers is to start preparing their companies to make the timely switch when the opportunity arises.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[According to the latest SWIFT tracker, renminbi (RMB) has advanced to the fifth most widely used currency for global payments. With the value of cross-border deals settled in the redback more than doubling in 2014, it is not surprising that more multinational companies are choosing to invoice in RMB as they look to improve profit margins.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[The trouble with preferential treatment]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>While free trade agreements continue to proliferate at a remarkable pace in Asia, the utilisation rates are on the whole negligible. Is this because governments have not effectively communicated the benefits? Or are FTAs simply not all they are cracked up to be?</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=148340B730F3AB03CD91CCF88DE7E00F"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7CFFFA947E7B9638D52BD4751DAA4CCF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=78F6C8BC47E61F323A3B6806B5DFD864"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AAB633E534660A80AE4BB8592799D1B7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6C31B20722E92D643333DD1785D0EF65"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Cranes forklifts at dusk" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AF6715D4DC7E95742D6AC22334C456D" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=7AF6715D4DC7E95742D6AC22334C456D"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>A well-known economic priority for many governments in Asia of late – and indeed in much of the Western world – has been to encourage companies to pursue a global strategy. Globalisation and technology have made the world a much smaller place and the companies today that don’t explore growth opportunities beyond their own shores are likely to drown in a sea of competition.</p>
<p>That makes sense. Ever since the economist David Ricardo observed that countries do well when they focus on what they are relatively good at producing, the benefits of free trade have never really been in doubt. However, governments should bear in mind that, counterintuitive as it sounds, the benefits of Free Trade Agreements (FTAs), which in Asia have been the dominant channel through which governments have sought to foster greater cross-border business, are not quite so evident.</p>
<p>Just look at the figures. While Asia has seen an enormous proliferation of FTAs across Asia in recent years – both bilateral and regional – utilisation rates of Asian FTAs are notably low. Usually uptake by businesses ranges between a mere 10% and 20%, according to Asia Development Bank (ADB) figures. Often the fact that few businesses seem to be taking advantage of FTAs open to them is blamed on poor communication. There is a common line of argument that says FTAs would see much greater uptake if only governments did more to publicise their existence to treasurers, Chief Procurement Officers (CPOs) and other key corporate decision makers.</p>
<p>Last year a HSBC sponsored study by the Economist Intelligence Unit argued this exact point. The survey revealed that of the 800 businesses – large and small – that were surveyed across a total of eight different jurisdictions, only 26% are using the FTAs that have been established. If you dig down a little further into the data, only 19% were taking advantage of bilateral FTAs, the agreements that have been most common across the continent. Does this apparent lack of enthusiasm for FTAs from the region’s exporters reflect the fact that exporters see no value in the agreements? Other findings suggest that this is not the case. Of the 26% who use FTAs, 86% reported that their exports had seen an increase as a consequence of trading under the terms of the agreement. An additional 24% told the researchers that they their exports had increased significantly as a result of their participation.</p>
<h3 id="legal-minefield">Legal minefield</h3>
<p>Not everybody is convinced this is always the reason, however. One alternative explanation is that companies are by and large aware of FTAs negotiated between countries where they do business; but they simply do not have the time, expertise and resources to make sense of what they need to do to take advantage of them. Usually certain complex criteria must be met in order for goods to be exempted from import duty or qualify for lower rates. And when you think about the number of FTAs in place across the Asia region, each containing perhaps hundreds of pages of dense legal text it is not difficult to imagine some companies reasoning that utilisation is not worth the hassle.</p>
<p>“Currently, the Rules of Origin differ in each FTA negotiated and it is not easy for laymen to comprehend the legal text of the concluded FTA,” says Angelia Chew, Partner, Trade &amp; Customs, Indirect Tax at KPMG in Singapore. “Although the benefits of FTAs are clear, the cost of not meeting these criteria is hefty. Customs authorities in the region are aggressively conducting FTA audits. Any non-compliance will result in penalties and interest payable on top of the duty shortfall. Many companies – including multinationals and small-medium enterprises – give up on applying for FTAs as they do not have sufficient resources to fully understand the rules in the agreements and are unable to manage compliance concerns.”</p>
<p>Can anything be done to resolve this issue? Well, as often is the case when complexity is the challenge, technology is one possible solution (for those that the initial outlay is not prohibitively expensive, of course). There are on the market a whole range of automation models that can integrate FTA functionality with company Enterprise Resource Management (ERP) systems and leverage the capability of similarly integrated Global Trade Management (GTM) systems.</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: Why FTAs remain on the shelf</h4>
<p><a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-07and08-tta-07-tr__chart-01__why-ftas-remain-on-the-shelf__1792x720.png?la=en&amp;hash=810363F5236AC6DEE2C3997E2284F4C3" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: Why FTAs remain on the shelf" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-07and08-tta-07-tr__chart-01__why-ftas-remain-on-the-shelf__1792x720.png?la=en&amp;hash=810363F5236AC6DEE2C3997E2284F4C3" width="967"/></a></p>
<p class="source"><em>Source: Economist Intelligence Unit</em></p>
<p>Solutions like these work by allowing companies to solicit and store origin data from suppliers, and calculate the origin for manufactured products. In addition, they can also make it easier to generate and track origin requests. All in all such tools such as these can provide companies with a structured, controlled process through which to calculate preferential origin and, importantly, eliminating the fear of non-compliance by ensuring everything is in place ahead of customs audits.</p>
<p>There is also another, third perspective on the issue. “I don’t think it is about information,” says Jayant Menon, Lead Economist, Economic Research and Regional Cooperation Department, ADB. Analyse the detail of the vast majority of FTAs and the rationale of those companies choosing not to utilise an FTA soon becomes apparent. “In a lot of these agreements, the difference between the preferential rate provided by the FTA and the normal Most Favoured Nation (MFN) rate, the difference is quite small or even zero. For some tariff lines, where there are much larger preference margins, utilisation might be higher and could be increased by more information. But by and large the problem is that the margins are simply not there to worry about using them.”</p>
<p>The fourth explanation relates to Asia’s distinctive trade relationships. As a recent ADB Working Paper on the matter points out, about two-thirds of intra-regional exports consists of intermediate goods (eg parts and components) and much, if not all, of this trade already travels duty-free, or at very low rates. There are several reasons. First, a significant proportion of the parts and components being traded are electronics exempt from tariffs under World Trade Organisation’s Information Technology Agreement. Second, many of these intermediate goods may also be subject to duty-drawback schemes under which tariffs can be waived. Then the last point to make, which is applicable to final as well as intermediate goods, is that tariffs have been in any case been declining in the region in recent years irrespective of any FTAs.</p>
<h3 id="too-many-ftas">Too many FTAs</h3>
<p>Governments in Asia should take note. There are currently more than 100 FTAs in place over the region, and many more still being negotiated. With the negotiation of each of these agreements using up considerable time and administrative resources, one would think it sensible to at least consider whether there might be more effective means by which greater intra-regional trade can be facilitated. FTAs, remember, are but one way to encourage trade and, in fact, can sometimes encourage the wrong kind of trade ie trade diversion.</p>
<p>That quickly becomes a vicious circle. Non-signatory countries, not wishing to lose market position, will endeavour to negotiate their own agreements. “They feel forced to come into the game and sign FTAs with others,” says Carlos Kuriyama, Senior Analyst at the APEC Policy Support Unit, Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC). “Everyone then wants to have preferential treatment over others and it creates distortions.” No wonder we’ve seen such a proliferation in bilateral and regional agreements in Asia-Pacific over the past ten years. FTAs, it seems, beget more FTAs.</p>


<blockquote>My view is that we’ve got to the point where there are so many FTAs, that they are becoming a burden rather than a benefit.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Jayant Menon, Lead Economist, Economic Research and Regional Cooperation Department, ADB</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>“My view is that we’ve got to the point where there are so many FTAs, that they are becoming a burden rather than a benefit,” says Menon. Radical though it may sound, instead of wasting yet more time and energy negotiating yet more agreements with one another why don’t policy-makers, Menon asks, focus on harmonising what is already in place and offer the accords to everyone on a non-discriminatory basis? This would be advantageous in two respects. “If you offer it to everyone, you would have lowered your barriers to trade and you’ve reduced your cost of administering multiple FTAs and multiple rules of origin. It would encourage greater trade and, ultimately, isn’t that the real objective of an FTA?”</p>
<p>That would appear to be the kind of thinking that has informed the Beijing-backed plans to establish a vast, Free Trade Area of Asia Pacific (FTAAP). At the APEC summit held in late 2014, the Chinese President Xi Jinping announced that the bloc had “approved the roadmap for APEC to promote and realise the FTAAP.” It was a ‘historic’ step, he added, and one which reflected the “confidence and commitment of the APEC members to promote the integration of the regional economy.”</p>


<blockquote>Companies should start seriously considering how they can best use FTAs to reap the benefits of duty savings as soon as possible.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Angelia Chew, Partner, Trade &amp; Customs, Indirect Tax, KPMG, Singapore</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Despite China’s apparent optimism there is no doubting that the diversity of markets in Asia will pose a big obstacle that will need to be overcome if this objective is to be realised. After all, one of the reasons that FTAs are so popular is that in most cases they involve fewer countries and so differences are easier to iron out. “It is possible for the Asia Pacific free trade area to become a reality in the next ten years but the biggest challenge lies in harmonising the rules of all the various FTAs signed,” says KPMG’s Chew. “While this will take some time, companies should start seriously considering how they can best use FTAs to reap the benefits of duty savings as soon as possible.”</p>
<p>If negotiations over the so-called ‘mega-regionals’ – the Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP) and the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (R-CEP) have become protracted, how long will it take to reach consensus between every economy in the region? If those can be concluded though it might just pave the way for something bigger. “Right now there are some big regional agreements being negotiated and if these don’t see the light of day it’s going to be hard for a free trade area across the Asia-Pacific to become a reality,” cautions APEC’s Kuriyama. “But I think those regional agreements, if they can be established, could serve as a stepping stone to something like the FTAAP.”</p>
<p>What now then? As negotiations over the so-called ‘mega-regionals’ – the contentious TPP and R-CEP – roll on, Menon’s observations raise the question of whether such agreements are worth pursuing at all. What precisely would be gained by those deals, even in the best-case-scenario? “We will end up with a fragmented world trade system carved up into different trading blocks,” he says. “This will not be good for members, or for non-members.”</p>
<p>Indeed, neither, perhaps, is that the type of distortion-free trading paradigm that David Ricardo had in mind when he articulated his theory of comparative advantage. To rework an old saying of the great Chinese philosopher Confucius, one might say that trade is actually really simple – it’s just that the governments of countries sometimes insist on making it complex.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[While free trade agreements continue to proliferate at a remarkable pace in Asia, the utilisation rates are on the whole negligible. Is this because governments have not effectively communicated the benefits? Or are FTAs simply not all they are cracked up to be?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/when-the-container-terminal-at-dusk-work-cranes-and-forklift-239182291-1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[The new trade paradigm in ASEAN]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=77FFDB57FD986F36D4CAD8A09348D1C3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A2A80634D40EF046718280E1AAA11248"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FA16E94FB7968D14267AEDAD29738E37"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=522D28B4AABCF87AC0489A241C595E12"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A970595F03FD6F54907E77AC8CD896EB"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="ss-creative-arrangement-of-technological-design-elements-and-circular-turbulence-as-a-concept-metaphor-110631776-1920x1080" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CCF3DFFE36F385466EF564958576E99D" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=CCF3DFFE36F385466EF564958576E99D"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><i>Later this year there will be an economic shake-up the like of which has never been witnessed before in Asia. Yet, for all the excitement around the birth of the ASEAN Economic Community (AEC) and the prospect of greater intra-regional trade on the horizon, the economic data appears to indicate that this ambition will not be realised overnight.</i></p>
<p>Boosting intra-ASEAN trade is important, for obvious reasons. All countries that – like China and India – boast a high share of global trade have one thing in common. The share of business being done with countries in close proximity to them is considerably higher than their counterparts. In the European Union (EU) and the North American Trade Association (NAFTA), for example, intra-regional trade currently averages around 50%. In ASEAN, the figure is not even half that.</p>
<p>Speaking about the soon-to-be established AEC at a recent trade summit, the Singapore Foreign Affairs and Law Minister, K. Shanmugam acknowledged this reality, and called upon the region’s leaders to step up to the challenge and make the elimination of trade barriers a priority of the new AEC in the coming years.</p>
<p>“What does [the AEC] mean for our people?” K. Shanmugam asked delegates. “It must increase trade. It must increase the economic relationship.”</p>
<h3 id="breaking-down-barriers">Breaking down barriers</h3>
<p>Although the ultimate goal is still some way off, recent ASEAN trade figures should make encouraging reading for K. Shanmugam. Ahead of the birth of the new AEC, an area which promises the freer flow of goods, services, investment and labour, trade between ASEAN economies has been rising. In fact, in recent years it has grown at a considerably faster rate than extra-ASEAN trade, boosted by the fact that the promise of integration has led a number of the region’s large multinationals to establish offices in regional hubs to support their trading activities. Faster intra-regional growth can be seen as a positive sign, even if it’s building, of course, from a much lower base.</p>
<p>“Countries in the ASEAN region seem to be buying and selling more to one another,” says Sonal Priyanka, Regional Head of Trade for South East Asia, India and the Middle East at Societe Generale. “It is being driven partly by the promise of ASEAN integration under the Asean Economic Community and the consequent loosening of trade barriers in some of the markets.”</p>
<h3 id="new-trade-flows">New trade flows</h3>
<p>Economic integration is only part of the story however. To gain a better understanding of how and why ASEAN trade flows are changing, one must look at another macroeconomic trend taking place in the region; a shift in the types of goods being exported from ASEAN.</p>
<p>For much of the early part of the millennium, export of intermediate goods – products used in the eventual production of a finished good – was the dominant trade flow from ASEAN. This is now changing. “There is a lot more export of finished products from ASEAN now, as more and more multinationals (MNCs) are using ASEAN directly as part of their international supply chains,” says Priyanka. And this is all leading, she explains, to “a shift from the sale of unfinished goods to finished goods.”</p>
<p>Countries in South East Asia are no longer simply sub-contracting from main suppliers in China, sending their intermediate goods for final assembly in China. As China becomes less attractive to some MNCs as a supplier of finished products, these MNCs are looking for alternatives, and ASEAN is rising as an alternate low-cost producer to China.</p>
<p>This trend is part of the region’s natural economic evolution, explains Simon Constantinides, Regional Head of Global Trade and Receivables Finance Asia Pacific at HSBC. “ASEAN is an economy with $2.4 trillion of GDP and 640 million people. It has vast natural resources and considerable manufacturing capacity. And now you’ve got good pricing from a labour cost perspective also,” he says. “I think that is driving a lot of the activity we are seeing combined with certain government intervention to improve FDI opportunities and promote a more flexible environment for cross border trade. So I think it is the natural evolution and growth of the emerging markets within the ASEAN block.”</p>
<p>As ASEAN’s role in the international supply chain changes, new trade relationships are beginning to blossom. Japanese investment in South East Asia, which has boomed in recent years, is one example, explains Priyanka. It’s been a remarkable resurgence. According to Dealogic, the value of mergers and acquisitions executed by Japanese companies –auto industry firms particularly – in ASEAN rose to $8.2 billion in 2013, a level not seen since the mid-1990s. “We are seeing growing Japanese interest in the region at the moment,” she says. “A lot of Japanese corporates are now setting up their manufacturing operations here, away from the traditional manufacturing hub of China, due to cost and other reasons.”</p>
<p>Despite the recent excitement around Japan, there is still only one economic powerhouse when it comes to trade in the region. ASEAN is now the fourth largest destination for outward investment from China, accounting for more than 60% of the country’s foreign direct investment (FDI) volume. Given the structural changes being witnessed in both ASEAN and China the nature of the goods being exchanged has changed, but China’s importance as a trading partner has never waned. On the contrary, increased trade flows can be seen in some countries. Trade flows between Malaysia and China, for example, grew from RMB 128 billion in 2009, to over RMB 203 billion in 2013. More broadly, annual bilateral trade between China and ASEAN’s ten member states is expected to rise $1 trillion by 2020.</p>
<p>Banks know they cannot afford to stand still in the face of these big changes now transforming the region. The new trade paradigm that can be seen emerging is creating new demands for trade solutions in the region. To meet these demands, banks have had to respond with a range of new solutions using a broader range of currencies and new forms of financing aligned with new ways of settlement.</p>
<h3 id="new-trade-flows-demand-new-solutions">New trade flows demand new solutions</h3>
<p>In ASEAN, like in much of the rest of Asia and the world, there has been a pronounced shift from traditional instruments such as the Letter of Credit (LC) to Open Account settlement. “There has been a steady growth in the documentary trade business, with a rise in Open Account trade amongst Asian corporates,” says George Fong, Asia Head of Trade Product Management and FI Advisory at J.P. Morgan.</p>
<p>Although this trend is not unique to ASEAN (80% of trade is now settled on Open Account globally), Fong believes it to be closely linked to recent developments on the ground, such as the growth in intra-ASEAN trade and the new financing needs this is generating amongst both Western and, increasingly, Asian multinationals. “We definitely see those local factors helping switch the terms of trade from instruments like the LC to Open Account or other negotiable trade instruments.”</p>
<p>But despite the ongoing decline of the LC, one of the biggest impediments to intra-ASEAN trade remains paper documentation. Trade finance in ASEAN remains highly paper-intensive, something which obviously slows down the whole settlement process. Electronic trade solutions, meanwhile, can offer both better business flows and improved security for corporates in the ASEAN region.</p>
<p>In 2013, the announcement of new International Chamber of Commerce rules to govern the use of the Bank Payment Obligation (BPO) raised industry hopes that such archaic instruments may soon be consigned to the history books. However, almost two years on, it is clear that this was never going to happen overnight. For the time begin at least, the BPO is only being used by a select handful of large corporates – mostly in the commodities space – and for everyone else with trade finance needs, manual, paper-based processes remain very much the order of the day. “Paper-based trade most certainly dominates still,” says HSBC’s Contstantinides. “The BPO is not a widely adopted capability within ASEAN yet,” he adds.</p>
<p>Why are electronic trade solutions such as the BPO finding it so difficult to get off the ground? Now that there is more legal certainty around the solution following the creation of the ICC rulebook, answers must be sought elsewhere.</p>
<p>Global banks have, on the whole, been very supportive of the BPO. That is all very well if you’re a treasurer for a company that is banking with one of these large, sophisticated organisations. But that’s far from the norm in ASEAN, MACT’s Azmi Abdullah, Group Treasurer of Genting Bhd and Malaysian Association of Corporate Treasurers (MACT) committee member points out. “The regional banks that dominate the banking scene in ASEAN will have to step up their efforts to automate some of these trade finance solutions in the coming years,” he says. “The global institutions, who are very selective in their clientele, still lead the business of providing trade solutions.”</p>
<p>The dematerialisation is certainly an important issue for corporates in the region of all shapes and sizes and it’s one which we will return to and explore in more depth in the next issue of Treasury Today Asia. Now, though, we will consider how trade in ASEAN is becoming less dollar-centric, shaped by China’s supremacy in the region and the recent efforts of its regulators to gradually liberalise the renminbi (RMB).</p>
<h3 id="rise-of-the-redback">Rise of the redback</h3>
<p>For any company doing business in China today – ASEAN domiciled or otherwise – settling trade transactions in RMB might make a lot of sense since it can reduce risk naturally, offering opportunities for hedging without having to go through a third currency.</p>
<p>It’s not surprising then that, given the growing opportunities for corporates to move RMB in and out of China now, settling in RMB is becoming an increasingly popular option. This phenomenon is bigger than China, of course. Ask any treasurer in the world today and most will tell you that the RMB is assuming an ever greater role in trade settlement. This anecdotal evidence is reinforced by recent data. The RMB now stands as the seventh-ranked global payments currency and accounted for 1.72% of global payments, an all-time record (<a href="#chart-1">see Chart 1</a>). In September 2014 alone, the value of RMB global payments increased by 13.2%, well above the average 8.1% growth for all currencies.</p>
<figure class="center">
<figcaption>
<h5 id="chart-1">Chart 1: RMB as world payments currency in value</h5>
<br/>
<p id="chart-1"><img alt="2015-01and02-tta-08-tr-chart-01-rmb-as-world-payments-currency-in-value-970x496" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/2015-01and02-tta-08-tr-chart-01-rmb-as-world-payments-currency-in-value-970x496.jpg?h=496&amp;w=970&amp;la=en&amp;hash=F789F6ACD4633F3CA66A2469F0E91CAC" style="width: 970px; height: 496px;"/></p>
</figcaption>
<p class="source"><i>Source: SWIFT Watch</i></p>
</figure>
<i></i><br/>
<p>ASEAN has been a part of the RMB’s rise, as much as any other country. RMB usage by ASEAN countries has, according to data supplied by Bank of America Merrill Lynch, doubled (+103%) year-on-year with an estimated FY value close to RMB 2.6 billion. “This is a significant move in anyone’s language and it shows that ASEAN trade is supporting RMB internationalisation confidently,” says Kuresh Sarjan, Head of Trade and Supply Chain at BofA Merrill. “Overall, the RMB has consistently strengthened its position in a relatively short period of time,” he adds.</p>
<h3 id="tomorrows-asean">Tomorrow’s ASEAN</h3>
<p>In less than 12 months’ time, ASEAN will open a new chapter in the history of its economic development with the creation of the AEC. Significant obstacles still stand in the way of this ambition, however, with the region still notorious, of course, for economic protectionism and stringently regulated financial markets.</p>
<p>But the incentives for ASEAN nations to overcome these obstacles are truly enormous. If the promised AEC succeeds in accelerating recent growth in intra-regional trade, the benefits it will bring for businesses operating in the region will be very significant indeed. Recent analysis conducted by the McKinsey Global Institute (MGI), for example, found that greater integration could translate into productivity benefits worth up to up to 20% of the cost base for some ASEAN manufacturers.</p>
<p>Corporates, of course, will want to be prepared as much as possible for the new opportunities that will be coming their way after 2015, looking at how changing regulation might impact the currencies they can and cannot use and the trade solutions available to them. It’s going to be a busy year for treasurers.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/trade-and-supply-chain/global-trade/sscreativearrangementoftechnologicaldesignelementsandcircularturbulenceasaconceptmetaphor11063177619.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[South-South trade: opportunity shifts east]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Trade flows lie at the heart of the global economic system. Cross-border transactions underpin the prosperity of nations, influencing anything from the current account to inflation rates. For much of the past three centuries, Europe and North America have dominated the patterns of international commerce.</p>
<p>But how long will this last? A surge in inter-regional trade between Asia, the Middle East, Africa and Latin America means that this supremacy may well decline in the long term. These ‘South-South’ trade flows are directed toward fast-growing emerging markets, side-stepping sluggish economies in the developed world. Moreover, they are already having formative impact on core treasury areas, such as foreign exchange (FX) management and supply chain strategies.</p>
<p>Emerging market exports have rebounded faster than world exports following the global financial crisis, according to a United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD) report in June. South-South exports increased by 30% between 2009 and 2010 alone, compared to 22% for the latter. Economic troubles in the West have spurred developing nations to realign their economic interests towards flourishing regions.</p>
<p>In 2010, for instance, China signed $16 billion worth of trade deals with India during a visit by the Chinese premier, compared to just $10 billion with the US when President Obama arrived in town. Brazil, Myanmar, Iran and Afghanistan all count China as their largest foreign investor, with much-needed funding ploughed into infrastructural projects that facilitate business and trade.</p>
<p>“The global financial crisis was a watershed moment from the perspective of increased focus and attention to South-South trade flows,” says Kah Chye Tan, Global Head of Trade and Working Capital at Barclays. “In many ways, it has been happening for quite some time. We are seeing less trade intermediation traditionally played by the European countries.”</p>
<p>Western governments and consumers, for their part, are busy deleveraging. As a result, aggregate demand remains weak and provides little incentive for emerging economies, such as China and Brazil, to devote substantial resources towards building trade relations down the line. Developing countries are understandably looking elsewhere for business opportunities.</p>
<p>“Global economic troubles have yet to subside, and that is evidenced by the challenges in Europe,” says Simon Constantinides, HSBC’s Regional Head of Global Trade and Receivables Finance, Asia Pacific. “We have started to see a knock on effect on China because of the continued slowdown on the European continent where China has large business interests. However, if you look at Asia you will find that the area is reliant on regional trade as well. Over 50% of China’s trade is with other Asian countries, for example.”</p>
<h3 id="asia-blooms">Asia blooms</h3>
<p>In a sense, South-South trade is very much trade with, and within, Asia. UNCTAD figures suggest that Asia accounts for over 80% of all South-South exports; and that nearly three-quarters of this figure can be attributed to Asian countries trading with each other. China acts as the centre of gravity for a new pattern of commerce stimulated by rapid urbanisation rates and infrastructural developments.</p>
<p>Latin America and Africa, on the whole, are marginal actors – though nevertheless important ones. These regions account for 10% and 6% of South-South exports, respectively. An Ernst &amp; Young corporate survey in 2011 pointed out that a significant portion of this inter-regional trade represents flows of goods between and within companies – such as rubber, plastics and metal products – as opposed to finished products for consumers.</p>
<p>“China is operating a two-way trade market with Latin America,” observes Constantinides at HSBC. “It is importing iron ore, soy and other commodities and at the same time offering a significant quantity of finished products that aims to satisfy the large consumer base in Latin America. And while there is growing potential for trade between those two regions, we also know that China and Africa have very active trade models, developing and competing with India.”</p>
<p>But India is no paper tiger either, argues Barclay’s Tan. “As a market, it has transformed quite nicely in the past five to ten years,” he notes. “India used to be an exceedingly closed market. There was always a lot of trade, but it was intra-India, things are changing rapidly. Indian trade flow with China has ballooned, and trade with Africa has increased too. The country has a strong competitive edge in manufactured goods and pharmaceutical products.”</p>
<p>Indeed, UNCTAD figures put manufactures at 60% of South-South exports. HSBC research in mid-2011 predicted that South-South trade and capital flows will jump by a factor of ten in the next 40 years. And the exact composition of that trade will likely change over time. As demand in developing regions increases, local preferences will figure in on a wider scale. The car industry is a good example. European manufacturers specialise in high-end, bulky automobiles, such as a Mercedes or BMW, that signify status as much as convenience. But Asian producers, such as the Indian firm Tata, have created a niche for themselves by manufacturing cheaper, lighter and durable cars that cater towards the needs of lower middle-class families that prize expediency over style.</p>
<p>With economic barriers still relatively high compared to trade policies in North America and Europe, the room for further improvements in scale and interdependency is huge. Trade is likely to flourish as obstacles to commerce become gradually dismantled.</p>
<h3 id="fx-risk-goes-red">FX risk goes red</h3>
<p>All this is well and good. But what do these developments mean for the corporate treasurer? The revolution in trade is manifesting itself in two core spheres of treasury practice: FX risk management and supply chain management. Taken together, these two trends are influencing key aspects of the international treasury landscape.</p>
<p>Where there are trade flows, there are capital requirements. With the US dollar beset by a troubled North American economy, the surge in South-South trade will be a powerful factor in the continued liberalisation of the Chinese redback. Corporates have become long accustomed to trading with an FX ‘triumvirate’ of the US dollar, euro and yen. But in the medium to long term, the renminbi (RMB) may well add a new dimension to this framework, particularly given that China will play a central role in future economic growth.</p>
<p>Since the late 1970s, China has become the workshop of the world, producing anything from simple toys to iPods. But underneath its economy lies a paradox. To date, despite the economic and military prowess of the Asian Tiger, its currency has played a minimal role in international financial affairs. A SWIFT paper in mid-2011 highlighted the fact that the yuan made up for just 0.9% of FX trades. This figure pales in comparison to the US dollar’s 45.9% and the 16.9% of the euro.</p>
<p>This situation is likely to change. China acts as a magnet that attracts the resources and goods of surrounding regions, a position that affords the country a tremendous bargaining power. It is an influence that feeds into cross-border transactions, too: the RMB is already gaining ground as the currency of choice used to execute trades.</p>
<p>“We know that 10% of China’s trade is settled in RMB,” says Constantinides. “This illustrates that companies are now becoming more astute, focused and interested in what trading RMB can do on a competitive basis. First, they get pricing visibility, because now they can get a two-way quote in either euro or US dollar (in terms of the RMB). Second, if China’s imports are going to grow significantly, Chinese buyers are going to want to use their currency. They don’t want to go into the market as much to buy dollars when they are going to get paid in RMB; so they would rather become more comfortable in eliminating the FX risk. We believe that the redback will become more and more significant as a major trade currency.”</p>
<p>An HSBC survey last October, for instance, suggested that 71% of Chinese corporates expect one-third of all Chinese trade to be executed in RMB. Moreover, four out of every ten Chinese businesses were willing to offer discounts of up to 3% on trades in RMB. Treasurers need to get used to the idea that FX risk management will take on an increasingly red hue. Best treasury practice is now likely to be in tune with the latest developments of onshore and offshore RMB markets. More corporates will be using RMB to manage their FX risks, in turn bringing operational and accounting advantages while based in the region. Indeed, key management meetings are now often held in Asia as a signal of the region’s importance to some international corporates.</p>
<p>So far, Chinese authorities have been reluctant to ease capital controls by too much. Policymakers in Beijing are all too aware of the example set by the Asian financial crisis in the late 1990s, when neighbouring economies in south-east Asia succumbed to sudden outflows of capital and fell into economic ruin. Countries such as Thailand had liberal capital regimes that allowed investors to exit by the click of a mouse button. The Asian Tiger largely escaped the chaos given its tightly controlled redback. And as a result, Chinese authorities are still cautious about dismantling capital barriers in one fell swoop. A gradual approach to liberalisation is preferred.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the redback is a currency with a bedrock of confidence. As long as there are business opportunities to be won, international companies will be willing to execute trades in yuan.</p>
<p>But a changed FX risk management arena is not the only symptom of South-South trade flows. Given that the RMB remains a tightly controlled currency, this will have implications for trade finance practice in developing economies. This restriction will inevitably feed into, and limit, the level of trade finance services offered by banks operating in Asia. On the one hand, corporates are lured into the region by strong demand. On the other, however, they face potential bottlenecks when it comes to executing RMB trades via trade finance instruments.</p>
<h3 id="supply-goes-south-south">Supply goes South-South</h3>
<p>The dynamics of supply chain management are also at the forefront of change. Emerging market prosperity has been coupled with (relatively) low wage growth, affording international corporates more attractive locations to set up shop. The appeal stems from greater political stability and hard-nosed business logic; and is strengthened by rock-bottom transport and transaction costs via air, sea and the electronic ether.</p>
<p>With business opportunities shifting eastward, there is an increasing incentive to shift supply chain towards the regions that matter: Asia and Latin America. This is all the more important for corporates that wish to tap into local demand in these areas. A regional supply chain allows the company to adapt quickly to shifts in the regional economy, or even changes in consumer preferences. And it can deliver large cost savings given the shorter delivery times involved.</p>
<p>Ernst &amp; Young’s 2011 corporate survey contended, “the fact that rapid-growth markets, and China in particular, will represent the fastest growing source of final demand over the coming decade, will provide additional impetus for firms to locate production in the destination region to serve emerging markets more responsively.” More than two-thirds of the companies surveyed, the report went on to remark, noted that their supply chain is increasingly being developed to service their company’s growth in emerging markets.</p>
<p>Strong relationships and trust were found to be the key factors influencing corporate strategies. Increasingly, international corporates are becoming more comfortable with suppliers based in multiple regions as opposed to concentrating all their eggs in one basket.</p>
<p>But this shift, while useful, is certainly not flawless. First, delegating the supply chain to regional actors entails a loss of centralisation and direct control over suppliers and production. And second, the corporate’s reputation is at risk in case of local failures to adhere to product quality and labour standards.</p>
<p>On top of these two issues comes the difficulty of establishing a proper foothold into the regions. Entry to South-South trade markets can be an arduous, time-costly process – although one that is alleviated by the fact that the shift in trade patterns is likely to continue into the long run. It is a matter for corporate treasurers to weigh short-term costs against the long-term benefits, a difficult task in the current harsh business environment.</p>
<h3 id="catching-up">Catching up</h3>
<p>“Trade flows are really changing,” says Tan at Barclays. “If you go back three or four decades, one leg of the transaction would have always ended up in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) market. Today you now find that one leg of the transaction will end up in the Asian market. It is very hard today to find a trade flow where one leg is not in Asia.” Many corporates would agree with Tan. Business opportunities are flowing eastwards along with trade. The only question is when corporates decide to tap into these currents.</p>
<p>The world economy is not a zero-sum game; the rise of the East does not necessarily come at the expense of the West. Indeed, the continued development of South-South trade can be beneficial for all parties, argues Tan. With China shifting to a consumer economy from an export-led one, international business can tap into the Asian giant’s rising tide of consumer wealth.</p>
<p>Emerging nations, for their part, benefit from a greater degree of economic independence. “Being able to loosen policy at a time of global economic and financial stress is a relatively new phenomenon for emerging market policy makers and it reflects improved external balance sheets, lower inflation and more flexible exchange rate regimes compared to earlier decades,” says Brian Coulton, Emerging Market Strategist at Legal and General Investment Management (LGIM).</p>
<p>And there is plenty of room for development. Per capita incomes, a proxy for assessing standards of living, remain rather low in China, Brazil, India and other developing economies. As trade flows persist, they will surely rise towards Western levels.</p>
<p>When viewed historically, South-South trade flows are just another example of an ‘economic catch-up’ at work. A millennium ago, Asia and Africa dominated the routes of world trade – at a point in time when Europe was still an undeveloped backwater. The US was a small economy in the mid-19<sup>th</sup> Century, but then went on to assume global leadership within 100 years. For now, it seems, economic affluence is swinging back to the East and it is likely to stay there for some time. Corporates should grab a hold while they can.</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2013-01-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Trade]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
