<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: Recruiting and retaining talent]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>“How is the competition for talent affecting treasury and what are the best strategies for recruiting and retaining talent?”</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AD0784AD7F34AF346A2F451F344CE5E8"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=2F33F00A1A45224B08A55329F97704C3"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=681EB379C2D19A35E566D2531BD2B2F7"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=F3AE0730C7C469DC217EDE9257E30838"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EF4A12DB13485574CDBBF015CBFBB1CD"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Black background with silhouettes and magnifying glass" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FCD057A49A6EC9E7BFEBED40D9A43C96" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=FCD057A49A6EC9E7BFEBED40D9A43C96"/></picture> 



<img alt="Portrait of Kemi Bolarin, Head of Treasury – Europe, GXO" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__kemi-bolarin__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=36344A77E3D18A261510621673EBF36F" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Kemi Bolarin, Head of Treasury – Europe, GXO" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Kemi Bolarin</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Treasury – Europe</h5>
<h5 class="org">GXO</h5>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>There is a great deal of talk about the Great Resignation which was triggered by the COVID-19 pandemic. It is more the great re-think or the great re-awakening! The lockdown was an opportunity for most to rethink and re-prioritise work-life balance. I was part of the great resignation, changing roles twice last year, including leaving a role I had for only a few weeks before moving to GXO. It was then and still is an employee-centred job market.</p>
<p>My first task at GXO was to set up a new treasury team based in Europe. I have filled most of the open positions and have two open roles left. One of the two open roles was filled last year, and the individual has since decided to move on. Testimony to a very active job market. While we speak to the impacts of the lockdown and the Great Resignation, treasury is fast evolving as a profession, and role requirements are changing.</p>
<p>As the treasury profession disentangles from pure operational treasury and transforms to a centre of excellence, we are looking beyond technical abilities in FX and cash management and expanding skills requirements to include data analysis and data science. I am looking for individuals that can think outside the box and help us use technology to elevate our treasury to world class. Individuals that are passionate about the application of AI, machine learning and robotics. To compound the recruitment challenges, fintechs are also in the same job market seeking these ‘tech-savvy’ talents.</p>
<p>So, the question is: how can we be attractive to the talents out there and retain them when hired?</p>
<p>Pre-pandemic recruitment process needs to be tweaked to attract the highly sought after ‘new wave talents’.</p>
<p>Organisations need to think creatively about pay packages that combine good market base rate and benefits, career growth opportunities and flexible working arrangements. ESG performance and reporting is also a recurring topic with applicants.</p>
<p>How do we achieve getting talents through the door? A close working partnership with good quality recruitment agencies that offer bespoke services is vital. This is no longer a one-size-fits-all-DIY-job advert job market. It is important to work together with reputable recruitment agencies in developing relevant job descriptions that will appeal to the modern-day applicants out there in the job market.</p>
<p>Talent secured, tick.</p>
<p>What next? Retain hired talent.</p>
<p>There is a list of considerations here – organisations need to adopt the human approach; it is foremost about people, mental health and wellbeing. Review work culture, train managers in how to maintain high team engagement and be aware of staff burnout; improve and promote a healthy work-life balance.</p>
<p>The lockdown has shown us that remote working is possible, and it is top of the list of applicants’ requests. At GXO, I recently interviewed a brilliant lady who demanded that full-time remote working be written into her contract. While we offer flexible working arrangements, I couldn’t commit the company to such a contract because circumstances change. Though the elements of the role appealed to the lady, and she was keen to join the team, 100% remote working was her top priority, so she gave up the offer. The lady accepted another role the next day at another organisation that offered her 100% remote working.</p>
<p>Managing a remote team comes with its challenges especially given the importance of retaining and keeping staff engaged. It is now more important than ever to ensure that managers are trained and equipped with the right tools to successfully manage remote teams.</p>
<p>At GXO, career development is very important to our executives; our Group Treasurer takes a keen interest in team members’ individual development plan. Once people know their employer is appreciative of enhanced knowledge, there is a high chance that they will stay motivated and engaged.</p>
<p>Recruitment is made more complicated with wage inflation, pay is all over the place. It’s challenging to benchmark talent and near impossible to assess upfront if the successful applicant has the right skills. Recruitment is expensive in fees and time, hence the importance of engaging good quality and experienced recruitment agencies in the field.</p>
<p>In my opinion, pay levels will eventually adjust but remote working is here to stay, and leaders need to embrace it.</p>




<img alt="Portrait of Mike Richards, CEO and Founder, The Treasury Recruitment Company" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__mike-richards__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=2B60E187DAD3D505E2C27806D31A4B46" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Mike Richards, CEO and Founder, The Treasury Recruitment Company" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Mike Richards</h3>
<h5 class="title">CEO and Founder</h5>
<h5 class="org">The Treasury Recruitment Company</h5>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>We are a global treasury recruitment firm recruiting at all levels from Treasury Analyst to Global Treasurer for large multinational corporates and consultancies.</p>
<p>Initially at the start of the pandemic you might have 100 people applying for a job. Then it dropped down to 50 and then it was ten and now it’s two. And it might be a perfect role and everything else, but the fact is people don’t need to move now. And that’s the thing employers must realise, they need to present an irresistible proposition if they want to attract the best talent.</p>
<p>I was talking to a client from a large global automotive company, famous brand, and everything else. He was saying to me that he was trying to recruit, and he showed me two or three different adverts that they were placing. And they were just a copy and paste of job descriptions and duties. And that’s the difference.</p>
<p>The most successful employers will get in the heads of a candidate and the ones that are able to sell themselves and present themselves in a way where people want to join them.</p>
<p>It’s a fact that you don’t need to work five days a week in the office now. No one does. The pandemic has proved that. It’s about working out how many days you think is your preference/needed and then reaching an agreement between the employee/employer to suit everyone.</p>
<p>I know that there’s a couple of my clients in the US who have found it quite difficult. They have found it hard because some of the older members of the team, for instance, the CFO who lives near the office, wants everyone in the team back in the office 100% of the time.</p>
<p>That’s starting to cause a problem for others who have long commutes and feel the pressure to return to the office. Employers need to work out their future policy and what’s going to happen in the world of work and flexibility, because if you’re not flexible you may lose out on top talent. Being able to be flexible in this area is where you are going to gain a competitive advantage or disadvantage in the market. The minute you can get past that is when you gain a competitive advantage.</p>
<p>And it’s not about you anymore. Now, candidates will vote with their feet, they won’t necessarily decide they want to come back for your second interview. And in terms of your current staff, if people don’t enjoy working with you and you don’t give them the flexibility and you can’t work together in partnership, then they will simply leave.</p>
<p>A client asked me the other day why would we use you?</p>
<p>I explained, because I’m not talking to candidates who are actively seeking new roles, I spend my time talking to candidates who aren’t seeking new roles. Ninety five percent of the people we speak to are passive candidates.</p>




<img alt="Portrait of Wei Kher Wong, Manger, Michael Page, Singapore" class="portrait" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__wei-kher-wong__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F048122D6A89BD068EE3085764D382D0" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" title="Portrait of Wei Kher Wong, Manger, Michael Page, Singapore" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn" style="margin-bottom:5px;">Wei Kher Wong</h3>
<h5 class="title">Manger</h5>
<h5 class="org">Michael Page, Singapore</h5>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>

<p>I have been with Michael Page in Singapore for four years where my clients largely comprise banks and MAS-licensed companies based in Singapore. We are a team of nine specialist recruiters working in the financial services industry to fill all positions from mid to senior levels, including treasury.</p>
<p>In contrast to other regions, the treasury employment market in Singapore is relatively flat at the moment. Mostly because the supply of professionals in front and back office treasury jobs is slow and movement is limited. Because there is a limited pool of treasury roles in Singapore, it makes for an element of musical chairs. This situation contrasts with sectors such as accountancy where we are seeing an abundance of new positions.</p>
<p>Movement and churn are also slow because most corporate treasury functions in Singapore are already lean. Treasury teams in Singapore are typically part of bigger APAC offices for example Hong Kong. However, when Hong Kong treasury teams struggle to recruit, we have noticed a shift to move those positions into Singapore. Although the treasury roles are relatively less here, the employment market has been very busy. As evident in our annual salary survey report, average salary increment has increased over the past two years.</p>
<p>During COVID we observed a churn in traditional banking and financial services roles. Virtual interviews led to a trend of candidates being offered two or three job, driving up competition and salaries. It was also not uncommon to see treasury candidates using these offers from different companies to drive their salaries higher and ask for increments.</p>
<p>It’s interesting to see the different ways companies are trying to retain staff. At Michael Page we have adopted a methodology that we share with our clients to help reduce attrition rates which have evolved around the work from home culture. WFH reduces human interaction and increases stress; we advise Wellness Days and that companies review their benefit packages. Candidates don’t just look at their salary anymore; they look at corporate culture and how well companies treat their staff. This also includes levels of inclusivity and how involved they are within the company. Pay is no longer the only factor.</p>



<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<p><em>“As the threat of recession becomes increasingly real, what should treasury prioritise?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[“How is the competition for talent affecting treasury and what are the best strategies for recruiting and retaining talent?”]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2022-07-08-tt-00-qa__qa__black-background-silhouettes-men-women-focus-1183433839__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2022-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Team Management]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Building a digital culture]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h5 id="rohit-talwar-fast-future"><img alt="Portrait of Rohit Talwar, CEO, Fast Future" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2017-09and10-tt-01-qa-rohit-talwar-100x150.jpg?h=150&amp;w=100&amp;la=en&amp;hash=B8C7E972223DB07E36A0091D1B35FE50" style="height: 150px; width: 100px;"/></h5>
<h5 id="rohit-talwar-fast-future">Rohit Talwar, CEO, Fast Future:</h5>
<p>For treasury today, perhaps the biggest challenges are those of raising the function’s technological literacy and evolving genuinely digital mindsets. As the digital disruption typhoon sweeps across the business landscape, surviving the storm requires senior treasurers to improve the understanding of themselves and their teams of what emerging technologies enable in terms of functionality and new ways of thinking and doing business. Opportunities are arising through new fintech solutions for treasury functions to bypass banks and other providers – but understanding and realising the opportunities requires deep digital literacy. Technology advances enable radically different concepts underpinned by dramatically different ways of looking at treasury activity, hence digital culture needs to encompass both the emerging technology and the associated mindsets.</p>
<p>At its heart, a digital mindset means seeing everything as data rather than physical objects represented by data – and hence something that can be analysed and manipulated in ever more clever and complex ways. For example, automotive industry leaders are starting to see that the biggest value in cars lies in software and the data it generates about every aspect of the car and what the passengers do while travelling – offering constantly updateable revenue streams rather than a single fixed purchase – the car has become a data generation platform. With the rise of Tesla’s autonomous vehicles and similar digitally-minded manufacturers such as Local Motors, who crowdsources their 3D printed car designs, a car is no longer just a means of transportation – it becomes a physical embodiment of digital products and services.</p>
<p>Successful digitally literate business leaders in treasury will need to embrace disruptive technologies such as artificial intelligence (AI), blockchain, cloud computing, hyperconnectivity, and process automation. The tools these technologies enable can help increase efficiency and effectiveness, and create more value for internal customers and others with whom treasury connects. As financial services firms and central banks start adopting blockchain and cryptocurrencies, the pace of change in the marketplace will only accelerate. China is exploring the technology with the intent of transforming its entire finance sector while others are looking at blockchain as a platform for frictionless sale and distribution of equities, currencies, bonds and other assets.</p>
<p>The secure and irrevocable nature of blockchain transactions, coupled with the reduction in transaction fees, make it an attractive proposition for executing direct peer-to-peer transactions between counterparties without the need for intermediaries such as banks. AI offers the potential for smarter analysis and automation of many routine tasks. Positive digital treasury cultures will explore ways of enhancing the role of people in the organisation through AI rather than simply automating the work. Finding deeper, more meaningful ways to connect to employees and encourage their best work, and providing worthwhile experiences for both employees and internal customers – ie building relationships, will be the true hallmarks of the digitally enlightened organisation.</p>
<img alt="Portrait of Sen Ganesh, Principal, Bain &amp; Company" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2017-09and10-tt-01-qa-sen-ganesh-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=D61259C8B612DE4178D16311B8071300" width="100"/> 
<h5 id="sen-ganesh-bain-and-company">Sen Ganesh, Principal, Bain &amp; Company:</h5>
<p>Corporate treasuries run the risk of being at a competitive disadvantage if they do not accelerate digitisation. But they face the challenge that embedding a new culture and way of working is always a marathon, not a sprint.</p>
<p>Corporate treasuries are increasingly critical to deliver the company’s strategy, drive operational efficiency, manage financial risk and controls, and be adaptable in rapidly changing market conditions and regulatory environment.</p>
<p>Achieving these objectives requires end-to-end digitisation of the treasury function. This entails enhancing technology solutions, building new capabilities and ways of working, and engaging in partnerships with banks and non-banks.</p>
<p>For example, increasing adoption of virtual accounts to rationalise a number of physical accounts provides greater transparency on cash and liquidity positions, and supports reconciliation processes. Leveraging emerging real-time cross-border payment schemes can improve cost efficiency and working capital through just-in-time payments. Additionally, companies can make use of improved cash flow forecasting that leverages market data and scenario planning or third-party platforms to manage supply chain invoice processing and enable financing decisions to maximise working capital.</p>
<p>Corporates face choices on how and where to invest in technology, build the necessary capabilities, and manage partnerships to achieve their goals. Some corporates are focused on working with primary banks to digitise and integrate systems. Others are investing in enhancing in-house treasury management systems and teams especially to re-engineer payments and collections processes. Corporates are also leveraging third parties for specialist capabilities to manage supply chain payments and financing.</p>
<p>Adoption of digital and achieving full potential requires changes in culture. Organisations are in different stages of maturity but typically focus on three key areas:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h5>Digital capabilities.</h5>
<p>Identify capabilities for differential investment to build digital leadership, eg data analytics. Across the organisation the bar will be higher on technical, managerial and behavioural skills impacted by digital. Ensure the right metrics (aligned to business goals) to incentivise new behaviours and remove the risk of failure that often hinders innovation and adoption of new ways of working.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Agile ways of working.</h5>
<p>Culture is the new organisation “king” and can be a source of competitive advantage in the digital age. Rapid adaption, failure recovery, trust and delegate and networked working represent profound shifts from the classic command and control or matrices approaches that typically exist today. Refine governance models to be faster and more responsive, delegating decision rights to teams whilst maintaining the appropriate reporting, financial and risk controls.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Partner engagement.</h5>
<p>Select and manage partnerships with banks and non-banks to accelerate opportunities to digitise and drive to full potential. This typically includes increased data sharing and integration of technology systems through private APIs, jointly exploring new innovative solutions through deep understanding of the corporate’s needs, and leveraging expertise and presence in local markets where corporates have limited footprint.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Another consideration for companies looking to change their ways of working is that leadership role modelling is critical: real change is driven from the top – and for this to happen, the leadership team needs to “live and breathe” the values and behaviours, listen, learn and loop back to understand what is truly important and adapt as necessary.</p>
<img alt="Portrait of Gulru Atak, Global Innovation Head for Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions, Citi" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/2017-09and10-tt-01-qa-gulru-atak-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=559439766673646218C0CBD8250E7CBD" width="100"/> 
<h5 id="gulru-atak-citi">Gulru Atak, Global Innovation Head for Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions, Citi:</h5>
<p>A digital culture is created when everybody within the organisation is thinking about how technology can improve the business. To do this, business leaders must give their workforce the mandate to be curious and explore how existing and emerging technology might solve the challenges that exist within the organisation.</p>
<p>The creation of a digital culture does not just happen overnight. For example, at Citi, it has been a clear focus for us over the past decade to encourage and foster a digital culture across the organisation. To achieve this, we have taken a multifaceted approach that is underpinned by making digital a key part of our mission statement. From this, a digital ethos has been embraced from the top, and filtered down throughout the organisation, so that everybody has the mandate to come up with new ideas that can benefit the business.</p>
<p>To further facilitate digital thinking throughout the organisation, we encourage all employees, no matter who they are, to pitch their ideas. And, perhaps most importantly, the organisation has made a commitment to listen to and test these ideas out. For me, this is crucial when building a digital culture because it gives people confidence to develop new ideas and allows us to learn what does and does not work together.</p>
<p>A type of culture and new way of thinking cannot be created in a silo. Around the world, there are hundreds of innovative companies that are developing new ideas and new ways of operating. It would be remiss of any business not to look at and learn from these organisations.</p>
<p>Just as becoming digital has been a top priority for the bank; I believe that it should be a top priority for corporate treasury departments as well. The role of treasury is undoubtedly growing within organisations. As it does, it will increasingly be looked at to provide technological solutions that facilitate the digital path the business is following.</p>
<p>This does not mean that treasurers need to be experts in blockchain technology, or implementing AI based solutions right now. But it does mean that they need to be thinking digital, by understanding the pain points the business has and what technology or process improvements can solve these.</p>
<p>At Citi, we are helping our clients on this journey by bringing them into our innovation labs to highlight issues and brainstorm solutions. The aim is to co-create and also to further improve the knowledge base of the corporate treasury community so that they can better serve the organisations they work for.</p>
<p>Through this work, and through all the other initiatives happening in the treasury space, I foresee most treasury professionals being digitally native in the next five years. As a result, treasury departments will have a digital culture by default, so it would be prudent for senior treasury leaders to start fostering this culture today.</p>

<h3 id="next-question">Next question:</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“What challenges have corporate treasurers based in the Middle East been faced with in the last 12 months? What solutions/strategies are they using to overcome these challenges?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2017-09-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Team Management]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Lessons on building a best-in-class team]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=03D32AFF1215718B890718A5C23FD3C5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=A28595755F3BA4DA4D3AC0CFA85B5AA1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=1E90CB4B447269BE70195B2A840A2F19"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=74F7512280AB485674D8CFB392E583E1"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B9CF3155A592CEA0504C92CA85AFCECC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Group of young people's hands" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=678FB858C08EED03A93DC7B09253DB0A" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=678FB858C08EED03A93DC7B09253DB0A"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Thousands of pages have been written about what makes a good team and how to get there. But perhaps the best examples come from the sporting world. We analyse what made one of the world’s most successful sports teams tick and the lessons that corporate treasury can take from this.</em></p>
<p>Any football fan could not help but admire FC Barcelona over the past decade. The Catalan giants have won multiple trophies, and did so with flair, ingenuity and togetherness. And there are many lessons that business leaders can learn from the ‘Barcelona way’.</p>
<p>Yes, some may argue that they have the best player to ever play the game in Lionel Messi, but without a stellar supporting cast he would not have reached the heights that he has and neither would Barcelona. As such, there are few better examples of an excellent team in any field, sporting or otherwise. But how does this abstract statement reflect in the treasury department and what comprises the ‘perfect team’?</p>
<h3 id="building-a-philosophy">Building a philosophy</h3>
<p>To begin, every successful team has a philosophy, that acts as a guiding principle for behaviour. Barcelona, for instance, under the stewardship of Pep Guardiola had a very simple philosophy based around the three Ps: play, possession and position. This defined everything that they did. The world’s most successful sports side, the New Zealand rugby team’s philosophy, however, is embedded deep in Maori culture, manifesting itself in humbleness and a willingness to do everything for the team to be successful. Their mantra: ‘leave the jersey in a better place,’ sums this up.</p>
<p>In business, a philosophy is equally important. Steve Jobs is a shining example of how having a philosophy, and imprinting this on your team, or business as a whole, can help foster success. Jobs, wasn’t completely motivated by money, or other metrics that traditionally measure success. His thoughts were more abstract: “Being the richest man in the cemetery doesn’t matter to me… going to bed at night saying we’ve done something wonderful… that’s what matters to me”. And it is this idea of “doing something wonderful” that arguably has permeated across the Apple product line, keeping it at the cutting edge of technological innovation.</p>
<p>In treasury circles, philosophy is also important and it enriches the pages of our Adam Smith Awards Asia Yearbook. Flex Group, the 2016 Top Treasury Team, for instance, encourages its people to be curious and explore new ways of doing things in an effort to seek best practice across all areas of its treasury operation. What’s more, its focus is not only on the here and now, but making sure that the treasury is future proof. Together, these two elements define its award winning philosophy.</p>
<p>The first question then on your way to establishing a best-in-class treasury; what is the philosophy of your department? This doesn’t have to be complex and built on anything deep and meaningful. It may simply be based around what the team does and how, perhaps promoting teamwork or the ability to be brave and try new things.</p>
<p>Sometimes this may be decided for you, a company with a strong philosophy, like McDonalds, might infuse this into the treasury team. Paul Pomroy, CFO for the company’s UK and northern Europe division certainly expressed this when he talked to Treasury Today about how the treasury team go into restaurants to experience the business “at the coal face” fostering inclusiveness and an all for one attitude across the business.</p>
<p>But whatever the philosophy of your treasury team, it is vital that it is not treated dogmatically. There is perhaps nothing more demotivating to an energetic young employee, trying to make his or her mark by doing something differently, than being told to stop and hearing the words, “that is the way we do things around here”. This isn’t a workable philosophy; it is a line from the management rulebook of a bygone era. A modern philosophy must be able to evolve and adapt as the forces of the modern marketplace converge, it is doing this that is the first step to success.</p>
<h3 id="fitting-the-philosophy">Fitting the philosophy</h3>
<p>The next step is to recruit people who fit this philosophy, but don’t confuse this with recruiting those best qualified or with the most experience. Of course, where possible, it is preferable to have a team of highly-qualified and motivated individuals with a wealth of experience under their belt. But what would one of these do if they were asked to perform a task that they saw as below them? Contrary to popular belief, a team of superstars is not always the best.</p>
<p>Again, FC Barcelona provide a wonderful example of this. In 2009, they signed the Swedish striker Zlatan Ibrahimović – one of the best goal scorers in the world – for a reported £59m. It was seen as the finishing touch to what was already a magnificent team. But Ibrahimović, a true modern day maverick, didn’t fit the selfless nature of the Barcelona team and he soon found himself shipped out of the club.</p>
<p>In corporate treasury, getting the right people that fit the ethos of the department and the organisation as a whole is just as critical when looking to build a best-in-class team. This point is summed up by Rikke Koblauch, a designer in the London studio of digital development firm, Ustwo, who said “good teams start with good people who trust each other to work toward a common purpose”. Gary Slawther, Financing Advisor to the CEO at Octal in Oman echoes this sentiment, stating “I’ve learnt throughout my career that if you get the right people with you, you can do almost anything. Get the wrong people and you can do nothing.”</p>
<p>Finding this in Asia Pacific is not necessarily the easiest task though, given the relatively small talent pool that both large corporations and domestic firms have at their disposal. A generic approach to talent management in the region could therefore prove futile. Employees need to see that the organisation they migrate to, and stay with, has a transparent plan in place that allows them to develop as individuals with the potential to fill important roles within the organisation. The employee, however, must also show a willingness to grow within the company.</p>
<p>Another source of potential exists within your own organisation. Indeed, at Treasury Today Asia’s pioneering Women in Treasury Forum, panellists have outlined how some of the best talent they have in their team came from within their own organisation. What’s more, these people were often originally from roles unrelated to treasury, but they had shown certain qualities to the treasury team that made them a good fit.</p>


<blockquote>If managers want their best people to stay, they need to think carefully about how they treat them. While good employees are as tough as nails, their talent gives them an abundance of options. Managers need to make people want to work for them.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Dr Travis Bradberry, President, TalentSmart</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Finally, it is proven that the most effective teams combine significant diversity – of personality, background, outlook and skills – but with a shared set of values. This is important: diversity without common values will lead to fragmentation, just as shared values without diversity leads to group-think which is an even greater threat to progress.</p>
<h3 id="tools-of-the-trade">Tools of the trade</h3>
<p>Of course, it is very unlikely that any new hire, internal or external, will tick all the boxes. Indeed, they have more than likely been hired because of the potential they show – only a senior treasurer should be close to the ‘finished article’. It is therefore incumbent on the senior treasurer to arm the team with the skills it needs, both core treasury and soft.</p>
<p>Starting with core treasury skills, there is a lot that can be learnt on the job. This is especially true if the treasury team is of size, enabling the younger members to work with those more experienced getting a taste for different aspects of the function without having direct responsibility. Even in smaller teams this is possible if the senior treasurer acts as a mentor.</p>
<p>Another channel to learn core treasury skills is through allowing staff to obtain qualifications from professional bodies such as the ACT and AFP. Senior treasurers should also encourage their junior members of staff to attend treasury events and network so that they can learn best practice and skills from their industry peers.</p>
<p>Soft skills can be harder to obtain. These include the ability to build relationships and to manage people and expectations, and are becoming increasingly important for treasurers as the role pivots to become more strategic within the business. For OCTAL’s Slawther, companies that overlook the value of soft skills do so at great cost. Treasury leaders should show the way here, again acting as mentors and demonstrating what it means to be a treasurer in this day and age.</p>
<h3 id="keeping-the-team-happy">Keeping the team happy</h3>
<p>If the treasury team has a philosophy in place and a team of well-trained people who believe in it, it may seem that the hard work is done. Unfortunately, this is not the case and all of that work can be quickly undone if treasury leaders do not have sufficient management skills to keep employees happy.</p>
<p>Dr Travis Bradberry, President at training and coaching services provider, TalentSmart and co-author of the work performance guide, ‘Emotional Intelligence 2.0’ has published widely on this matter. His headline argument is that spending time on people management, a role which although considered somewhat negatively as ‘soft’ is actually vital to the success of any team.</p>
<p>Indeed, low staff morale can be common in roles such as treasury, which are high-pressure. This can cause issues for staff such as exhaustion, poor sleep, anxiety and depression. Aside from potentially contravening the duty of care companies have to their employees, the result is often a lowering of productivity and an increase in staff turnover.</p>
<p>“All that’s required is a new perspective and some extra effort on the manager’s part to give employees autonomy and make their work feel less demanding,” suggests Bradberry. The key to this change lies in understanding what may be lowering staff morale. For Bradberry some key culprits include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Overworking staff.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Holding people back.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Playing the blame game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Not letting people pursue their passions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Withholding praise.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>“If managers want their best people to stay, they need to think carefully about how they treat them,” notes Bradberry. “While good employees are as tough as nails, their talent gives them an abundance of options. Managers need to make people want to work for them.”</p>
<h3 id="an-eye-on-the-future">An eye on the future</h3>
<p>All good things must however come to an end at some point. At Barcelona, for instance, Pep Guardiola’s trophy laden reign came to an end in 2012 and some thought that the team would fall into disarray as a result. This did not happen, and today, under the stewardship of Luis Enrique who managed the Barcelona B team during Guardiola’s reign, the team continues to excel.</p>
<p>In business the same is true; nothing is static and things change such as the economy, business and people. In fact, by creating a best-in-class team it is likely that individuals will naturally grow and develop their capabilities and will eventually want to move up or out. The key is to not fear this evolution and embrace periods of disruption, and see it as an opportunity to reconstitute the team in an even better form.</p>
<p>This is perhaps the final lesson that can be taken from successful sports teams: they always have an eye on the future. Because no team of people, no matter how good at their jobs, will last forever, but the philosophy that makes them successful, if passed on correctly, can.</p>




<h3 id="why-teams-fail">Why teams fail</h3>
<p class="management-summary">As well as knowing what makes a successful team, it can also be useful to know why teams fail.</p>
<p>The most common leadership model amongst senior executives is a ‘hub and spoke’ team model. This is in action where “a kind of uneasy truce” exists between participants, notes Mark Loftus, a Chartered Clinical Psychologist, an Associate Fellow of the British Psychological Society and Managing Director of The Thinking Partnership. “Each will accept direction from their own boss but can be reluctant to accept influence from each other across the team.”</p>
<p>The reason why some executives choose to isolate themselves may simply be down to the performance management structure imposed upon them, where accountabilities are made very specific and personal. This builds incentives around those accountabilities, tending to drive individualistic behaviour.</p>
<p>But, notes Loftus, the typical psychology of individuals who rise to senior positions must also be taken into account. “Often they have got there because they are strong solo operators; they are very competent and are not used to relying on someone else,” he explains. Motivated by taking on major challenges, these are the people who always step up to the plate but then find it difficult to let the reins slip too far from their control.</p>
<p>Intellectually, these individuals may be well-acquainted with the stories of great leaders throughout history who, having failed to place sufficient trust in their generals, faced their own gradual undoing. But it becomes quite another thing to apply this understanding to their own professional endeavours; it is perhaps a stubborn belief that it will not happen to them. In his ‘Five Dysfunctions of a Team’, management consultant, Patrick Lencioni describes how teams often struggle to “row together”, citing absence of trust as a key issue.</p>
<p>Lencioni’s approach – a commonly used framework for building a tighter functioning team – further warns of the damage caused by the fear of conflict where teams avoid engagement by sidestepping the ‘difficult conversation’.</p>
<p>His list of dysfunctions also includes individual lack of commitment. This often manifests itself through what psychologists call ‘social loafing’, where the individual is part of the team yet somehow is never there when the small jobs need doing (the commercial equivalent of always managing to avoid emptying the dishwasher, seemingly insignificant in itself but a cumulative irritant for those that are attentive).</p>
<p>Inattention to results is another Lencioni dysfunction. This, explains Loftus, can be the negative consequence of teams that have overdosed on team-building exercises and end up in “a bit of a love-in”, where the realisation that the team exists to perform is lost amidst the thrill of connection. This, he hastens to add, has never been his experience when working with treasury teams. Most frequently teams fail because they do not have a clear enough sense of the common purpose that defines their very existence.</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Thousands of pages have been written about what makes a good team and how to get there. But perhaps the best examples come from the sporting world. We analyse what made one of the world’s most successful sports teams tick and the lessons that corporate treasury can take from this.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/group-of-young-people-s-hands-ss-105224906-1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Team Management]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[There are many ‘I’s in team]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=9B7AD2859AF9E2494375311B4E1CF3A0"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B47605591F7FD1FB57A4B150AAD74A81"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=07803C65FEC4D4789A3AD7A04D667E53"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=304E10651B958F07A006232FC028719C"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AC0E794531C4ADB2A6B5E7D12307FEB5"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Team of people rowing" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B5555AAF03DCC35868A055CF2DE73D99" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B5555AAF03DCC35868A055CF2DE73D99"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Team-playing is not for everyone but then if the nature of human expectation and motivation is really considered in depth, very few have the required skills to make it work en masse. For the rest of us, how can teamwork be improved, what happens when it goes wrong and how can we improve matters?</em></p>
<p>The worn out old cliché that ‘there is no I in team’ ought to be retired disgracefully. Of course there are: in fact, ‘team’ is entirely made up of ‘I’s – that is why building a well-functioning team is challenging. The key to building a strong team is to recognise that different people will take a different approach to a role, even within the same function. This seems obvious, but recognising that getting the best out of people is not about trying to force a square peg into a round hole, instead it is about seeing that real progress and creativity is driven by managing different outlooks, cultures and opinions and then steering these outlooks in the same direction.</p>
<h3 id="getting-it-right">Getting it right</h3>
<p>Exemplifying this view is the digital development sector where companies can crash spectacularly but they can also succeed beyond most people’s wildest dreams: Apple, Google, Amazon and Microsoft are amongst the world’s mega-companies for good reason. They achieved great things by purposefully encouraging and exploiting teamwork and peoples’ differences to move far beyond the norm.</p>
<p>The principles that these firms – and many more like them – adopt are built upon a single, non-negotiable truth and Rikke Koblauch, a designer in the London studio of digital development firm, Ustwo, sums it all up when she says “good teams start with good people who trust each other to work toward a common purpose”. The company, which amongst other things develops digital interfaces for high profile clients such as Jaguar cars, does not pay lip service to the development of team culture. It is, states Koblauch, “much more than a football table and a Friday beer”. For her, and many others in this sector, “culture is a safe environment in which everyone can be themselves, ask questions, make mistakes and grow”.</p>
<p>It might be argued that the worlds of the bright young things in digital development and the cautious old-school professionals of treasury are so far removed that this notion falls flat on its face. But read the stories of the winners over the years of the Treasury Today Adam Smith Awards and it is clear that they didn’t get where they are today by standing still – these are all fully engaged, creative and responsive teams who, without exception, cite the imagination and commitment, skills, talent, experience and cultural outlooks of their co-workers as being vital to their success.</p>
<p>“I’ve learnt throughout my career that if you get the right people with you, you can do almost anything. Get the wrong people and you can do nothing.” The message from Gary Slawther, Financing Advisor to the CEO at Octal in Oman, could not be any clearer: it does not matter ultimately what the role of that team is, the need to properly consider the suitability of each individual member, as per Koblauch’s assertion above, is indeed non-negotiable.</p>
<p>But team building is not an exact science and there is no magic formula that works every time. “The problem is that nobody teaches you how to identify what you need in human resources, how to manage staff that aren’t performing – and how to manage those that are – and how to build good relationships with the banks,” says Slawther. It is, he determines, “something that only comes with experience”.</p>
<h3 id="soft-skills">Soft skills</h3>
<p>Of course, the core competencies of a treasurer are a given, but for those working in this space who are anticipating promotion, they also need to have a wide variety of business experience and expertise in the so-called ‘soft skills’. These include the ability to build relationships and to manage people and expectations. Building a team therefore means thinking carefully about what personal qualities each role needs to best fulfil it. Whilst it may be desirable to seek individuals who will question processes, display common sense and be able to “ruthlessly prioritise what needs to be done”, Slawther feels that companies which overlook the value of soft skills do so at great cost.</p>
<p>But it is not just an individual manager’s responsibility to create the right environment. Vivian Peng, Asia Treasurer and VP of Treasury, Flex Group, (and winner of the Adam Smith Awards Top Treasury Team Asia 2015) points to a further essential element of success. “We have strong support from our management and our culture allows the team to innovate in a complex environment,” she reports. That same culture fosters “a great team spirit”, informing her belief “their hard work, their ability to work as a team and also their willingness to learn” is the very key to success.</p>
<p>The point that Peng makes about being able to innovate in a complex environment is one that is taken up wholeheartedly by Christine McCarthy, Senior EVP and CFO, The Walt Disney Company. When it comes to working with her staff, McCarthy steers clear of micro-management. “I learnt a long time ago from one of my mentors in banking that when you find someone who has potential, you give them enough rope to hang themselves but hopefully they won’t.”</p>
<p>As part of her remit to develop talent, McCarthy believes it is essential to keep high-potential people motivated. To do that you have got to give them the ability to make decisions and earn acknowledgment for the work they do. “I want them to be out in front getting the recognition they deserve; the downside risk is that they must perform and succeed. It can be a high-risk strategy on my part so I can’t give everyone the same amount of rope; I have to discern who is ready for those challenges.”</p>
<p>She may be taking some “highly calculated” risks but her nurturing process is well managed as part of her belief in team spirit. “I don’t just put them out to pasture, I keep my eye on them,” she says. “The more they can do and the more they can achieve, the more they will grow as professionals.”</p>
<h3 id="keep-talking">Keep talking</h3>
<p>When it comes to developing skills and knowledge, it is important to keep in touch with the wider treasury peer group. Ingmar Bergmann, Corporate Treasurer and Head of Corporate Finance for Dutch real-estate firm, NSI, is a firm believer that the international community of treasurers can help each other to do a better job. “If you want to take treasury to a higher level then you definitely have to communicate and open up to others.”</p>
<p>Certain aspects of the role are naturally bound by the rules of competition; he is not advocating passing on ‘trade secrets’. But he argues that some facets of the job – such as the administration of a common project such as the recent SEPA demands – are not necessarily best served in the realm of secrecy. Here, treasurers can help each other by openly discussing project implementations, the pitfalls and the best expert contacts.</p>
<p>Uniting under a common cause creates a stronger voice too and for Bergmann “it’s time to make sure within the inner circle of treasurers that we maintain the clarity of our voice so that people keep listening”. The cornerstones of promoting the values (and value) of the treasury function are the Associations of Corporate Treasurers that exist in many countries. As a former chairman of the Dutch ACT and a member of the pan-European EACT, he notes that it is only a relatively recent experience for the voice of treasury to be heard with any real attentiveness in the discussions around setting international regulations. “Corporates, together with the EACT, have been able to raise their voices and show these bodies, especially the European Union, that they should listen to the ‘voice of the real economy’,” he states. “As treasurers we should be willing to help work towards well-balanced regulation.” For him, mutual support is an essential part of teamwork.</p>
<h3 id="why-teams-fail">Why teams fail</h3>
<p>The most effective teams combine significant diversity – of personality, background, outlook and skills – but with a shared set of values. This is important, notes Mark Loftus, a Chartered Clinical Psychologist, an Associate Fellow of the British Psychological Society and Managing Director of The Thinking Partnership. Just as shared values without diversity leads to stultifying group-think, so diversity without common values will lead to fragmentation.</p>
<p>Indeed, notes Loftus, teams often fail because they do not have a clear enough sense of the common purpose that defines their very existence. At a senior level, the reluctance or inability of people to ask each other questions is a major cause of frustration. Where an individual possesses a depth of technical expertise there is often an imbalance between the twin concepts of advocacy and enquiry (propounding your own views versus enquiring into someone else’s). “The evidence seems to be that a 50/50 balance is indicative of good team functioning, whereas most frequently we would see a 90/10 split in favour of advocacy,” he notes. This disparity tends to generate “furious agreement” amongst experts, instead of intelligent questioning of what is really meant by the other proponents.</p>
<p>A major key to progress as a team is thus the free-flow of conversation. However, common amongst teams of senior executives, Loftus observes a ‘hub and spoke’ model in action where “a kind of uneasy truce” exists between participants. Each will accept direction from their own boss but can be reluctant to accept influence from each other across the team. The reason why some executives choose to isolate themselves in this way may simply be down to the performance management structure imposed upon them, where accountabilities are made very specific and personal. This builds incentives around those accountabilities, tending to drive individualistic behaviour. But, notes Loftus, the typical psychology of individuals who rise to senior positions must also be taken into account. “Often they have got there because they are strong solo operators; they are very competent and are not used to relying on someone else,” he explains. Motivated by taking on major challenges, these are the people who always step up to the plate but then find it difficult to let the reins slip too far from their control.</p>
<p>Firmly believing that “teams become teams by working together on a common purpose”, Loftus comments that it is nonetheless rare for corporates to focus on helping people learn the skills of being in a team. Help is out there but, at his own admission, the team-building industry has not always covered itself in glory, prone as it is to “psycho-babble and mumbo jumbo”. Don’t dismiss it all though, he advises. “People are right to be sceptical but at the same time do look for the small percentage that is useful.”</p>
<p>Unfortunately, of the companies that are alert to the benefits of co-operative working, many are too keen to force team-play or decide merely to pay lip service to it. In trying to manipulate the right environment they see team-building exercises – often referred to as away-days – an ‘event’ in themselves. This, argues Loftus, frequently creates “toe-curling” bonding sessions that can ultimately create inattention to results as the realisation that the team exists to perform is lost amidst the thrill of connection. This, he hastens to add, has never been his experience when working with treasury teams.</p>
<h3 id="the-team-builder">The team-builder</h3>
<p>As a practitioner of many years’ experience, James Koh, Group Treasurer of Vertu Corporation, has set up a number of global treasury teams from scratch giving him the opportunity to handpick and work with some of the best teams, having, as he says, “learned the hard way” as to what works and what doesn’t.</p>
<p>The mark of a great team for him is one that is “tightly knit and which gels well together”. By encouraging each member to be “competitive from start to finish, highly communicative and always striving to be the best in class”, Koh says it is possible to create a highly motivated team. When that team has a clear set of treasury objectives and is led by a hands-on treasurer, he feels the function can be a well-respected and integral part of finance, “in-step with the CFO and the company objectives”. Indeed, he adds, “the role performed by treasury is an integral part of the finance function; a good CFO knows that and relies upon the utmost professionalism from the treasury team”.</p>
<p>Having been at the sharp end of treasury for a variety of businesses and sectors Koh has built up an impressive CV but has seen on his journey a number of instances where teams have failed to perform. Lack of direction and no clear set of KPIs and no monitoring, mentoring nor specific training often play a role in the underperforming treasury. But Koh digs deeper, recognising the damage that can be inflicted by a treasurer lacking in motivation. This can be exacerbated where there is no close working relationship with CFO or little support from them, and communication within the team itself team or between the treasurer and CFO fails.</p>
<p>When creating an effective team there are a number of elements that need to be taken into account to achieve best results says Koh and for him it all starts with a group of people who are “loud and communicative”, even about the problems. “Shout so the whole team and the treasurer know what’s going on,” he advises. “It’s all about communication. It’s vital: no quiet team please!” Not being afraid to make “noise” is a good way of airing any mistakes at the earliest possible time “so they are easier to deal with”. It is, after all, a team effort “and we stand or fall as one”.</p>


<blockquote>The role performed by treasury is an integral part of the finance function; a good CFO knows that and relies upon the utmost professionalism from the treasury team.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">James Koh, Group Treasurer, Vertu Corporation</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Picking the “right crew for the right results” is his goal but he admits that setting up a treasury from scratch is not easy. “The best drivers and KPIs, the correct motivation and ongoing tracking, all require constant attention,” he states. “All I might add without compromise and strictly as per group treasury policy as mandated by the board.”</p>
<p>A great treasury team comes in all shapes and sizes, notes Koh. “The greater the diversity, the richer the team is. But it takes a good treasurer to recognise these talents, to grow and nurture them – not cushion them but to stretch them beyond their comfort zone but still within their capabilities.” The methods he uses to spot and develop potential amongst staff include challenging KPIs and individual objectives. The team has to be motivated to achieve these hard but achievable goals and targets. “I personally take on board key members of my team for special hands-on mentoring,” explains Koh. “It is always such a pleasure when they pass their letters, excel in their delivery and move on to greater and better things. I am glad I had the opportunity to be part of and help shape their greater career in treasury.”</p>
<p>Of course, personnel issues can arise and as an experienced treasurer, Koh says he tends to be able to “pick the good ones from the bad” quickly. “It helps to have an instinct for spotting potential problems; it’s part of my job and my employers expect no less,” he says. When dealing with negativity in addition to ensuring a “tight and constant working relationship” with the CFO and the Board of Directors, Koh suggest “lots and lots of clear and precise communication” is required between the treasurer and treasury team. This must be backed up by setting clear and precise KPIs and objectives to ensure each member knows what is expected of them. “And if and when they achieve or exceed their KPIs, they then get rewarded,” states Koh. “When the treasury team performs well, I also perform well. That is my motivation for wanting my team to succeed. Simple!”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Team-playing is not for everyone but then if the nature of human expectation and motivation is really considered in depth, very few have the required skills to make it work en masse. For the rest of us, how can teamwork be improved, what happens when it goes wrong and how can we improve matters?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/treasury-talent/team-management/team-of-rowing-people-sailing-against-camera-in-sunset-ss-318310229-1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-04-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Team Management]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Talent management]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float:left;margin-right:2em;margin-bottom:2em;"><img alt="Portrait of Tzeitel Fernandes" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2015/03/2015-03and04-tta-02-qa-tzeitel-fernandes-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="tzeitel-fernandes">Tzeitel Fernandes, Principal, Performance &amp; Rewards, Aon Hewitt in Asia Pacific:</h5>
<p>Treasury skills like liquidity and risk management have always been ‘hot skills’ in Asia. Yet, increased collaboration with banks has meant a reduction in the size of treasury teams, leaving them more vulnerable in case of attrition. While firms continue to have large finance teams, the specialised skills of the treasury function are not easily found in the traditional finance professional.</p>
<p>Attracting talent into the treasury is tricky, as the correct skills are very difficult to find. Most employers are now using a combination of social media and traditional methods to root out qualified professionals for their treasury teams. However, most firms prefer to grow talent from within, especially in the case of ‘hot’ areas like treasury.</p>
<p>Aon Hewitt’s research shows that the best employers tend to fill just under half (43%) of their managerial vacancies internally, versus approximately only a third (34%) for employers in general. This strategy works much better than hiring from outside; not only is it more cost effective, but it comes with reduced training time and smoother transitions. It also demonstrates the organisation’s commitment to providing career opportunities to its employees, thereby increasing the engagement of the team as a whole. As we have known for a while, ‘career opportunities’ have long been a key driver of employee engagement in Asia Pacific.</p>
<p>In order to maximise return on investment in talent, firms need to identify their high potential employees in the treasury, and adopt proactive measures to keep them engaged. Typical strategies used by the best employers to retain and motivate high potentials include leadership development programmes, developmental assignments, special projects and increased access and interaction with senior executives.</p>
<p>Besides these, there are certain specific steps that firms could take to develop, retain and motivate staff in their treasury departments. One of the most effective is to send high potential, high performing staff for treasury-related certification courses. These courses are offered by various reputed associations or educational organisations and have a three to 12 month duration. Employees value them enormously, not only for the learning opportunity they provide, but also as they enhance the message that the organisation is willing to invest in their development to help them build a career within the treasury.</p>
<p>In larger firms, junior to mid-level professionals are often rotated between teams within the treasury. This promotes collaboration between teams, enhances the teams’ skills and knowledge about the working of the function, and enlarges the talent pool which the firm can draw from when it needs to fill a position. Increased centralisation of the treasury teams has made this more possible in hub locations, such as Hong Kong and Singapore, in the last few years.</p>
<p>Finally, the most successful firms are those that understand the importance of internal recognition. Through a combination of rewards, special projects and even ‘meet the leadership’ events, firms that are able to demonstrate appreciation for their employees also have a higher chance to engage and retain them.</p>
<h5 id="tim-raiswell">Tim Raiswell, Managing Director, CEB and Alex Bant, Research Director, CEB:</h5>
<p>Despite an ongoing war for talent in many geographies, 50% of finance leaders say that their current teams lack the right mix of skills to meet evolving business demands. Essentially, business leaders want finance partners who can tell a clear story about the drivers of business performance and guide them to better decisions and processes. However, the typical finance team’s strengths tend to be functional and technical capabilities. So it’s not surprising that we see many finance leaders searching desperately for better partnership, communication and leadership capabilities in their people. Unfortunately, CEB finds that it is exceptionally rare to find all of these skills in individuals, which is why the best finance functions focus on building better teams, not finding individual stars.</p>
<p>Companies have pressed ‘pause’ on finance talent development. During the lean years between 2008 and 2011, we found that 63% of finance teams paused recruitment efforts, 52% put training and development programmes on hold, and 51% reduced their learning and development budget.</p>
<p>There is a growing gap between HR-led strategies and finance needs. HR competency designations, such as “soft skills” or “leadership skills,” are often applied broadly across corporate functions without tailoring to finance’s unique needs. There is also a lack of leadership training. The middle management layer for many finance teams is decreasing, leading to managers who are unprepared to take on additional responsibilities and train junior staff. In fact, we found that 81% of finance executives are dissatisfied with the strength of their leadership pipeline.</p>
<h5 id="the-skills-that-matter-most-for-treasury">The skills that matter most for treasury</h5>
<p>Treasury executives are worried about the impact of these widening skill gaps on corporate and individual performance, but they find it difficult to identify which skills are missing within their team and what to do about it. We surveyed more than 2,200 finance professionals to identify the non-technical competencies that are critical to bridging this gap in treasury:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h5>Builder:</h5>
<p>An ability to develop talent, manage and utilise a portfolio of skill sets, and manage teams.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Persuader:</h5>
<p>Strong communication skills, such as using narratives and graphics to convey messages.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Strategist:</h5>
<p>Understanding of business operations and technology.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Learner:</h5>
<p>Flexibility, learning, and improvement skills.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Doer:</h5>
<p>Strong functional expertise combined with problem solving and judgment skills.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Most finance teams have a surplus of people with ‘doer’ and ‘learner’ competencies, but the best teams over-invest in ‘builder’, ‘strategist’, and ‘persuader’ competencies. Most finance leaders will need to change their current hiring strategy if they are to find people with these skill sets.</p>
<figure class="portrait left" style="float:left;margin-right:2em;margin-bottom:2em;"><img alt="Portrait of Christine Wright" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2015/03/2015-03and04-tta-02-qa-christine-wright-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="christine-wright">Christine Wright, Managing Director, Hays, Asia</h5>
<p>Staffing demand is intensifying in Asia and the labour market is becoming exceedingly tight in many areas, including treasury departments. Given ongoing demand for highly skilled professionals, employers need to look at more innovative strategies to attract and retain talent in treasury departments.</p>
<p>With more businesses centralising the treasury function where possible, there has been an increase in control over cash management across the region. This has offered treasury professionals the opportunity to work in larger teams, which is a positive retention measure as staff gain access to more career development opportunities. Also, increased project exposure has been a critical driver in retaining talent with many individuals now regularly involved with acquisitions and integrations.</p>
<p>Attracting and retaining employees in treasury departments also involves understanding the recruiting equation. This is made up of branding, promoting what your organisation can offer and demonstrating honesty and respect. You also need to promote the ongoing learning and development on offer. This is otherwise known as the Employee Value Proposition (EVP). Every organisation should have its own unique EVP that can communicate to potential employees the experience of working for your company and distinguish it from others. To come up with something that truly appeals to the type of person who will thrive in your department, it helps to think of your EVP as a description of why your business is the right place for the type of people who succeed there, and nobody else.</p>
<p>Next, seek the opinion of your successful employees by asking them why they chose to join you – and what keeps them there. You may be surprised at what attracted them to your organisation in the first place. Then, make sure your company statement reflects reality. You want people who are attracted by what you say and find it’s true when they get there. Don’t run the risk of saying one thing and delivering another. People will share their experience on social media if you do and your department and the company’s reputation will be tarnished.</p>
<p>In-house talent can be developed to add more value to the company in a number of ways. Performance management is central to development and can be as simple as a robust, regular appraisal system that is user friendly and which managers are committed to. Formal performance feedback is also an excellent opportunity to ensure talent is engaged.</p>
<p>Secondly, provide career progression opportunities for your treasury team. Lack of career progression is often the primary reason given by candidates when asked why they are looking for a new job, followed by a desire for new challenges. Candidates often rank it above the salary on offer.</p>
<p>Training and development doesn’t necessarily mean formal courses, although it can. One-on-one training and taking on additional duties can be just as effective. Investing in your employees’ skills development allows them to be the best they can be, which has obvious rewards for both them and you. Mentorships are a useful training and development tool to aid in retention and they can also be used to develop, retain and pass corporate insight on to other employees. A trend we have noticed is an increase in regional coverage with many treasury professionals taking on broader portfolios in order to develop their skills.</p>
<p>Finally, reward and recognition programmes can be used as part of a successful retention programme, as long as there is a fair and equal system of processes for rewards. Despite your best efforts, some staff may still go. Making leaving a positive experience can be a challenge but it is very powerful for leavers to speak highly of an organisation even though they no longer work there.</p>
<figure class="portrait right" style="float:left;margin-right:2em;margin-bottom:2em;"><img alt="Portrait of Jeff Tang" height="150" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2015/03/2015-03and04-tta-02-qa-jeff-tang-100x150.jpg" width="100"/></figure>
<h5 id="jeff-tang">Jeff Tang, Hong Kong Managing Director at Towers Watson</h5>
<p>Being innovative must begin with an open mind, and the courage to be, and act differently. This requires deep insight into what motivates an organisation’s talent in terms of attracting, retaining and engaging staff.</p>
<p>The treasurer’s role continues to evolve and is becoming multi-dimensional beyond its traditionally technical aspects. This is leading to a wider and diverse talent pool, which is a blessing, but could also be a curse, as it presents its own challenges in terms of understanding and matching the variety of attraction and engagement drivers such as healthcare and wellness benefits, job security, base pay, career advancement opportunities, relationship with manager and management of work-related stress.</p>
<p>High performing organisations tend to have a deep knowledge of their organisation, including what it stands for, and have a clear employment proposition that reflects the organisation’s values. This should also be formally articulated and well executed.</p>
<p>Often, Towers Watson has advised clients who have poorly communicated employment deals or elements of the deal that are contradictory. This makes one wonder whether the organisation is better off not having one at all. Towers Watson research shows organisations with highly evolved employment deals (well articulated, well communicated, customised for different employee segments, and differentiated) have less challenges in retaining critical skills compared to less well thought out ones.</p>
<p>Our research tells us that there is often a mismatch between what employers understand and employees prefer, in terms of drivers of attraction and retention. Understanding what drives employees to be attracted and retained by an employer is equally crucial.</p>
<p>Employers are taking a more robust approach by adopting deeper analytics to develop solutions that match the employees’ preferences. Total rewards optimisation analytics enable employers to understand preferences, perceived values and “trade-offs” that employees are prepared to make. This provides powerful insights for employers to design the “right” deal.</p>
<p>Solutions around the theme of “choice and ownership” are becoming more popular, and this is partly a result of diverse lifestyles experienced by the current workforce that has evolved from multiple generations of workers.</p>

<h3 id="the-next-question">The next question:</h3>



<blockquote>Given the drive towards ‘green business’, is e-invoicing a technology that corporates in Asia should be embracing? If so, what recommendations can be made about successfully adopting e-invoicing solutions? Also, are there any specific developments in this space for treasurers to be aware of?</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source"></p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Team Management]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
