<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<data>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[GCC: what should treasurers know about this region?]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<p><em>In April 2019, the IMF had forecast real gross domestic product growth in the six members of the Gulf Cooperation Council at 2.1%. By October 2019, that figure had dropped to 0.7%. The growth for 2018 was 2%, so what do these fluctuating figures mean for treasurers in the region and those looking to enter it?</em></p>
<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass=".heroarticle_summary__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=05C3ECFA11AB01434D0765261C204856"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=AD11AFA095474D2524825FFB7FC111AC"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=EE88119F8CDBE932667FB3F537215D2B"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=3E0508D03AFC8D9717E17D4F6590C262"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6773706D69EA22AC129E53F152977172"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Newtons cradle swinging to the left" class=".heroarticle_summary__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=957D74B1EB7530F3850BAFBFE4F758CB" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=957D74B1EB7530F3850BAFBFE4F758CB"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>The IMF reported that the deceleration of GDP growth “mainly reflect[ed] oil production cuts in line with Opec+ agreements”. The World Bank published its Gulf Economic Update in December 2019, noting that economic growth in the GCC is “likely to recover over the medium term to 2.2% in 2020 and 2.6% in 2021”. But, the report adds, this is conditional on a “gradual recovery in oil prices and continued spending on mega projects as well as continued growth in non-hydrocarbon sectors.”</p>
<p>Fitch Solutions published its MENA Monthly Outlook: Key Themes for 2020 in December 2019, theorising that the GCC will “face its own set of challenges in the year to come.” It claims that oil prices are exerting pressure on the countries and will likely result in a “resumption of fiscal consolidation and a renewed focus on enticing foreign capital.”</p>
<h4 id="the-current-environment">The current environment</h4>
<p>The GCC region is often described as one of the fastest growing in the world. Indeed, David Aldred, Head of Corporate &amp; Public Sector Sales TTS at Citi, explains that there are some areas where the GCC is “leapfrogging” some developed economies. Adam Boukadida, SVP Treasury, Tax &amp; Finance at Etihad Aviation Group, gives SWIFT gpi and the practical use of blockchain as good examples of the countries working to digitise processes.</p>
<p>However, Aldred notes that when it comes to the current environment in the GCC region, “you can’t comment without acknowledging the current geopolitical tensions,” and that treasurers need to be mindful of that. “But it’s a very resilient region,” he says, adding that the mentality is simply “business as usual”.</p>
<p>This resilience is a necessary trait for any organisation in the region – both corporates and banks. Boukadida explains that access to funds can still be a challenge for SMEs and start-ups. “These companies often have no choice but to accept short-term loans with high margins and fees, while larger corporates with good credit ratings are in a better position,” he says. Additionally, those large corporates can arrange for funding outside of the GCC region.</p>
<p>However, he adds, as currencies in the region are pegged to the US dollar, any change in LIBOR will affect those markets immediately. “Last year, we saw continuous rate cuts by the Fed, which has spiralled into the GCC markets. The low interest rate environment has given a boost to lending in both the retail and corporate sectors, and also to the stock market.”</p>
<h4 id="the-booming-tourism-industry">The booming tourism industry</h4>
<p>When it comes to businesses in the GCC, many countries are looking to diversify beyond oil. As demand for sustainable and renewable resources grows, the demand for fossil fuel falls. Thus, countries in the region look to develop other industries: Expo 2020 Dubai and the 2022 FIFA World Cup in Qatar are just two examples of branching into the tourism industry.</p>
<p>The cost of Expo 2020, and projects related to the event, is estimated at around US$10-15bn, according to Deloitte, which includes the site, an extension of the metro line, and a new Museum of the Future. Meanwhile, Qatar is reportedly forecast to spend over US$200bn on preparations – not only on stadiums, but also on a new airport, hospitals and roads.</p>
<p>Outside of oil and gas, infrastructure, tourism, transport and logistics are by far the largest areas that GCC countries are investing in, and Aldred explains that the United Arab Emirates (UAE) “was ahead of the game” with it. “Anyone operating here or coming here should not think that the GCC is going to remain as it was for the last 50 years,” he says. The rapid acceleration seen in just the past five years is showing no signs of slowing down, and Aldred says that treasurers therefore need to keep a strong view on “corporate agility and strategy”.</p>
<h4 id="becoming-global-hubs">Becoming global hubs</h4>
<p>For several consecutive years now, Dubai has been the busiest airport in the world in terms of passenger traffic. With almost 90 million passengers in 2018, it’s no surprise that aviation is expected to be 37.5% of Dubai’s GDP in 2020. For Aldred, the GCC’s position as a global hub is what organisations should be looking at when considering treasury centre locations.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Gary Slawther, Interim Group Treasurer at Eddie Stobart Logistics Limited, points out that the city of Salalah in Oman is the tenth biggest trans-shipment port in the world. “Everything comes from the East – you’ll have a ship full of Toyotas from Japan and a ship full of toys from China, and something else from South Korea. That cargo will be going to ten different destinations. So they’ll stop at Salalah, swap freight and then each ship will go to their final destination with the required mixed load,” he explains.</p>
<p>Indeed, shipping giant Maersk quotes Salalah to Newark in the US as taking around just 20 days, and the port was made into a main transhipment hub in the company’s global network. This only makes sense when you consider the GCC’s position in the world – arguably in the centre – especially with regards to Asian and Western Europe time zones, says Aldred.</p>
<h4 id="educating-the-masses">Educating the masses</h4>
<p>Randy Bell, Director of the Atlantic Council Global Energy Centre, wrote that “diversification of the economy cannot be measured by comparing oil to non-oil GDP alone. Instead, countries need to examine how connected their oil economy is to the rest of their economic activities and work to develop sectors that will thrive independently.” He specified that GCC countries should be making efforts to attract “tech talent and build innovation hubs”.</p>
<p>Indeed PwC’s paper, The Lost Workforce: Upskilling for the Future in conjunction with the World Government Summit, notes that “The GCC must urgently upskill for the future”, and that “Designing a robust organisational structure that prepares the company for the future is a key priority for CEOs from the Middle East.”</p>
<p>Slawther notes that there is a huge effort in the GCC to try and build the skills of the local population and encourage them to join the private sector. A report by management consulting firm, Oliver Wyman, Maximising Employment on Nationals in the GCC, explains that “the availability of an affordable foreign workforce willing to occupy blue-collar jobs, combined with attractive public sector jobs, enabled GCC nationals to limit their employment within the private sector, or only consider the more suitable opportunities within it.”</p>
<p>Slawther explains that this could prove challenging because of just how attractive the public sector is in the region: the hours are often less demanding, and the pay and benefits are generally much better. Additionally, GCC citizens are accustomed to the wealth distribution strategies and therefore governments need to adjust these to incentivise the citizens to build their own.</p>
<p>For Boukadida, industries like tourism, transportation, healthcare, banking and investment are now the top tier sectors in the GCC. He believes that “the opportunities that are coming from this transition are great, creating a healthy environment for treasury professionals to pursue a career in the GCC countries.” However, like Aldred, he notes that this rapid change and focus on automation means that treasury professionals need to look for the opportunities to upskill themselves. “Today’s world calls for professionals who are adaptive and those who welcome change,” says Boukadida.</p>
<p>There are other developments too, particularly bureaucratic reform. For example, Qatar’s visa-free entry programme was expanded to include Indian and Ukrainian nationals; Bahrain introduced a wage protection scheme to end the exploitation of staff – and for Saudi Arabia’s Saudi Vision 2030, the country has implemented more business-related reforms to boost international investment than any other GCC country.</p>


<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">What are free zones?</h2>
<p>Also known as ‘free economic zones’ or ‘free economic territories’, free zones are a class of special economic zone. They are areas in which companies are either taxed very lightly or not at all to encourage business. In the GCC, free zones often allow expatriates to have 100% ownership of a company, while elsewhere they may require a majority (51%) be owned by nationals.</p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h4 id="regulatory-differences">Regulatory differences</h4>
<p>Slawther, who spent eight years working in the region – only leaving in November 2019 – has witnessed these changes first-hand. “The economy, or the banking system, does suffer from a lack of transparency and credit information, but steps are being taken to address that,” he says. This is largely due to the fact that in the region, unless a company is listed on a stock exchange, there is no obligation to release financial information. This is changing though, explains Slawther. For example, companies in the UAE are now required to submit financial information to the Etihad Credit Bureau.</p>
<p>Boukadida has also found that “There is pressure on banks and service providers to prioritise regulation changes and updates, to digitise their processes and develop solutions that emphasise security and transparency.”</p>
<p>Additionally, Slawther notes that the rapid expansion of countries, and more specifically, banks within those countries – such as Abu Dhabi Commercial Bank and Emirates NBD – means that they have to have an international level of transparency and corporate governance.</p>
<h4 id="business-is-getting-easier">Business is getting easier</h4>
<p>For Aldred, “Governments have to be the enabler” when it comes to making inward foreign direct investment (FDI) easier. Things like free zones make investing in a notoriously tricky region more accessible to foreign investors. The Fitch Solutions report notes that “tighter fiscal space will encourage GCC governments to focus on business environment reform”, and that although the GCC states have improved in recent years, they still lag behind others by a considerable margin.</p>
<p>One notable example is that of Saudi Arabia, where a recent focus on reform saw it move 30 places up the World Bank’s Doing Business Index in 2019, now at 62 out of 190 countries. The UAE, meanwhile, is in the top 20 at 16 and Bahrain is at 43. Oman sits at 68, Qatar at 77, and Kuwait at 83.</p>
<p>The report cites Saudi Arabia as the economy that improved the most across three or more areas measured. These areas include: starting a business, dealing with construction permits, getting electricity, getting credit, protecting minority investors, trading across borders, enforcing contracts, and resolving insolvency. The only two areas Saudi Arabia did not improve on were registering property and paying taxes.</p>
<p>Similarly, Bahrain implemented the highest number of regulatory reforms and the only area missing was starting a business. Aldred has noticed the improvements Bahrain has made with initiatives like Fintech Bay and Fawri+ which aim to make the area more attractive to potential businesses and investors. Similar initiatives include the Dubai International Financial Centre, Fintech Hive in Dubai and Abu Dhabi Global Market.</p>
<h4 id="keeping-culturally-aware">Keeping culturally aware</h4>
<p>One of the most important things to keep in mind when working in the GCC region, according to Slawther, is the difference in culture. This isn’t just to show respect for the citizens, but also because the culture dictates a different way of working. “It’s a very conservative region,” he explains. This extends to the banks too, and in his experience, that’s something a treasurer might find a bit frustrating.</p>
<p>“In the construction sector, for example, you’ll find that the bonding requirements (protection against non-performance) are quite substantial and the risk transference is a very different way of doing it from how we would have in the UK, Europe, Far East and Australia. Elsewhere the risk transference will be using surety, whereas the Middle East works on bank bonding and they won’t touch sureties,” explains Slawther.</p>
<p>From his banking role in the region, Aldred is aware of these challenges, and recommends that treasurers “embrace new ways of doing business but be very cognisant and respectful of traditional ways of doing business.” For example, for things like payables and receivables, where cash and cheque has been dominant, have one eye on the new digital ways of doing business, because there is a “real desire for economic and digital progress”.</p>
<p>To help navigate these unfamiliar waters, Slawther recommends leaning on colleagues are local to the region and who will be able to help understand the customs. Other key relationships, says Boukadida, include those with banking or technology partners. “It is crucial for corporates to carefully and strategically select their partners to ensure they receive a service that is appropriate for their specific business needs. If you find a banking partner or a technology provider who is an industry leader in their own right, typically the service that you will receive follows a standard benchmark,” he says.</p>
<p>Despite the challenges, Boukadida explains why he likes the region: “Its diversity is unapparelled, with more than 200 nationalities living and working here. Not only it is a great place to build and progress your career, it is also one of the safest countries, where you will have access to world-class healthcare, education and activities catering for all interests. While the UAE is a leader in promoting peace and tolerance, it is important to be sensitive and considerate in respecting each countries culture and traditions – as when we are anywhere else in the world.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[In April 2019, the IMF had forecast real gross domestic product growth in the six members of the Gulf Cooperation Council at 2.1%. By October 2019, that figure had dropped to 0.7%. The growth for 2018 was 2%, so what do these fluctuating figures mean for treasurers in the region and those looking to enter it?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2020-03-04-tta-05-rf__newtons-cradle-this-3d-render-illustration-63858544__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2020-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury in the Middle East]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><img alt="Chris van Dijl" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2017-11and12-tt-01-qa__chris-van-dijl__100x150.jpg?h=150&amp;w=100&amp;la=en&amp;hash=E8D2C0C1C926738E314985D52151CADA" style="height: 150px; width: 100px;" width="100"/></p>
<h5 id="chris-van-dijl">Chris van Dijl, Founder, Cugavadi:</h5>
<p>Treasurers in the Middle East have had an interesting 12 months with a significant amount of economic and geopolitical uncertainty.</p>
<p>The lower oil price has led to lower government spending. Those regions that have diversified themselves away from oil revenues, such as Dubai, have additionally been impacted by the global economic challenges which has led to a reduction in global trade and tourism. Throw in some new developments in geo-political instability within the GCC and you can easily see why corporate treasurers in the Middle East have not had the easiest of times in the past 12 months.</p>
<h4>Arranging finance</h4>
<p>As a direct consequence we have seen a shrinking of liquidity at financial institutions leading to a stricter lending regime. For the treasurer in the region this has meant that they have had to become creative in obtaining financing for their ongoing operations. In many cases this has led to an inward focussed ‘living within your means’ approach, or in other words fund growth internally with an enhanced focus on cash forecasting and especially cash forecasting automation.</p>
<h4>Introduction of VAT</h4>
<p>In a region where tax departments are virtually non-existent, in some cases the treasurer has become tasked with preparing the organisation for the implementation of VAT in January 2018.</p>
<p>Whether or not he or she is responsible, the implementation could lead to a burden on working capital requirements as VAT is transferrable to the Federal Tax Authority based on invoice date, rather than collection date. In a region that is notorious for stretching payment terms, this requires significant planning and cash flow forecasting analysis to ensure that funds remain available for business operations. Again, sophisticated cash forecasting solutions have been looked at by several organisations.</p>
<h4>Geo-political events</h4>
<p>The sudden blockage of Qatar by several countries in the region highlighted that instant and real-time access to cash balances and positions is vital in today’s ever-changing environment. Treasurers were involved in the initial risk assessment as well as immediate action by moving funds back to the centre: moving funds back into Qatar for Qatari companies and out of Qatar for non-Qatari companies. As supply routes had to be sourced into Qatar, treasurers were also involved in establishing trade finance arrangements for these new trade relationships.</p>
<p>Because of these challenges, real-time visibility and access to positions and exposures have once again become very important and some organisations have taken the initiative to consider treasury management systems with daily MT940 reporting capabilities, centralisation of treasury operations and/or implementation of in-house banking solutions.</p>
<p>What treasurers in the region have shown in the past year is that flexibility and keeping an open mind is a very important professional trait. Especially during times of change and uncertainty, the treasurer needs to be even closer to the commercial operations in order to support operations and ensure that it’s business as usual.</p>
<img alt="Emre Karter" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2017-11and12-tt-01-qa__emre-karter__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=3BD7002A3CD4DEE15C7BD1F1B9A78EB7" width="100"/> 
<h5 id="emre-karter">Emre Karter, Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions Head for Middle East, North Africa, Pakistan &amp; Turkey, Citi:</h5>
<p>As Middle Eastern economies continue to diversify away from energy-led growth and considering government spending made up of almost 70% of GDP, this has led to interesting results for the private sector who have been reliant on continued government spending to continue with their own growth.</p>
<p>Recent trends show that private and public sectors alike are tightening up their belts on expenses, pushing more efficiency measures, engaging in innovations and enhancing working capital cycles.</p>
<p>In a bid to improve efficiencies and reduce expenses, companies (especially the multinational corporates) have embarked on centralisation themes.</p>
<p>These include:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Moving transactions into shared service centres (with added benefits of control and standardisation).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Managing liquidity via a regional/global pool to centrally optimise internal versus external borrowing for working capital needs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Evaluating options that allow the use of liquidity to offset transaction costs.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Citi has worked with various companies (public and private sector) to consult, advise and create such structures that have facilitated their vision. Additionally, the bank has recently developed products to support clients who have or are in the process of creating a regional treasury centre in Dubai.</p>
<p>The other theme that has emerged in a rather strong way is working capital.</p>
<p>While this is not new in the world of a treasurer, the requirement now is ‘off-balance sheet treatment’ and ‘extension of working capital’. The words ‘without recourse discounting’ of receivables and ‘extension of payment terms’ with suppliers is now a common practice.</p>
<p>We have rolled out numerous SCF structures (or expanded existing ones) with many clients in this region over recent years. Companies have also been interested in sales financing solutions (allowing receivable discounting), which is giving them a much-needed breather in their cash conversion cycle and supporting the balance sheet.</p>
<p>Corporates are also interested in adopting cashless strategies and extending payables to their long-tail suppliers. As a result, they are looking to leverage commercial cards and we have recently launched a solution in the UAE called ‘Early Pay’. This further enables corporates to pay their long-tail suppliers who do not accept cards as a means of payment, allowing these smaller suppliers to be part of a supply chain finance programme.</p>
<img alt="Enrico Camerinelli" height="150" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2017-11and12-tt-01-qa__enrico-camerinelli__100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FB85F682D8A435BD06CCA53CEB669A41" width="100"/> 
<h5 id="enrico-camerinelli">Enrico Camerinelli, Senior Analyst, Aite Group:</h5>
<p>Treasurers operating in regions that are at a crossroads of international trade face even more demand to operate in environments characterised by international exchanges, multibank relationships, multicurrency transactions, visible financial transactions and efficient treasury staff activities. The ability to adapt to dynamically changing conditions with the appropriate use of people, processes and technologies represents competitive advantage.</p>
<p>The Middle East is a region showing a fast-growing import-export volume of goods exchanged with international trade partners: the countries in the Gulf Cooperation Council region (comprising Bahrain, Kuwait, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates) rank eighth among the most active in global trade flows.</p>
<p>Corporate treasurers in the Middle East are accountable and directly responsible for cash and liquidity management processes (FX/interest, cash management, trading/capital markets). Their responsibility is less direct (a higher percentage of them share control) for the settlements and trade finance functional areas that underpin the export-trade-driven nature of the market in which these organisations operate. Risk management remains a shared responsibility, while supply chain finance, collections and payables are far from where best practices suggest they should be. Corporate treasurers in the region seek to run their businesses beyond operations execution (cash management, reporting, liquidity management, cash forecasting) and to espouse “intelligent” decision-making in the context of a treasurer’s business strategy.</p>
<p>Treasury departments across the globe still use electronic spreadsheets extensively and companies in the Middle East are no exception. When asked to project their intentions for the near future, respondents strongly assert they will reduce the time spent on these systems in favour of more advanced and automated solutions. Enterprise resource planning (ERP) systems are likely to provide the functional applications that corporate treasurers in the Middle East will run to manage their business processes. Most likely, ERPs will soon be paralleled by more dedicated treasury management systems (TMSs).</p>
<p>The direct consequence of these trends is that companies in the Middle East are steadily moving away from building systems internally.</p>
<p>From an organisational perspective, corporate treasurers in the Middle East will continue to run traditional cash and liquidity management processes; based on research findings, anecdotal evidence, I expect it will take time (at least three years) to make the necessary steps and move toward a more decision-making role.</p>
<p>Most likely treasurers in the region will adopt a federated (ie regionalised) structure, and will expect banks in the region to provide the necessary support to facilitate the growing volume of trade flows to and from countries in the Far East. From a business process management perspective, corporate treasurers in the Middle East will continually seek information, technical solutions, and good practices to manage risk factors tied to interest rates, commodities and production operations.</p>
<p>In terms of information technology applications, corporate treasurers in the Middle East will migrate to ERP and TMS as their main applications platforms to run cash and treasury applications in the next three years. They will also use software applications for basic cash and liquidity management operations, while scrutinising solutions and services offered by banks.</p>

<h3 id="next-question">Next question:</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“How should treasurers go about rationalising their bank accounts?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2017-11-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Treasury in the Middle East: shifting sands]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[


<picture class="hero__picture" imgclass="heroarticle__img"><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1440px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=1800&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=6F9E0BEAE79C6932425398041CF4F2E9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1200px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=1400&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=B4BB8D98FF9A0CAB64E9A5DE96CD9D75"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 1024px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=1200&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=678BA5C481BA2E3930DA51259B15A3A9"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 769px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=1024&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=BEE96557F93BDFA604C1D51744528FFF"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><!--[if IE 9]><video style='display: none;'><![endif]--><source media="(min-width: 550px)" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=638&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=91130A13E6283E82EF89EB813D7797D6"/><!--[if IE 9]></video><![endif]--><img alt="Sand pouring out of someones hand" class="heroarticle__img" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=532ABC320693B1D09B6B194B0AECED08" srcset="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg?w=420&amp;usecustomfunctions=1¢ercrop=1&amp;hash=532ABC320693B1D09B6B194B0AECED08"/></picture> 

<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Over the last century, the Middle East has transformed into a global economic powerhouse, driving the world forward with its plentiful oil supplies. Yet, as oil prices plummet, the region and its businesses are heading into uncharted waters. In this article, Treasury Today explores the impact this is having on the corporate treasury function and what it is like to work in the profession across the region.</em></p>




<h3>Key economies in the Middle East</h3>
<h5>Egypt</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Capital:</dt>
<dd>Cairo</dd>
<dt>Population:</dt>
<dd>88,487,396</dd>
<dt>GDP real growth:</dt>
<dd>2.2% (2014 est.)</dd>
<dt>Currency:</dt>
<dd>Egyptian pound</dd>
</dl>
<h5>Qatar</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Capital:</dt>
<dd>Doha</dd>
<dt>Population:</dt>
<dd>2,194,817</dd>
<dt>GDP real growth:</dt>
<dd>4% (2014 est.)</dd>
<dt>Currency:</dt>
<dd>Qatari rial</dd>
</dl>
<h5>Saudi Arabia</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Capital:</dt>
<dd>Riyadh</dd>
<dt>Population:</dt>
<dd>27,752,316</dd>
<dt>GDP real growth:</dt>
<dd>3.5% (2014 est.)</dd>
<dt>Currency:</dt>
<dd>Saudi riyal</dd>
</dl>
<h5>UAE</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Capital:</dt>
<dd>Abu Dhabi</dd>
<dt>Population:</dt>
<dd>9,445,624</dd>
<dt>GDP real growth:</dt>
<dd>4.6% (2014 est.)</dd>
<dt>Currency:</dt>
<dd>UAE dirham</dd>
</dl>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>During the course of history, the Middle East has been a region of vital importance, politically, economically and culturally, due in large part to its strategic position at the meeting point of the Asian, African and European continents. In the modern era, the Middle East has arguably risen to even greater importance following the discovery of oil in 1908. Today the region is best known for its wealth of national resources, making it the world’s major oil exporter and home to 66% of the world’s oil reserves.</p>
<p>Despite its abundant resources, the region’s economic prospects are beginning to stagnate. This is the view of the World Bank, who, in their Economic Outlook for the Middle East and North Africa October 2015 report, predicted that for the third year running growth across the region will be less than 3%. Losses in revenue from oil exports – which the IMF predict will have reached $300bn by the end of 2015, or 21% of the Gulf’s GDP – is a major contributor to this decline in growth. Moreover, continued low oil prices, conflicts, the global economic slowdown and the US interest rate hike, make the short-term prospects of a recovery unlikely, according to the World Bank.</p>
<p>Governments across the region, as a result of the slowing growth, have seen the need to diversify their economies in order to build a sustainable economic future. The UAE, and in particular Dubai, has set the example in this regard by focusing on international finance and high quality tourism.</p>
<p>Of course, this diversification will open up new opportunities for businesses domiciled in the region and also further afield. Yet the Middle East – with a particular focus in this article on Kuwait, Bahrain, Qatar, the UAE, Oman, Saudi Arabia and Egypt – remains a complex region with well-publicised geopolitical challenges and great diversity. But, it is also one filled with much promise and opportunity for businesses.</p>
<h3 id="uneven-development">Uneven development</h3>
<p>The diverse economic landscape across the region corresponds with the varying levels of corporate treasury sophistication. Some companies match, and in some cases exceed, international best practice, whilst others remain underdeveloped. “There are a number of large MNCs that operate out of the region that run very mature treasury departments, leveraging the head office treasury systems and mirroring their processes where possible,” explains Sunil Veetil, Regional Head of Payments and Cash Management – Middle East and North Africa at HSBC. “On the other hand, there are the large local companies (typically referred to as family owned businesses) that have started to recognise the importance of the treasury function. Finally, there are those mid-level companies and SMEs that for the most part have some way to go before they match their peers in Europe and the US.”</p>
<p>The reasons for this uneven development in treasury sophistication across the region vary, and are influenced by internal and external forces. Location, for one, is a big driver. The economic development of countries like the UAE and Bahrain in particular has encouraged the expansion of the financial services sector and investment in infrastructure, attracting an influx of talent from overseas and affording corporates access to international best practices and services.</p>
<p>The nature of the region’s companies also has a large role to play. As Irshad Jooma, Head of Treasury Advisory Services Deloitte Middle East, explains: “It is typical for family-owned businesses to have wealthy shareholders who have been able to pump cash into the company at times of stress,” he says. “As a result, the need to develop high quality skill levels around cash and liquidity management and financing has been limited due to this safety net.” Similarly, despite many family owned businesses being very large, their growth has typically only been regional, again limiting the complexity of the function. “The result is a limited role for the corporate treasury in these companies and little room to influence as a strategic partner.”</p>
<h3 id="new-drivers-of-change">New drivers of change</h3>
<p>These conditions however, have begun to evolve. As HSBC’s Veetil – who is currently enjoying his second term in the region – outlines: “When I returned to the Middle East in 2013, after eight years away, the dynamics had changed. Both the economies and businesses had expanded and now operate with a global outlook.”</p>
<p>As a result of these companies growing in size and complexity, the role of the treasury function, as has been the case in other regions, has become increasingly important. “Many of these companies couldn’t have survived with their original treasury systems and frameworks,” he adds. “Today the treasury requirements of a large family owned business, are for the most part, as sophisticated as those from MNCs.”</p>
<p>External factors, like tightening liquidity conditions across the region brought on by the dramatic drop in oil prices, may also be having an impact. The low oil prices have initiated a domino effect where governments have begun to pull their substantial cash deposits from the region’s banks to plug budget deficits. Banks as a result have been required to seek alternative funding, and are borrowing at higher rates, primarily from the loan market. The net impact is reduced access to funding and higher costs for corporates.</p>
<p>According to Deloitte’s Jooma, current conditions are raising the profile of cash and liquidity management, particularly in the family run businesses. “The current environment has increased the need to bring in greater control, improve visibility and become more efficient in terms of liquidity management,” he explains. “For many businesses, which have typically been cash rich and afforded the luxury of cheap funding, this is a new challenge and one that can’t be solved by simply throwing money at the problem. Real changes have to be made and best practice treasury management has to be utilised.”</p>
<h3 id="a-wealth-of-treasury-tools">A wealth of treasury tools</h3>
<p>To help treasurers obtain best practice and scale up operations, there may be a need to invest in treasury systems and look to use innovative products. Thankfully, the region is well serviced in this regard. For instance, on the cash management side, corporates are able to pool (physical and notional) and concentrate their cash – typically USD – domestically in the majority of countries across the region. Cross-border pooling structures however are more restricted due to regulatory restraints, and, for the most part, are afforded only to those companies based in the more open economies such as the UAE and Oman.</p>
<p>On the payments side, the usage of cash remains heavy in the region. Cheques are also used frequently in the UAE by some businesses and are perceived to provide an extra layer of security due to the illegality of issuing a cheque that bounces – something that individuals moving into the country should be wary of in their personal lives. That being said, payments innovation is occurring in the region and corporates are increasingly able to move to more efficient cashless solutions. Some leading companies in the region, for instance, deal with few cheques and instead use electronic forms of payments, including SWIFT messaging. Although again the diversity and uneven development of the payments infrastructure across the region creates challenges for corporates looking for a consistent and uniform payment process.</p>


<blockquote>Today the treasury requirements of a large family-owned business, are for the most part, as sophisticated as those from MNCs.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Sunil Veetil, Regional Head of Payments and Cash Management – Middle East and North Africa, HSBC</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>As well as the solutions offered by the banks in the region, corporate treasurers are also afforded access to cutting-edge treasury technology in the form of TMSs and ERPs. But whilst access to this technology is helpful, Deloitte’s Jooma sees a regular pitfall that many privately owned family companies are falling into. “There is a trend to just install these solutions without having robust processes in place first,” he says. “The outcome is that they are most likely going to be putting garbage in and getting garbage out which is not helping them manage the treasury more efficiently.” In some cases as well such technology is not being utilised.</p>
<h3 id="differing-strengths">Differing strengths</h3>
<p>With most markets serviced by both local and international players, there is a good breadth of products and services available. However, there may be certain nuances when compared to other regions such as Europe and the US. Pricing, for instance, may sometimes be more expensive and also the documentation can be different in order to comply with local regulations.</p>
<p>Moreover, the strengths of the local banks compared to international banks can differ. Local banks are unable for the most part to match the US dollar clearing strength and international payment network of the global players. Yet, when processing dirham payments and basic domestic services such as payroll, the local banks excel. Then there are those areas where they are equal in terms of both quality and pricing, FX and interest rate risk management and debt financing, for example.</p>
<p>Aside from the traditional banks, the region is home to a number of large Islamic finance centres – namely Saudi Arabia and the UAE – whose banks offer various Sharia compliant solutions to corporates. Yet, it must be noted that for the most part the vast majority of companies still use conventional banking solutions, unless the treasury policy strictly dictates that Islamic products must be used. Corporates will however tap these banks for funding purposes.</p>
<h3 id="living-and-working-in-the-middle-east">Living and working in the Middle East</h3>
<p>Although a good range of products and services are on offer, readily available talent is not. Treasury departments across the region have therefore turned to the west and brought in experienced treasury professionals to lead their treasury teams and even fill some operational roles. This can be boiled down to the fact that the treasury profession is fairly young, meaning that there is limited talent being produced locally. Moreover, there is a very shallow pool of labour looking for work, or looking to move roles because of visa requirements in countries like the UAE – an individual’s residency visa is typically tied to their employment visa, creating an issue when trying to switch jobs, a challenge that is quite unique to the region.</p>


<blockquote>Most companies have established a structured programme for developing and sourcing local talent from the graduate level upwards.</blockquote>
<p class="quote-block__source">Ricky Thirion, Group Treasurer, Etihad Airways</p>


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>To help change this dynamic and reduce the costs associated with importing talent from overseas, a concerted effort is being made to develop local talent at all levels. “Most companies have established a structured programme for developing and sourcing local talent from the graduate level upwards,” explains Ricky Thirion, Group Treasurer at Etihad Airways. “At our company alone we have recently established two internal programmes, one for our existing team and the second for a newly established specialised Emirati graduate scheme.” The ACT have also been active in the region for eight years, promoting the profession.</p>
<p>In the meantime, whilst the profession looks to grow the local talent pool, there may be more opportunities for treasurers overseas to move to the Middle East and help continue to develop the profession. For those that decide to make the move it can be very rewarding, if not slightly challenging at first.</p>
<p>“The region is extremely culturally diverse when you look at corporate treasury and financial industry and a large focus is placed on relationships,” explains Etihad’s Thirion. “As professionals we therefore need to be more culturally aware of the various ways in which to interact with the different profiles of counterparts that we encounter. These considerations impact on style of negotiation and also social engagements. This is true both within our own organisation as well as when dealing with external counterparts.” As well, as a result of the emphasis on relationships some technology solutions used elsewhere, e-dealing for instance, are seeing a slower take up in the region.</p>
<p>Geopolitical instability may also be a concern to some and can have an impact on business – many companies across the region can no longer do business in Syria for instance. Yet, in countries that are largely stable such as the UAE there is little impact, however.</p>
<p>Despite these challenges, businesses are continuing to grow in the Middle East and as the role of corporate treasury develops and becomes of greater importance across the full-spectrum of companies, the future looks bright. This is the view of Etihad’s Thirion: “Our playing field is made up of economies that have great opportunity for growth and evolution supported by leaderships that are focused on the future and in bringing in efficiency, innovation and technology as a key enabler to everything that we do,” he says. It therefore seems that the role of the corporate treasury function will continue moving from strength to strength and that the role treasurers play in companies of all shapes and sizes will almost certainly increase.</p>




<h3 id="a-hub-for-the-region-and-beyond">A hub for the region and beyond</h3>
<p>In recent years, there has been an increased desire to establish local treasury centres to support operations across the Middle East, the Levant, Africa and occasionally, parts of Asia. The UAE in particular, has seen the emergence of a number of centres because of its position as a financial centre and its skilled workforce, a high quality of living, competitive cost bases and excellent infrastructure.</p>
<p>Treasury centres have many advantages. However, there are also a number of challenges that need to be considered when looking to establish such operations in the Middle East; traditional practices and habits are being challenged and as a result, are beginning to evolve. “Education is pivotal, especially in light of many treasury professionals relocating from western countries, where advances including, digitisation, centralisation, in-house banking and even shared service centres have been a reality for decades,” explains Nicoletta Stella, Head of Liquidity and Investments MEA, Head of International Cash Management MEA at BNP Paribas. “Central banks and regulators are also taking positive moves to push forward best-in-class treasury operations by encouraging large local corporations to embrace and implement state of the art banking solutions, such as SWIFTNet or electronic billing.”</p>
<p>Another topic, which requires attention and is often not considered with the gravitas required, is the evolving regulatory and reporting environment. “Whilst regulatory procedures are optimised to support fully fledged treasury centres, organisations need to be aware of the changing landscape,” explains Stella. “A particular example of this is in relation to taxation. Many still think that tax is a non-issue; this could be a significant error. We strongly encourage corporates to seek advice from tax professionals who have the expertise and are able to advise on sophisticated treasury set-ups.”</p>
<p>Another example which Stella believes isn’t always optimised is the understanding of different forms of company structures: JVs and partnerships, local sponsors, professional advice on possible set-ups can be a key catalyst for success. “What is clear however, is that the current pace of change is set to continue and this will be exemplified through a combination of education, diversity, evolving demographics and regulatory developments,” she adds.</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Over the last century, the Middle East has transformed into a global economic powerhouse, driving the world forward with its plentiful oil supplies. Yet, as oil prices plummet, the region and its businesses are heading into uncharted waters. In this article, Treasury Today explores the impact this is having on the corporate treasury function and what it is like to work in the profession across the region.]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2016-03-04-tt-10-ktr__sand-pouring-out-of-someones-hand-ss342688172__1920x1080.jpg]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2016-03-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Dubai: your gateway to Africa]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p><em>Setting up a regional treasury centre in Africa is a notoriously intricate process. This is precisely why informed multinationals have been looking for a more efficient route into the continent. Could Dubai’s geographical proximity, favourable business environment, and significant technological and infrastructure investments, provide the solution?</em></p>



<img alt="David Aldred, Head of Sales for Middle East, North Africa, Pakistan and Turkey, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-06-tt-03-st__david-aldred__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=2B53AEB64F5274AFB0D8DCA7A87E1371" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">David Aldred</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Sales for Middle East, North Africa, Pakistan and Turkey, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi" class="logo org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" width="50"/></p>


<img alt="Geoffrey Gursel, Head of Sales for Sub-Saharan Africa, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi" height="200" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-06-tt-03-st__geoffrey-gursel__150x200.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=74BA6B9F206CEB7807ADBD22328948BC" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="150"/>
<h3 class="fn">Geoffrey Gursel</h3>
<h5 class="title">Head of Sales for Sub-Saharan Africa, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi</h5>
<p><img alt="Citi" class="logo org" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-50x29.svg?la=en&amp;hash=4BA4967739E8473BDD8A9468631DE8E0" style="margin-top:1.5em;" width="50"/></p>



<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Earlier this year, Dubai International overtook London Heathrow to become the world’s busiest international airport. Whilst passengers have been travelling from Dubai to all four corners of the globe, there has been a noticeable uptick in traffic to Africa. In fact, Dubai-based airline, Emirates, is now the largest carrier in Sub-Saharan Africa and the main non-African airline into the continent.</p>
<p>Whilst this snapshot of the aviation industry highlights an interesting micro trend, it is also illustrative of a much bigger shift that is impacting the way in which multinational companies do business, and where they do it from. “Dubai is fast becoming a centralised hub, not just for conducting business in the Middle East and Asia, but also for doing business in Africa,” notes Geoffrey Gursel, Head of Sales for Sub-Saharan Africa, Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi. “Just as airline traffic has increased, the payments flows between Dubai and Africa have also rocketed in recent years.”</p>
<h3 id="a-rising-star">A rising star</h3>
<p>“Although Dubai has been a strategic port for millennia, what we are now seeing is something of a perfect storm,” adds David Aldred, Head of Sales for Middle East, North Africa, Pakistan and Turkey for Treasury and Trade Solutions, Citi. “The more traditional drivers for Dubai as a strategic business hub – such as its favourable taxation regime, comparatively easy operating environment, local talent pool, stable political and economic backdrop, and geographical proximity to Europe, Asia and Africa – are now being supported by significant domestic and regional advancements in technology and infrastructure,” he explains.</p>
<p>Indeed, the Dubai government has promised to invest over $8.1bn in new infrastructure in order to host the World Expo 2020. The aviation industry is set to be a primary beneficiary of this investment, as the emirate looks to further open its doors to both businesses and tourists. Another key initiative that is boosting Dubai’s attractiveness is the Smart City vision. The aim is to use the latest advances in technology – such as fibre optic wireless internet – to create a model for providing government services that are easily accessible, quick and efficient, using smart devices. These will include business-related services from ports, customs and bourses.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, the well-documented shift in global economic power is also working in Dubai’s favour, says Gursel. “Since Dubai enjoys a strategic location on the new Southern Silk Road, it is well poised to take advantage of economic activity into and among the world’s high-growth emerging markets (EMs), such as Africa, as part of the evolving South-South trade corridor.”</p>
<p>Being an emerging economy itself, and therefore familiar with the challenges of transitioning into a developed economy, Dubai is leading the way in terms of EM-to-EM connectivity, he says. And as Africa also becomes more sophisticated, connecting, integrating, travelling and speaking with the continent from Dubai is becoming easier and easier.</p>
<p>“Numerous Chinese banks and corporates have already realised this and are now leveraging Dubai as a means to access the African markets,” confirms Gursel. “Many other Western and Latin American companies – across all sectors – are also becoming increasingly interested in Dubai’s potential as the gateway to Africa.”</p>
<h3 id="treasury-matters">Treasury matters</h3>
<p>For treasurers, the beauty of all this is that it is now possible to run African treasury operations from outside of Africa, whilst achieving the desired level of visibility and control. As Aldred explains, “With the ongoing drive towards centralisation and bank account rationalisation, the days of having seven treasury centres around the world are, to a large extent, behind us. Having an on-the-ground finance presence in every continent, or in some cases country, simply isn’t practical; neither is it necessary in the digital age.</p>
<p>“That said, to achieve the right level of governance, it is important for multinationals to be in tune with their local markets. So, increasingly, we are seeing global corporates cut back to having two or three regional treasury centres. And if the Middle East and/or Africa is part of the company’s growth agenda, then Dubai is a great place to locate a treasury hub.”</p>
<p>Whist deciding to locate the regional treasury centre in Dubai rather than in Africa might provide numerous strategic advantages, it does not de facto solve the cash management challenges that treasury in Africa involves. Citi’s 2014 Treasury Diagnostics results reinforce that corporate treasurers have a “need for speed” real time treasury management, continued centralisation (efficiency and control) and an acute focus on risk management. As a result, real time and quality data analytics to help clients manage their business and assist with bank account rationalisation, control and visibility are critical. Aldred adds “Citi believes that mobile and tablet technology combined with integrated FX Payment solutions will drive value, efficiency and be extremely relevant for our clients as the treasury organisation continues to centralise and become even more efficient. This view is supported by our clients and the key treasury trends that we see.”</p>
<p>According to Gursel, some of the most common questions asked by Middle East corporates looking to do business in Africa revolve around: enhancing visibility with real-time balances; managing FX, country and counterparty risk; centralising payments and trade finance activity; domestic and regional cash concentration structures; compliance and control; and last but not least, connectivity standards and formats, such as XML and SWIFT.</p>
<p>“There is no one-size-fits-all approach to overcoming these concerns,” he adds. “The answers or solutions will certainly vary from company to company, and while I would encourage corporates to of course maximise their bank’s physical network, today it is critical to understand how SWIFT connectivity and sophistication is changing the tide with ‘virtual branches’ and how banks are enhancing the connectivity for our clients. And don’t settle for a piecemeal solution. Yes, achieving the right level of local capability is important, especially in Africa, but it is also important that your bank can deliver platform consistency across the region. Otherwise, the integration and efficiency benefits of setting up the regional treasury hub will be severely diminished.”</p>
<h4 id="chart-1">Chart 1: SWIFT traffic from Dubai to Africa</h4>
<a class="enlargeable" href="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-06-tt-03-st__chart-01__swift-traffic-from-dubai-to-africa__1503x850.png?la=en&amp;hash=8BB9B04939A17F3FFC9AE7838072118D" target="_blank"><img alt="Chart 1: SWIFT traffic from Dubai to Africa" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-06-tt-03-st__chart-01__swift-traffic-from-dubai-to-africa__1503x850.png?la=en&amp;hash=8BB9B04939A17F3FFC9AE7838072118D" width="800"/></a>
<h4 id="seizing-the-opportunity">Seizing the opportunity</h4>
<p>Embracing digitisation will also be key to making the most of the African markets, says Gursel. “After all, digitisation is changing the way everyone – businesses, governments, and consumers – handle financial flows.”</p>
<p>“Mobile banking, for example, has revolutionised financial inclusion, and trade dynamics, in Africa: in February 2015, mobile network operators in Kenya facilitated 80,000,000 payments to m-wallets, compared to 2,500,000 ACH payments via banks. Therefore, consumers, corporates and banks are all in an era of technology-adaptation in Kenya. From a treasury perspective, mobile payment approvals and authorisations are now available across Africa. And with electronic banking also available in every country, real-time visibility is achievable, and on a multi-bank basis in many instances.”</p>
<p>“As digitisation takes hold across Africa, the reliance on traditional bank branches is being challenged. Bricks and mortar presence is no longer a must-have and electronic formats are making for a much more efficient financial infrastructure,” explains Aldred. “Treasury centres have a similar opportunity to rationalise and streamline their operations, whilst also leveraging technology and innovation to gain visibility and manage cash and trade flows across Africa – all from the unique vantage point that Dubai affords.”</p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[Setting up a regional treasury centre in Africa is a notoriously intricate process. This is precisely why informed multinationals have been looking for a more efficient route into the continent. Could Dubai’s geographical proximity, favourable business environment, and significant technological and infrastructure investments, provide the solution?]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-06-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[True]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Question Answered: ME cash management]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading">This issue’s question</h3>
<p><em>“With so much focus on electronic payments in the region, what do readers consider to be the key developments in the Middle East cash management space today?”</em></p>



<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Murali Subramanian, Executive Vice President, Abu Dhabi Commercial Bank" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-05-tt-01-qa-murali-subramanian-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FACA5A7587B03AFBA37C935572802B16" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Murali Subramanian</h3>
<h5 class="title">Executive Vice President</h5>
<h5 class="org">Abu Dhabi Commercial Bank</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>In the Middle Eastern cash management space, handling of physical cash is still critical though non-cash payment products have been in use for many decades. Credit and debit cards for instance have increased in use in the region over the past 25 years, in keeping with the consumption orientation of the larger economies in the region. The infrastructure to support non-cash payments outside the wealthiest economies (UAE, and other GCC countries) is still developing. Retail sales continue to attract large volumes of cash though tax avoidance has never been an issue – this relates more to the cost of non-cash transactions that is slowly coming down as governments seek to improve the ratio of non-cash usage.</p>
<p>The value of cash transactions is reducing because large corporate-to-corporate payments are now electronic or cheque-based, but SMEs still need to be further integrated into the alternative payments space.</p>
<p>Central Bank initiatives within the region, including GCC RTGS (Real Time Gross Settlement), direct debits, and FCY clearing, together with other payment initiatives such as M-Wallet and intelligent Cash Deposit Machines are advancing the region’s infrastructure capabilities. Today, what the West perceives as ‘conventional financial infrastructure’ – credit and debit transfers, high and low value transfers, ACH, RTGS – is largely in place in all ME countries. There has also been focus on adding further clearing capabilities in the region; in addition to local currencies, there is talk of potentially introducing dollar and euro clearing capabilities domestically as approximately a third of all dollar and euro payments originating from the ME actually goes back to the region.</p>
<p>For corporate treasurers in the ME, payment and clearing is just one dimension of their role. There has been a progressive upscaling of their remit over the past few years with more responsibilities coming their way. Managing liquidity, risk and forecasting market operations – amongst other accountabilities – means automation is a priority in the bank selection process. In the ME region, however, the level of shared infrastructure capabilities found in a more developed economy are not consistently available. Yes, there are banks that do everything in an automated way, but equally there are many that insist on receiving paper instructions or may receive an electronic instruction but convert it back to paper.</p>
<p>Adding to the complexity of bank relationships in the region is the fact that treasurers need to hedge their liquidity, but there isn’t a well-developed domestic debt capital market in the region. So, the only way a treasurer can fund their enterprise needs is through bilateral funding from banks (unless the company chooses to list on an exchange overseas – but that would be a decision for only the biggest of entities and would involve other considerations such as having to obtain a credit rating).</p>
<p>As such, maintaining good banking relationships continues to be a priority for the treasurer. By definition, this means having to deal with several banks, but equally there is a clear focus on wallet share. Of key consideration is placing and integrating their operating business with as few banks as possible (because banking in the region is still, by and large, quasi-manual – the true level of automation and shared infrastructure is not quite here yet) but also having borrowing capabilities with as many as possible. For larger companies, a desire to be agnostic is somewhat commonplace; behaviour that tends to be in defence of reducing the number of banks a corporate wishes to use for payments and collections. In this instance, the qualifier for bank selection will be whether it is SWIFT enabled.</p>
<p>Looking forward, the preoccupation of tactical management of bank relationships and cost management will be joined by increasing focus on management of liquidity, management of market risks from FX, ensuring continuity of business and selecting architecture of enterprise platforms to automate workflows.</p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Alawi H. Al-Shurafa, Treasurer, Saudi Chevron Phillips &amp; Affiliates" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-05-tt-01-qa-al-shurafa-alawi-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=F45E69E068F77D34B8B898C28A54C568" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Alawi H. Al-Shurafa</h3>
<h5 class="title">Treasurer</h5>
<h5 class="org">Saudi Chevron Phillips &amp; Affiliates<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Of particular current and relevant concern to the cash management landscape in the Middle East (ME) are several key factors including: liquidity, compliance, automation and de-risking. Naturally, liquidity will always be important in this part of the world as many companies are centered on the spectrum of oil but, with the current pricing environment of crude, corporates are justified in being nervous. There is a requirement, at the very least, to ensure the company has enough cash to fulfil its commitments. To this end, I have seen a number of corporates renewing their revolving credit facilities and looking at the possibilities of expanding existing revolvers.</p>
<p>With regard to compliance, the lack of standardised Know Your Customer (KYC) processes and the difficulties in keeping up with changes can be a headache for corporates in the region. The different circumstances in the ME are not always reflected. For example, for global banks, something as simple as certifying the physical address of a board member of a company in certain places in the ME where people use PO boxes can have implications for fulfilling compliance requirements. Local banks have an enhanced understanding of the ME environment but, for global companies, cross-border presence is crucial.</p>
<p>The tighter controls and compliance is, the harder it is for corporates in terms of ease of doing business. There is a move from KYC to Know Your Customer’s Customer (KYCC) – banks do not always engage in trade finance transactions because of international sanctions and associated risk; requirements for such transactions, therefore, can put pressure on corporates’ working capital.</p>
<p>Moreover, the global banks are increasingly careful in their business dealings and aren’t as keen to explore areas with potential risk. The banks’ approach to calculated risk and the occurrence of de-risking is an area of concern for treasurers. Consequently, what the region is seeing is a bank-corporate relationship that needs to be in line with an expanded scope of compliance, coupled with cautious risk-weighing. Despite the aforementioned, treasurers must look at banking relationships holistically, optimising the presence of key banking partners who are well suited to support the corporates’ operational needs.</p>
<p>Finally, the amount of attention automation is receiving in ME is interesting these days after lagging behind areas, such as Europe, for a long period of time. I like to call it ‘SWIFTism’: after relying for so long on banks’ propriety platforms and host-to-host connectivity, there is a trend of corporates looking at SWIFT – in particular, SWIFT Alliance Lite2 – to do their cash management activities. Corporate treasury departments in the region are already technology-focused but as many corporates implement or consider implementing SWIFT, the region is becoming increasingly globally connected.</p>


<!-- BOXED -->

<img alt="Pradeep Prakash, Senior Treasury Manager, Majid Al Futtaim Holding LLC" src="https://treasurytoday.com:443/-/media/images/regional-focus/middle-east/2015-05-tt-01-qa-pradeep-prakash-100x150.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=9B05E04799AC6B25048A1AE9E5733FFA" style="float:left;margin:0 2em 2em 0;" width="100"/>
<h3 class="fn">Pradeep Prakash</h3>
<h5 class="title">Senior Treasury Manager</h5>
<h5 class="org">Majid Al Futtaim Holding LLC</h5>

<!-- BOXED -->


<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Cash management in the Middle East (ME) continues to be an evolving landscape. In just five to six years, it has developed into what is now a very interesting time for innovative ways to manage cash. Having said that, most corporate treasuries prefer to follow a tried and tested model. The main developments in the ME cash management space revolve around four key areas – visibility, pooling, payments and collections. Whilst visibility of cash is not the concern it once used to be, the emerging ways to manage this issue today are focused on innovative MT940 reporting and bank statement aggregation by lead banks. In addition, having a dynamic group treasury sign-off on any new banking relationship helps capture new bank accounts, which in the past would be ‘invisible’. Majid Al Futtaim has a quarterly process in place that reconciles the internal bank position to bank confirmations. A number of banks offer this statement aggregation service (albeit at a balance reporting level and not transaction level), and various e-platforms and vendors offer both balance and transaction reporting.</p>
<p>With an increasing sense of urgency, innovative solutions to achieve pooling are being sought out by corporates since this acts as a source of internal funding to optimise debt positions. However, good forecasting still remains a challenge to managing optimal cash positions. Other key hurdles to pooling in ME are withholding taxes in geographies such as Egypt, so hybrid pooling is crucial. Selecting a banking partner who can offer the best solution is important and requirements need to be clearly defined at the start of the partnership. Innovative pooling solutions (offered mainly by international banks) are freeing up a lot of captive cash in various markets.</p>
<p>Traditionally, from a pure finance background, payables processing staff have been either unaware of, or unable to see the importance of improving payment methods. Majid Al Futtaim works on current industry-standard payment methods, via middleware and SWIFT. This has helped to demonstrate a very good value proposition across our businesses – through cost/benefit analysis and negotiating a reduction in bank transaction costs, along with the obvious benefits of reduced operational risk and achieving greater STP rates.</p>
<p>Increasingly, a large number of corporates are starting to look at the payments and cash management landscape as an area of innovation which could truly result in a bank agnostic model. This would give treasurers much more operational freedom in consolidating balances, by providing better visibility, and greater yield optimisation potential on corporate cash. With a bank agnostic model, we see existing house-banks trying to retain relationships and ‘lock-in’ new clients through traditional host-to-host propositions. However, it is interesting to see that some leading international banks are also still trying to inject a level of bank-required customisation in file design. This would, to a very minor extent, dilute a true 100% bank agnostic proposition.</p>
<p>In the collections space, the direct debit mandate by United Arab Emirates Central Bank is the newest initiative, which currently applies to the financial institution (FI) space. Corporates have shown a cautious interest, and not many banks offer such a service. We see a lot of banks trying to position direct debits as a value proposition, if only to ensure new business. The feedback we get from our underlying businesses is on the security of cheques that have been tendered against receivables, and whether direct debits would offer the same level of legal protection that the cheques do today.</p>
<p>In conclusion, we continue to be excited by the change in the traditional view of payments, and see this to be an increasingly dynamic space for innovation and greater value propositions among both banks and corporates.</p>

<h5>Footnote</h5>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>These are the personal views of the spokesperson, not the views of Saudi Chevron Phillips &amp; Affiliates <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>



<h2 class="h3 copy__heading">Next question:</h2>
<p><em>“How is treasury benchmarking evolving? With increasing use of technology, are there any new measures which should be used to benchmark the performance of treasury departments?”</em></p>
<p>Please send your comments and responses to <a href="mailto:qa@treasurytoday.com">qa@treasurytoday.com</a></p>


]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[“With so much focus on electronic payments in the region, what do readers consider to be the key developments in the Middle East cash management space today?”]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2015-05-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Doing Business in Iraq: mitigating financial supply chain risks ]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<p>Iraq’s potential has attracted increasing interest from investors and companies looking to take advantage of its significant energy reserves, large infrastructure needs and young, growing population. However, there are also significant risks to doing business in this market. These risks should not be an impediment to entry and can be managed through innovative financial supply chain strategies and structures which will ensure that doing business in Iraq is truly rewarding.</p>
<h3 id="the-iraq-opportunity">The Iraq opportunity</h3>
<p>The fact that Iraq is a unique business opportunity has been increasingly recognised over the last few years. For example, in a paper published in 2011, Citi’s Chief Economist identified Iraq as one of only 11 global growth generators over the next 40 years. This growth story has been echoed in numerous other articles and seminars.</p>
<p>There has been notable success in tapping one of the world’s largest oil reserves; production has sharply risen to more than 3m barrels per day (bpd). Iraq’s infrastructure is also in focus after decades of war and sanctions; the National Investment Commission estimates that Iraq’s reconstruction needs would be approximately $200 billion over the next five years. And lastly, a population of 30m represents one of the largest consumer markets in the region with growing purchasing power.</p>
<h3 id="key-considerations-and-risks-to-doing-business">Key considerations and risks to doing business</h3>
<p>However, it is key to note that while Iraq is a significant opportunity, companies looking to do business in Iraq need to bear in mind the fact that this is a frontier market that warrants enhanced due diligence. This article aims to provide a summary of the main financial supply chain challenges that businesses could face and suggests mitigating factors.</p>
<h4 id="banking-sector">Banking sector</h4>
<p>Iraq’s banking sector is dominated by the main public sector banks which have limited ability to facilitate international financial flows. Private banks, while more numerous, need further development and strengthening. There have been recent instances of select banks being placed into guardianship. This has led to potential counterparty risk when using Iraqi banks for local cash management needs.</p>
<p>Companies also need to consider issues around exporting into Iraq. Traditional risk mitigation mechanisms, such as Letters of Credit (LCs) issued by Iraqi banks have limited acceptance. More recently, there have been restrictions, both market and regulatory-driven, around the availability of foreign currency leading to delayed payments to exporters.</p>
<p>Lastly, banks also play an extremely limited role in financial intermediation thereby limiting access to credit. Iraqi banks extended credit representing only 9.8% of GDP (compared to 55% for the MENA region). Alternative sources of financing such as stock market bond issuance or investment schemes are either non-existent or miniscule (for example, the Iraq Stock Exchange has a market capitalisation of only IQD 3.5 trillion).</p>
<p>The main state owned banks also have antiquated technology platforms. The systems of the private banks are comparatively more advanced but vary quite significantly from bank to bank. Additionally, a lack of trained and qualified staff impacts customer service.</p>
<p>The above factors combined with other issues such as regulatory uncertainty has meant that only one in three financial transactions flow through banks; cash is still king. This is inefficient, expensive and could present a potential security risk.</p>
<h4 id="regulatory-uncertainty">Regulatory uncertainty</h4>
<p>Iraq’s evolving regulatory and legal regime is also a factor that companies need to take into consideration. From a financial supply chain perspective, some recent regulatory changes that have caused uncertainty are:</p>
<h5 id="fx-controls">FX controls</h5>
<p>The Central Bank of Iraq has introduced regulations that have impacted the availability of foreign currency, especially US dollars in country. These coupled with reduced supply of US dollars in the daily auctions has resulted in severe shortage of the currency and a spike in the spread between the official exchange rate (1166/US dollars) and the “market” rate (1250 and upwards). This has had a twofold impact; one, it has become more difficult to remit funds from Iraq, and two, more expensive. Conversely, when remitting funds into Iraq, firms face challenges in paying their employees or suppliers in US dollars.</p>
<h5 id="tax-payments">Tax payments</h5>
<p>Companies should obtain clarity on the most appropriate tax rates applicable to their line of business and nature of payments from qualified advisers. However, the two most common tax payments affecting the financial supply chain are withholding and social security payments. These are typically required to be paid through banker’s cheques in Arabic, drawn on an Iraqi bank and payable in select cities. However, over the last year, companies have reported that the authorities have occasionally either not accepted cheques drawn on private banks or only cheques below a certain threshold amount which has affected supply chain processes.</p>
<h4 id="other-considerations">Other considerations</h4>
<h5 id="company-registration-capital-injection-account">Company registration – capital injection account</h5>
<p>There are various corporate forms in Iraq, ranging from sole proprietorships to joint stock companies which can be used to do business. To establish the above entities and obtain a registration certificate, a capital injection account (in IQD) will need to be opened with an Iraqi bank. The utilisation of the injected capital also needs to be considered; should it remain in Iraq to be used for local operations (and transactions effected through a local bank) or should it be repatriated to a treasury centre? Repatriation can be challenging in light of some of the currency and regulatory challenges detailed earlier.</p>
<h5 id="guarantee-issuance">Guarantee issuance</h5>
<p>When bidding for business in Iraq, especially for government contracts, guarantees will need to be issued (though public sector banks for the latter case). As mentioned earlier, Iraqi banks have limited international correspondent networks (especially the dominant domestic-focussed public sector banks). Multinational companies find it a challenge to issue these guarantees through their relationship banks (who may not have correspondent relationships with Iraqi banks).</p>
<h5 id="letter-of-credit-confirmation">Letter of credit confirmation</h5>
<p>Exports into Iraq are growing at a swift pace and expected to touch $80 billion by 2014. The public sector dominates official imports into Iraq but there is a thriving trade increasingly driven by the private sector. Exporters look to mitigate the risk of exporting into Iraq. The challenge is that very few international banks have credit appetite on Iraqi banks and can confirm or reissue LCs issued by Iraqi banks.</p>
<h3 id="operating-in-iraq-suggested-financial-supply-chain-factors">Operating in Iraq: suggested financial supply chain factors</h3>
<p>The following suggestions can potentially mitigate some of the related risks and issues described earlier:</p>
<h4 id="offshore-model">Offshore model</h4>
<p>Many companies have discovered that they can support almost all their financial supply chain needs through an offshore approach. This envisages the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Maintaining bank accounts outside Iraq thereby mitigating both counterparty and cross-border risk while still retaining the ability to make all types of payments within the country.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Exporting into Iraq and exploring trade risk mitigation strategies including LC confirmation through select international banks or more recently, credit insurance or Export Credit Agency structures.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Similarly, guarantee issuance favouring beneficiaries in Iraq can be initiated through banks based offshore leveraging their correspondent banking network in Iraq.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Receipt of sales proceeds into accounts domiciled abroad thereby mitigating both currency and transferability issues.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Leveraging centralised treasury centres to initiate payments with further integration with company-wide ERP or TWS systems.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course in select instances, a completely offshore solution may not work. Hence, where sales are in IQD and generated throughout the country, there will be a need for a local bank and its branch network to act as a collection bank. There is an associated challenge in remitting these receivables from Iraq (if required).</p>
<h4 id="banking-partner">Banking partner</h4>
<p>One of the key factors in supporting an offshore model is identifying appropriate banking partners. As detailed earlier, Iraqi banks present potential issues of cross-border and counterparty risk as well as having to deal with evolving technology and service standards. On the other hand, international banks have superior technology platforms and harmonised service standards; moreover, notwithstanding recent global events, they also represent better credit risk than their Iraqi peers. However, there are a limited number of foreign banks with a presence in Iraq and they do not have wide branch networks.</p>
<p>In identifying a banking partner, the following need to be considered:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Network</h5>
<p>Does the bank have an extensive network in Iraq? Also, is there diversity in the network thereby enabling a diverse solution set; ranging from guarantee issuance and LC confirmation to payment solutions across the country?</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Service and Technology Model</h5>
<p>Considering the service standards in Iraqi banks, it is preferable to deal with the relationship teams of an international bank. The global bank should liaise with its’ correspondent banks rather than allowing the company to deal with the local bank.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Credit Exposure</h5>
<p>One of the key advantages of the offshore model is the ability to mitigate counter-party and cross-border risk issues. Therefore, it is essential that the banking partner have appropriate credit appetite on their correspondent bank.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Liquidity and Accounts</h5>
<p>Most important choice in a banking provider, especially from a cash management perspective, is the account structure that will be used to support the business in country. The bank should be able to support all payment types, whether to a beneficiary in Iraq or globally, through accounts held outside the country thereby mitigating cross-border risk.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="trusted-advisors">Trusted advisors</h4>
<p>Needless to say, doing business in Iraq can be complex. It is vital to work with trusted legal, tax and other business advisors. Not only do they act as advisors but also perform valuable on the ground services. Hence, law firms also liaise with the Iraq Registrar of Companies during registration and will arrange for attestation of documents by the relevant Iraqi Embassy or Consulate in the country of domicile. Accounting firms facilitate payment of taxes by picking up certified cheques from the designated branches of select Iraqi banks. This obviates the need to maintain administrative staff in these locations for these functions.</p>
<p>Companies also look for advice and guidance from their peers who have already been operating in Iraq. This could either be through formal industry associations (for example, the US Business Council in Iraq or the Iraq Britain Business Council) or informally through <em>ad hoc</em> meetings and one-one discussions. These forums are also an opportunity to share best practices and suggest appropriate providers based on experience.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>The economic potential of Iraq is unquestioned. A combination of one of the world’s most significant hydrocarbon reserves, large population and immense infrastructure needs makes it not just an ideal investment opportunity but also one of the most exciting emerging markets for the medium-long term. Companies cannot afford to not have an Iraq focussed-strategy</p>
<p>However, as with other emerging markets, there are challenges and risks to doing business in the country. Needless to say, it is essential that extensive due diligence be performed and risks and associated rewards be identified. Financial supply chain issues can be mitigated by using an <strong>Offshore Model</strong> that is executed by an appropriate <strong>Banking Partner</strong> working in conjunction with <strong>Trusted Advisors</strong>. This winning combination will ensure that doing business in Iraq is truly rewarding.</p>
<h3 id="citi-supporting-clients-in-iraq">Citi: supporting clients in Iraq</h3>
<p>Citi has been supporting clients doing business in Iraq since 2003. Since then, it has worked on a number of key initiatives including:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Joint book runner on Iraq’s first sovereign debt issue of $2.7 billion (“Iraq 2028”).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Export Credit Agency (ECA) Structure with OPIC (Overseas Private Investment Corporation) and Iraq’s dominant trade bank.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Developed an LC Reissuance and confirmation structure for a leading public sector bank as well as select private banks.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Organised road shows over 2011-2012 in India, Turkey, China, Japan, UK, France, Germany, Switzerland and UAE.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Training seminars for Iraqi Ministries and Banks in Amsterdam, Baghdad, and Beirut coupled with regular meetings at Iraq forums in Washington, Istanbul and other locations.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Today, Citi has one of the largest correspondent banking networks in Iraq through five leading public and private sector banks with more than 100 branches across Iraq and Kurdistan. Citi’s innovative cash management services are utilised by nearly 40 clients across the country including a majority of companies in the energy sector. Additionally, Citi is also one of the leading reissuing and confirming banks for Letters of Credit issued by the dominant public sector trade bank in country and, since 2006, has reissued Letters of Credit for nearly 250 companies, both large multinationals as well as smaller regional firms, exporting to Iraq.</p>

<h2>Case study</h2>
<h3 id="cash-management-services-in-iraq">Cash management services in Iraq</h3>
<h5 id="company-1">Company</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Large US-based oil field services company.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Offices in two locations in Iraq with approximately 500 employees on the ground.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Struggled with Iraq’s antiquated banking infrastructure, risk and existing local bank’s lack of online banking (subsidiary of an international bank).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="clients-need-1">Client’s need</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Need to make payments (payroll, vendors, tax) across Iraq in both USD and IQD.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>International payments in US dollars, GBP and select other currencies. (Existing process: managed through parent’s treasury centre in USA).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Need for a centralised solution, elimination of manual processes and strong on-the-ground support.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Mitigation of risk of doing business in country (cross-border and counterparty).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="citi-solution-1">Citi solution</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Online access to CitiDirect® Online Banking (Citi’s online banking platform) to meet payment needs in both IQD and US dollars.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Tax payments through cheque disbursements in IQD at main branch of alliance bank in Baghdad (handed over to representative from client’s audit firm).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Payroll solution through opening of employee bank accounts and installation of shared ATM at camp-site to support servicing of the payroll solution; direct transfer of payroll through CitiDirect®.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>International payments through WorldLink®, Citi’s international payments platform.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="exports-into-iraq-lc-reissuance-and-confirmation">Exports into Iraq: LC reissuance and confirmation</h3>
<h5 id="company-2">Company</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Large Indian pipe manufacturer.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Won large contracts awarded by the Ministry of Oil (and select subsidiaries) to supply specialised steel and line pipes.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="clients-need-2">Client’s need</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Needed a global bank that would be able to confirm these LCs as well as provide guidance on some of the key issues related to exporting to Iraq.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ensure that payments are secured with country risk also covered.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="citi-solution-2">Citi solution</h5>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Citi had a series of discussions pre and post issuance of LCs with the client.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Comprehensive review of underlying commercial agreement between applicant and client.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Citi prepared a structured LC which will allow client to secure their payments over the period of the contract.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Citi was able to leverage a focused multi-country/multi-product team to execute the transaction in a very short timeframe.</p>
</li>
</ul>


<p>To understand how Citi can support you in Iraq, please do contact the author:</p>

<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Rohit Fernandes</dt>
<dd class="title">Client Sales Manager, UAE &amp; Iraq</dd>
<dt class="org">Citi Transaction Services</dt>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+971 4 604 4599</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:rohit.fernandes@citi.com">rohit.fernandes@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<p>Or<p>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Taoufik Rabbaa</dt>
<dd class="title">Head, Client Sales Management, Middle East &amp; Pakistan</dd>
<dt class="org">Citi Transaction Services</dt>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+971 4 604 4518</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:taoufik.rabbaa@citi.com">taoufik.rabbaa@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Surendra Bardia</dt>
<dd class="title">Head, Citi Transaction Services, Iraq</dd>
<dt class="org">Citi Transaction Services</dt>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+971 4 604 4414</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:surendra.bardia@citi.com">surendra.bardia@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Asif Ali</dt>
<dd class="title">Trade Sales Head, Middle East &amp; Pakistan</dd>
<dt class="org">Citi Transaction Services</dt>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+971 4 604 4319</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:asif1.ali@citi.com">asif1.ali@citi.com</a></dd>
</dl>
</p></p>
<img alt="Citi" class="logo" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-blue-2012-70x40.png" width="70"/>


<h5 id="notes-and-sources">Notes &amp; Sources:</h5>
<p>I US dollars: 1166 IQD (Central Bank of Iraq)</p>
<p>Citi does not provide tax, legal or related advice and would recommend that you engage qualified advisors for such purposes. The risks and key considerations provided in this document are not exhaustive and do not purport to discuss any risks emanating from inter alia, corruption and money laundering etc.</p>
<p>Buiter, Willem and Rahbari, Ebrahim, “Global Growth Generators: Moving beyond ‘Emerging Markets’ and ‘BRIC’”, Citi Global Economics View, February 2011</p>
<p>UK Trade &amp; Investment, “The New Iraq: 2012 Discovering Business”, November 2011</p>
<p>Kami, Aseel, “Iraq’s central bank places Warka bank under guardianship”, Reuters, March 2012</p>
<p>World Bank, “Republic of Iraq Financial Sector Review”, September 2011</p>
<p>Kami, Aseel and Bayoumy, Yara, “Banks that can’t cash a cheque slow Iraq economy”, Reuters, March 2012</p>
<p>Anon, “Cabinet agrees to accept instruments of private banks IQD 25 million instead of 5 million”, AKNews, July 2012</p>
<p>Saleh, Ahmed &amp; Opdyke, Tom, Perspectives on Iraq’s Private Banks: Growth, Consolidation and Outlook, 2011 Annual Report”, Iraqixchange in collaboration with Al-Fawz Brokerage, September 2011</p>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[ad hoc]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2012-10-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
	<node>
		<title><![CDATA[Doing business in the United Arab Emirates]]></title>
		<content><![CDATA[




<h2 class="h2 copy__heading"></h2>
<h3 class="sub-heading copy__sub-heading"></h3>
<h3 id="oil-rich-and-rapidly-diversifying">Oil-rich and rapidly diversifying</h3>
<p>The seven Trucial States of the Persian Gulf – as they were then known – gained their independence from Britain in 1971. The states subsequently adopted a federal constitution, referring to themselves as the United Arab Emirates (UAE).</p>

<img alt="Country map of the United Arab Emirates" height="162" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/2011/07and08/2011-07and08-tt-12-cp-uae-map-filled-with-flag-205x162-ss-23803378.png" width="205"/>
<h4 id="key-facts">Key facts</h4>
<h5 id="geography-and-society">Geography and society</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Population:</dt><dd>5,148,664</dd>
<dt>Population growth rate:</dt><dd>3.282%</dd>
<dt>Official language:</dt><dd>Arabic</dd>
<dt>Capital city:</dt><dd>Abu Dhabi</dd>
<dt>Time zone:</dt><dd>GMT +4</dd>
<dt>Land boundaries:</dt><dd>Oman (410km) and Saudi Arabia (457km)</dd>
<dt>Coastline:</dt><dd>1,318km</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="economy">Economy</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Currency:</dt><dd>Emirati dirham (AED)</dd>
<dt>GDP per capita:</dt><dd>$252.7 billion (2010 est.)</dd>
<dt>CPI:</dt><dd>2.2%</dd>
<dt>Member of:</dt><dd><abbr title="World Trade Organization">WTO</abbr>, <abbr title="Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries">OPEC</abbr>, <abbr title="International Monetary Fund">IMF</abbr>, <abbr title="Gulf Cooperation Council">GCC</abbr></dd>
<dt>Fiscal year:</dt><dd>Gregorian calendar year</dd>
<dt>Financial capital:</dt><dd>Dubai</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="history-and-politics">History and politics</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Independence:</dt><dd>2<sup>nd</sup> December 1971</dd>
<dt>Government type:</dt><dd>Federation; certain powers delegated to the federal government and others reserved for individual emirates</dd>
<dt>Chief of state:</dt><dd>Khalifa bin Zayed Al Al-Nuhayyan</dd>
<dt>Prime Minister:</dt><dd>Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktum</dd>
<dt>Legal system:</dt><dd>Mixed Islamic Shari’a law and civil law</dd>
</dl>
<h5 id="country-credit-rating">Country credit rating</h5>
<ul><li>AA+ (The Emirate of Abu Dhabi)</li></ul>
<h5 id="trading-partners">Trading partners</h5>
<dl>
<dt>Top five import sources:</dt><dd>China, India, US, Germany, Japan.</dd>
<dt>Top five export destinations:</dt><dd>Japan, South Korea, India, Iran, Thailand.</dd>
</dl>

<p>The UAE, consisting of Abu Dhabi, Ajman, Dubai, Fujairah, Ras al-Khaimah, Sharjah and Umm al-Quwain, joined the World Trade Organisation (WTO) in 1995. As a result, the emirates signed up to a free enterprise agenda and have since sought to attract overseas investment by establishing a number of free trade zones (FTZs).</p>
<p>These zones exempt the businesses operating in them from corporate tax and reduce the tariffs on their imports and exports. The Dubai International Financial Centre (DIFC), which was established in 2004, is perhaps the best-known FTZ in the region.</p>
<p>Until 1950, when oil was struck in the north-east of Abu Dhabi, the economy of the emirates was largely based on fishing and pearl harvesting. Today, the UAE sits on 7% of the world’s oil and 4% of its natural gas reserves. The country’s oil industry has attracted an influx of workers from India, Pakistan and Bangladesh. In fact, over three-quarters of the population is now of non-emirati origin.</p>
<p>The vast wealth that the emirates have derived from their oil exports has allowed them to develop their public infrastructure and meant that local residents enjoy some of the highest per-capita incomes in the world. This has not prevented the member states from seeking to diversify their economies, however. This is particularly true of Dubai, which, with far less oil than neighbouring Abu Dhabi, has promoted itself as a tourist destination and financial centre. To this end, the government licensed the NASDAQ Dubai, the stock exchange then known as the DIFX, in 2005.</p>
<p>With credit cheap and plentiful during the 2000s, Dubai experienced a property boom throughout the decade. In 2009, though, the emirate’s flagship investment vehicle, Dubai World Group, and Naheel, its highly-leveraged property development arm, asked creditors for a ‘stand-still’ on their debt and threatened to default if maturities weren’t extended by six months. In 2010, after much wrangling, creditors finally agreed to restructure the $25 billion they were owed, converting $8.9 billion of the debt into equity and leaving Dubai World to pay the remaining $14.4 billion over a revised payment schedule. The debt will be repaid in two tranches: $4.4 billion over five years and $10 billion over eight years.</p>
<p>The problems associated with the property bubble aside, Dubai and the other emirates have continued to thrive. Demand is growing for Shari’a-compliant banking products and the Islamic banking sector continues to grow. In fact, 16% of all banking assets in the UAE are Islamic.</p>
<h4 id="legal-and-regulatory-requirements">Legal and regulatory requirements</h4>
<p>Because the UAE is a member of many international bodies, including the World Trade Organisation (WTO) and the International Monetary Fund (IMF), its legal and regulatory framework broadly resembles that of many Western European countries.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The banking sector is supervised and regulated by the Central Bank of the United Arab Emirates according to the legal framework laid out in the country’s banking law of 1980. The central bank is divided into seven departments: Banking Supervision and Examination, Banking Operations, Research and Statistics, Administrative Affairs, Financial Control, Treasury, and Internal Audit.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The UAE is working with the Institute of International Finance (IIF) to improve existing corporate governance guidelines and monitoring. The country’s Central Bank has some of the most respected anti-money laundering systems and policies in the world, which focus on combating terrorism. All banks and financial institutions operating in the UAE are required to report suspicious activities directly to the Central Bank.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Financial institutions in the UAE banks are among the best capitalised in the world. Stringent capital adequacy requirements set by the UAE Central Bank mean that local banks already meet the requirements set by the Bank for International Settlements (BIS) as part of the Basel III accords. S&amp;P, the ratings agency, reported in 2011 that the region’s bank capital adequacy ratios are “in the high teens and in some cases up to 20%”.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All companies listed on the Abu Dhabi Securities Exchange (ADX) are required to publish IFRS financial statements. Note that companies from UAE Emirates other than Dubai are listed on the ADX, in addition to Abu Dhabi companies. All companies listed on the Dubai Financial Market (DFM) and NASDAQ are required to publish IFRS financial statements.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>All banks in the United Arab Emirates are required by the central bank to publish IFRS financial statements. Although IFRS is not legally required for unlisted companies other than banks, it is a considered best practice for these companies to adopt IFRSs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Commercial Companies Law in the UAE regulates the activities and the registration of foreign companies looking to establish a presence in the UAE. This law applies not only to foreign companies carrying out their main business activities in the UAE, or those that have their headquarters in the country, but also to foreign companies looking to set up a branch office. Local legislation in each emirate may also apply.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Neither the UAE nor the individual emirates impose foreign exchange controls. The Emirati dirham is pegged to US dollar at a rate of $1: AED 3.6725. There has however been talk of a single currency for the six countries of the Gulf Co-operation Council: the UAE, Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, Kuwait, Oman and Qatar.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Foreign Institutional Investors (FIIs) can own up to 49% of a UAE business. If the business operates in a FTZ, a 100% stake is allowed.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="taxation-framework">Taxation framework</h4>
<p>There is no single federal tax regime in the UAE. However, five of the seven emirates (Abu Dhabi, Ajman, Dubai, Fujairah and Sharjah) have similar regimes. Professional tax advice should be sought in the region, but the main taxation points which apply to the UAE are:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Except for oil and gas exploration companies and branches of foreign banks, corporation tax is not imposed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Withholding tax is not imposed, neither is stamp duty.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>No transfer pricing or thin capitalisation rules apply.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The UAE currently has more than 30 double taxation treaties in place for income and/or capital together with a growing number of shipping and air transport treaties.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Municipal taxes are imposed on hotel services and income derived from rental of property. Annual rental income of residential and commercial tenants are taxed at 5-10%.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="treasury-activities">Treasury activities</h4>
<h5 id="local-banking-sector">Local banking sector</h5>
<p>The UAE’s banking sector has been a major beneficiary of the country’s strong economic growth in recent years. Historically, the government has dominated the UAE’s banking sector, which currently consists of a total of 52 banks (24 domestic and 28 foreign). The World Trade Organisation has encouraged the UAE to open up its banking sector to foreign banks. Although the central bank has started to issue more licences to foreign banks, the number of branches that they can open is restricted. Islamic banking continues to evolve in the Gulf region and the majority of banks operating in the UAE either have an Islamic subsidiary or offer Shari’a-compliant products.</p>
<h5 id="payments">Payments</h5>
<p>The main payment methods in use in the UAE are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>Cash</h5>
<p>– still the preferred choice for retail payments as it is estimated that only just over half of UAE residents have a bank account.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Credit transfers</h5>
<p>– used for high value payments and salary payments. Retail transactions can be processed through e-banking systems whereas inter-bank transfers are arranged using the Central Bank FTS system and SWIFT messages.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Direct debits</h5>
<p>– usage is limited but growing for low-value frequent payments, such as utility bills. Direct debits are not carried out across the Central Bank and as such, parties to a direct debit must have a bilateral agreement in place and generally use the same bank. Most systems were introduced within the last five years.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Cheques</h5>
<p>– these remain one of the major cashless payment methods and the value of cheques in the UAE is typically high.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Card payments</h5>
<p>– usage has increased significantly but there have been high instances of card fraud and the Central Bank is considering a move across to the chip and pin system.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>e-Dirham cards</h5>
<p>– sometimes referred to as a ‘secure electronic purse’, the e-Dirham card is a government initiative that allows customers to pay for goods and services without cash. The fixed value e-Dirham card is available in a number of denominations – from 100 to 5,000 dirhams. They cannot be re-used once the balance has been spent. The government client card is intended for people who wish to make frequent cashless payments. Initially used by local governments to collect revenues, the system is now also used in the private sector. Unlike its fixed counterpart, the government client card can be re-used.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Mobile e-payments</h5>
<p>– a relatively new but growing technology that enables customers to pay for items and transfer money via their mobile phone handsets.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h5 id="clearing-and-settlement">Clearing and settlement</h5>
<p>A clearing house in maintained by the Central Bank in each emirate, and all banks are clearing members. The UAE’s Central Bank operates a number of clearing and settlement systems:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h5>The UAE Funds Transfer System (UAEFTS)</h5>
<p>The UAE Funds Transfer System is the Central Bank’s real-time gross settlement system for funds transfer between banks, cash withdrawal/deposit pre-authorisation, account status monitoring and account reconciliation facilities. The system, which was developed in-house to maintain full control over the facilities, reduces systemic risk, eliminating the need for Central Bank intervention in the inter-bank payments. This system is being made mandatory later in 2011.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>Image Cheque Clearing System (ICCS)</h5>
<p>Image Cheque Clearing System was introduced in July 2008 and features cheque truncation and T+0 settlement. This means that settlement takes place on the same day that the cheque is presented into clearing. According to figures from the Central Bank, ICCS processes 97,000 items and AED 3.8 billion worth of transactions each day.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>International Bank Account Number (IBAN)</h5>
<p>The UAE Central Bank has taken steps to make the International Bank Account Number (IBAN) applicable across UAE. The move is aimed at supporting the federal government’s strategy, which calls for adopting modern technology with a view to boosting systems and improving the services provided to bank customers</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>UAESWITCH</h5>
<p>UAESWITCH was introduced in 1996, the UAESWITCH system comprises 45 member banks and over 3,200 ATMs. Through its connection to GCCNET, UAESWITCH allows cardholders to use ATMs throughout the Gulf region.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h5>The Wages Protection System (WPS)</h5>
<p>The Wages Protection System was introduced by the Central Bank in conjunction with the Ministry of Labour in September 2009. The system intends to provide a safe, efficient and robust mechanism to allow the timely payment of employees’ wages. All financial institutions registered with the central bank can act as agents to this system, and this has resulted in significant increase in efficiency and automation of salary payments.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="case-study">Case study</h2>
<h3 id="dubal-dubai-aluminium-company-limited">DUBAL (Dubai Aluminium Company Limited)</h3>

<h4 class="fn">Hussain N H Al Sayegh</h4>
<h5 class="title">Treasury Manager, DUBAL</h5>
<img alt="Dubal Dubai Aluminium logo" class="logo org" height="45" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/dubal-dubai-aluminium-logo-2011-90x45.png" title="Dubal Dubai Aluminium" width="90"/>

<p class="management-summary">One of the largest non-oil contributors to the economy of Dubai.</p>
<h4 id="the-challenge-1">The challenge</h4>
<p>DUBAL, one of Citi’s key clients in the UAE, grappled with two cash management challenges. The lack of a centralised electronic payments system meant that payments to DUBAL’s suppliers had to be made manually through physical signing and delivery of bank letters. Also, DUBAL held over 50 multi-currency bank accounts spread over eight relationship banks which created a logistical problem both in terms of its consolidated daily cash balance and timely, efficient reconciliation.</p>
<h4 id="the-solution-1">The solution</h4>
<p>DUBAL has been a cornerstone client for Citi in UAE since 1996. Citi proposed a two-fold solution, both components of which used CitiDirect®. Firstly, DUBAL’s cumbersome payments system was shifted to electronic processing through CitiDirect® Online Banking, effectively eliminating the need for manual payments while also facilitating cross-currency payments. Secondly, DUBAL’s SAP enterprise software system was integrated with CitiDirect®. This eliminated the need for manual aggregation of a blizzard of papers from numerous banks for DUBAL to gain data visibility over its cash management position. It also enabled electronic automated bank reconciliations.</p>
<h4 id="the-result-1">The result</h4>
<p>By successfully integrating its systems with Citi’s, DUBAL now has online access, real-time visibility and control over its accounts, payments and reports. The new arrangement also gives DUBAL automated access to cross-currency payments. This has placed DUBAL as one of the most progressive companies in the region in terms of best practice treasury management. In addition, Citi is now DUBAL’s lead bank for all functional currencies (other than AED). The changes significantly reduced the time spent on bank reconciliation and increased straight through processing (STP) levels.</p>
<p>Hussain N H Al Sayegh, DUBAL’s Treasury Manager, says: “We evaluated similar solutions from other banks as well as Citi, but after consideration, we believed that Citi could deliver best practice in technology and excellent customer service. Now 99% of payments to suppliers are made electronically through CitiDirect. Instead of having two drivers constantly taking letters to the bank, we have only ‘half a driver’ doing the job. Also, processing has become faster and we know about problems more quickly. The whole system is more transparent.”</p>


<h2 id="case-study">Case study</h2>
<h3 id="jbf-rak-llc">JBF RAK LLC</h3>
<h4 id="the-challenge-2">The challenge</h4>
<p>JBF RAK LLC is a JV with the Ras Al Khaimah Investment Authority and has a capacity of 1200 tonnes per day for manufacturing polyester resin for packaging incorporating the latest technology. The facilities are located at Emirate of Ras Al Khaimah, U.A.E. JBF was looking to increase the efficiency of its trade cycle, specifically through reducing the time taken for export documentation to reach the confirming bank, and the time involved to resolve any discrepancies in order to more effectively manage its cash flow and ensure faster realisation of its trade receivables.</p>
<h4 id="the-solution-2">The solution</h4>
<p>Citi positioned Direct Presentation®, which eliminated the need for physically delivering documents between JBF’s office in RAK and Citi’s office in Dubai. This solution enabled online presentation of documents, and for Citi to commence the document examination process within minutes of online document generation. Discrepancies could be resolved much quicker as documents no longer needed to travel back and forth between JBF and Citi. Supporting this foundation was Citi’s unique service model that consistently processed documents from within a few hours to one working day, compared to an industry average of four to five days. Export documents were processed more quickly, resulting in faster realisation of export receivables for JBF and a reduction in DSO by two to five days. Citi also conducted training sessions for JBF during the on-boarding process to facilitate a smooth transition.</p>
<h4 id="the-result-2">The result</h4>
<p>Through its recommended trade solution, Citi generated compelling economic value, reducing turnaround time to improve JBF’s receivables realisation efficiency and reducing aligned expenses.</p>

<h4 id="cash-management">Cash management</h4>
<p>Domestic and cross-border cash pooling is permissible in the UAE but the concept of cash management is relatively new in the area. As such, some of the cash management products on offer are either not yet as sophisticated as in western countries or not widely available.</p>
<p>Interest is paid on call accounts but the majority of current accounts in the UAE are subject to local restrictions on interest. Accounts can however be held in both Emirati dirham (AED) and foreign currency, domestically and abroad:</p>
<figure>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Type of bank account</th>
<th>Location</th>
<th>Permitted</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>AED</td>
<td>UAE</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AED</td>
<td>Abroad</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Convertible into foreign currency</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Foreign currency</td>
<td>UAE</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Foreign currency</td>
<td>Abroad</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non resident foreign currency</td>
<td>UAE</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>-</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Non resident AED</td>
<td>UAE</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>Convertible into foreign currency</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</figure>
<p>Where paid, local interest rates are comparable to the US which results in many multinational companies centralising cash.</p>
<p>Other short-term investment options available in the UAE include time deposits in AED or foreign currency with tenors of one, two, three, six, nine or 12 months, certificates of deposit, repos and government issued bills, notes and bonds. Overdraft facilities are available for UAE companies and the central bank also provides overdraft facilities for commercial banks.</p>

<h4 id="key-websites">Key websites</h4>
<dl class="websites">
<dt>Government website:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.government.ae" target="_blank">www.government.ae</a></dd>
<dt>Central Bank of the UAE:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.centralbank.ae" target="_blank">www.centralbank.ae</a></dd>
<dt>Emirates Banks Association:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.eba-ae.com" target="_blank">www.eba-ae.com</a></dd>
<dt>Ministry of Economy:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.economy.ae" target="_blank">www.economy.ae</a></dd>
<dt>Ministry of Finance and Industry:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.mof.gov.ae" target="_blank">www.mof.gov.ae</a></dd>
<dt>Abu Dhabi Securities Exchange:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.adx.ae" target="_blank">www.adx.ae</a></dd>
<dt>Dubaï International Financial Centre:</dt>
<dd><a href="http://www.difc.ae" target="_blank">www.difc.ae</a></dd>
</dl>


<h3 id="citis-capabilities-in-the-uae">Citi’s capabilities in the UAE</h3>
<p>Citi has been present in the United Arab Emirates since 1964 when the bank opened its first branch in Dubai. The bank is directly represented in several markets in the Middle East including the UAE, Egypt, Jordan, Lebanon, Qatar, Bahrain and Kuwait.</p>
<p>Citi’s Markets and Banking (CMB) division successfully combines a top-tier investment bank with world-class corporate banking services. Our investment banking group provides tailored and unique solutions to top corporations, financial institutions and governments worldwide, offering strategic and financial advisory services including acquisitions, mergers, divestures, financial restructuring, equity and fixed income products, loans, foreign exchange and cash management.</p>
<p>In line with its strategy of customising its products to local market requirements, Citi recently unveiled a suite of Shari’a-compliant banking solutions under the Treasury &amp; Trade Solutions business designed to meet the working capital needs of its corporate clients.</p>
<p>Citi has a repertoire of award-winning, leading edge technology platforms like CitiDirect®, CitiConnect®, IntraLinks and Treasury Vision which are offered to a host of multinational, local corporate, financial institutions and public sector organisations. These platforms give clients in the UAE access to globally accepted tools to optimise liquidity and cash management, improve operational efficiency and risk management processes across their requirements spanning their entire working capital cycle.</p>
<p>Citi’s Treasury Services offer retail and corporate clients unique investment opportunities including Gulf currencies FX execution capabilities, access to Levant and North African markets, FX options capabilities on Saudi Riyal and Kuwaiti Dinar and FX swap capabilities in UAE Dirham up to five years. These are backed by structured, value-added solutions to meet customer hedging and investment requirements and an access to in-depth analysis and world-class research on regional and international markets.</p>
<p>Citi consistently ranks as the premier choice for cash management and trade services, foreign exchange products, portfolio products, corporate finance, investment management and custodial services in more markets, including the UAE, than any other bank according to industry surveys.</p>
<p>Citi has won several prestigious accolades in 2008 alone including the Best Treasury and Cash Management Bank and Provider for the Middle East from Global Finance and the Best Cash Management House in the Middle East from Euromoney.</p>

<h5 id="contact-details">Contact details:</h5>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Surendra Bardia</dt>
<dd class="role">Treasury and Trade Solutions Head – UAE and Iraq</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+971 (4) 604-4414</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:surendra.bardia@citi.com">surendra.bardia@citi.com</a></dd>
<img alt="Citi logo" class="logo org" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-2012-70x40.png" style="display:none;" title="Citi" width="70"/>
</dl>
<dl class="vcard">
<dt class="fn">Sanjeev Ganjoo</dt>
<dd class="role">Global Transaction Services Head – Abu Dhabi</dd>
<dd class="tel"><span class="value">+971 (2) 604 3060</span></dd>
<dd class="email"><a href="mailto:sanjeev.ganjoo@citi.com">sanjeev.ganjoo@citi.com</a></dd>
<img alt="Citi logo" class="logo org" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-2012-70x40.png" style="display:none;" title="Citi" width="70"/>
</dl>

<img alt="Citi" class="logo" height="40" src="http://treasurytoday.com/i/logo/citi-logo-2012-70x40.png" width="70"/>



]]></content>
		<excerpt><![CDATA[]]></excerpt>
		<featuredimage><![CDATA[]]></featuredimage>
		<publishdate><![CDATA[2011-07-01]]></publishdate>
		<category><![CDATA[Middle East]]></category>
		<issponsored><![CDATA[False]]></issponsored>
	</node>
</data>
